<?xml version="1.0"?>
<TEI.2>
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt n="The Martyred President: A Sermon Preached in the First Presbyterian Church, Brooklyn, N. Y.">
            <title>  The Martyred
President: A Sermon Preached in the First Presbyterian Church,
Brooklyn, N. Y.  </title>
            <author>Robinson, Rev. Chas. S.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Compiled and edited by</resp>
               <name>Beck
Center</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent/>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Lewis H. Beck Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Emory University</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Atlanta,
Georgia</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>1996 Emory
University. Permission is granted to download, transmit, or otherwise
reproduce, distribute or display the contributions to the work claimed
by Emory University for non-profit educational purposes, provided
this header is included in its entirety.  For inquiries about
commercial uses, contact the Director, 
Pitts Theology Library, Emory
University, Atlanta, Georgia 30322</p>
            </availability>
            <date>1999</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Lincoln
Sermons Project</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Robinson,
Rev. Chas. S. The Martyred President: A Sermon Preached in the First
Presbyterian Church, Brooklyn, N. Y.  On the Morning of April 16th,
1865.  New York: John F. Trow, Printer, 50 Greene Street.  1865.</bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This text derives from the Special Collections 
of Pitts Theology Library, Emory University, and is produced in 
collaboration with the Lewis H. Beck Center a, the Emory 
Preservation Office, and Pitts Theology Library.</p>
            <p>TRANSCRIBER: Lewis H. Beck Center and Emory University 
Preservation Office.</p>
            <p>PRODUCER:  BookLab, Inc., 1606 Headway Circle, 
Suite 100, Austin, TX 78754</p>
            <p>CAPTURE DEVICE: XEROX DocuImage 620S flatbed scanner</p>
            <p>CAPTURE DETAILS: Scanner software: XEROX ScanTool 
version 4.2.3; no gamma correction; images are all bitonal.</p>
            <p>CHANGE HISTORY: Using the Adobe Photoshop Batch Processor, 
we interpolated  the original TIFF files to 8-bit grays, 
and altered the resolution to 144 dpi, producing screen 
images twice the original size.  We then saved them in 
JPEG format.  We produced GIF thumbnails from the JPEG files.</p>
            <p>RESOLUTION: 600 ppi</p>
            <p>COMPRESSION: Resolution 144 per inch with Constrain 
Properties to 72 per inch.</p>
            <p>SOURCE: Original documents.</p>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>1999</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Scott
Ellis</name>
               <resp>Staff</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <item>SGML tags inserted in
compliance with TEI guidelines using TEILITE</item>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div1 id="robinson.001" n="The Martyred President: A Sermon Preached in the First Presbyterian Church, Brooklyn, N. Y." type="text">
            <head pn="1"> 
               <bibl> 
                  <title> The Martyred President: A
Sermon Preached in the First Presbyterian Church, Brooklyn,
N. Y.</title> 
                  <date>April 16th, 1865</date> 
                  <pubPlace>Brooklyn,
NY</pubPlace> 
                  <author>Robinson, Rev. Chas. S.</author> 
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>John F. Trow,
Printer</publisher>
                     <date>1865</date>
                  </imprint> 
               <idno type="ark">http://pid.emory.edu/ark:/25593/15qzd</idno></bibl> 
            </head>
            <p pn="1">
               <figure entity="robinson1">
                  <figDesc>1st page of
Rev. Chas. S. Robinson's The Martyred President: A Sermon Preached in
the First Presbyterian Church, Brooklyn, N. Y.</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <p pn="1">The Martyred President:</p>
            <p pn="1">A</p>
            <p pn="1">SERMON</p>
            <p pn="1">PREACHED IN THE</p>
            <p pn="1">FIRST PRESBYTERIAN CHURCH, BROOKLYN, N.Y.,</p>
            <p pn="1">BY THE PASTOR,</p>
            <p pn="1">REV. CHAS. S. ROBINSON,</p>
            <p pn="1">ON THE MORNING OF</p>
            <p pn="1">APRIL 16th, 1865.</p>
            <p pn="1">NEW YORK:</p>
            <p pn="1">JOHN F. TROW, PRINTER, 50 GREENE STREET.</p>
            <p pn="1">1865.</p>
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p pn="2">
               <figure entity="robinson2">
                  <figDesc>2nd page of
Rev. Chas. S. Robinson's The Martyred President: A Sermon Preached in
the First Presbyterian Church, Brooklyn, N. Y.</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <p pn="2">BROOKLYN, N. Y., <hi rend="italic">April 17th</hi>, 1865
<lb/>
Rev. CHAS. S. ROBINSON:
<lb/>
Dear Sir: As members of the congregation to which you minister, we
wish to indicate to you our warm appreciation of the discourse
delivered in your pulpit on yesterday morning, occasioned by that
appalling dispensation of Providence which has imprinted the deepest
sorrow in every loyal bosom in this afflicted land.</p>
            <p pn="2">We regard the Sermon as embodying a fitting and felicitous tribute
to the character of ABRAHAM LINCOLN, our late President, who has
fallen an illustrious martyr to the cause of constitutional government
and universal freedom of man.</p>
            <p pn="2">We respectfully request that you will furnish us a copy of it for
the press, believing that by its preservation in a permanent form it
will embody a just record, proper to be filed among the archives of
the Church, and handed down to our children, of the unwavering loyalty
of Pastor and people to the cause of national integrity and
constitutional rule during these eventful and perilous years of
conflict with organized and armed rebellion.</p>
            <p pn="2">With assurances of our cordial regards
	<lb/>FISHER HOWE,	HENRY SHELDON,
	<lb/>CYRUS P. SMITH,	LOWELL HOLBROOK,
	<lb/>SILAS H. STRINGHAM,	JONATHAN OGDEN,
	<lb/>SAMUEL HUTCHINSON,	HENRY BUTLER,
	<lb/>HENRY IDE,	W. HASTINGS,
	<lb/>HENRY K. SHELDON,	NOAH T. SWEZEY,
	<lb/>DANIEL POMEROY;	JAMES R. TAYLOR,
	<lb/>JONATHAN D. STEELE,	RICHARD J. DODGE,
	<lb/>ANDREW A. SMITH,	HOBART FORD,
	<lb/>ALEXANDER M. EARLE,	ABIJAH FISHER.</p>
            <p pn="2">FIRST PRESBYTERIAN CHURCH, BROOKLYN, April 18th, 1865. 
<lb/>
To Messrs. FISHER HOWE, Hon. C. P. SMITH, Rear Admiral
S. H. STRINGHAM, SAMUEL HUTCHINSON, and others:</p>
            <p pn="2">Gentlemen: The Discourse which you request, prepared so hurriedly in
the midst of such confusion and excitement, takes all its value from
your cordial endorsement of its sentiments.</p>
            <p pn="2">We are just closing a four years' war; the air is vibrating with
tidings of victory as I write. But we are beginning a new war of more
than four years, the weapons of which are not carnal.</p>
            <p pn="2">Much of the peril of that conflict will be forestalled by a frank,
firm stand taken at the outset.  And I am unaffectedly happy in your
willingness to commit yourselves, as a church, now with me, to the
truth, fearless as you all have ever been in your steadfastness to the
principles involved in the war. 
		<lb/>Very truly and affectionately,
		       <lb/> Your friend and Pastor
		<lb/>CHAS. S. ROBINSON.</p>
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p pn="3">
               <figure entity="robinson3">
                  <figDesc>3rd page of
Rev. Chas. S. Robinson's The Martyred President: A Sermon Preached in
the First Presbyterian Church, Brooklyn, N. Y.</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <div2 id="robinson.002" n="The Martyred President." type="sermon">
               <head pn="3">The Martyred President.</head>
               <epigraph pn="3">
                  <p pn="3">HE WAS A GOOD MAN, AND A JUST.-Luke xxiii: 50.</p>
               </epigraph>
               <p pn="3">ONE other Sabbath like this I remember, and only one; that
of which this is the exact anniversary, four years ago. What
humiliated the nation then is now measurably rectified. The ensign of
our country floats once more on the ramparts from which it had just
been torn by the fierce hand of treason. The same batteries that
hurled shot and shell at the fortress, whose name has become historic,
have been forced to pour forth their empty salutes in honor of the
restoration. And the proclamation is already in the air, which was to
summon the grateful Republic to a thanksgiving for t he manifold mercy
of Almighty God.</p>
               <p pn="3">Right in the midst of our rejoicing we are dashed into sorrow deeper
than ever.  To-day it is not the humbling of our pride that makes us
mourn, but the wounding of our hearts in their keenest
sensibilities. For he who has been our leader lies low in his coffin;
foul murder has been done at the capital; and the nation stands hushed
in the presence of its unburied dead.</p>
               <pb n="4"/>
               <p pn="4">
                  <figure entity="robinson4">
                     <figDesc>4th page of
Rev. Chas. S. Robinson's The Martyred President: A Sermon Preached in
the First Presbyterian Church, Brooklyn, N. Y.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <p pn="4">Have the old days of barbarism returned upon us? Is assassination
become civilized? Has the bullet of a murderer recognition as a
belligerent right? In what age do we live? Is justice dead? Where are
we? How happens it that the wires quiver with tidings of deeds worthy
only of the darkest years of Venetian conspiracy and shame?</p>
               <p pn="4">I said, we have got the flag back again on Sumter. So we have. But
only at half-mast. It reached the staff just in time to droop. Men
began to cheer--suddenly they turn to wailing. The triumph seems a
mockery. Victory waits recognition unheeded, for the bells are
tolling. He who made our success welcome is not here to share
it. ABRAHAM LINCOLN, the honored and beloved head of the nation, is no
more!</p>
               <p pn="4">My brethren, bear me record here to-day. This pulpit has never
uttered one timid, troubled word in these four years. I have not lost
heart for a moment in the essential righteousness of our cause, nor
confidence in the final success that would come to it. You will
misunderstand my language now, and mistake my temper, if you imagine I
am cowed into any wavering, startled into any irresolution, or grieved
into any distrust, by the terrible events of the hour. But I shall not
attempt to conceal from you that I am shocked more than ever before,
and under the cloud of God's providence as I never expected to be. I
do not know the meaning of this awful transaction. 
<pb n="5"/>
                  <figure entity="robinson5">
                     <figDesc>5th page of
Rev. Chas. S. Robinson's The Martyred President: A Sermon Preached in
the First Presbyterian Church, Brooklyn, N. Y.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
I could almost wish it was the custom to wear sack-cloth, and put
ashes on mourners' heads. All the day would I fittingly sit silent
under the shadow of a common grief with you. I speak truly when I say,
I have met no greater sorrow in my manly life than this.  "I behave
myself as though be had been my friend or brother; I bow down heavily,
as one that mourneth for his mother." And all this sensibility, I
know, you are sharing with me.</p>
               <p pn="5">The feeling which rests on each mind and heart to-day is not a
simple feeling. To us all it is, in some measure, undefined. I cannot
be of any real help to you, I fear, save in the way of giving you an
analysis of your grief, and suggesting the form of its expression.</p>
               <p pn="5">I.--Let me say, then, that in this complex mourning of heart is
found, first of all, our admiration of that great man's character,
whose sudden death has saddened the entire nation. Surely, you will
not need that I enter into argument to prove that these words of the
text I have chosen, applied to the counsellor from Arimathea in the
inspired record, are most fitting when applied to our late Chief
Magistrate.</p>
               <p pn="5">He was "a good man." Called by the great voice of the American
people to leave his rural home, and assume the highest honors it could
confer, his parting request to his old friends and neighbors was only
for their continuous prayers. With the sincerest humil-
<pb n="6"/>
                  <figure entity="robinson6">
                     <figDesc>6th page of
Rev. Chas. S. Robinson's The Martyred President: A Sermon Preached in
the First Presbyterian Church, Brooklyn, N. Y.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
ity, he accepted his place as the minister of the nation, and the
servant of God. He had no higher ambition than to know his duty and
perform it. He felt himself swept out into the current of a purpose,
as majestic in grandeur as it was celestial in origin; the sublime
purpose of Him to whom nations belong, to care for this western
Republic in the hour of its manifest peril. From that day to this, he
has never swerved from the line of his integrity. No man has ever been
maligned as he has; no man has ever outlived abuse as he has. When the
nation shall have laid his remains in the burial-yard of the village
where he lived, there will never be heard a hiss by his tomb-stone,
there, will be no trail of any serpent across his grave. Even now we
have hardly ceased to hear the dignified tones of his voice,
wonderfully pathetic, almost prophetic, as he told us, in the second
inaugural address, of the simplicity of his faith, the humility of his
estimate of himself, and his profound reliance upon the infinite
God.</p>
               <p pn="6">He was a "just" man. Through all these years it has been touching to
notice how implicitly the true-hearted believed, Abraham Lincoln to be
true. The mean hirelings of place, and the mere parasites of office,
kept out of his way. The demagogues and partisans grew passionate over
his perversity to their principles, and called him an impracticable
leader, because of his steadfast loyalty to truth and fairness as
between man and man. When one received injus-
<pb n="7"/>
                  <figure entity="robinson7">
                     <figDesc>7th page of
Rev. Chas. S. Robinson's The Martyred President: A Sermon Preached in
the First Presbyterian Church, Brooklyn, N. Y.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
tice, and could not, in the confusions of the times, make his
righteousness appear, how instinctively he thought of the President,
and knew, if he could only have a hearing from him, all would be
well. When military commanders failed, and popular clamor was raised
under the dangerous disappointment, calmly and generously the good man
waited till they should make another trial. He stood true to those,
who were seeking to undermine his power, with a magnanimity
sublime. Oh, the patience of that great, kind heart, in the days when
it cost something to be considerate! And now, after the smoke has
cleared away from two political battle-fields, fought more savagely
than any other such in our history, there comes to view no one act of
his at which a citizen will blush. His sun went down while to us it
yet seemed day; but at the evening time it was light. He died at the
height of his fame. All rancor of party has disappeared. The clouds
that dimmed his noon gather now, at the twilight, to, glow in his
praise.</p>
               <p pn="7">So much, then, is true; "he was a good man, and a just." But there
is a question, which our intelligent, Bible-reading, people  are wont
to ask when any one of their great men dies-was he a Christian man?
There is no reason why we should turn away, unanswered, an inquiry
like this. It is not an impertinent and obtrusive investigation of his
interior life. He made, no mystery of his faith. His own
<pb n="8"/>
                  <figure entity="robinson8">
                     <figDesc>8th page of
Rev. Chas. S. Robinson's The Martyred President: A Sermon Preached in
the First Presbyterian Church, Brooklyn, N. Y.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
tale of his religious experience is something like, this--coming in
more than one way, and attested with more than one witness:</p>
               <p pn="8">
                  <q pn="8" direct="unspecified">"When I left Springfield, I felt my utter dependence upon
God. The responsibility weighed heavily upon my heart. I knew I should
fall without a divine help. But I was not then a Christian. When my
child died, I felt that I needed the comfort of the Gospel. It was the
severest affliction that ever fell upon me. Then I wanted to be a
Christian. But never did I feel, that I reached the point, till I
wandered one day, alone, among the graves of the boys that fell at
Gettysburg. There, when I read the inscriptions, so full of hope and
faith, I began to think I loved and trusted Jesus as my Saviour."</q>
               </p>
               <p pn="8">Thus our image of this humble, noble, man rises on our vision
complete. Gifted with great intellectual power; proverbial for his
rectitude; bearing "honest" for his title as Aristides bore "just" for
his; affectionate, with all the instincts of common humanity, even to
the lowliest; fearless and brave; he added the crowning grace to his
memory with his unaffected piety as a Christian.</p>
               <p pn="8">II.--For all this the nation mourns his loss. But I am not mistaken
in believing there is an element in our sorrow here to-day, far more
subtle and experimental than mere admiration of his spotless
character. There is, in the second place, a feeling of personal
bereavement. Singularly identified with us all has this man come to
be. Test your heart now. Tell me, of all the leaders in civil life, of
all the commanders in the field, who has the hold upon your
<pb n="9"/>
                  <figure entity="robinson9">
                     <figDesc>9th page of
Rev. Chas. S. Robinson's The Martyred President: A Sermon Preached in
the First Presbyterian Church, Brooklyn, N. Y.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
manly affection that this great-hearted man of the people had? Your
ideal of him was like that of a relative -one of your
household. Never, till the hand of an assassin struck him, did you
know how dear he was. I see, in all this, that which makes me happy
and hopeful; here is a token of the infinite capacities of tenderness
in the spirit of the American people.</p>
               <p pn="9">I think to-day, as the fearful news is flashed across the land, of
the families that live in the valleys, and among the hills, and over
the prairies, to some member of which be has been kind and so has
endeared himself to all. How they will weep as for a brother beloved!
Village bells are knelling all over the continent. A great hand waved
darkly across the landscape, and swooped the banners down from
exultation into grief. Oh, we have never known how many letters his
own pen has written to bereaved wives and mourning mothers! When news
of a terrible death, in many an inconspicuous household, was to be
communicated, the President of the United States took time, from his
few hours of privacy, to send an epistle, so generous, so full of
grateful sympathy, so gentle and appreciative, that the wounded hearts
felt soothed, and bore the bereavement without breaking. He knew how
to say kind things so well, and loved to say them!</p>
               <p pn="9">I think of the soldiers, also, whose interests he watched like a
jealous parent. In these trying times
<pb n="10"/>
                  <figure entity="robinson10">
                     <figDesc>10th page of
Rev. Chas. S. Robinson's The Martyred President: A Sermon Preached in
the First Presbyterian Church, Brooklyn, N. Y.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
of partisanship and confusion there was always a likelihood of haste,
and consequent injustice, in the administration of military
tribunals. Many a man, innocent of alleged inadvertence or crime, was
unable to show it, and so was in peril of shame or death. Patiently
that busy President studied out complicated accounts; bent all his
legal ability to the investigation of contradictory testimony; read
the long, tedious documents on either side; simply determined that
every man should get his due; and then, beyond that, as much leniency
as was safe to give him. How the soldiers loved him! They are telling
to each other, this very day, stories of his kindness to them. Only
last week he spent the day that remained to him in Richmond, going
through the wards of the hospitals, saluting, with his warm-hearted
grasp, each wounded hero in turn; and, when they bad no hands to
offer, he laid his big palm on their foreheads, and thanked them in
the name of the country!</p>
               <p pn="10">I think, more than all, of the poor freedmen, when they hear of the
President's death. How they will wonder, and will wail! They called
him "Father," as if it were part of his name. Oh, they believed in
Abraham Lincoln! They expected him, as the Israelites did Moses. Some,
no doubt, imagined he was a deity. They were unsophisticated and
ignorant, and that good, kind man seemed so like a being from
heaven. They said he would come. They prayed he would come. They
waited for him
<pb n="11"/>
                  <figure entity="robinson11">
                     <figDesc>11th page of
Rev. Chas. S. Robinson's The Martyred President: A Sermon Preached in
the First Presbyterian Church, Brooklyn, N. Y.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
to come. And then he came! When those untutored sons of slavery saw
him in the streets of the rebel capital, after its capture, they
fairly blasphemed, without being aware of it. He seemed to them and
their children a second Messiah. He never broke a promise to their
hope. When they were certain he had uttered one word, they rested on
it, as they would on God's. He stood by the poor creatures his hand
had freed, under all obloquy and suspicion. He put his signature to a
parchment that made them men and women with souls and bodies. Then the
enfranchised millions opened their very souls to him, as if out under
the sunshine. His name was a spell to quiet or to rouse them. What
will they do, now he is dead! Alas! alas! for the weeping and the
wonder they will have when they know how he died!</p>
               <p pn="11">Thus, we all weep together. Christian resignation offers its high
consolations, and we have no spirit of murmuring or complaint. Yet,
none of us will deny that this is the severest blow, which, as a great
people, we have ever received. The nation has, twice before, lost its
Chief Magistrate by death; but there has been no mourning like this
to-day.</p>
               <p pn="11">III. --A third element in our grief, under this afflictive
dispensation of Providence, is the fear of impending calamity.  It is
impossible to free our minds of the deepest solicitude for the
future. Alas! we say, for the nation bereaved of its pilot, when
<pb n="12"/>
                  <figure entity="robinson12">
                     <figDesc>12th page of
Rev. Chas. S. Robinson's The Martyred President: A Sermon Preached in
the First Presbyterian Church, Brooklyn, N. Y.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
out in the midst of such a sea as this! Palinurus has been suddenly
swept, by a wave, from the helm.</p>
               <p pn="12">I suppose this anxiety is natural; and yet, I am sure,  it is
needless. Difficult questions are coming up. The practical wisdom of
our recognized leader was cutting knots which men's perversity kept
tying. We trusted him. We were knitting ourselves together in closer
confidence in his decisions. That shrewd, native judgment, that
clear-sighted penetration, that incorruptible integrity--oh how we
used to throw ourselves back upon qualities like these, and feel
secure! We found fault with him more than once; but, eventually, he
was justified in his course. We said he was slow; but he went as fast
as God did. He reasoned with logic that events taught him. We were
inordinately cast down under defeat; he kept us cheerful. We grew
boisterous under victory; he was calm himself, but glad to have us so
happy. He was never disheartened, never unduly elated. When he failed,
he became humbler; when be succeeded, he thanked God. When the way was
open, he was as alert as anybody; when the way was hedged up, he was
strong enough to sit still. By and bye we learned to know him well and
rest in him sublimely.  Meantime, he urged us to look beyond him. He
made us devout. Put a man on the busiest street-corner, and let him
keep looking upward, and he will gather a crowd that will all be
looking upward. So our President gave unaffected
<pb n="13"/>
                  <figure entity="robinson13">
                     <figDesc>5th page of
Rev. Chas. S. Robinson's The Martyred President: A Sermon Preached in
the First Presbyterian Church, Brooklyn, N. Y.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
praise to God, until we all began to sing with him. Spectacles like
these, which have been witnessed daily, have never been known in this
land before; Mammon has learned the doxologies belonging to God.</p>
               <p pn="13">When such a leader is taken suddenly away, there is nothing
unphilosophical in the feeling of utter dismay and apprehension that
men are apt to experience. But, in our case, all this is needless. My
brethren, I commend to your calm consideration, one solemn thought,
concerning the lessons of all history. Men are nothing but instruments
in the hands of their Maker, in working out his purposes. Just as a
sculptor needs now a chisel, now a file, now a graver, and never
thinks he must apologize or explain to us, who stand by to watch him,
why he drops one tool, or takes up another; for he is making a statue,
which he intends for a worthy immortality,--so the all-wise God,
carrying out his vast plans, assumes one man and lays aside another,
and never answers any of our curious questions while his "eternal
Thought moves on his undisturbed affairs." We are to blame seriously,
if we allow ourselves to be depressed with forebodings. God's rule, in
all this four years' war, has been, to bring to nought the things that
are, not by the things that are, but by the things that are not. We
have lived under the unvarying discipline of surprise. By this time,
we ought to have learned our lesson.</p>
               <p pn="13">With courage undiminished, therefore, let us be-
<pb n="14"/>
                  <figure entity="robinson14">
                     <figDesc>14th page of
Rev. Chas. S. Robinson's The Martyred President: A Sermon Preached in
the First Presbyterian Church, Brooklyn, N. Y.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
lieve that God will fit this coming man for the duties of his
unexpected office. Be on the alert now for the discovery of some new
purpose. The infinite plans of the Almighty are shifting their phase
for some disclosure that will relieve our embarrassment. It is
expedient that even such offences as these should come. There can be
no doubt that God means to make good out of this evil.  And the
question. is this: Will you and I be quiet in all the pain of our
bereavement, if we are only sure that the event will be overruled to
the benefit of the cause, the race, the nation? Will we accept the
counsel of Caiaphas as possibly adapted to our crisis: "Ye know
nothing at all; nor consider that it is expedient that one man should
die for the people, and that the whole nation perish not?" Perhaps, in
this very alarm for the future, there will be found a healthier spirit
for us all.</p>
               <p pn="14">IV.--For, in the fourth place, I remark, we find, as an element in
our mourning to-day, a deep-seated indignation at the horrible crime
which has been committed. Humanity sickens and shudders at the
diabolical ingenuity, the malignant hatred, of this culminating act of
the rebellion. If there ever was a time in which to obey the command,
"Be ye angry, and sin not," that time has come now. "There was no such
deed done nor seen from the day that the Children of Israel came up
out of the land of Egypt unto this day; consider of it, take advice,
and speak your minds."</p>
               <pb n="15"/>
               <p pn="15">
                  <figure entity="robinson15">
                     <figDesc>15th page of
Rev. Chas. S. Robinson's The Martyred President: A Sermon Preached in
the First Presbyterian Church, Brooklyn, N. Y.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <p pn="15">Let a vast public sentiment be aroused and organized, that shall
exhibit this vile wickedness in its true light. Let us invoke
Christendom to make it an eternal hissing. With a recoil of feeling so
violent that it wearies my will, and shocks my very being, with
uttermost loathing for an offence so abominable; seeing in it that
keen, fine relish of depravity that marks it not only as devilish, but
one of the master works of the prince of devils, I stand simply
appalled-wondering, with unspeakable wonder, how it can be accepted by
any creature wearing the form of civilized humanity! It is an outrage
on the community, whose tolerance it defies. It is an insult to
decency, a rebuke to forbearance, an offence unto God. It is without
the power of language to reach the condemnation it merits. The words
of denunciation die on my lips in their own feebleness. It is with an
affecting sense of gratitude to God that I discover the positive
poverty of my mother-tongue in epithets of vileness befitting its
description. As much as in you is, live peaceably with all men; but
there ought to be a voice of opinion so stern, so outspoken, that  no
man of credited decency should stand tamely by and hear a crime, so
unparalleled in its baseness, even extenuated.</p>
               <p pn="15">Is the world going back into savagery? Is this Christian land to
become the rival of Dahomey? This is no isolated act. The history of
this slaveholders' rebellion is full of such. Again and again
<pb n="16"/>
                  <figure entity="robinson16">
                     <figDesc>16th page of
Rev. Chas. S. Robinson's The Martyred President: A Sermon Preached in
the First Presbyterian Church, Brooklyn, N. Y.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
have the lives of our chief men been threatened with the dirk, the
bullet, and the knife. Poison has been put in their food. Their homes
have been entered by spies. Their steps have been way-laid in the
streets. And our common people have fared no better. Quiet villages
have been invaded, and women and children shot down with fiendish
glee. Cars, crowded with unsuspicious travellers, have been thrown
from the track.  Public buildings have been fired over a whole city at
once. And all this under the shadow of authority claimed through a
paper commission. Yet the nation has kept its temper. The spectacle of
a great people, thus outraged beyond a parallel, yet so patient and
forbearing, has been sublime enough to make our enemies wonder. They
have called our magnanimity meanness, and complimented us upon our
manifold spaniel-like virtues, with sarcasm that burnt in upon manly
sensibility like fire.</p>
               <p pn="16">This assassination is the earliest reply which chivalry has had to
make to forbearance unmeasured and friendliness almost fraternal. Now,
let us have done with it! Talk to me no more of "our misguided
brethren." Some are misguided--and it is those who misguide them I
denounce. Cain was brother to Abel.  Relationship is a perilous thing
when it says, "Art thou in health, my brother," and then stabs under
the fifth rib. Talk to me no more of the same race, educated at the
same colleges, born of
<pb n="17"/>
                  <figure entity="robinson17">
                     <figDesc>17th page of
Rev. Chas. S. Robinson's The Martyred President: A Sermon Preached in
the First Presbyterian Church, Brooklyn, N. Y.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
the same blood." Satan was of the same race as Gabriel, and educated
at the same celestial school of love and grace; but one became a
rebel, and between them ever thereafter was "a great gulf fixed." He
cannot be brother of mine, he belongs to no race of mine, who, in the
foul cause of human bondage, fights with a rural massacre, makes war
with midnight arson, and crowns his unmanly barbarity with stabbing a
sick man in his bed, and shooting an unarmed husband in the very sight
of his wife!</p>
               <p pn="17">Let no one deem this violence unnecessary. They tell us that none of
our utterances are lost; the vibrations of the air on which they fall
perpetuate them into an eternity of circles, spreading wider and
wider. If I am ever again to meet these denunciations of mine,
conscientiously spoken in this Christian pulpit, let me find them in
company with a declaration that will explain them. There are in this
community, to-day, men and <hi rend="italic">women</hi>--God forgive
them!--nurtured under the hot debasements and vile luxuries of the
slave system, sojourning here on our charitable sufferance, in order
meanly to escape the perils of the ruinous war they have helped to
incite, who clap their hands in applause of this murder! I think, in
serious self-defence, we are to see that this thing is ended. This
wickedness clamors for retributive judgment, and invokes the wrath of
God.</p>
               <p pn="17">V.-Thus I am led, naturally, to speak of a fifth element in our
feeling of mourning to-day; the pro-
<pb n="18"/>
                  <figure entity="robinson18">
                     <figDesc>18th page of
Rev. Chas. S. Robinson's The Martyred President: A Sermon Preached in
the First Presbyterian Church, Brooklyn, N. Y.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
found conviction of necessity that the law of the land should now take
its course in relation to all the aiders and abettors of this infamous
rebellion. There was, perhaps, needed one more proof of the
unutterable sin of treason. Here has it been flashed out upon us, like
the final stroke of a departing thunderstorm, the least expected, but
the most fearfully destructive of all that have fallen. We have been
growing more and more loose in our estimates of guilt. We were
catching from each other a spirit of sentimentalism that boded no
good. Tired of war, longing for quiet, eager for trade, sickened with
bloodshed, we were ready to say, let the criminals be pardoned, let
the penalties of law be remitted. The next act in our national history
was, in all likelihood, to be a general amnesty
proclamation. Suddenly, the band which would have signed it was
smitten down into death.  Then our eyes were opened to the fixed
unalterable malignity in the temper of our foes. A great conspiracy is
disclosed. Murder is done at the capital. Our beloved President
becomes a victim to the very magnanimity he was inculcating. Warned
fully of the peril, he would not  believe human nature could be so
base. He trusted, and was betrayed. The entire government was menaced,
in the moment of its open-hearted proffer of good will.</p>
               <p pn="18">We are satisfied that all this is perilous pusillanimity now. There
is no fitness of generosity to malignants venomous as these. So, while
our hearts
<pb n="19"/>
                  <figure entity="robinson19">
                     <figDesc>19th page of
Rev. Chas. S. Robinson's The Martyred President: A Sermon Preached in
the First Presbyterian Church, Brooklyn, N. Y.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
are chilled, their affection hurried back on themselves in curdling
horror, with pity ineffable, and sorrow that cannot be repressed, we
are united in saying, let the will of the law be done! When there was
rebellion in heaven, the rebels were punished. God sent the fallen
angels to hell. We are not to find fault with that kind of
administration. Men can forgive. I do not believe there is one unkind
sentiment in any heart in the house of God this day. We draw a
distinction, world-wide, between a crime and a criminal. The one we
denounce, the other we pity. But the majesty of law must be
vindicated. No puritan had a right to be the defender of Guy
Fawkes. No patriot had a right to screen Benedict Arnold from
justice. Let there be now no violence. Let the common people be
spared. But, on the track of the villains that have opened this
insurrection, and urged it along its bloody track even to this
dreadful consummation, let the footsteps of justice follow swiftly,
relentlessly.</p>
               <p pn="19">It may, possibly, be said, by some, that this assassination of the
officers of government is a mere act of madness done by a brace of
frantic fanatics; and that it is not equitable and fair to hold a
whole people responsible for its wickedness.</p>
               <p pn="19">Let it be said, in reply, that the tidings of this murder, going
into the ranks of rebellion, will be hailed with a howl of gladness
and satisfaction equal to the yell in Pandemonium, when Satan seduced
<pb n="20"/>
                  <figure entity="robinson20">
                     <figDesc>20th page of
Rev. Chas. S. Robinson's The Martyred President: A Sermon Preached in
the First Presbyterian Church, Brooklyn, N. Y.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
Adam, and buried a race in ruin. It will never be disowned, save by a
few of the most exposed leaders, who, seeing in it their own ruin,
will repent, not like Peter, for sin, but like Judas, for the results
of sin. Even now, the instincts of every rebel sympathizer are on the
alert to befriend the assassins, and block the way of
justice. Furthermore, let it be said, that this crime happens to be
conspicuous and heart-rending, because it has marked the nation's idol
for its victim; but it is only one of fifty thousand murders, actual,
intelligent, committed during the last two years by the parties in
power through the revolted States. And these murders in the prisons
are, every one of them, just so much the more diabolical, as
starvation slowly is more horrible than the quicker death of the
bullet. The spirit is the same in all cases. This wickedness is the
legitimate outgrowth of that system of slavery which originated the
rebellion, and debauched, from time immemorial, all the finer
instincts of man.</p>
               <p pn="20">Hence, there is no revenge in the popular heart to-day, but only
retribution. We pity the malefactors; we pray for them; but in this
determination we are fixed-let the majesty of the law be vindicated
upon them as traitors; let justice pursue them, one by one; let the
gates of the world be closed to their search for asylum; let judgment
follow on as implacable as a doom.</p>
               <p pn="20">VI.--I might well pause here, in the enumeration
<pb n="21"/>
                  <figure entity="robinson21">
                     <figDesc>21st page of
Rev. Chas. S. Robinson's The Martyred President: A Sermon Preached in
the First Presbyterian Church, Brooklyn, N. Y.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
of elements in the feeling we are all cherishing under the pressure of
this heart-rending sorrow. But there is one more, which I detect in my
own heart, and know is in the hearts of my hearers. We desire to know
what instruction the all-wise God has intended us to receive. We would
inquire for His counsels, and humbly learn of Him. My office, as a
Christian minister, will be discharged this morning, when I have
sought to point out to you some few of the lessons forced into vivid
illumination by this terrible dispensation of Providence.</p>
               <p pn="21">1. First of all, then, let us learn here how history is composed. I
am certain we have no proper conception of the magnitude of an event
like this. We are too near it to discover its proportions. Travellers
tell us they are always disappointed with the earliest glimpse of vast
mountains. Standing close under the shadow of awful forms, so peerless
in majesty, they have no adequate notions of their loftiness and
amazing mass. These need distance on the landscape to be truly
appreciated. So an event like this is never really reverenced as it
should be. It needs time for the free play of the imagination. We are
all unconscious of the spectacle we are to present to posterity.</p>
               <p pn="21">The dreadful deed, which has filled our minds with horror, will be a
growing vision of weird wickedness, shining with a strange luridness
of its own, as one of the wildest tragedies of the world's most un-
<pb n="22"/>
                  <figure entity="robinson22">
                     <figDesc>22nd page of
Rev. Chas. S. Robinson's The Martyred President: A Sermon Preached in
the First Presbyterian Church, Brooklyn, N. Y.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
welcome remembrance. It ranks with the suicide of Cleopatra, the death
of Caesar, the murder of William the Silent, the conspiracy of
Catiline, the gunpowder plot of Guy Fawkes, the imperial incidents in
the wide empire of crime. To us the event seems simply personal; our
views of it are necessarily narrow. Our leader has fallen. Our
government has been menaced. But we only speculate upon its immediate
results. The criminals will soon be apprehended. The insurrection will
end, and all the excitement will subside. But when the mighty future
shall receive the inheritance, it will be weighed by other balances,
and estimated more truly.</p>
               <p pn="22">Thus history selects and perpetuates its own materials. Each
thought, each word, each deed, each flash of sentiment, each outbreak
of passion, each exercise of influence, enters into the grand
aggregate of human recollection and intelligence, which we call our
Age. Out of this the pen of unerring history compiles its annals.</p>
               <lg type="stanza">
                  <l>For Humanity sweeps onward; where to-day the martyr stands,</l>
                  <l>On the morrow crouches Judas, with the silver in his hands;</l>
                  <l>Far
in front the cross stands ready, and the crackling fagots burn,</l>
                  <l>While the hooting mob of yesterday in silent awe return</l>
                  <l>To glean
up the scattered ashes into History's golden urn."</l>
               </lg>
               <p pn="22">2. In the second place, let us learn the essential iniquity and
barbarism there is in any system of human oppression. It was long ago
remarked by Lamartine, that no man ever bound a chain around
<pb n="23"/>
                  <figure entity="robinson23">
                     <figDesc>23rd page of
Rev. Chas. S. Robinson's The Martyred President: A Sermon Preached in
the First Presbyterian Church, Brooklyn, N. Y.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
the neck of his fellow-man, without God's binding a chain of equal
links around his own. Whoever debases the image of God will certainly
become debased. This thought receives an illustration here that
amounts almost to a demonstration. This crime is the manifest outshoot
of American slavery.</p>
               <p pn="23">I suppose no one remains now who doubts that all this aggregated
mass of abomination, this summation of villanies, whose tide of murky
violence is rolling itself along before our weary eyes, had its
fountain-head in the malignant ambition of a few men, who started the
stream of revolution in order to waft themselves into continuous
power. These miserable criminals, whom justice is pursuing with eager
scent, are but the merest minute-hands on the outermost dial of that
popular sentiment which they represent. The spring that has set them
in motion, the mechanism that gave them all their power, even the
delicate balances that have timed their present success, are out of
sight, yet easily discoverable in the dark intricacies of that
domestic and political life based on the humiliation of a feebler
race. You may tear these index-pointers away, but the clockwork will
run on. There will still remain the secret progress of debasement, on
the bold face of which they have happened to become conspicuous. You
will gain nothing till you tear the hideous system to pieces, and
break the spring that lies coiled within it.</p>
               <p pn="23">What is this crime? Nothing new, surely; only
<pb n="24"/>
                  <figure entity="robinson24">
                     <figDesc>24th page of
Rev. Chas. S. Robinson's The Martyred President: A Sermon Preached in
the First Presbyterian Church, Brooklyn, N. Y.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
more public. It is one of a million crimes, each of which God has
seen. The same reckless imperiousness of will, that has so many times
struck at laws, has now struck at the Executive of law-that is
all. The same thwarted passion, that has more than once shot a slave
unpunished, now has shot a President-that is all. That same spirit is
unsubdued. It is ready to fly in the face of anything that stands in
its way. To continue a system of social life that now has become a
necessity in a measure, as a minister to laziness and lust, these
people have dismembered the church, divided the republic, fought their
own brothers, and at last taken to murder and assassination. No one
can fail to see that there is one single line of connection running
all through the history of this infamous rebellion. The pride of
power, engendered by the tyranny, petty at first, over the unprotected
black race, has betrayed these miserable wretches into the mistake of
supposing they could lord it over the white race-that is all.</p>
               <p pn="24">This latest crime is more showy, but the hearts are no blacker than
before. And the hearts have been made black, by the system. How else
will you explain this appalling fact; there are <hi rend="italic">women</hi>, with babes in their arms, who will declare
that this murder in cold blood of a man in the presence of his wife is
<hi rend="italic">chivalrous</hi>! This is monstrous, when judged by any
system of philosophy. There is but one solution of the mystery:
underlying all the ferocity of such a
<pb n="25"/>
                  <figure entity="robinson25">
                     <figDesc>25th page of
Rev. Chas. S. Robinson's The Martyred President: A Sermon Preached in
the First Presbyterian Church, Brooklyn, N. Y.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
sentiment, is found the subtle working of mere pride of caste. Slavery
has debased the feminine and human sentiments with which they were
born. That code of morals always did tend to barbarism. The young men
of the South were corrupt before the war. The women were brutalized in
the finer feelings of natural decency. They would send women to be
stripped and whipped by men for a price. Passion grows wild with mere
indulgence. Hence it is that a deed combining so much of execrable
meanness with so much of hellish cruelty, finds women unsexed enough
to applaud it! Home on the diabolical system it represents, do I
soberly urge the responsibility of this murder. It is high time to
have done with it, root and branches.</p>
               <p pn="25">3. Once more: Let us learn here to-day the power of martyrdom in
fixing great principles. President LINCOLN has been useful in his
life, far beyond what falls to the common lot of even the most
patriotic and public-spirited men. But his death has confirmed his
usefulness-made it illustrious, influential, and immortal.</p>
               <p pn="25">In the natural course of time his period of official service would
have ended. His administration of the government would have been
canvassed cautiously, and, perhaps, uncharitably criticised, and, by
some parties, condemned. By this sudden, tragic close of it, however,
it has been forced into prominence. It will now be marked forever. All
the principles it
<pb n="26"/>
                  <figure entity="robinson26">
                     <figDesc>26th page of
Rev. Chas. S. Robinson's The Martyred President: A Sermon Preached in
the First Presbyterian Church, Brooklyn, N. Y.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
has aimed to establish are settled hereafter beyond a
peradventure. The documents he has added to the archives of the nation
are sealed with blood. This republic will take no step backwards from
the vantage-ground to which he had led the banner of its
sovereignty. Even his policy will have weightier influence than that
proposed by any living man. The noble archer has fallen in death,
before he could really know how princely were the shots he made; but
the arrows he sped latest are yet out in the air, over the sea, and
will strike unerringly the mark. And when they who stand nearest to
the spot where the shafts bang quivering, look around to discover
whose was the sinewy strength that sent them so forcefully and so
true, they will find that another hand, just as firm, has assumed the
bow, and another eye, just as keen, has discerned the same target.</p>
               <p pn="26">They who oppose an honest man living, are ever among the first to
honor him dead. Nobody dares uproot a standard planted by a loved
leader who poured out his life at the foot of its staff. Perhaps it
was this which was needed to bring our people together
permanently. Perhaps this was the essential condition of our
restoration to unity, that we become reconciled over an open grave. It
may be that party-spirit will yield now, and bury the bitterness of
its animosity in a martyr's tomb.</p>
               <p pn="26">You will recall the touching fable of Roman history. A vast seam
opened in the land, in the very
<pb n="27"/>
                  <figure entity="robinson27">
                     <figDesc>27th page of
Rev. Chas. S. Robinson's The Martyred President: A Sermon Preached in
the First Presbyterian Church, Brooklyn, N. Y.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
midst of the Forum, disclosing a yawning abyss which they could not
fill with rocks or with soil. At last the soothsayers declared that
the commonwealth could be preserved only by closing the gulf; and the
gulf could be closed only by devoting to the gods, who had opened it,
what constituted the principal glory and strength of the people. At
this all stood aghast. But there was one Curtius, a youth of high
birth, who, hearing the deliverance, demanded of his countrymen
whether their arms and their courage were not the most valuable
possessions they owned. They gave him assent with their silence. And
then the heroic warrior, arraying himself in full armor, and mounting
his horse, rode headlong into the chasm; whereupon the earth
immediately closed, and over the memorable spot swept a placid lake
bearing his name.</p>
               <p pn="27">Shall we say that now our divided country will come together again,
when he who seemed the glory and strength of the American people has
gone down in the breach? Shall not his sacrifice avail for
propitiation to that foul spirit of sectional pride which rent the
land asunder?</p>
               <p pn="27">4. And this leads me on to mention a final lesson. We see now the
inevitable triumph and perpetuity of our cause. We are not
hero-worshippers in any degree. We never were. But we believe in
God. We entered upon this war not willingly, not of our own accord. We
have been fighting for a principle. 
<pb n="28"/>
                  <figure entity="robinson28">
                     <figDesc>28th page of
Rev. Chas. S. Robinson's The Martyred President: A Sermon Preached in
the First Presbyterian Church, Brooklyn, N. Y.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
That we have never surrendered nor forgotten. What we loved this
leader for was what we deemed truth to our cause.</p>
               <p pn="28">What is our cause? It is easier to say what it is not; for its
essence is negative. Whatever this crime of assassination is, whatever
it represents, whatever it aimed at, whatever was the spirit that
prompted it, whatever may be now wickedly offered in its apology--just
<hi rend="italic">not that</hi> is our cause. And as that crime, in
spirit, in purpose, in instigation, was all in the interest of human
bondage, so our cause embraces all that is antagonistic to that
system. There never has been but one issue in this terrible
contest. Underneath all these evident questions has been lying one
which some of us studiously labored to ignore; and that was concerning
the dignity of universal labor, and the absolute equality of all races
before the common law. He who, at this late day, shuts his eyes to
this fact, is neither intelligent nor wise. We have fought for an open
Bible, a free school, an unfettered press, and a Scriptural pulpit.</p>
               <p pn="28">In all the doctrines ostentatiously put forth by our foes-States'
rights, uncontaminated blood, family pride, sectional
independence-there has ever been this keen, sharp liking for slavery
as a social system. They recognized it as a kind of secret zest among
themselves; as voluptuaries recognize, with an understood leer, a
favorite lust; as wine-bibbers recognize the subtle flavor of an
indescribable liquor. Our
<pb n="29"/>
                  <figure entity="robinson29">
                     <figDesc>29th page of
Rev. Chas. S. Robinson's The Martyred President: A Sermon Preached in
the First Presbyterian Church, Brooklyn, N. Y.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
cause consists in precise opposition to that. We, therefore, have
stood for the rights of men, the truth of the Gospel, the principles
of humanity, the integrity of the Union, the power of Christian people
to govern themselves, the indefeasible equality of all the creatures
of God in natural conditions of existence, no matter what may be the
color of their skin. So the nations of the world have looked upon us,
and held us responsible. We were the enemies of all class-systems,
castes, and aristocracies. We were the champions of manhood in all
that was noble, of womanhood in all that was pure. This has been, and
still is, our cause.</p>
               <p pn="29">And what I call you to learn now is, that this cause is safe. A
martyr's blow has sealed the covenant we are making with
posterity. Oh, the glories of our immediate prospect of usefulness in
the years to come! The republic is secure. The Union is confirmed as a
perpetual federation of States. The peril through which we have just
passed has no parallel. Our government, as an entirety, was aimed at
with one savage blow. Such a stroke, on any other nation, would have
rocked Christendom to its centre. Yet our nation is untremulous as the
primeval granite. The most delicate balances of commercial life show
not even the semblance of noticeable variation, even when this
violence of a ton's weight all at once jars the beam! Our cause is
eternally secure!</p>
               <p pn="29">Think, then, as we close our meditation upon this
<pb n="30"/>
                  <figure entity="robinson30">
                     <figDesc>30th page of
Rev. Chas. S. Robinson's The Martyred President: A Sermon Preached in
the First Presbyterian Church, Brooklyn, N. Y.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
martyr-life, how strangely God has overruled much that seemed so
destructive to our good. On that very day-they call it Good
Friday-there is annually represented, in the Sistine Chapel, at Rome,
the disaster of the world when the Redeemer was crucified. Thirteen
lamps are lit in the darkness, ranged in pyramidal form, the topmost
one conceived to be the symbol of Messiah. A low, mournful chant from
the Lamentations continues to echo through the building, while one
light after another is extinguished at intervals, until twelve are
gone out. Only the loftiest and the brightest remains; and still the
chant moans on. Then the last one is struck, and every glimmer
perishes in total gloom. Thereupon the music ends. A moment succeeds,
of unutterable oppression--rayless and stifled--and then one voice
breaks the silence; a voice wailing, piercing, as if from a crushed
and broken heart, lifting the burden of the Miserere; the grief of the
race over its Helper and its Hope.</p>
               <p pn="30">Fitting seems the symbol to us now, as we look only on the earthly
side of this tremendous loss; on that same day, while the shadows were
gathering in the chapel of that seven-hilled city, our light appeared
to go out, and the nation was in the gloom.</p>
               <p pn="30">But to-day, let us look on the heavenly side. How sweet and calm it
is to think of that great, brave heart, this Easter Sabbath! He is not
here, but risen. Far beyond the sound of battle, far beyond the
turmoil of state, in the infinite realms of gladness,
<pb n="31"/>
                  <figure entity="robinson31">
                     <figDesc>31th page of
Rev. Chas. S. Robinson's The Martyred President: A Sermon Preached in
the First Presbyterian Church, Brooklyn, N. Y.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
that troubled mind has found its rest. Mourned, as never before martyr
was mourned; loved, as never before statesman was loved; honored, as
never before patriot was honored; he has gone down to a spotless
grave. High over all human passion that disembodied spirit stands,
free as the thought that follows him; the eye of faith seems to behold
him even now on the radiant plain of eternity; on either side falls
away every official adornment; the soul of the Christian man bends in
all humility before his Maker's presence, saved by grace; saved, not
because he wore the robes of the highest station on the globe; saved,
not because of his rare gifts of affection or intellect; saved, not by
reason of the blessed deeds he had done; saved, merely because of his
faith in the Saviour, that he learned by the graves of the boys that
fell at Gettysburg; and, as you gaze after him, with a subdued and
tearful heart, you can only pay him the tribute that trembles on the
lip that speaks it--</p>
               <p pn="31">"HE WAS A GOOD MAN, AND A JUST!"</p>
            </div2>
         </div1>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI.2>
