<?xml version="1.0"?>
<TEI.2>
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt n="Memorial Sermons">
            <title>Memorial Sermons</title>
            <author>Webb, Edwin B.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Compiled and edited by</resp>
               <name>Beck
Center</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent/>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Lewis H. Beck Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Emory University</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Atlanta,
Georgia</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>1996 Emory
University. Permission is  granted to download, transmit, or otherwise
reproduce,  distribute or display the contributions to the work
claimed by Emory University for non-profit educational  purposes,
provided this header is included in its entirety.   For inquiries
about commercial uses, contact the Director,  Pitts Theology Library,
Emory University, Atlanta, Georgia 30322</p>
            </availability>
            <date>1999</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Lincoln
Sermons Project</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Webb, Edwin
B. Memorial Sermons.  The Capture of Richmond.  Some of the Results of
the War.  The Assassination of the President.  Boston: Press of
Geo. C. Rand &amp; Avery, 3 Cornhill. 1865.</bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This text
derives from the Special Collections  of Pitts Theology Library, Emory
University, and is produced in  collaboration with the Lewis H. Beck
Center a, the Emory  Preservation Office, and Pitts Theology
Library.</p>
            <p>TRANSCRIBER: Lewis H. Beck Center and Emory University 
Preservation Office.</p>
            <p>PRODUCER:  BookLab, Inc., 1606 Headway Circle, 
Suite 100, Austin, TX 78754</p>
            <p>CAPTURE DEVICE: XEROX DocuImage 620S flatbed scanner</p>
            <p>CAPTURE DETAILS: Scanner software: XEROX ScanTool 
version 4.2.3; no gamma correction; images are all bitonal.</p>
            <p>CHANGE HISTORY: Using the Adobe Photoshop Batch Processor, 
we interpolated  the original TIFF files to 8-bit grays, 
and altered the resolution to 144 dpi, producing screen 
images twice the original size.  We then saved them in 
JPEG format.  We produced GIF thumbnails from the JPEG files.</p>
            <p>RESOLUTION: 600 ppi</p>
            <p>COMPRESSION: Resolution 144 per inch with Constrain 
Properties to 72 per inch.</p>
            <p>SOURCE: Original documents.</p>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>1999</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Scott Ellis</name>
               <resp>Staff</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <item>SGML tags inserted in compliance
with TEI guidelines using TEILITE</item>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div1 id="webb.001" n="Memorial Sermons" type="text">
            <head pn="1"> 
               <bibl> 
                  <title>Memorial
Sermons</title> 
                  <date>[N/A]</date> 
                  <pubPlace>Shawmut Church,
Boston</pubPlace> 
                  <author>Webb, Edwin B.</author> 
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Boston</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Press of Geo. C. Rand &amp;
Avery</publisher>
                     <date>1865</date>
                  </imprint> 
               <idno type="ark">http://pid.emory.edu/ark:/25593/15rgk</idno></bibl> 
            </head>
            <p pn="1">
               <figure entity="webb1">
                  <figDesc>1st page of Edwin B. Webb's
Memorial Sermons.</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <p pn="1">MEMORIAL SERMONS.</p>
            <p pn="1">THE CAPTURE OF RICHMOND.</p>
            <p pn="1">SOME OF THE RESULTS OF THE WAR.</p>
            <p pn="1">THE ASSASSINATION OF THE PRESIDENT.</p>
            <p pn="1">BY</p>
            <p pn="1">EDWIN B. WEBB,</p>
            <p pn="1">PASTOR OF SHAWMUT CHURCH, BOSTON.</p>
            <p pn="1">BOSTON:</p>
            <p pn="1">PRESS OF GEO. C. RAND &amp; AVERY, 3 CORNHILL.</p>
            <p pn="1">1865.</p>
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p pn="2">
               <figure entity="webb2">
                  <figDesc>2nd page of
Edwin B. Webb's Memorial Sermons.</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p pn="3">
               <figure entity="webb3">
                  <figDesc>3rd page of
Edwin B. Webb's Memorial Sermons.</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <p pn="3">BOSTON, April 19, 1865. </p>
            <p pn="3">REV. E. B. WEBB.</p>
            <p pn="3">Dear Sir,--</p>
            <p pn="3">The undersigned beg leave to ask a copy of each of the
discourses delivered by you in the Shawmut Church on the mornings of
the 9th, 13th, and 16th inst., for the press.</p>
            <p pn="3">Approving the sentiments which they contain, and believing them
adapted to perpetuate the memory of those <hi rend="italic">momentous
events</hi> which followed in such rapid succession, and which gave to
a great nation so much joy and such intense sorrow, we hope you will
not deny our request.</p>
            <p pn="3">Very
respectfully yours,</p>
            <p pn="3">L. R. SHELDON,
                                                                                                             <lb/>DANIEL
HARWOOD,<lb/>
OSBORNE HOWES, <lb/>CHARLES HUTCHINGS,<lb/>
C. A. PUTNAM, <lb/>MOSES W. RICHARDSON, <lb/>
               <hi rend="italic">Committee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p pn="3">BOSTON,
April 20, 1865.</p>
            <p pn="3">GENTLEMEN, --</p>
            <p pn="3">The sermons for which you so kindly ask are very humble and hasty
efforts; but, indorsed by a large and intelligent congregation of
citizens, they may help to shape the popular opinion, and to record
the fearful struggle between loyalty and treason, and also the sudden
transition from one extreme of unutterable feeling to another, through
which we have passed in these times which have no parallel in national
history.  They are, therefore, submitted to your disposal.</p>
            <p pn="3">With ever-increasing affection,</p>
            <p pn="3">I am faithfully your pastor,</p>
            <p pn="3">E. B. WEBB.</p>
            <p pn="3">To L. R. SHELDON, M. D.., DANIEL HARWOOD, OSBORNE HOWES, CHARLES
HUTCHINGS, C. A. PUTNAM, MOSES W. RICHARDSON, Esqrs.,
<lb/>
               <hi rend="italic">Committee.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="4"/>
<!-- blank page -->
<!--            <p>
               <figure entity="webb4">
                  <figDesc>4th page of
Edwin B. Webb's Memorial Sermons.</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p> -->
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p pn="5">
               <figure entity="webb5">
                  <figDesc>5th page of
Edwin B. Webb's Memorial Sermons.</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <div2 id="webb.002" n="THE CAPTURE OF RICHMOND." type="sermon">
               <head pn="5">THE CAPTURE OF RICHMOND.</head>
               <epigraph pn="5">
                  <p pn="5">"The Lord is my strength and song, and he is become my
salvation: he is my God, and I will prepare him a habitation; my
fathers' God, and I will exalt him." --EXODUS XV. 2.</p>
               </epigraph>
               <p pn="5">THE past has been a week of great joy. Not one city, not one State,
but the whole loyal North, from Maine to California, has been
jubilant. Not waiting for official requisitions, the
people--spontaneously, unitedly, universally--have given thanks to God
in prayer, have united in songs of thanksgiving, have thrown their
flags and streamers to the winds, have made their houses from attic to
cellar luminous with expressions of gladness; and at the call of
authority, citizens have assembled with bands of music, amid the peal
of cannon, with waving banners, in vast crowds, to congratulate each
other, and give utterance to the general feeling of exultation.</p>
               <p pn="5">And manifestly this has not been a. mechanical self-excitation: men
have been moved; hearts have been oppressed with feelings that words
could not utter; and the shouts of living, sympathetic masses have
been called for, and Te Deums with full orchestra,
<pb n="6"/>
                  <figure entity="webb6">
                     <figDesc>6th page of Edwin B. Webb's
Memorial Sermons.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
to express even partially what every one has felt. We have rejoiced
before, but then with fear and dark forebodings; now with no vague,
oppressive apprehensions, with no reservations, but with full and deep
respiration, and unclouded hope. Men feel that the foundations are
sure, that the instincts of a loyal people are right, that justice
lives, that God reigns.</p>
               <p pn="6">And what is the occasion of all this gladness and congratulation?
Just that which called forth the Song of Moses from which our text is
taken: "Thy right hand, 0 Lord, is become glorious in power: thy right
hand, 0 Lord, hath dashed in pieces the enemy."</p>
               <p pn="6">A little more than a year ago, a modest, reticent, but able and
magnanimous commander was called to Washington, and made
commander-in-chief of all our armies. Up to that time, the strength of
the Rebellion had been once or twice checked, but never humbled. The
leader of those rebel legions had never met his master. He was still
abroad, free, and able to move when and where he pleased. When he
chose, he fortified and lay behind his works; when he chose, he
invested the capital or invaded the loyal States. His power was
unbroken, his spirit undaunted, his limbs unfettered.</p>
               <p pn="6">With a quiet determination, our new commander said that <hi rend="italic">General Lee must be controlled</hi>, his army must be
conquered. The strength of the Rebellion is here. Operations
aggressive and successful
<pb n="7"/>
                  <figure entity="webb7">
                     <figDesc>7th page of Edwin B. Webb's
Memorial Sermons.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
elsewhere are worthless while the heart of the Confederacy is
untouched. Quietly but efficiently, as the forces in Nature accomplish
their end, General Grant set himself to his unmatched and terrible
work. The sight is sublime, as, with his carpet bag in his hand, and a
single attendant at his side, he crossed the Potomac to undertake and
execute his masterful design. On the first secular day of May, 1864,
he crossed the Rapidan to find and fight the enemy,--the enemy of the
Republic and the enemy of mankind. What work followed, for days and
nights and weeks and months, in the Wilderness, at Spottsylvania, and
all the way down to Cold Harbor, across the Pamunkey, and finally
across the James, and to the environs of Richmond and Petersburg, you
all know. How many brave fellows found a bloody grave; how many
thousands found the hospitals only to sleep there their final sleep;
how many more thousands found themselves sent home with honorable
wounds,--will be known wherever history is read. Such fighting, so
determined, prolonged, and persistent; such courage; such fortitude;
such marching; such endurance of heat and wet, incessant fatigues and
bloody battles,--the world never saw.</p>
               <p pn="7">And how much we owe to that tenacity of purpose which never let go
its hold, and never was
<pb n="8"/>
                  <figure entity="webb8">
                     <figDesc>8th page of Edwin B. Webb's
Memorial Sermons.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
diverted from its aim, which fought till the blood stood in pools on
the ground, and never failed to follow up an advantage,--is not known
yet, as we believe. It evinces the true greatness of the
Lieutenant-general to sit there before Petersburg in grim patience,
planning brilliant campaigns for popular leaders, and praising them
with shotted salutes for their splendid execution; doing nothing
himself that the world can see or praise or photograph. There is
something of moral heroism as well as of intellectual greatness, in
the man who thus silently holds the organized military strength of the
Rebellion with the powerful grasp of one hand, and with the other
points out what can be done in the Valley of the Shenandoah, and at
Nashville, and along the Atlantic coast, and through the central and
vital parts of the Confederacy.</p>
               <p pn="8">After a council of war, on Monday night, March 27, 1865, at which
were present men whose names will head new chapters
in-history,--Lincoln, Grant, Sherman, and others,--the great army of
the Lieutenant-general began to move, under his immediate
supervision. The solution of the mighty problem which has engrossed
not only the thoughts and energies of this nation, but has interested
and influenced to a great extent the nations of the whole earth, is
about to be solved. A bold, stupendous plan is just unfold
<pb n="9"/>
                  <figure entity="webb9">
                     <figDesc>9th page of Edwin B. Webb's
Memorial Sermons.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
ing its ultimate design. For five long, weary days, marching through
dense forests, floundering through swamps, fording streams, drenched
with rain, exhausted in the mud, catching a few moments' sleep in the
ranks, or upon the cold spongy ground, while waiting for orders to
move,--for five weary, memorable days the uncertain struggle has
raged. Back and forth over the same ground the veteran combatants,
horse and infantry, swayed and surged. Friday closed gloomily for the
loyal cause. The rebel leaders had become fully aware of the
disposition of our forces, and of their own immediate peril. And,
putting forth all their long-enduring, disciplined strength, our
cavalry was driven back; our infantry was repulsed; our veterans of
the fifth corps, many of them, were killed, wounded, captured. But, as
if helped by the inspiration of the Almighty, and confident that the
hour and the end were nigh, our lines reformed, and, becoming steady,
once more moved forward, like a good ship that feels her helm again
after the, staggering shock of some tremendous wave. Gaps are filled
up, connections made; and feeling one another's strength, and the
confident, steady <hi rend="italic">will</hi> of a present commander,
the aspect of the whole field is gradually changed. An unseen hand
ministers courage to fainting hearts. Cheers break out in well-known
accents along the Union lines. The crisis is passed. Forward, forward!
and <hi rend="italic">wrong</hi>
                  <pb n="10"/>
                  <figure entity="webb10">
                     <figDesc>10th page of Edwin
B. Webb's Memorial Sermons.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
long defiant, cowers before the <hi rend="italic">right</hi>. Rebellion
acknowledges its master.</p>
               <p pn="10">And now what means this joy of the loyal people, this exultation of
loyal hearts seeking expression through every possible symbol of
gladness and congratulation?</p>
               <p pn="10">It means that the serpent, driven hissing and defiant into her den,
and kept there by a cordon of fire, is making her escape with the
whole slimy brood, along a tortuous way,--the only one open to
them,--dodging and dipping their vile heads to avoid the conqueror's
uplifted heel.</p>
               <p pn="10">It means that victory, complete and final victory, crowns the loyal
cause. It means that the fortifications and forts, and all the
defences of the rebel stronghold, are stormed and carried. It means
that the spirit and strength of Rebellion are at length subdued and
conquered. It means that the so-called Confederate Government is a
vagabond, without a capital, without a home, without resources,
without revenues, without currency, without friends, and execrated by
all peoples under heaven. It means that Lee, who was educated by the
Government, as by a munificent mother, at her best-endowed schools,
and in her best positions; who remained with General Scott just long
enough to learn unmistakably all the resources and secrets and
purposes of the Government; and who for the last four years, has been
using all
<pb n="11"/>
                  <figure entity="webb11">
                     <figDesc>11th page of Edwin
B. Webb's Memorial Sermons.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
that knowledge, and all his education, and energy, and military skill,
that with perjured hand he might plunge his sword into the bosom that
nursed him, it means that Lee, the pet and pride of the Rebellion, is
foiled and vanquished at last.</p>
               <p pn="11">The old mother has had too many sons to stand between her and the
weapons poised and aimed by traitorous hands. Lee is flying, a
criminal, he knows not where, to escape a merited halter, he knows not
how; his army beaten, his braves captured, his followers deserting.</p>
               <p pn="11">It means that the Lieutenant-general and the loyal armies are
master of the field, and master of the Confederacy. It means that
slavery, the one dark cause of all our bitterness and bloodshed, is
forever dead. It means, no more massacres at Fort Pillow; no more
Union soldiers in Libby Prison, nor starved, emaciated, dying
skeletons at Salisbury or Andersonville,--names to be pronounced with
righteous indignation, and remembered with a shudder. It means, no
more threats on the floor of Congress, no more tyranny of opinion, no
more forced silence anywhere, no more iniquitous compromises, and no
more repeal of righteous ones. It means that the old flag, which was
planted, in the resplendent morning of April 3, 1865, on the ramparts
of Richmond, conquered and captured by Liberty's thundering legions,
shall float, the emblem of strength, freedom and justice, over
<pb n="12"/>
                  <figure entity="webb12">
                     <figDesc>12th page of Edwin
B. Webb's Memorial Sermons.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
every capital and city and village and inhabitant of our original
domain.</p>
               <p pn="12">It means that the war, the long terrible war that has trampled down
our harvests, and burdened our industry, and desolated our homes, and
bereaved our hearts, and made delicate wives widows, and helpless
babes orphans,--this war for the overthrow of a beneficent government
is virtually ended.</p>
               <p pn="12">It means that Republican Government, a Government of the people and
by the people, is no longer a question and an experiment. It means
that the people have the <hi rend="italic">right</hi> and the <hi rend="italic">capacity</hi> to govern themselves in peace and in war;
and, therefore, that the Republic of the United States of America is a
government and a success. It means that our institutions, affording
security and liberty and opportunity and education and religion to <hi rend="italic">all men</hi>, are to triumph.</p>
               <p pn="12">Such is the occasion of our joy to-day; and well may we
congratulate each other, and utter forth praise, and take up the
strains of ancient Israel, "The Lord is my rock, and my fortress, and
my deliverer; by thee I have run through a troop, and by my God have I
leaped over a wall." Well may we repeat after Moses and Miriam, taking
up that sublime strain which the shore echoed to the sea, and the sea
back to heaven again, "I will sing unto the Lord, for he hath
triumphed gloriously.... Thy right
<pb n="13"/>
                  <figure entity="webb13">
                     <figDesc>13th page of Edwin
B. Webb's Memorial Sermons.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
hand, 0 Lord, is become glorious in power, thy right hand, 0 Lord,
hath dashed in pieces the enemy." "He maketh wars to cease unto the
end of the earth; he breaketh the bow, and cutteth the spear in
sunder; he burneth the chariot in the fire." "If it had not been the
Lord who was on our side when men rose up against us, then they had
swallowed us up quick when their wrath was kindled against us."</p>
               <p pn="13">Let me not fail, my friends, to turn your thoughts and your
thanksgivings directly to God. As of old, when the prophet warned the
king, "Behold the people shall rise up as a great lion, and lift up
himself as a young lion: he shall not lie down until he eat of the
prey and drink the blood of the slain! "he exclaimed, "What hath God
wrought!" so now, when the prophecy has such a striking fulfilment, as
our forces, almost without rest, or food, or sleep, <hi rend="italic">sweep on, aroused, resistless, dominant</hi>, let us
repeat, "What hath God wrought! what hath God wrought!</p>
               <p pn="13">Everybody admits, consciously or unconsciously, that God's hand
planted the nation. He prepared the seed; he prepared the soil. He
controlled the forces of Nature, and the will, and the wickedness of
man, to the end that Plymouth Rock should be the landing-place of our
fathers, and Puritan principles the foundation on which we should
build; and whether the people of this nation purpose and execute, or
purpose and fail, the building is going up. God
<pb n="14"/>
                  <figure entity="webb14">
                     <figDesc>14th page of Edwin
B. Webb's Memorial Sermons.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
knows how to make the wrath of man praise him. The model of this
nation has been determined by the great Builder, and made certain by
the principles which he has already wrought into it. Virgil, the first
of Roman poets, represents the goddess mother of Aeneas presenting him
with a celestial armor with which he is to triumph over his enemies,
and establish the foundations of imperial Rome. He examined it all
with intense interest;</p>
               <lg type="stanza">
                  <l>"But most admires the <hi rend="italic">shield's</hi> mysterious
mould,</l>
                  <l>And Roman triumphs rising on the gold;"</l>
               </lg>
               <p pn="14">for on that shield, celestial hands had prefigured the destiny, the
course and glory, of Rome.</p>
               <p pn="14">When a tabernacle was to be built in which the Israelites should
worship, Moses was to have control of the work, as indeed he had of
every thing which that nation did; and the people were voluntarily to
supply the materials; but it was to be built, <hi rend="italic">the
whole</hi> and <hi rend="italic">every part</hi> of it, according to a
pattern wrought in the Heavens. "After the pattern that was showed
thee in the mount, even so shall ye make it."</p>
               <p pn="14">So for us, whether <hi rend="italic">we</hi> see it or not, before
celestial eyes, wrought by the divine hand, our history is written in
prophecy, --and not the grand outline merely, but the perfect model
and all the working plans of the glorious structure completed; and
just according to that pattern all the resistless forces of this nation
<pb n="15"/>
                  <figure entity="webb15">
                     <figDesc>15th page of Edwin
B. Webb's Memorial Sermons.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
are building. Who has not felt again and again during these last four
years that we were putting the mighty efforts and sacrifices of the
nation as materials for our future into unseen hands; that as the two
great armies, alternately aggressive and receding, ebbed and flowed
back and forth between the two capitals, an omnipotent hand held the
scales, and weighed the issue of battles? Was God present with the
people whose deeds the Old Testament records? Then he has been present
with us. Was God present when Israel and Amalek fought and the battle
fluctuated in the wilderness and Plain of Rephidim,--present to give
Joshua the victory? So has he been present with our armies. Did he
have respect unto the rod of Moses as he lifted it high towards heaven
in prayer?--and when his hands were weary, and his voice faint, and
the enemy prevailed, did he acknowledge the renewed exertions and
united supplications of Aaron and Hur? Then has he been with us,
answering our prayers and succeeding our endeavors. Over all these
battles, over all these humming messengers of death, over all these
night assaults and defeats, over all these weary, exhausting marches
through swamps and forests and mountain gorges, God has presided,
rifting results as huge stones from the quarry, and hewing and fitting
them as materials for the great structure which is rising,--rising
according to the pattern shown in <hi rend="italic">the mount</hi>.</p>
               <pb n="16"/>
               <p pn="16">
                  <figure entity="webb16">
                     <figDesc>16th page of
Edwin B. Webb's Memorial Sermons.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <p pn="16">Let us thank him! let us pitch our songs to reach his ear! let us
praise Israel's God, our fathers' God, and our God, for unexpected,
thorough, complete, and glorious victory! "The Lord is my strength and
song; and he is become my salvation."</p>
               <p pn="16">Let us thank God for the gift and endowments of the
Lieutenant-general! Oh! how easy it seems to conquer now; but let us
call to mind the feeling which blanched our cheeks, and bowed in the
dust our hearts, when, after long and confident expectation in
campaign after campaign, the only despatch that stayed us up against
immediate despair was the poor mockery of our grief, "The Army of the
Potomac is safe;" that is, safe in its retreat, safe in its
intrenchments again, safe from immediate annihilation. All unused to
war as we were, soldiers could not be made in a day, much less a
commander. Besides, any man who is physically sound--and most are till
a draft is ordered--may soon learn his duty and perform it. But who is
to guide these forces when armed and disciplined? Who is to employ,
with plan and skill and foresight, the mighty hosts scattered over the
country, and time their movements, and turn their concentric exertions
to account in securing the one great end? Here is a demand for the
highest order of mind, and for that peculiar combination of
intellectual and moral endowment which has appeared only at rare
intervals in the history of the
<pb n="17"/>
                  <figure entity="webb17">
                     <figDesc>17th page of Edwin
B. Webb's Memorial Sermons.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
world. How long did England seek before she found her Wellington?
France has had but one Napoleon. And who but Washington showed the
necessary qualifications of a captain during all our long struggle for
independence? The times do not make men, they call for them; and the
more you think of it, the more deeply will you feel how absolutely
dependent upon God we have been for such a man, and for getting him
into the commander's position so soon. Of course, no man can predict
his future, nor is it necessary. Enough that, bold in conception as he
is reticent in speech, quiet in person as he is efficient in command,
modest in appearance as he is unconquerable in purpose, he has been
endowed, and raised up, and put in command, to serve and save the
nation. Cyrus was not more the gift of God to the Jews than is Grant
to this nation. U. S. G. means hereafter the <hi rend="italic">United
States General</hi>. Let us appreciate God's goodness in furnishing us
this leader, and be thankful,--thankful to the Creator and Preserver
and Disposer of men and nations!</p>
               <p pn="17">Let us thank God also for the brave men who have executed his plans
and achieved the victory. Oh, what courage to go forth when certain
death stared them in the face! Oh, what a spirit of self-sacrifice to
close up broken ranks, and press steadily forward across ground once,
twice, thrice lost, tramping in the blood of the dead and dying, and
over
<pb n="18"/>
                  <figure entity="webb18">
                     <figDesc>18th page of Edwin
B. Webb's Memorial Sermons.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
friend and foe! Would that those titled and untitled heroes could have
seen this day, and lived to enjoy the victories which their valor
helped to win, and the new future which their blood helped to
inaugurate! Such unfaltering courage from the Rapidan to the James,
from Nashville to Atlanta, (a whole army dependent on one exposed
rickety railroad, which was like a hundred men clad in marine armor
going down into the deep sea to fight unknown forces, and only one
little, brittle tube for all to breathe through,) and now from the
Confederate capital to the capture of the Confederacy,--such dauntless
courage, such almost superhuman endurance, such continued
self-sacrifice,--let us thank God for such soldiers! And, remembering
the patience, fidelity, and heroism of the navy, for such sailors
too!</p>
               <p pn="18">Mark also what a spirit God has given the people. How bravely they
have sustained the Government! How patiently they have borne defeat
and loss! How cheerfully they have anticipated the drafts! How readily
they submit to taxation! How submissively they mourn their slain in
battle! Neither Rome nor Sparta knew nobler fathers and mothers than
weep to-day among our New-England hills and over our Western
prairies. The God of all consolation comfort them!</p>
               <p pn="18">Mark also how God has disposed the nations towards us, compelling
us to develop our own re
<pb n="19"/>
                  <figure entity="webb19">
                     <figDesc>19th page of Edwin
B. Webb's Memorial Sermons.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
sources, and to depend upon own energies, keeping us clear of all
foreign entanglements and hostile intervention.</p>
               <p pn="19">But I must leave the story of God's goodness half told: I can only
hint at the multitude of mercies which should call forth our
praise,--our praise to Him "who is glorious in holiness, fearful in
praises, doing wonders."</p>
               <p pn="19">In conclusion, my friends, what shall we render unto the Lord for
all his benefits towards us? Shall we not serve him as these soldiers
have served their country? This is what we want now, in the Church as
in the Republic, only bloodless, and, without carnal weapons, a grand
triumphant advance. You all remember the exhortation of the Apostle,
"No man that warreth entangleth himself with the affairs of this life,
that he may please Him who hath chosen him to be a soldier." Were our
self-devoted soldiers under obligations to the country that we are not
under to our God? If this war, on our part a holy one, is only
subservient to the far-reaching designs of Jesus, our captain and
king, what shame ought to burn the cheeks of many in the ranks of the
Church! Entangled with the affairs of this life, some of us can just
make out to render once a week, a poor half-day's service on the
sabbath, manifestly having no purpose or principle that does not
govern an enemy or alien to the cause of Christ. Entangled with the
<pb n="20"/>
                  <figure entity="webb20">
                     <figDesc>20th page of Edwin
B. Webb's Memorial Sermons.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
affairs of this life, whole divisions are seldom present at the
regular weekly appointments of the church, and never at an extra
service, though conquests and captives wait their hands in our Great
Captain's cause. Ah! if many of you who have enlisted in the ranks of
the Church should bring yourselves to the standard of the New
Testament, as you ought, or to the standard of that army discipline
which makes conquering soldiers, one-half of you would condemn
yourselves as stragglers and deserters, deserving no share in the
successes of the Church, as manifestly, consulting your own ease and
convenience, you bear no part in her sleepless vigilance and
protracted conflict.</p>
               <p pn="20">When would our armies have won without discipline, self-denial, and
heroic self-sacrifice? Shame! shame on such indifference, laxity of
principle, skulking, and cowardice as is found creeping into the ranks
of the Church!</p>
               <p pn="20">This world is in revolt against the Son of God. It is to be
conquered and subdued to his righteous sceptre. Already the battle is
joined. Unwavering devotion, prompt obedience, patient faith, and
persistent purpose,--these are the elements that win. Let us each hear
for himself the clarion call of the great warrior apostle ringing
along our lines like the echoes of a bugle-note among the hills:
"Thou, therefore, endure hardness as a good soldier of Jesus
Christ."</p>
               <pb n="21"/>
               <p pn="21">
                  <figure entity="webb21">
                     <figDesc>21st page of
Edwin B. Webb's Memorial Sermons.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <p pn="21">Then shall the Church, like the Republic, advance to new conquests
and possessions; and our sabbath-songs thrill like a battle-hymn on a
nation's anniversary. Then shall we sing, more sweet, more loud, "The
Lord is my strength and song, and he is become my salvation: he is my
God, and I will prepare him a habitation; my father's God, and I will
exalt him."</p>
               <pb n="22"/>
<!-- blank page -->
<!--               <p>
                  <figure entity="webb22">
                     <figDesc>22nd page of
Edwin B. Webb's Memorial Sermons.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </p> -->
               <pb n="23"/>
               <p pn="23">
                  <figure entity="webb23">
                     <figDesc>23rd page of
Edwin B. Webb's Memorial Sermons.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 id="webb.003" n="SOME OF THE RESULTS OF THE WAR." type="sermon">
               <head pn="23">SOME OF THE RESULTS OF THE WAR.</head>
               <p pn="23">1 Chronicles xxii. chapter, 6-16 verses. I will not transcribe the
passage, but only so much of it as is necessary to exhibit its spirit
and the foundation of my discourse.</p>
               <p pn="23">"And David said to Solomon, My son, as for me, it was in my mind to
build a house unto the name of the Lord my God; but the word of the
Lord came to me, saying, Thou hast shed blood abundantly, and hast
made great wars: thou shalt not build a house unto my
name. . . . Behold, a son shall be born to thee, who shall be a man of
rest: he shall build a house for my name.</p>
               <p pn="23">"Now, my son, the Lord be with thee, and prosper thou and
build,--only the Lord give thee wisdom and understanding, and give
thee charge concerning Israel, that thou mayest keep the law of the
Lord thy God. Then shalt thou prosper, if thou takest heed to fulfil
the statutes and judgments which the Lord charged Moses with
concerning Israel: be strong and of good courage; dread not, nor be
dismayed.</p>
               <p pn="23">"Now, behold, in my trouble I have prepared for
<pb n="24"/>
                  <figure entity="webb24">
                     <figDesc>24th page of Edwin
B. Webb's Memorial Sermons.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
the house of the Lord a hundred thousand talents of gold, and a
thousand thousand talents of silver; and of brass and iron without
weight; timber also and stone. Moreover, there are workmen with thee
in abundance,--hewers and workers of stone and timber, and all manner
of cunning men for every manner of work.</p>
               <p pn="24">"Of the gold, the silver, and the brass, and the iron, there is no
number. Timber and stone also, all is in abundance. Arise therefore,
and be doing, and the Lord be with thee."</p>
               <p pn="24">Like David, our period of war and bloodshed is passing away. Like
Solomon, a new period of peace and rest, its offspring and successor,
is about to succeed. Generally, it is true that every era is the child
of that which preceded it; but the era upon which this nation is now
entering is peculiarly and strikingly the offspring of that which is
passing away. The present, these four years and more of pain and agony
and travail are not merely giving place to the peaceful future,--this
closing present is the parent of the hopeful, matchless future that is
just stepping into its place.</p>
               <p pn="24">And upon this rising future is devolved the inspiring but
tremendously responsible task of building a national structure whose
magnificence and glory shall be to that which preceded the war, as the
temple of Solomon was to the tent or tabernacle in which
<pb n="25"/>
                  <figure entity="webb25">
                     <figDesc>25th page of Edwin
B. Webb's Memorial Sermons.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
David worshipped. Using the text analogically, the points of discourse
to which your attention is invited are two; viz., the materials
accumulated, and the laws which must govern a successful use of
them.</p>
               <p pn="25">1. And first, as to the materials secured and prepared for future
use by this period of war. After the boundaries of a nation are
settled (and we are now pretty well defined in this particular, I
think; at any rate, between the oceans on the <hi rend="italic">east</hi> and <hi rend="italic">west</hi>, and between the
lakes on the north and the Rio Grande on the south, we are not likely
to have any hostile or divisive lines run for some time to
come),--after the boundaries of a nation are determined, the next
question relates to the materials,--the materials of self-development,
of growth, and greatness; and these, if the nation is to attain
prominence and permanence, must be abundant and varied. Not for the
building of the temple alone, but for the building of the nation as
well, there must be gold and silver and brass and iron and stone; and
was ever a nation more abundantly provided than we are with all rich
mines of precious metals, minerals, and ores? As to our gold mines on
the Pacific coast, we have been in the habit of congratulating
ourselves for the last fifteen years that they were kept concealed
till those western slopes, which connect the lofty line of perpetual
snow with the warm waters of the gentle
<pb n="26"/>
                  <figure entity="webb26">
                     <figDesc>26th page of Edwin
B. Webb's Memorial Sermons.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
Pacific, came into the possession of a Protestant Christian nation.</p>
               <p pn="26">But does it not seem as if the value of those mines was reserved
especially for these days of war and bloodshed? What should we have
done without them in the disturbed state of our currency? Where should
we have obtained the vast amounts of gold that we have been obliged to
export while we were issuing paper and promises to pay at such a
fearful rate? What a timely deposit these mines have proved!</p>
               <p pn="26">And, so far from being exhausted it would seem that we have but
just begun to comprehend their extent and value. We have gathered up
what has been washed out upon the surface. The great vaults hidden in
the mountains, and the richly veined avenues that lead to them, are
yet to be opened. During these years of bloody war, we have learned
much as to the value and position of these deposits, and, therefore,
are prepared to draw against them for the future.</p>
               <p pn="26">Great advances have been made, too, in the discovery of silver, of
copper, and lead and iron.</p>
               <p pn="26">Of petroleum what shall be said? Who could have divined, four years
ago, that seas of oil should be discovered in the interior of the
earth during this tremendous civil war?--an oil of so many and such
remarkable qualities, that we have but just begun
<pb n="27"/>
                  <figure entity="webb27">
                     <figDesc>27th page of Edwin
B. Webb's Memorial Sermons.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
to conjecture the uses to which it may be put in the economy of
civilization.</p>
               <p pn="27">Doubtless, many a property and many a company are alike bogus; and
yet, after due allowance for all speculation and gambling, the real
discoveries of precious metals, minerals, and ores, have been many and
of immense value; and around all these mines must be gathered from
overcrowded centres and cities a population., more or less dense, of
capitalists and laborers. Here, at the base of the mountain, in the
forest never traversed before, except by the Indian and the buffalo,
manufactories will rise, villages spring up, and fields be cleared;
and whoever secures the building of a house, or a barn, or workshop or
factory, or the converting of a tract of wild land into a farm on the
coast of the Pacific, or in the forests of Pennsylvania, adds to the
wealth and prosperity of the nation.</p>
               <p pn="27">Our agricultural resources were large and rich before; but we add
to them immensely by the issue of this bloody war. Now the sunny South
is open to free labor and all the healthful rivalries of personal
productive industry. Here are vast plantations to be made as the
garden of the world under the economy of the Northern farmer; here are
unmeasured wastes of virgin soil waving in an unshorn wantonness of
tropical luxuriance; and broad meadows white with cotton from
generation to generation;
<pb n="28"/>
                  <figure entity="webb28">
                     <figDesc>28th page of Edwin
B. Webb's Memorial Sermons.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
and immense swamps reeking with a heat and moisture that may grow rice
for the world. All these plantations, wastes, wildernesses, meadows,
swamps, and unexplored lands stretching from the Chesapeake Bay far
down to the Gulf of Mexico, and around it, are to be divided, like our
Northern lands and Western prairies, into innumerable farms and
freeholds occupied and improved by the willing, intelligent owner,
white or black, and thus to become an incalculable means of growth and
wealth to the nation.</p>
               <p pn="28">As regards all such materials of national greatness, the war closes
with nothing wanting. Leaving now the productiveness and extent of the
soil, and all the minerals, mines, ores, metals, deposited beneath its
surface, let us turn to the people dwelling here. This is a material
without which the wealth of the mines and soils are of little
account. Manifestly, there is a great difference in peoples; one
nation "living out feebly and obscurely the term of its existence, and
then sinking into complete oblivion; another exercising a powerful
influence over its contemporaries, and leaving a luminous track in the
annals of the world." Lord Bacon, speaking of the true greatness of
kingdoms, says, "The greatness of an estate in bulk and territory doth
fall under measure; and the greatness of finances and revenue doth
fall under computation. The population may appear by mus-
<pb n="29"/>
                  <figure entity="webb29">
                     <figDesc>29th page of Edwin
B. Webb's Memorial Sermons.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
ters, and the number and greatness of cities and towns by cards and
maps; but yet there is not any thing amongst civil affairs more
subject to error than the right valuation and true judgment concerning
the power and forces of a State."</p>
               <p pn="29">"Walled towns, stored arsenals and armories, goodly races of horse,
chariots of war, . . .ordnance, artillery and the like,--all this is
but a sheep in a lion's skin, <hi rend="italic">except the breed and
disposition of the people be stout and warlike</hi>." Just at this
point was our weakness. Our pursuits, our education, our love of
wealth and ease, had unfitted all the inhabitants of the free States
for the perilous adventure and bloody carnage of war. We had every
thing else, but we had not the <hi rend="italic">stout disposition</hi>
and <hi rend="italic">warlike temper</hi>. We had become broad of
forehead, but narrow of chest, intellectual and far-sighted, but weak
of nerve and faint of heart. The dollar, so grateful to the palm, had
unfitted it to clasp the sword and the musket. Our young men sought
places behind the counter, avoided the out-of-door toil, the frown of
the elements, and the heat of the sun; and so they had come to have
neither strength for the camp nor courage for the fight. They could
not and they would not go to war. So multitudes believed; and thus our
Government was like a rich prize, waiting only a mailed hand to pluck
it,--such was the talk on the floor of Congress, such was the
expectation of our enemies;
<pb n="30"/>
                  <figure entity="webb30">
                     <figDesc>30th page of Edwin
B. Webb's Memorial Sermons.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
but I need not say how completely the war has revolutionized and
corrected all this. The spirit of '76 had not died with our
fathers. The heroic spirit of Spartan mothers was in our women; and
the endurance of Roman soldiers in the men that answered to the
country's call.</p>
               <p pn="30">We have discovered or developed that stock and spirit, and
marvellous power of adaptation, which, with the blessing of God,
insures the perpetuity of our Government and our free institutions
against all secession and revolt at home, against all interference and
insult from abroad.</p>
               <p pn="30">All unprepared for such a gigantic and formidable rebellion, and
abhorring the carnival of war, we have, nevertheless, created a navy
which exacts the most deferential regard of the nations; and, turning
the country into a camp, and the makers of cars and pianos into the
makers of cannons and rifles, we have tried and settled the question
of self-preservation; and it will be a new element in our future,--a
truth demonstrated and priceless, that the Republic wants neither
living patriotism, nor the people warlike power.</p>
               <p pn="30">And, in settling the question of self-preservation, we have also
settled the question of capacity,--the capacity of the people to
govern themselves. However clearly the <hi rend="italic">right</hi> of
self-government may be deduced from abstract principles, to maintain
that right
<pb n="31"/>
                  <figure entity="webb31">
                     <figDesc>31st page of Edwin
B. Webb's Memorial Sermons.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
successfully, without the <hi rend="italic">capacity</hi> of
self-government, is clearly impossible and absurd. We had kept along
well enough in peace, as the most unseaworthy craft may keep her keel
in smooth water, and the most incompetent pilot hug the land in fair
weather. Up to 1861, it was an open question, whether the people of
this Republic were capable of self-government. Then came the storm and
test; and who was certain of the issue? Who had faith in the people
then? Some voices will be very loud <hi rend="italic">now</hi>, telling
of courage and confidence and prophecy; but no man heard them in
1861. We listened in vain for a clear, commanding utterance from any
quarter. No man knew what to do. Those who should have directed and
led the way stood paralyzed. Senators left their seats. States seceded
and organized within the limits and jurisdiction of the United
States. Our statesmen faltered,--<hi rend="italic">made
defenceless</hi>, apparently, by the Constitution which they had sworn
to <hi rend="italic">defend</hi>. Our politicians <hi rend="italic">babbled</hi> more than usual. The Old World looked from
her thrones across the water, and said, "Yes, yes, I told you so: the
great bubble has burst; your Republic has gone up!"</p>
               <p pn="31">But by and by Beauregard opened fire on Sumter, humbling the flag,
which, after four years, in the shot and smoke of battle, goes up
again to-morrow, to float in triumph over the old fort, and over the
humiliation of every traitor that has ever lifted his hand to assail
<pb n="32"/>
                  <figure entity="webb32">
                     <figDesc>32nd page of Edwin
B. Webb's Memorial Sermons.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
it; <hi rend="italic">and that fire was something that the people could
understand and decide about</hi>: that was an act of war which went
booming through the land, waking a power that instantly took control
of the Government,--comprehending the issue, and rushing volunteers
into the ranks by the hundred thousand. Resistance--instantaneous,
unconcerted, sympathetic, inflexible resistance--evinced the unity,
the instinct, and the purpose of the people; and in all these four
years, tried sorely, disappointed in the repulse and defeat of their
armies, impatient of delays, the people have never
faltered. Politicians faltered; many of the chief rulers began to
think of retreat, of some kind of settlement; newspaper editors cried,
Enough!--enough of blood, enough of drafts, enough of debt!--and hied
them away from the great city to the Canada shore, by the Falls, to
plot something, to do something, they knew not what; but the people,
following their instincts, held steadily on their way as if inspired
by the Almighty. There was no wavering, no signs of weakness, no want
of capacity, with the people.</p>
               <p pn="32">In addition to all this, and adding immensely to the strain, in the
very midst of the storm and fury of civil war, a Presidential election
came. The polls were opened; bayonets did not guard nor govern
them. The day passed as quietly as the sun runs his course, and closed
with benedictions and doxolo-
<pb n="33"/>
                  <figure entity="webb33">
                     <figDesc>33rd page of Edwin
B. Webb's Memorial Sermons.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
gies; <hi rend="italic">and the capacity</hi> of the people for
self-government is proved. The question of capacity is settled and
recorded forever. A gifted and worthy son of Massachusetts, speaking
at a time when every mind was burdened with apprehension, says, "If
the people shall go through this election freely and fairly, whatever
may be the result as regards parties, our institutions will have
received a triumph: no nobler spectacle will have been witnessed in
this land, since it first asserted its title to be called a land of
liberty." Behold, the triumph, the nobler spectacle!</p>
               <p pn="33">Another question, and one of vast importance in this nation, has
been settled; and the conclusion, definite and dominant, is one of the
grandest materials to be built into our rising future: I mean the
question of <hi rend="italic">State sovereignty</hi>. Out of this
doctrine of State sovereignty comes the claim to declare null and void
a law of the United States,--out of this comes secession and war. This
suicidal doctrine of <hi rend="italic">State sovereignty</hi> is not in
the Declaration of Independence: that reads, "We, therefore, the
representatives of the United States of America, . . . <hi rend="italic">by the authority of the</hi> GOOD PEOPLE <hi rend="italic">of these colonies</hi>, solemnly publish and declare that
these United Colonies are, and of right ought to be, free and
independent States." Mark two things: 1. This is done by authority,
not of the States, but of <hi rend="italic">the people</hi>. 2. The
<pb n="34"/>
                  <figure entity="webb34">
                     <figDesc>34th page of Edwin
B. Webb's Memorial Sermons.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
States are declared "free, independent," but not sovereign.</p>
               <p pn="34">The doctrine was in the old confederation, which lasted thirteen
years from the time of the Declaration of Independence, and was a
failure.</p>
               <p pn="34">The doctrine is not in the Constitution. That starts off, like the
full sweep and swell of the sea: "We <hi rend="italic">the people</hi>
of the United States,. . . do ordain and establish this Constitution."
Our national government is not the creation of sovereign States,--is
not a compact, or league, to which they may accede, and from which
they may secede. This is the "people's Constitution, the people's
Government, made for the people, made by the people, and answerable to
the people;" and this same people, and not sovereign States, have
declared this national Government supreme, and the Constitution the
supreme law of the land. "This Constitution . . . shall be the supreme
law of the land, . . . any thing in the constitution or laws of any
State to the contrary notwithstanding. John Quincy Adams says tersely,
speaking of this doctrine of State sovereignty, "The Declaration says,
It is not in me. The Constitution says, It is not in me."</p>
               <p pn="34">And yet, this very doctrine, having no fixed foundation in our
history, and none in the great exponents of our national life, and
absolutely destructive of the very idea of self-preservation, exposed
and exploded
<pb n="35"/>
                  <figure entity="webb35">
                     <figDesc>35th page of Edwin
B. Webb's Memorial Sermons.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
by Mr. Webster in his reply to Hayne, and again triumphantly denied as
false, and denounced as suicidal, in his reply to Calhoun,--this
doctrine, like the genius of evil, has ever been intruding its bastard
presence through all our history. No argument could expel it from the
minds of Southern men. They wanted to believe it, and they would
believe it. From history, from argument, on the floor of the senate,
from the judgment of the people, they appealed to the bloody
arbitrament of the sword; and the decision is again as always, against
them,--triumphantly, overwhelmingly against them. There is no other
appeal. Beaten on every field; compelled to surrender their armies as
prisoners of war; in the midst of all the poverty, mourning, anguish,
and desolation, which they have brought upon themselves, compelled to
see the old flag raised again upon the forts, arsenals, post-offices,
and custom-houses of the United States,--they are not likely to repeat
their appeal to the sword. The question of State sovereignty is,
therefore, settled; and the settlement is a cornerstone in our new
structure.</p>
               <p pn="35">And the settlement of this question settles the policy of the
Government and the destiny of the South. The Government must sustain
the loyal men of the South, whatever their social condition or
color. Any other hypothesis is too base to be entertained. Multitudes
of these rebel leaders have fled,
<pb n="36"/>
                  <figure entity="webb36">
                     <figDesc>36th page of Edwin
B. Webb's Memorial Sermons.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
abandoning their homes, their social position, their property. Loyal
men, having no occasion to fly, have remained, and must occupy these
vacant places and this abandoned property. Already this transfer has
been made largely, is now being made rapidly, will continue to be made
heavily; and these loyal men, established directly by the Government
on these rice lands and cotton plantations, or in the cities through
the failure of rebels to pay their taxes or redeem their
estates,--these loyal men, having come into the possession of the
forfeited social position and property of the guilty, must receive
three things; viz., 1. The jealous protection of the
Government. 2. The unqualified support of the Government. 3. And the
immense patronage of the Government. And then, further, if human
nature can be relied upon as a basis of reasoning, these men will
appeal to each other those who are there, and those who shall go there
for mutual support; and they will appeal to the Government against the
restoration, and against the return, of those known by their neighbors
to be guilty, as well as against those who have confessed their guilt
by flight, or by the arms captured in their hands. Let us not be
disturbed, therefore; for there are causes at work, whatever may be
the leniency of our national authority,--causes that have gone too far
to be resisted or controlled,--causes which must decide the future of
the South. Let Congress keep strictly
<pb n="37"/>
                  <figure entity="webb37">
                     <figDesc>37th page of Edwin
B. Webb's Memorial Sermons.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
within its power to inflict punishment for treason, and maintain that
"No attainder of treason shall work corruption of blood, or
forfeiture, except for life." Those leaders in rebellion are to be
leaders no more. Passing those who will pay the penalty of their crime
with their lives,--as some of them surely must, or all crime go
unpunished,--not one of those men who sat in the councils of the
nation, nor one of those who, with perjured hands, drew their swords
against the Government that had educated and supported them,--not one
of those traitors, nor their children, will ever regain their former
position. The power is neither with <hi rend="italic">them</hi> nor <hi rend="italic">their</hi> constituents. It has passed at the fountain
into other hands. The road to their old supremacy is held, at the
popular end of it, by other people; and the very gate of entrance
controlled by new views, new doctrines, and new sympathies. These
Southern men have yet to learn, and possibly a few others also, how
completely they have revolutionized their own society. Henceforth, the
Government is a unit, controlled and worked in the interests of
loyalty, freedom, and nationality; and this will be found another and
a mighty element in our rising future.</p>
               <p pn="37">Such, my friends, as well as I can describe them now, are some of
the elements or materials gathered and prepared by this war for the
building which is to rise in the days of peace upon which we are en-
<pb n="38"/>
                  <figure entity="webb38">
                     <figDesc>38th page of Edwin
B. Webb's Memorial Sermons.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
tering; and they are as essential and as abundant certainly as the
materials prepared by David for the building of the temple.</p>
               <p pn="38">I have been compelled to write in weariness and in haste; but I
cannot conclude without touching an essentially practical thought for
us all. How shall these materials be put together? on what foundation?
in accordance with what laws? beautified with what ornament?</p>
               <p pn="38">1. First as to the foundation. The temple, which is the glory of
Jerusalem, rested on deep foundations of solid rock; and so our vast
national structure must rest upon an immutable foundation; that is,
upon the fundamental doctrines and principles of the inspired <hi rend="italic"> word</hi>. The Christian religion is the only secure
basis on which we can build.</p>
               <p pn="38">Expediency has its place in the affairs of Government; but, as a
foundation on which to raise a vast and permanent superstructure, it
is a quicksand. Neither can morality alone bear the tremendous weight
of Government. Religion--the religion of the New Testament, vital,
immutable, eternal--is our only foundation.</p>
               <p pn="38">Washington, in his Farewell Address says, "Religion and morality
are indispensable supports of every habit and disposition that can
contribute to national prosperity;" and then adds like a
discriminating preacher of the gospel, "and let us with caution in-<pb n="39"/>
                  <figure entity="webb39">
                     <figDesc>39th page of Edwin
B. Webb's Memorial Sermons.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
dulge the supposition, that morality can be maintained without
religion,--morality cannot prevail in exclusion of religious
principle." And then he adds with a power of exhortation which has
lost nothing of its point or pertinency, "Who, that is a sincere
friend to the <hi rend="italic">Government</hi>, can look with
indifference upon attempts to shake the foundation of the fabric?"</p>
               <p pn="39">The declaration of the prophet has been mournfully illustrated in
the downfall of many and mighty structures: "For the nation and
kingdom that will not serve thee shall perish." Jesus Christ is the
corner-stone of our national as of our personal salvation.</p>
               <p pn="39">2. Then again: in accordance with what laws shall we build? There
is no objection to a leaning tower, as an object of curiosity to
attract the traveller; but the walls that are to stand must rise in
accordance with the laws of gravitation: not more surely must the
fabric of the nation rise in accordance with the laws of God. "This
way of tying walls together with iron, instead of making them of that
substance and form, that they shall naturally poise themselves upon
their butment, is against the rules of good architecture," says one;
and George Herbert has this line: "Houses are built by rule, <hi rend="italic">and commonwealths</hi>."</p>
               <p pn="39">To determine what the will of God is, as respects society, and to
define that will in laws to which the
<pb n="40"/>
                  <figure entity="webb40">
                     <figDesc>40th page of Edwin
B. Webb's Memorial Sermons.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
judgment and conscience of the people will respond, is the great work
of the legislator. To re-affirm the ordinances of Nature, to re-enact
the laws of the Creator and Sovereign and Judge of the world,--this is
the essence of all wise legislation.</p>
               <p pn="40">We are indeed through the war; but we have a mighty work on our
hands,--one over which, in the midst of all our joy, we may well fast
and pray,--a work requiring the profoundest wisdom, the firmest
adherence to principle,--a work that can only be done in obedience to
the commands of God.</p>
               <p pn="40">This is what we must do,--all the people of this land,--render the
hearty, scrupulous obedience of Christian men in all our work. No
mistake is more fatal than that a great nation, with such materials as
we have, can afford to be lax and lawless and irreligious. Just the
reverse is true. Any thing that will live, endure, must render an
obedience stricter as it is greater. For instance, a grain of dust may
not always and uniformly obey the laws of gravitation; but the
heavenly bodies, sun, moon, and stars, must obey. The great ocean must
obey influences that little lakes and rivers are not required to
recognize even.</p>
               <p pn="40">Just so, like the sun and the sea, this nation must obey the laws
and precepts of the Almighty. Let us each one, with heart and hand,
with lip and life, however humble, however lofty our part, do all in 
<pb n="41"/>
                  <figure entity="webb41">
                     <figDesc>41st page of Edwin
B. Webb's Memorial Sermons.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
strictest obedience to Him who filled the temple with his glory, and
honors them that honor him!</p>
               <p pn="41">3. And, finally, as to the adorning of our temple: above all the
splendor of art, above all the creations of genius in stone or on
canvas, let it be like the inscription on the bells of the horses in
the last days;--on all our door-posts and windows, on ceiling and
walls and floor; let it be, "The beauty of holiness;" "Holiness to the
Lord;" and let it be reflected by all the builders, "The ornament of a
meek and quiet spirit, which is, in the sight of God, of great price."
"Thus saith the Lord of hosts, . . . the fast of the fourth month
shall be, to the house of Judah, joy and gladness and cheerful feasts:
. . . therefore love the truth and peace."</p>
               <p pn="41">And do thou, 0 Lord, for whose sake we would build our temple
enduring, lofty, and beautiful, "make us glad according to the days
wherein thou bast afflicted us, and. the years wherein we have seen
evil. Let thy work appear unto thy servants, and thy glory unto their
children. And let the beauty of the Lord our God be upon us: and
establish thou the work of our hands upon us; yea, the work of our
hands establish thou it."</p>
               <pb n="42"/>
<!-- blank page -->
<!--               <p>
                  <figure entity="webb42">
                     <figDesc>42nd page of
Edwin B. Webb's Memorial Sermons.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </p> -->
               <pb n="43"/>
               <p pn="43">
                  <figure entity="webb43">
                     <figDesc>43rd page of
Edwin B. Webb's Memorial Sermons.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 id="webb.004" n="THE ASSASSINATION OF THE PRESIDENT." type="sermon">
               <head pn="43">THE ASSASSINATION OF THE PRESIDENT.</head>
               <epigraph pn="43">
                  <p pn="43">He calleth to me out of Seir, Watchman, what of the
night? Watchman, what of the night?</p>
                  <p pn="43">The Watchman said, The morning cometh, and also the
night.</p>
               </epigraph>
               <p pn="43">THESE words seem to me strikingly appropriate to our present
circumstances. Last Sabbath morning it was my privilege to place
before your minds some reasons for thankfulness,--thankfulness to
God. Then the streets were decked with symbols of joy; gladness in
welcome accents broke from every lip. Men's countenances were bright,
as if reflecting the coming of the morning. We clasped each other's
hands with a jubilant pulse, and every eye answered back hope,
inspiration, to the eye that looked into it.</p>
               <p pn="43">But how changed is all in a moment! Yesterday morning flags were
set at half-mast. Even Sumter's flag is but half raised. As the day
advanced, emblems of mourning drooped from the highest windows to the
sidewalk. <hi rend="italic">The President is assassinated</hi>! Men hold
their breath, and turn pale at the appalling words. Citizens meet, and
<pb n="44"/>
                  <figure entity="webb44">
                     <figDesc>44th page of Edwin
B. Webb's Memorial Sermons.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
shake hands, and part in silence. Words convey nothing when
uttered. All attempt to express the nation's grief is utterly
commonplace and insignificant. An eclipse seems to have come upon the
brilliancy of the flag,--a smile seems irrelevant and
sacrilegious. Even the fresh, green grass, just coming forth to meet
the return of spring and the singing of birds, seems to wear the
shadows of twilight at noonday. The sun is less bright than before;
and the very atmosphere holds in it, for the tearful eye, a strange
ethereal element of gloom. Surely "<hi rend="italic">the night
cometh</hi>." And as we gather here this morning, after an absence of
only two days, how appalling, in this cheerful home of our religious
affections, are these wide-hung emblems of grief and anguish! It is
manly to weep to-day. The coming of the morning, and also the night,
are strangely mingled.</p>
               <p pn="44">Had death overtaken any one of our brilliant military leaders in
the field, we should have said it was a thing to be expected. Had any
sudden reverse in the fortunes of war visited one of our armies, it
would have been a terrible grief, but still a kind of calamity to
which we have become accustomed. Had the President fallen by a chance
shot in Richmond, or by the hand of some lurking assassin, as he
passed the fortifications through which our hearts did not consent to
his going,
<pb n="45"/>
                  <figure entity="webb45">
                     <figDesc>45th page of Edwin
B. Webb's Memorial Sermons.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
we should but have realized some of our transient forebodings. But
after his safe return, and the triumph of our arms, which he took so
much pleasure in telegraphing to the people, we had almost dismissed
from our minds any fears for the safety of his life. And hence the
telegram announcing the death of the President at such a time, in such
a way, falls upon us like a crash of thunder from an unclouded sky.</p>
               <p pn="45">Wearied with the duties of his high position, and the persistent
annoyance of petty office-seekers, and unwilling to disappoint the
people even in their unreasonable expectations, he sought an hour's
recreation in the theatre. And what a horrible tragedy! The actor,
having thoroughly prepared his part, and being often defeated in one
way and another from the fiendish acting of it, finds his opportunity
at last. With the stealthy step of a base, brutal coward, with a
damning lie on his tongue, and the heart of a demon in his breast, he
approaches the generous, unsuspecting man in the rear of his seat,
and, aiming the fatal weapon with practised hand at the back of his
head, puts the ball directly through his brain, and then makes his
escape through the screens and drapery and doors with which his
calling had made him acquainted. There are no last words for wife or
children,--no word for the people's heart to which he always
spoke,--no part-
<pb n="46"/>
                  <figure entity="webb46">
                     <figDesc>46th page of Edwin
B. Webb's Memorial Sermons.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
ing counsel for a bereaved and almost bewildered nation. The hand that
signed the <hi rend="italic">emancipation proclamation</hi> hangs
helpless in death; the mind which had borne so evenly the tremendous
strain of four unparelleled years is hurled from its throne; the
great, good, magnanimous heart is stilled; those generous lips which
have spoken mercy so often, and would perhaps, like martyred
Stephen's, have said in their last articulate speech, "Lord, lay not
this sin to their charge," are sealed forever. The nation has lost a
father; the human race a sincere, devoted, and able leader!</p>
               <p pn="46">I have had no time to analyze the character, or choose out words to
express our sense of the worth, of the late Abraham Lincoln. But I may
employ, with your approbation I am sure, the words used by Daniel
Webster concerning Zachary Taylor: "He has left on the minds of the
country a strong impression; first, of his absolute honesty and
integrity of character; next, of his sound, practical good sense; and,
lastly, of the mildness, kindness, and friendliness of his temper
towards all his countrymen."</p>
               <p pn="46">Yes: "towards all his countrymen." He was, on the very day of his
untimely death, exerting all the kindness of his unselfish nature, and
prepared, it is believed, to peril all his great popularity, in
inaugurating a policy <hi rend="italic">most lenient, most
forgiving,</hi>
                  <pb n="47"/>
                  <figure entity="webb47">
                     <figDesc>47th page of Edwin
B. Webb's Memorial Sermons.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
towards those who had forfeited every thing except the right to be
hung. They have put aside their friend. They have murdered the
new-born mercy which waited to bless them. No man could if he would,
and no man was disposed to, do so much for them as Abraham Lincoln.</p>
               <p pn="47">And how the loyal people confided in him! how implicitly the common
people trusted him! The world has scarcely seen the like. He came to
the chair of the Chief Magistrate from the rough experience of
frontier life. He owed his election, and the favor with which he was
received, to the belief, in the minds of the people, that he was an
honest man.</p>
               <p pn="47">And did he disappoint that confidence? Did he show himself
unworthy? Did he ever incur the suspicion of dishonesty or corruption?
Or did he ever swerve from what he conceived to be the path of duty to
win popular applause? Never. On the other hand, so impartial was he in
selecting men from all parties to fill the high offices of government,
so artless was he in all that he did, so transparent were his deeds
and his motives, that, by a popular vote scarcely paralleled, the
people called him a second time to guide the nation for another four
years. He knew nothing of tricks or double-dealing or party-shifts, or
crooked policies. He was a sincere, impartial, straightfor-
<pb n="48"/>
                  <figure entity="webb48">
                     <figDesc>48th page of Edwin
B. Webb's Memorial Sermons.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
ward, honest man. And the people saw it and felt it, and were glad of
an opportunity to honor him with an overwhelming repetition of their
well-placed confidence. What a noble example is he to all young men
looking to office or popular regard! With no military reputation, with
no brilliant oratory, with no winning grace of manners, he was the
foremost man for the highest office in the gift of a great, free, and
intelligent people, once and again, because he was a man of absolute
honesty and integrity of character.</p>
               <p pn="48">And besides these unselfish, impartial, upright elements of
character, there was a masterful common sense, a genial mother-wit,
and a practical statesmanship, which showed themselves in some of the
most compact specimens of argument, happy avoidances of difficulty,
and a thorough apprehension of popular instincts and judgments.</p>
               <p pn="48">He was unpolished in style, but he was profound in thought. He was
pithy in his sentences, but original and patient in investigation;
rough on the exterior, but a jewel within,-</p>
               <lg type="stanza">
                  <l>"Rich in saving common sense."</l>
               </lg>
               <p pn="48">How much we owe to his unambitious example; how much to his
far-reaching discernment; how much to his good-natured hearing of all
sides; how much to his steady calm judgment, which held the scales, in
<pb n="49"/>
                  <figure entity="webb49">
                     <figDesc>49th page of Edwin
B. Webb's Memorial Sermons.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
the fury and gusts of the storm, as equally poised as if in the
atmosphere of peace and calm; how much to his great forbearance under
stinging reproach; how much to his knowledge of and unwavering
confidence in the people and the people's cause, God knows, but we
know not as yet. May the day never come, when, by bitter contrast, we
shall learn how wise and safe was the confidence which we reposed in
him!</p>
               <p pn="49">This nation mourns to-day as it never mourned before. The statesmen
of the land had learned to trust him in the greatest exigencies; the
impatient were restrained by his moderation; the immovable and morose
were moved and almost brought into time by his steady, sympathetic
step forward; the one-eyed were made ashamed of their ignorance by an
hour in his society; the revengeful learned magnanimity from his
deeds. The soldiers loved him, and the soldier's mother loved him, and
confided in him. The negroes loved him; oh, how they will mourn for
him! Moses was not allowed to lead the children of Israel into the
land of peace and plenty; neither was he allowed himself to enter it,
but only to survey its broad prospect from Pisgah's top. And so <hi rend="italic">their</hi> deliverer and <hi rend="italic">ours</hi> is only
permitted to come to the border, and, in these last few days, catch
pleasing glimpses of the glorious, opening future. And as when Moses
died, his eye not dim, and his natural
<pb n="50"/>
                  <figure entity="webb50">
                     <figDesc>50th page of Edwin
B. Webb's Memorial Sermons.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
force not abated, there was mourning throughout all the camp, till the
plain of Moab resounded with the cry of sires and sons, mothers and
maidens; so now there will be mourning in the camp, and mourning on
the prairies, and far away over the mountains; but nowhere keener
anguish and disappointment than among the sable hosts whom his noble
heart and hand has freed. All men unconsciously speak of him as our
beloved President; and the hand of the assassin has embalmed him with
all his virtues and greatness, and made him sacred and sublime in our
fond, loving hearts, and in the heart of the world forever.</p>
               <p pn="50">Were I to select some one thing by which to characterize Abraham
Lincoln, I should name his profound apprehension and appreciation of
the popular instinct,--that instinct which is true to the right as the
needle to the pole, in all storms, and on every sea. He believed in
God. He believed God was to be recognized in this war. He believed
that the <hi rend="italic">set</hi> of the loyal masses,--the deep,
silent current, which bears on events, is in the line of God's
advance; and, thus believing, he governed himself by his apprehension
of the people, and of God, as manifest in their silent set or
drift. As the philosopher learns the plans of God from an unprejudiced
study of Nature, so he learned the purposes of God from the instincts
of the people. As the naturalist discovers from the structure of the
<pb n="51"/>
                  <figure entity="webb51">
                     <figDesc>51st page of Edwin
B. Webb's Memorial Sermons.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
animal what its mode of life and habits must be, so he saw from the
essential peculiarities of our Government whither our future must
tend. He did not mean to be ahead of the popular feeling; for then
there would be a re-action against his policy. He did not mean to be
much behind it; for then some other agent might be sought, through
which to give it expression: and so, regarding the voice of the loyal
people, in this great crisis of the Republic, as the voice of God, he
kept his ear open and his eye attent, and marshalled his policy not
quite abreast of the divinely led masses. He sought not to control an
age thus moved and inspired, but to be controlled by it.</p>
               <p pn="51">Herein was his wisdom, herein his greatness, herein his power. This
was the secret of his success, the source of that light which, in all
coming time, shall gild with unfading splendor the name of Abraham
Lincoln.</p>
               <p pn="51">As the Netherlands mourned for William, Prince of Orange, as France
mourned for Henry IV., "We have lost our father, we have lost our
father!" so America mourns to-day.</p>
               <lg type="stanza">
                  <l>"Such was he; his work is done;</l>
                  <l>But, while the races of
mankind endure,</l>
                  <l>Let his great example stand</l>
                  <l>Colossal,
seen of every land;</l>
                  <l>And keep the soldier firm, the statesman
pure,</l>
                  <l>Till in all lands and through all human story,</l>
                  <l>The path of duty be the way to glory.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb n="52"/>
               <p pn="52">
                  <figure entity="webb52">
                     <figDesc>52nd page of
Edwin B. Webb's Memorial Sermons.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <lg type="stanza">
                  <l>But speak no more of his renown, </l>
                  <l>Lay your earthly
fancies down;</l>
                  <l>And in the vast cathedral leave him,</l>
                  <l>God
accept him, Christ receive him!"</l>
               </lg>
               <p pn="52">1. And now, my friends, what are the lessons of this great
calamity? <hi rend="italic">First of all, submission</hi>. God reigns:
we are absolutely dependent and sinful. The Emperor Mauritius seeing
all his children slain before his face at the command of the bloody
tyrant and usurper, Phocas, himself expecting the next stroke,
exclaimed aloud, in the words of David: "Righteous art thou, 0 Lord,
and upright are thy judgments." This event takes us by surprise; but
the origin, maturity, and perpetration of this awful crime, was all
under the sleepless eye of God. For reasons which we cannot fathom
now, nor find, he has permitted it. Perhaps, when this day, <hi rend="italic">the</hi> 14<hi rend="italic">th of April</hi>, forever
marked in our calendar; marked by the humbling of the flag at Sumter;
marked by the exaltation of the flag four years after,--perhaps, when
the 14th of April comes round four years hence, we shall know more of
God's designs in permitting this foul murder of our beloved
President. There is ONE whom the hand of violence cannot reach; and he
has not led us thus far to desert and destroy us now. Meanwhile, as
becomes us, let us bow our heads in meek submission to the divine
will! Surely his footsteps are in the great deep; his designs are
hidden
<pb n="53"/>
                  <figure entity="webb53">
                     <figDesc>53rd page of Edwin
B. Webb's Memorial Sermons.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
from us in the dark; but let us trust him; let us cleave unto him!
Submitting penitently to the rod of affliction, let us put our hand in
his, and say, Father, lead; Father, spare and bless!</p>
               <p pn="53">2. A second lesson is this: Execute justice in the land. What is
the foundation of our confidence in God? Is it not that he will do
right? Is it not what David says over and over again in all his
trials?--<hi rend="italic">justice</hi> and <hi rend="italic">judgment</hi> are the habitation of his throne. And just
these--<hi rend="italic">justice</hi> and <hi rend="italic">judgment</hi>,
are the foundation of every throne, and of every government. I spoke
on Thursday, as far as it was appropriate to my theme, of the
tremendous mistake and folly and sin for the people of a great nation
to think that they can neglect or violate the laws of God with
impunity. Just here has been our danger. There has been a miserable,
morbid, bastard philanthropy, which, if it did not make the murderer's
couch a bed of flowers, and set his table with butter and honey, made
him an object of sympathy, and, after a while, of executive
clemency. We are weak in our sense of justice. Why how long is it
since a man was pursued in the streets of Washington, and, though
begging for his life, shot to mutilation? He was guilty of a foul
crime? Yes; but did that give the injured man a right to murder him?
Are there no courts, no ministers of justice, in the land? But the
murderer was acquitted with applause in the
<pb n="54"/>
                  <figure entity="webb54">
                     <figDesc>54th page of Edwin
B. Webb's Memorial Sermons.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
court-room. Only this very spring, a young woman shot one of the
clerks dead in the hall of the treasury-building. To be sure, she said
he had broken his vow to marry her. And, when I was in Washington a
few weeks since, it was confidently expected that she, too, would be
acquitted. And here in Massachusetts, not to speak of other States
now, where the punishment of murder is death, the guilty wretch--who
could brood over his infernal plan for weeks, and finally, after
several attempts on the same day, execute it upon an innocent,
unsuspecting young man, and all for the sake of a few hundreds, or, at
the most, thousands, of dollars--is allowed to live, and become an
object of sympathy. To shield his forfeited life imperils that of
every young man who stands behind a counter in Massachusetts. Living,
he is an encouragement to all persons like-minded to do likewise. Yea,
saith the governor, ye shall not surely die.</p>
               <p pn="54">And so in regard to the leaders of this infernal Rebellion: the
feeling was gaining ground here to let them off really without
penalty. They are our brethren, it is said. Then, we reply, they have
added <hi rend="italic">fratricide</hi> to the enormity of their other
crimes, and are unspeakably the more guilty!</p>
               <p pn="54">The punishment which a nation inflicts on crime is the nation's
estimate of the evil and guilt of that crime. Let these men go, and we
have said practi-
<pb n="55"/>
                  <figure entity="webb55">
                     <figDesc>55th page of Edwin
B. Webb's Memorial Sermons.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
cally that treason is merely a difference of political opinion.</p>
               <p pn="55">I do not criticise the parole which was granted; though, for the
life of me, I cannot see one shadow of reason for expecting it will be
kept by men who have broken their most solemn and deliberate oath to
the same Government. It was not kept by the rebels who took it at
Vicksburg. Nor will I criticise, for I cannot understand, the policy
which allows General Lee to commend his captured army for "devotion to
country," and "duty faithfully performed." But I considered the manner
in which the parole was indorsed and interpreted as practically
insuring a pardon; and to pardon them is a violation of my instincts,
as it is of the laws of the land, and of the laws of God. I believe in
the exercise of magnanimity; but mercy to those leaders is eternal
cruelty to this nation,--is an unmitigated, unmeasured curse to unborn
generations! It is a wrong against which every fallen soldier in his
grave, from Pennsylvania to Texas, utters an indignant and unsilenced
rebuke. Because of this mawkish leniency four years ago, Treason
stalked in the streets, and boasted defiance in the halls of the
capitol; Secession organized unmolested, and captured our neglected
forts and starving garrisons. Because of a drivelling, morbid
perverted sense of justice, the enemy of the Government has been
permitted to go at large, under the shadow
<pb n="56"/>
                  <figure entity="webb56">
                     <figDesc>56th page of Edwin
B. Webb's Memorial Sermons.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
of the capitol, all through this war. God only knows how much we have
suffered for the lack of justice. And now to restore these leaders
seems like moral insanity. Better than this, give us back the stern,
inflexible indignation of the old Puritan, and the <hi rend="italic">lex
talionis</hi> of the Hebrew Lawgiver. Our consciences are debauched,
our instincts confounded, our laws set aside, by this indorsement of a
blind, passionate philanthropy.</p>
               <p pn="56">Theodore Parker has a passage in his work on religion, in which he
gathers into heaven the debauchee, the swarthy Indian, the imbruted
Calmuck, and the grim-faced savage, with his hands still red and
reeking with the blood of his slaughtered human victims. And the idea,
to me, of placing the leaders of this diabolical Rebellion in a
position where they might come again red-handed into the councils of
the nation, is equally revolting and sacrilegious. It makes me
shudder; and yet I think there was an indecent leniency beginning to
manifest itself towards them, which would have allowed to these men,
by and by, votes and honors and lionizing. The soldiers did not relish
this prospect. They are not to be deceived by the misapplication of
the term "magnanimity" to an act that turns loose into the bosom of
society the men who systematically murdered our prisoners by
starvation, and again and again shot prisoners of war after they had
surrendered,--shot gallant officers, even
<pb n="57"/>
                  <figure entity="webb57">
                     <figDesc>57th page of Edwin
B. Webb's Memorial Sermons.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
in these last battles, after being told that they were mortally
wounded, and strung up Union men in North Carolina, because they had
enlisted in the Federal army.</p>
               <p pn="57">And now, <hi rend="italic">we</hi> see and feel just as the soldiers
do. The spirit that shot down our men on the way to the capital; the
spirit that shot Ellsworth at Alexandria; the spirit that organized
treachery, treason, and rebellion; the spirit that armed those leaders
to strike at the life of the Government,--is the same hell-born spirit
that dastardly takes the life of our beloved President, is the same
atrocious spirit that seeks the bed-chamber of a sick and helpless
man, and cuts his throat, and strikes the murderous dirk at the heart
of every attendant. We see its malignant, fiendish nature now!</p>
               <p pn="57">And what shall be done with these secessionists if we succeed in
arresting them before they get out of the country, with the blood of
the President, and of the Minister of State on their hands? Pity them
as insane? parole them as prisoners of war? Doubtless, like the
St. Albans raiders, they have their commission from Richmond! Does
this make your blood boil? is this too shocking to suppose? Well,
shall we hang them?--hang the less guilty, and let the more guilty go
free? hang the miserable, worthless hirelings, and let the principals
and chiefs live? To do that is to arm men, and goad them to take ven-
<pb n="58"/>
                  <figure entity="webb58">
                     <figDesc>58th page of Edwin
B. Webb's Memorial Sermons.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
geance into their own hands. The instinctive justice of the human
conscience must be satisfied by the action of Government, or it will
have private revenge. There is a consciousness of right in the masses,
that will not be tampered with in such a time as this. Not the
branches of this accursed tree, but the trunk and the roots, must be
<hi rend="italic">exterminated</hi> from the land. Hear me, patriots,
sires of murdered sons, weeping wives and orphans,--I say <hi rend="italic">exterminated!</hi> "Ye shall take no satisfaction for the
life of a murderer, and ye shall take no satisfaction for the life of
him that is fled, that he come again to dwell in the land; for blood
it defileth the land, and the land cannot be cleansed but by the blood
of him that shed it." And, when David died, he charged Solomon to
fulfil this divine command in regard to Joab and Shimei, who had been
too strong for him during his life.</p>
               <p pn="58">3. One thing more: <hi rend="italic">let us face the future, and all
the solemn responsibilities of these uncertain hours, with
courage</hi>. We have God on the throne that no violence can
reach,--the God who has always been with us. "Why art thou cast down,
0 my soul? and why art thou disquieted in me? Hope thou in God; for I
shall yet praise him who is the health of my countenance and my
God."</p>
               <p pn="58">And then, such is the happy structure of our Government, that no
assassination can arrest its wheels. 
<pb n="59"/>
                  <figure entity="webb59">
                     <figDesc>59th page of Edwin
B. Webb's Memorial Sermons.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
A terrible calamity has overtaken us; but it will only the more
exhibit the inherent vitality of our institutions, and the greater
strength of the people.</p>
               <p pn="59">Andrew Johnson, who now becomes the Chief Magistrate by the
mysterious providence of God, is unquestionably an able man. He has
been much in public life, and never failed, except in his speech on
inauguration-day, to meet the exigencies of his position. Besides, he
has had a schooling in Tennessee which may have prepared him to lead
at this very time. When I was in Washington, four years ago, I heard
much in his praise. He told the secessionists, who were just then
leaving their seats in the Senate to inaugurate the Rebellion,--told
them to their faces, for substance: "Were I President of the United
States, I would arrest you as traitors, and try you as traitors, and
convict you as traitors, and hang you as traitors." And, judging from
the speech which he made at Washington after the news of the fall of
Richmond, he has not changed his mind.</p>
               <p pn="59">We want no revenge: we will wait the forms and processes of law. We
want justice tempered with mercy. We want the leaders punished, but
the masses of the people pardoned. Let us confide in him as our
President. And do you make crime odious, disfranchise every man who
has held office in the rebel government, and every commissioned
officer in the rebel army; make the halter certain to the
<pb n="60"/>
                  <figure entity="webb60">
                     <figDesc>60th page of Edwin
B. Webb's Memorial Sermons.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
intelligent and influential, who are guilty of perjury and treason,
and so make yourself a terror to him that doeth evil, and a praise to
him that doeth good,--and we will stand by you, Andrew Johnson.</p>
               <p pn="60">Another ground of courage is, that the nation is a unit against
rebellion to-day as it never was before. It is too much to hope, I
suppose, that any traitor will have his eyes opened to see the true
character of the awful work in which he has been engaged, though it
seems as if such an atrocious butchery were enough to make him see it;
but of this be sure, that all loyal men are united now: and woe be to
the secessionist who does not instantly sue for mercy or fly the
country! I have seen them launch a great ship. The ways are laid solid
and secure; and then the workmen split away, one after another, the
blocks from underneath the keel. Gradually the huge structure settles
upon the slippery ways, and glides majestically into her future
element. The two ways under our ship of State are <hi rend="italic">justice</hi> and <hi rend="italic">mercy</hi>. In the
providence of God, block after block has been knocked away, prop after
prop removed, till now, just ready to glide into the new future, she
is settling all her weight upon her ways,--ways made slippery by the
blood of the murdered Chief Magistrate, and Minister: <hi rend="italic">woe, woe, woe</hi> to him who puts himself
<pb n="61"/>
                  <figure entity="webb61">
                     <figDesc>61st page of Edwin
B. Webb's Memorial Sermons.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
in the line of her course! Infinitely better for him had he been
strangled at the birth!</p>
               <p pn="61">Be sure, this people will mourn from sea to sea; but be sure also,
that any provocation will bring out the indignant, instant,
sympathetic cry from every lip, "Die, traitors, assassins all! live,
the republic, liberty, and law!"</p>
               <p pn="61">The God of infinite justice and mercy be our helper! Amen.</p>
               <p pn="61">NOTE. --Preached Sunday morning, April 16, after the news of the
assassination of President Lincoln.</p>
            </div2>
         </div1>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI.2>
