<?xml version="1.0"?>
<TEI.2>
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt n="A Memorial Discourse on the Character of Abraham Lincoln">
            <title>  A Memorial
Discourse on the Character of Abraham Lincoln </title>
            <author>Day,
P. D.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Compiled and edited by</resp>
               <name>Beck Center</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent/>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Lewis H. Beck Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Emory University</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Atlanta,
Georgia</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>1996 Emory
University. Permission is granted to download, transmit, or otherwise
reproduce, distribute or display the contributions to the work claimed
by Emory University for non-profit educational purposes, provided
this header is included in its entirety.  For inquiries about
commercial uses, contact the Director, 
Pitts Theology Library, Emory
University, Atlanta, Georgia 30322</p>
            </availability>
            <date>1999</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Lincoln
Sermons Project</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl> Day, P. D. A
Memorial Discourse on the Character of Abraham Lincoln, President of
the United States, Delivered at Hollis, N. H., on the Day of the
National Fast, June 1, 1865.  Concord: McFarland &amp; Jenks.  1865.</bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This
text derives 
from the Special Collections 
of Pitts Theology Library, Emory University, and is produced in 
collaboration with the Lewis H. Beck Center a, the Emory 
Preservation Office, and Pitts Theology Library.</p>
            <p>TRANSCRIBER: Lewis H. Beck Center and Emory University Preservation Office.</p>
            <p>PRODUCER:  BookLab, Inc., 1606 Headway Circle, Suite 100, Austin, TX 78754</p>
            <p>CAPTURE DEVICE: XEROX DocuImage 620S flatbed scanner</p>
            <p>CAPTURE DETAILS: Scanner software: XEROX ScanTool version 4.2.3; no gamma correction; images are all bitonal.</p>
            <p>CHANGE HISTORY: Using the Adobe Photoshop Batch Processor, we interpolated  the original TIFF files to 8-bit grays, and altered the resolution to 144 dpi, producing screen images twice the original size.  We then saved them in JPEG format.  We produced GIF thumbnails from the JPEG files.</p>
            <p>RESOLUTION: 600 ppi</p>
            <p>COMPRESSION: Resolution 144 per inch with Constrain Properties to 72 per inch.</p>
            <p>SOURCE: Original documents.</p>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>1999</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Scott
Ellis</name>
               <resp>Staff</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <item>SGML tags inserted in
compliance with TEI guidelines using TEILITE</item>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div1 id="day.001" n="A Memorial Discourse on the Character of Abraham Lincoln" type="text">
            <head pn="1">
               <bibl> 
                  <title>A Memorial Discourse on the Character of Abraham
Lincoln</title> 
                  <date>June 1, 1865</date> 
                  <pubPlace>Hollis,
N. H.</pubPlace> 
                  <author>Day, P. D.</author> 
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Concord</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>McFarland &amp;
Jenks</publisher>
                     <date>1865</date>
                  </imprint> 
               <idno type="ark">http://pid.emory.edu/ark:/25593/15q1p</idno></bibl> 
            </head>
            <p pn="1">
               <figure entity="day1">
                  <figDesc>1st page of P. D. Day's A Memorial
Discourse on the Character of Abraham Lincoln </figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <p pn="1">A</p>
            <p pn="1">MEMORIAL DISCOURSE</p>
            <p pn="1">ON THE</p>
            <p pn="1">CHARACTER</p>
            <p pn="1">OF</p>
            <p pn="1">ABRAHAM LINCOLN,</p>
            <p pn="1">PRESIDENT OF THE UNITED STATES,</p>
            <p pn="1">DELIVERED AT HOLLIS, N. H.,</p>
            <p pn="1">ON THE DAY OF THE NATIONAL FAST, JUNE 1, 1865.</p>
            <p pn="1">BY</p>
            <p pn="1">P. B. DAY,</p>
            <p pn="1">PASTOR OF THE CONGREGATIONAL
CHURCH.</p>
            <p pn="1">PUBLISHED BY REQUEST.</p>
            <p pn="1">CONCORD:</p>
            <p pn="1">PRINTED BY McFARLAND &amp; JENKS.</p>
            <p pn="1">1865.</p>
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p pn="2">
               <figure entity="day2">
                  <figDesc>2nd page of
P. D. Day's A Memorial Discourse on the Character of Abraham Lincoln</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p pn="3">
               <figure entity="day3">
                  <figDesc>3rd page of
P. D. Day's A Memorial Discourse on the Character of Abraham Lincoln</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <div2 id="day.002" n="DISCOURSE" type="sermon">
               <head pn="3">DISCOURSE.</head>
               <p pn="3">WE are here to-day, my friends, at the request of the
highest authority of our land, to unite with the great mass of our
countrymen in the memorial services of our late lamented and endeared
President. The mysterious events of a wise Providence have taken from
us the second Father of our Country, and a bereaved nation mourns. A
cruel and ruthless hand has smitten him down, and bathed us all in
tears. We have come to mingle our sorrows; to dwell upon his virtues,
and to learn such lessons as his untimely death is calculated to
teach.</p>
               <p pn="3">Never, since time began, has the departure of one man filled so
many hearts with sadness, and never have so many gathered, on one
occasion of mourning, as will be gathered this day. The cruel manner
of our President's death; the critical period of public affairs in
which he fell; the loss of so much experience, talent, and honest
purpose, and the sundering of so many cords of personal love, all
conspire to make the event one of the most mournful interest. All
civilized nations tender us their sympathy, and unite with us in
sorrowing over our sad bereavement. Thirty millions of hearts have
been pierced by one foul blow of the assassin,
<pb n="4"/>
                  <figure entity="day4">
                     <figDesc>4th page of P. D. Day's A
Memorial Discourse on the Character of Abraham Lincoln</figDesc>
                  </figure>
and all the enlightened world pause to sigh, and to utter their
grief. The very Goddess of Liberty comes to the bier of her martyred
chief, with folding robes, to weep.</p>
               <p pn="4">That my remarks may take the form of a religious discourse,
they will be based upon--</p>
               <p pn="4">II. SAMUEL 3: 32, 38.</p>
               <p pn="4">
                  <q pn="4" direct="unspecified">"AND THE
KING LIFTED UP HIS VOICE AND WEPT AT THE GRAVE OF ABNER, AND ALL THE
PEOPLE WEPT....AND THE KING SAID UNTO HIS SERVANTS, KNOW YE NOT THAT
THERE IS A PRINCE AND GREAT MAN FALLEN IN ISRAEL THIS DAY."</q>
               </p>
               <p pn="4">There were <hi rend="italic">two</hi> things which made the
death of Abner such an afflictive event among the Jews. <hi rend="italic">One</hi> was the <hi rend="italic">manner</hi> by which he
came to his end. He was invited aside, to hold a friendly interview,
by one of equal rank with himself, and there, while enjoying, as he
supposed, the protection of friendship and of honor, he was stabbed
under the fifth rib, and died. The deed was regarded with horror by
friends and foes, and all alike bewailed the event. David would have
put to death the assassin, as he did those of Saul and Mephibosheth,
but he found the sons of Zeruiah too hard for him, and he left the
punishment to Solomon, who executed his father's command.</p>
               <p pn="4">The other consideration which enhanced the grief of the
Jews was the fact that a man of <hi rend="italic">great worth</hi> had
fallen. Precisely in what Abner's greatness consisted, his brief
biography does not inform us, but certain it is he was a man
possessing extraordinary
<pb n="5"/>
                  <figure entity="day5">
                     <figDesc>5th page of P. D. Day's A
Memorial Discourse on the Character of Abraham Lincoln</figDesc>
                  </figure>
virtues. It was the combination of these two circumstances that threw
the whole Jewish people into such depths of sorrow.</p>
               <p pn="5">It is these two considerations that have pierced so deeply
the heart of this great nation, in the death of ABRAHAM LINCOLN. He
had led this people through the most trying period that a people ever
passed. He took the helm of state at a time when the storm was
breaking upon us; when the political sky was filled with dark,
portentous clouds; when the hearts of men quailed with fear; and, by a
rare sagacity and firmness, he piloted us through our perils. Though
at first unknown, his signal ability and devotion soon secured our
confidence and love. We saw his comprehensive thought; his christian
faith; his cheerful disposition; his persistency in the right; his
reliance on divine support; his integrity, firmness, and superior
foresight, and our hearts went out toward him. They clustered around
him as the magnetic sands around the needle, or as a family of
children around a father, when a beast of prey howls around the
dwelling. We felt a great security while he was guiding our destinies,
and worked on in cheerfulness and in hope. We should have been sad,
indeed, had he fallen by disease. Yet, had God sent some messenger of
sickness or accident to cut him of we should have had the <hi rend="italic">grief</hi>, without the indignation; but when cruelty and
atrocity are added, our cup is more than full. Our grief, our sense of
justice, our holy and unholy cravings for revenge, are all aroused,
and the national heart cries out for redress from the depths of her
sorrow.</p>
               <p pn="5">But MR. LINCOLN and his cruel murderer are both
<pb n="6"/>
                  <figure entity="day6">
                     <figDesc>6th page of P. D. Day's A
Memorial Discourse on the Character of Abraham Lincoln</figDesc>
                  </figure>
gone to their reward, and we will not pause to scrutinize further this
mysterious Providence. Justice has been defrauded of her dues, by the
sudden death of the assassin. Before the victim at which he aimed his
deadly blow was in his tomb, he died in agony, and was ingloriously
buried in an unknown grave. Millions of curses roll over his head, and
the execrations of posterity will sink him deeper and deeper in
infamy. MR. LINCOLN'S name will stand upon the pages of history as the
great martyr of civil liberty, and will be honored and admired to the
end of time. Washington and Franklin <hi rend="italic">lived</hi> for
the Republic. MR LINCOLN <hi rend="italic">died</hi> for it; and so long
as a monument of American greatness and virtue shall stand, <hi rend="italic">his</hi> will be visited and revered.</p>
               <p pn="6">Among the many causes which have led to so deep and
universal regret at his death is the fact that he was <hi rend="italic">beloved</hi> by the nation, and they loved him because he
first loved them. Love is a rare attribute in the chief magistrate of
a great people. We do not demand nor expect that he who stands at the
helm of state shall be a lovely or loving man. We have even felt that
such virtues would disqualify one for the sterner duties of judicial
or military administration. We have demanded justice, firmness,
integrity, comprehensive views of government, and have thought that
the less of the heart the better. We have so long regarded an iron
will and an iron heart as the first requisite for a ruler, that we
have thought tenderness and love a weakness. But  MR. LINCOLN has
changed our views. He was one of those rare men who could sit with
dignity and ability in the chair of State, under the ermine of
domestic and
<pb n="7"/>
                  <figure entity="day7">
                     <figDesc>7th page of P. D. Day's A
Memorial Discourse on the Character of Abraham Lincoln</figDesc>
                  </figure>
social virtue. While he was equal to any of his peers in
statesmanship, and could hold the reins of government with firmness
and strength, he could also assume the position of a father, brother
and friend. While he commanded respect and admiration as a magistrate,
he threw around him a greater charm by the manly and lovely virtues of
his great heart. He often denied men their requests, but he did it so
kindly and convincingly that they went away feeling he was their best
friend.</p>
               <p pn="7">He had neither pomp nor aristocracy in his veins. He was
born and always lived among the common people. All his associations
were with that class who obtained a livelihood by honest toil, and who
cherish the domestic virtues. Believing these virtues to be the
underlying elements of all elevated humanity, whether in high life or
in low, he took them to himself. He had no sympathy with that
so-called high, chivalrous life, which ignores purity, affection and
love.</p>
               <p pn="7">Accordingly, when he was elevated to the chief office of
the nation, he brought his character with him. He went into the White
House determined to be a <hi rend="italic"> man</hi>, as well as a <hi rend="italic">ruler</hi>; and if compelled, in some measure, to conform
to the common usages of diplomacy, he would not sink his <hi rend="italic">manhood</hi>. He would still be kind, merciful and true to
christian and social virtue.</p>
               <p pn="7">Hence the people <hi rend="italic">loved</hi> him--loved him
as they never loved a President before. He was plain, honest,
straight-forward, unsophisticated. They saw he was unambitious, and
had the courage to stand between intriguing politicians and
themselves. They heard
<pb n="8"/>
                  <figure entity="day8">
                     <figDesc>8th page of P. D. Day's A
Memorial Discourse on the Character of Abraham Lincoln</figDesc>
                  </figure>
of his genial humor, his amusing stories, his happy illustrations,
and, above all, his instinctive, genuine good sense, and persistency
in the right. They saw his self-abnegation, and his continual aim at
the public good. They saw that he laid aside the robes and airs of
royalty, and came down among them. Their souls went out toward him as
a man after their own heart. When he spoke it was like a brother or a
father. The soldier in his misfortune, the mother in her sorrow, and
the wife in her grief, were not afraid to approach him. You well
remember that wife who stood three days in the antechamber of his
house, with a babe in her arms, to ask the pardon of a husband about
to be shot, and how the cry of that child awoke all the tenderness of
his great heart, and secured the husband's release, and how the old
servant said, "Madam, it was the <hi rend="italic">baby</hi> that did
it." You remember, also, that mother whose husband and three sons had
enlisted in the service, and who, after the death of her husband, came
to ask the discharge of one of the sons, to help sustain herself and
little ones, and that before the order of release had reached that son
he was also dead, and how she came again, and the President said, "I
know what you want, you need not ask; we will divide the other two
sons between us. You shall have one, and I will retain the other." You
remember, too, how this grateful mother, with tears running down her
cheeks, dared to pass her trembling hand over his rough hair, as he
sat writing an order for the son's discharge, and said, "The Lord
bless you, Mr. President." Is it strange that such a ruler should be
loved by his people? Is it strange that they should exclaim, in the
bereaving
<pb n="9"/>
                  <figure entity="day9">
                     <figDesc>9th page of P. D. Day's A
Memorial Discourse on the Character of Abraham Lincoln</figDesc>
                  </figure>
strains of the ancient bard, "Thou wast slain in thine high places. I
am distressed for thee, my brother. Very pleasant hast thou been unto
me; thy love to me was wonderful, passing the love of women."</p>
               <p pn="9">The people also had great confidence in MR. LINCOLN'S <hi rend="italic">judgment</hi>, as well as <hi rend="italic">love</hi> for
his character. Burke said that confidence was a plant of slow growth;
but under the pressure of emergencies it will sometimes grow
fast. That was true of MR.LINCOLN. When he assumed his official trust,
the dark clouds of war were hovering around us. He was a stranger to
us, and we were fearful.  He came from civil life, and without
military experience. The circumstances of the country were all new;
there was no fixed and settled policy. Public sentiment was like
immense sea-surges, rolling over the breakers. All was agitation. If
there was any man in which the country had confidence, it was in
General Scott. What  MR. LINCOLN did was of course subject to the
severest criticism; not so much because his critics were sure he was
wrong, as they could not see, in their own inexperience, that he was
right. They had no confidence in their own judgment, and therefore had
none in his. His official position often prevented him from explaining
the reason for his course, and crafty politicians were constantly
thwarting his plans. He, therefore, was misjudged. But as time passed,
and the reasons of his policy were more fully known, and he became
more independent of the earlier influences which surrounded him, the
people saw his superior wisdom. They saw that he had a farther reach
of mind than themselves; that he took into view and balanced
considerations which they had not thought of;
<pb n="10"/>
                  <figure entity="day10">
                     <figDesc>10th page of P. D. Day's A
Memorial Discourse on the Character of Abraham Lincoln</figDesc>
                  </figure>
that he swept the whole horizon of public interest in his vision. They
learned at length to suspend their judgment when in doubt about his
policy, and to wait till all the facts were made public; and so
uniformly did his wisdom appear, that they trusted him as a child does
a father. His opinions were law. When, therefore, he was taken from
us, we felt that our compass had been dropped into the midst of the
sea, and we were left with the ship of state on our hands upon a dark,
tempestuous ocean. But thanks to Him who has hitherto shaped our
destiny, we are still on our course, and, though guided by another
compass, we trust <hi rend="italic">it</hi> will also be true to the
polar star of Liberty and Union.</p>
               <p pn="10">The people, likewise, had great confidence in MR. LINCOLN'S
<hi rend="italic">honesty</hi>. He inherited this virtue from his
boyhood, and brought it to the Presidential Chair. His early
designation was "Honest Abe." This virtue was so fully constitutional,
and so long habitual, that many thought it would disqualify him to
cope with cunning politicians. But it has been seen that a true,
honest purpose is not incompatible with able statesmanship, and that
men can successfully wield the scepter of state without letting
themselves down into the mine of political chicanery. This virtue was
as <hi rend="italic">grateful</hi> to the people as it was <hi rend="italic">rare</hi>. There is something, as Mr. Webster says, about
plain honesty in a ruler, that takes wonderfully with the people. It
is this, more than all things else, that gives us security in our
public interests. Who does not know that every civilized country has
suffered more for the want of <hi rend="italic">honesty</hi> than of <hi rend="italic">ability</hi>, in their rulers? Statesmanship is now a
science, and reduced
<pb n="11"/>
                  <figure entity="day11">
                     <figDesc>11th page of P. D. Day's A
Memorial Discourse on the Character of Abraham Lincoln</figDesc>
                  </figure>
to rules, and men of <hi rend="italic">ordinary</hi> capacity can
succeed in it. It is not superiority here that we need, as much as
unswerving integrity. We need men of intelligence, to <hi rend="italic">see</hi> the right with firmness enough to <hi rend="italic">maintain</hi> it; discernment, to discover the wrong, with
principle and independence enough to oppose it. We need men who can
cut off supernumeraries; keep the hands of under officers out of the
public treasury, and discharge those who are untrue to their trusts;
men whom others can not approach with a bribe; before whom others fear
to be dishonest, and who stand before the whole nation as a
personification of rectitude. MR LINCOLN has inaugurated a new
dispensation in this respect. Who ever said or thought he was subtle
or tricky? Who ever felt he would tolerate such a course in those over
whom he had authority? We are grateful for his rare example of honest
purpose.</p>
               <p pn="11">The people also had confidence in his <hi rend="italic">sagacity</hi> to manage our great national conflict. We
sometimes speak of greatness in men, as if it always consisted in
making eloquent speeches, in going deep into the mysteries of science,
or in laying up masses of ancient learning. But greatness often runs
in other directions, and makes other achievements. Men are often great
who are singularly destitute of all these attainments. That man is
great who is so deeply versed in the practical duties of life as to
use men and things so as to accomplish a great end. He is great who
can use great men at his pleasure, who can discover their talents,
weaknesses, and sagacity, and shape their course for a given purpose,
and who knows by instinct what others learn in schools and by
experience. Mr. 
<pb n="12"/>
                  <figure entity="day12">
                     <figDesc>12th page of P. D. Day's A
Memorial Discourse on the Character of Abraham Lincoln</figDesc>
                  </figure>
Lincoln had this greatness. It was the greatness of intuition. His
native sagacity taught him what others obtained by study and
observation. Some of his generals sought to override his judgment
because they had graduated at West Point. But his strong good sense
was better than their science. Jealousy among our military leaders was
our greatest evil. Campaign after campaign failed on this account, and
Mr. Lincoln was obliged to raise up one and put down another. It
seemed he would not have a friend left, and yet his removals were
always so kind and so clear in their necessity, that he secured the
good will of nearly all.</p>
               <p pn="12">But the rarest and highest virtue of our fallen chief was
his <hi rend="italic">christian faith</hi>. It is rare that we can speak
with so much confidence and satisfaction of a statesman's religious
character. The last request on leaving his fellow-citizens at his home
in Springfield was, "Pray for me." And we have reason to believe that
from that day till the day of his death he was himself a praying
man. It has been said by those who knew, that his first duty in the
morning was a season of devout meditation on the holy scriptures, and
a bowing at the altar. His last inaugural was a wonderful production,
and indicated a high christian culture. Some have called it a
religious homily. It was rather the outbreathing of a great
statesman's heart, who dared to recognize the hand of God in the rule
of nations, and to exhort the people to do justly and love mercy. It
came from a mind imbued with the spirit of the gospel. "Fondly do we
hope and fervently do we pray."  "With malice toward none; with
charity for all; with firmness in the right, as God gives us to see
the right, let us strive to finish
<pb n="13"/>
                  <figure entity="day13">
                     <figDesc>13th page of P. D. Day's A
Memorial Discourse on the Character of Abraham Lincoln</figDesc>
                  </figure>
the work we are in, and to bind up the nation's wounds." Such were the
noble christian sentiments of our departed chief, which secured love
and respect for him among thousands at home and abroad.</p>
               <p pn="13">When a company of clergymen called to pay Mr. Lincoln their
respects in the darkest days of our civil conflict, he said,
"Gentlemen, my hope of success in this great and terrible struggle
rests on the immutable foundations of justice, and the goodness of
God; and when events are very threatening and prospects are very dark,
I still hope, in some way which man can not see, all will be well in
the end, because our cause is just, and God is on our side." It is
said, on the day of the receipt of the capitulation of Gen. Lee, the
Cabinet meeting was held an hour earlier than usual. "Neither the
President nor any member of the Cabinet was for the time able to give
utterance to his feelings. At the suggestion of Mr. Lincoln all
dropped on their knees, and offered in silence and in tears their
humble and heartfelt acknowledgments to the Almighty, for the triumph
he had granted to the national cause."  It is in these little
incidents, which speak volumes, that we see the workings of a
christian heart.</p>
               <p pn="13">"I can never think," says one, "of that toil-worn man,
rising long before the household, and spending an hour with his Maker
and his Bible, without tears. In that silent hour of communion he has
drawn from the fountain which has fed all those qualities that have so
won on our faith and love. Ah, what tears, what prayers, what
aspirations, what lamentations, what struggles have been witnessed by
the four walls of that quiet room. Aye, what food have the angels
brought him there! There, day after day, while we
<pb n="14"/>
                  <figure entity="day14">
                     <figDesc>14th page of P. D. Day's A
Memorial Discourse on the Character of Abraham Lincoln</figDesc>
                  </figure>
have been sleeping, has he knelt and prayed for us, prayed for the
country, prayed for victory, prayed for wisdom and guidance, prayed
for strength for his great mission, prayed for the accomplishment of
his great purposes. There has he found consolation in trial, comfort
in defeat and disaster, patience in reverses, courage in labor, wisdom
in perplexity, and peace in the consciousness of God's approval."<ref target="day.002.n01">*</ref>
It was while standing by the graves of the heroes of Gettysburg, who
laid down their lives for us, that he gave his heart to One who had
laid down his life for him. And do we know, my friends, how much of
our success in our late military struggles we owe to the divine
guidance given to our President? What confidence, what courage, what
love these prayers of his have inspired in us all? Our leader,
commander-in-chief, our foremost man in all the nation, like Moses and
David kneeling at the altar, a simple-hearted child of God. What a new
and strange thing for these latter days! What a noble example is left
on record for the rising young men of our land!</p>
               <p pn="14">These are some of the leading features of this remarkable
man who has been taken from us; and these features are the more
remarkable when we remember the great deficiency in his early
training. They show an extraordinary mind, and what a true and honest
purpose, with the blessing of God, can accomplish for a diligent man
without the advantages of schools.</p>
               <lg type="stanza">
                  <l> "He was a man, take him
all in all,</l>
                  <l>We shall not look upon his like again."</l>
               </lg>
               <p pn="14">A late issue of a London paper sums up the character of
Mr. Lincoln in the following language:</p>
               <p pn="14">
                  <note pn="14" id="day.002.n01" n="*" type="foot" anchored="yes">Dr. Holland's address at Springfield, Mass.</note>
                  <pb n="15"/>
                  <figure entity="day15">
                     <figDesc>15th page of P. D. Day's A
Memorial Discourse on the Character of Abraham Lincoln</figDesc>
                  </figure>
And we take pleasure in presenting it, because it comes from a source
where we should not be likely to find an over-drawn eulogy:</p>
               <p pn="15">
                  <q pn="15" direct="unspecified">To us Abraham Lincoln has always seemed the finest
character produced by the American war on either side of the
struggle. He was great not merely by the force of genius--and only the
word genius will describe the power of intellect by which he guided
himself and his country through such a crisis--but by the simple,
natural strength and grandeur of his character. Talleyrand once said
of a great American statesman, that without experience he 'divined'
his way through any crisis. Mr. Lincoln thus divined his way through
the perilous, exhausting and unprecedented difficulties which might
well have broken the strength and blinded the prescience of the best
trained professional statesman. He seemed to arrive by instinct--by
the instinct of a noble, unselfish and manly nature--at the very ends
which the highest of political genius, the longest of political
experience, could have done no more than reach. He bore himself
fearlessly in danger, calmly in difficulty, modestly in success. The
world was at last beginning to know how good, and, in the best sense,
how great a man he was. It had long, indeed, learned that he was as
devoid of vanity as of fear, but it had only just come to know what
magnanimity and mercy the hour of triumph would prove that he
possessed. Reluctant enemies were just beginning to break into eulogy
over his wise and noble clemency, when the dastard hand of a vile
murderer destroyed his noble and valuable life. We in England have
something to feel ashamed of when we meditate upon the true greatness
of the man so ruthlessly slain. Too many Englishmen lent themselves to
the vulgar and ignoble cry which was raised against him. English
writers degraded themselves to the level of the coarsest caricaturists
when they had to tell of Abraham
<pb n="16"/>
                     <figure entity="day16">
                        <figDesc>16th page of P. D. Day's A
Memorial Discourse on the Character of Abraham Lincoln</figDesc>
                     </figure>
Lincoln. They stooped to criticise a foreign patriot as a menial might
comment on the bearing of a hero. They sneered at his manners, as if
Cromwell was a Chesterfield; they accused him of ugliness, as if
Mirabeau was a beauty; they made coarse pleasantry of his figure, as
if Peel was a posture master; they were facetious about his dress, as
if Cavour was a D'Orsay; they were indignant about his jokes, as if
Palmerston never jested. We do not remember any instance since the
wildest days of British fury against the 'Corsican Ogre,' in which a
foreign statesman was ever so dealt with in English writings as
Mr. Lincoln. And when we make the comparison we can not but remember
that while Napoleon was our unscrupulous enemy, Lincoln was our steady
friend. Assailed by the coarsest attacks on this side the ocean, tried
by the sorest temptations on that, Abraham Lincoln calmly and
steadfastly maintained a policy of peace with England, and never did a
deed, never wrote or spoke a word, which was unjust or unfriendly to
the British nation. Had such a man died by the hand of disease in the
hour of his triumph, the world must have mourned for his loss. That he
has fallen by the coward hand of a vile assassin, exasperates and
embitters the grief beyond any power of language to
express."</q>--<title>London Star.</title>
               </p>
               <p pn="16">Such at last came to be the estimate which our friends
across the water put upon our cherished President. Such we believe
will be the final verdict of the civilized world.</p>
               <p pn="16">Mr. Lincoln lived to see the last throes of the rebellion,
and we thank God that, like Moses, he was permitted to see the
promised land. He led his people to the borders, and gazed upon it,
and we prayed he might go over Jordan and possess it. But God had a
higher and more glorious reward for him. 
<pb n="17"/>
                  <figure entity="day17">
                     <figDesc>17th page of P. D. Day's A
Memorial Discourse on the Character of Abraham Lincoln</figDesc>
                  </figure>
He had toiled, and wept, and prayed for his people, and now the time
had come to give his labors into other hands; to lay down his armor,
and take up his crown. And we doubt not, while we are clothed in
habiliments of mourning in his behalf; while our pillars, and pulpits,
and rostrums are draped; while our minute guns are firing, our flags
are at half mast, and we are pronouncing his eulogies, he is dressed
in the royal robes of his exalted Master, and is joining the great
orchestra of heaven in paeans of victory. We are weeping, he is
rejoicing. We are toiling, he is resting. We are going toward the
grave, he is receding from it. We are bearing the cross and he is
wearing the crown. Nevertheless we mourn. We mourn as one friend
mourneth for another. We mourn his loss in our national councils, the
loss of his excellent example, the loss of his intuitive wisdom and
his experience, and more than all, the manner of his death. He went
into the place of public resort, not to please himself, but to please
the people, and while there, in this act of kindness, a vile hand
struck him down.</p>
               <p pn="17">While we thus mourn, we are thankful that his sun went down
without a spot upon it. Few public men die without leaving some record
of serious mistakes or folly. But Mr. Lincoln was a rare exception in
this respect. Not that every act of his, in all its details, will be
found to be the wisest possible that might have been, but no blemish
will adhere to his name. His memory will shine in ages to come like a
fixed star in a cloudless night, on which continents may gaze with
admiration.</p>
               <p pn="17">As painful as the event of our President's death is
<pb n="18"/>
                  <figure entity="day18">
                     <figDesc>18th page of P. D. Day's A
Memorial Discourse on the Character of Abraham Lincoln</figDesc>
                  </figure>
to us, we think we can see the divine hand in it. It was necessary
that this great, superlative act of treason, which has cost the North,
according to official statements, two hundred and forty thousand
lives, and the South probably more than that number, should be shown
to the world in its true light; that it should make its culmination in
such an act as will stamp its odious character for all time. It was
necessary to present it right in history, and especially to arouse
public sentiment at the North to mete out justice to the leading
spirits of the rebellion. This last foul act has opened the eyes of
the civilized world, and led them more fully to appreciate the <hi rend="italic">animus</hi> of the crime with which we have been
contending. Our first impressions were that the plot of assassination
was confined to a few fanatics. But the evidence in trial goes more
and more to implicate the Confederate authorities, and the blame of
the act does not rest so much on the immediate agents in the plot, as
upon those who directly or indirectly encouraged them. Especially upon
authorities privy to it, and upon the disloyal press both North and
South. If there are any special criminals in this work they are the
reputed wise men who have talked treason, and the press which has lent
its influence to slander and blacken the character of the
President. This is the virus which has poisoned poor, unbalanced
minds, and urged them on to their deadly deeds. So history will ever
view it. It was Booth who shot the President; but Booth was educated
for the deed. He had masters who taught and encouraged him, and who
fired up his deadly passions to the work. These masters were those,
whether with pen or voice, who
<pb n="19"/>
                  <figure entity="day19">
                     <figDesc>19th page of P. D. Day's A
Memorial Discourse on the Character of Abraham Lincoln</figDesc>
                  </figure>
vilified the Chief of the nation. If a tithe of what they said was
true, it might almost seem that one was doing God's service to remove
him. And the next great mission which we have to do for our country
will be to check the lawlessness of the press. Let men discuss
principles as fully and as plainly as they please; let them state
facts in regard to the public acts of men; let them not apologize for
nor throw any disguise over official corruption, but let them not
blacken the character of honest and worthy men, so as to make them
appear as monsters. Who does not see that this is offering a reward to
the reckless and fanatical to cut them off.  Who does not see that our
tree of liberty never can flourish under this constant girdling of its
trunk.</p>
               <p pn="19">Turning from the past to the future, let us be thankful
that we have been carried through the perils of a gigantic civil war,
and have secured a complete triumph, and not an ignoble peace. We
have, surrendered to us, the last regiment of Confederate soldiers,
and have in our possession the man who, above all, is the
personification of the rebellion. And there will be strength and
firmness enough we trust in the government to give him his dues. We
have likewise destroyed the causes of the rebellion, by cutting up the
roots of that institution out of which it grew.</p>
               <p pn="19">Who would have thought that in so short time all these
portentous war clouds would have passed away, and the olive branch of
peace would have cast its shadow on all our borders? Who would have
thought that secession would have come to such an inglorious end, and
taper out in a grand finale of a woman's dress. 
<pb n="20"/>
                  <figure entity="day20">
                     <figDesc>20th page of P. D. Day's A
Memorial Discourse on the Character of Abraham Lincoln</figDesc>
                  </figure>
God has brought in the ridiculous to help in giving odiousness to the
crime; and it will not be strange if the emblem of secession will
hereafter be a spurred man, decked with crinoline and halter. "Though
hand join in hand the wicked shall not go unpunished." We are thus
taught the wisdom and the safety of trusting in the right. Though our
pathway is dark, and not a star is seen gleaming through the
threatening clouds, it is safe to press onward in duty. It may cost us
dear, but our reward is sure.</p>
               <p pn="20">Let us then learn to prize our government more. Let us
remember what it has done for us in these tempestuous times. How it
has preserved order, and made our homes sacred amid the confusion of
civil war. Let us cling more closely to the old ship of state that has
been tempest-tost so long, but has finally brought us all safe into
port. Though the old pilot has been taken from us, let us trust the
new. Let us be wise in adjusting our remaining difficulties, that we
may go forth on our new mission before the world,--that of carrying
the blessing of liberty, intelligence, enterprise and christianity to
our entire race. Millions will be allured to our shores by the virtues
of Washington and Lincoln, and help to roll the tide of civilization
on to the Pacific, while the moral grandeur of our institutions and
our victories will command the respect of all the earth.</p>
            </div2>
         </div1>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI.2>
