<?xml version="1.0"?>
<TEI.2>
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt n="The Mission of Abraham Lincoln">
            <title>  The Mission of
Abraham Lincoln </title>
            <author>Jeffery, R.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Compiled and edited by</resp>
               <name>Beck
Center</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent/>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Lewis H. Beck Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Emory University</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Atlanta,
Georgia</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>1996 Emory
University. Permission is granted to download, transmit, or otherwise
reproduce, distribute or display the contributions to the work claimed
by Emory University for non-profit educational purposes, provided
this header is included in its entirety.  For inquiries about
commercial uses, contact the Director, 
Pitts Theology Library, Emory
University, Atlanta, Georgia 30322</p>
            </availability>
            <date>1999</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Lincoln
Sermons Project</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Jeffery,
R. The Mission of Abraham Lincoln. A Sermon Preached Before the Fourth
Baptist Church, Philadelphia, Thursday Morning, June 1st, 1865.
Philadelphia: Bryson &amp; Son, Printers and Stationers, No. 8 North
Sixth Street. 1865.  </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This text derives from the Special Collections 
of Pitts Theology Library, Emory University, and is produced in 
collaboration with the Lewis H. Beck Center a, the Emory 
Preservation Office, and Pitts Theology Library.</p>
            <p>TRANSCRIBER: Lewis H. Beck Center and Emory University 
Preservation Office.</p>
            <p>PRODUCER:  BookLab, Inc., 1606 Headway Circle, 
Suite 100, Austin, TX 78754</p>
            <p>CAPTURE DEVICE: XEROX DocuImage 620S flatbed scanner</p>
            <p>CAPTURE DETAILS: Scanner software: XEROX ScanTool 
version 4.2.3; no gamma correction; images are all bitonal.</p>
            <p>CHANGE HISTORY: Using the Adobe Photoshop Batch Processor, 
we interpolated  the original TIFF files to 8-bit grays, 
and altered the resolution to 144 dpi, producing screen 
images twice the original size.  We then saved them in 
JPEG format.  We produced GIF thumbnails from the JPEG files.</p>
            <p>RESOLUTION: 600 ppi</p>
            <p>COMPRESSION: Resolution 144 per inch with Constrain 
Properties to 72 per inch.</p>
            <p>SOURCE: Original documents.</p>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>1999</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Scott Ellis</name>
               <resp>Staff</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <item>SGML tags inserted in compliance
with TEI guidelines using TEILITE</item>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div1 id="jeffery.001" n="The Mission of Abraham Lincoln" type="text">
            <head pn="1"> 
               <bibl> 
                  <title>The Mission of
Abraham Lincoln</title> 
                  <date>Thursday Morning, June 1st, 1865</date>
                  <pubPlace>Fourth Baptist Church, Philadelphia</pubPlace>
                  <author>Jeffery, R.</author> 
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Philadelphia</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Bryson &amp; Son,
Printers and Stationers</publisher>
                     <date>1865</date>
                  </imprint>
               <idno type="ark">http://pid.emory.edu/ark:/25593/15qfb</idno></bibl> 
            </head>
            <p pn="1">
               <figure entity="jeffery1">
                  <figDesc>1st page of R. Jeffery's The
Mission of Abraham Lincoln.</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <p pn="1">THE MISSION OF ABRAHAM LINCOLN</p>
            <p pn="1">A SERMON</p>
            <p pn="1">PREACHED BEFORE THE</p>
            <p pn="1">FOURTH BAPTIST CHURCH, PHILADELPHIA,</p>
            <p pn="1">THURSDAY MORNING, JUNE 1ST, 1865.</p>
            <p pn="1">BY</p>
            <p pn="1">R. JEFFERY, D.D.</p>
            <p pn="1">PHILADELPHIA:</p>
            <p pn="1">BRYSON &amp; SON, PRINTERS AND STATIONERS, No. 8
NORTH SIXTH STREET.</p>
            <p pn="1">1865.</p>
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p pn="2">
               <figure entity="jeffery2">
                  <figDesc>2nd page of
R. Jeffery's The Mission of Abraham Lincoln.</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <p pn="2">Correspondence.</p>
            <p pn="2">REV. R. JEFFERY, D.D.</p>
            <p pn="2">
               <hi rend="italic">Dear Sir</hi>:--We, the
subscribers, joining in the general wish of your congregation,
earnestly request for publication a copy of your able Discourse on the
"<hi rend="italic">Mission of Abraham Lincoln</hi>," delivered in the
Fourth Baptist Church, June 1st,--the day of our National Fast.</p>
            <p pn="2">Yours truly,</p>
            <p pn="2">GEO. SNYDER,            A. ENGLISH,<lb/>
THOMAS MORGAN,          ASA JONES, <lb/>ROBERT PHARES,
WM. BOUKER, <lb/>A.G. HINES,             JOHN LOUTEY, <lb/>HENRY BEAGLE,
H.L. HALLOWELL, <lb/>L.B. CROSBY,            ALFRED HALLOWELL,<lb/>
E.G. DALTON,            R.N. PRATT.  <lb/>WM. H. LONGCOPE,</p>
            <p pn="2">PHILADELPHIA, June 2d, 1865.</p>
            <p pn="2">PHILADELPHIA, June 2d,
1865.</p>
            <p pn="2">GEO. SNYDER,             THOS. MORGAN, <lb/>ROBERT PHARES,
A.G. HINES, and others.</p>
            <p pn="2">
               <hi rend="italic">Gentlemen</hi>:--In response to
your kind request, I place my manuscript at your disposal.</p>
            <p pn="2">Yours truly,</p>
            <p pn="2">R. JEFFERY.</p>
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p pn="3">
               <figure entity="jeffery3">
                  <figDesc>3rd page of
R. Jeffery's The Mission of Abraham Lincoln.</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <div2 id="jeffery.002" n="THE MISSION OF ABRAHAM LINCOLN." type="sermon">
               <head pn="3">THE MISSION OF ABRAHAM LINCOLN.</head>
               <epigraph pn="3">
                  <p pn="3">"WHO KNOWETH WHETHER THOU ART COME TO THE KINGDOM FOR
SUCH A TIME AS THIS!"-ESTHER, iv. 14.</p>
               </epigraph>
               <p pn="3">WE meet to-day in accordance with the Proclamation of the
Chief Magistrate, in order to commemorate the death of the late
President of the United States. This appointment as a formal and
official recognition of such an important event is eminently
appropriate; yet as a means of attesting our respect for the office of
the deceased, of expressing our esteem for his personal character, or
of manifesting our horror at "the deep damnation of his taking off,"
this service was needless. All these have been done already. The grief
at the event was too universal, too irrepressible, to wait the process
of a formal expression. The spontaneous sorrow of a great nation could
admit of no restraint. The body of ABRAHAM LINCOLN has been followed
to the grave by twenty millions of mourners; his character has been
eulogized by the pulpit and the press of the entire land; his virtues
have been acknowledged by the unaffected sorrow of the civilized
world; his memory is enshrined in the hearts of all good men; and his
name is bequeathed to us, a legacy of goodness and of greatness
forever.</p>
               <p pn="3">What, therefore, remains to be said now? To what new
emotion can we appeal? And how is it possible by any present
expression to intensify the sincerity of our sorrow, or the
genuineness of our love? Yet the occasion of the hour affords an ample
theme for
<pb n="4"/>
                  <figure entity="jeffery4">
                     <figDesc>4th page of R. Jeffery's
The Mission of Abraham Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
profitable contemplation. The death of ABRAHAM LINCOLN deserves to be
commemorated, not simply because he was the incumbent of the highest
office in the gift of a great nation, not merely because his personal
traits won the affections of the good and inspired the confidence of
all, but specially because he seems to have been called by the
Providence of God to achieve an important mission, and because he
faithfully discharged the trust committed to him. Confessedly his
administration has been one of peculiar importance, and is destined to
exert a momentous and lasting influence upon the future of our own
country and the civilization of mankind. And "whoso is wise will
observe these things and discern" a providential purpose in bringing
ABRAHAM LINCOLN to the Presidency at such a time as that which marked
the epoch of his administration.</p>
               <p pn="4">I am aware that it is a delicate, and indeed a presumptuous
task, to infer the special designs of God, from the peculiarity of
human affairs. Those affairs themselves are ordinarily so incomplete,
occupy so small a place in the great drama of His unfolding
providences, are so interlinked with events that go before and that
follow after, and we ourselves are so limited in vision, and so easily
biased by partisan sympathies, that an attempt to interpret the
purposes of God in current events, is often a pitiable illustration of
the vanity of our imaginings, and a proof of our inability "by
searching to find out God."</p>
               <p pn="4">But in the events which make up the administration of our
lamented President, God has revealed himself. He has transcribed his
secret purposes to the pages of our national history, has written his
will in char-
<pb n="5"/>
                  <figure entity="jeffery5">
                     <figDesc>5th page of R. Jeffery's
The Mission of Abraham Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
acters of blood, and in letters so plain that he who runs may read. He
has shone forth from the darkness of his pavillion. "Out of the
heavens he has made us to hear a voice, that he might instruct
us."<ref target="jeffery.002.n01">*</ref> "The Lord hath made bare his
holy arm in the eyes of all the nations; and all the ends of the earth
have seen the salvation of our God.<ref target="jeffery.002.n02">&#x2020;</ref> "To-day, we are not called to peer
into the uncertain future, but to study the accomplished past. We are
not at a loss to know what the end of these things will be, for the
things undertaken have been performed. The results of four years of
internecine war are now distinct, accomplished, and inevitable
facts. We now know that</p>
               <lg type="stanza">
                  <l>"Behind a frowning providence </l>
                  <l>God hid a smiling face;"</l>
               </lg>
               <p pn="5">for he has caused those clouds</p>
               <lg type="stanza">
                  <l>"To break,</l>
                  <l>With blessings on our head."</l>
               </lg>
               <p pn="5">And therefore in the light of accomplished facts, we may, without
presumption, interpret the designs of God in permitting the late
events to take place. It was the design of God to accomplish the
things which have been accomplished. It was his design to accomplish
them in the manner in which they have been accomplished. It was his
design to accomplish them by the agent by whom they were
accomplished. The purpose of God has been fulfilled. ABRAHAM LINCOLN
was called to the kingdom at such a time in order to perform it. God
specially raised him up and qualified him for this self same
purpose. He did not intend that he should die until his work was
finished, and He did not intend that he should live after it was
done.</p>
               <note pn="5" id="jeffery.002.n01" n="*" type="foot" anchored="yes">
                  <p pn="5">Deut.iv. 36.</p>
               </note>
               <note pn="5" id="jeffery.002.n02" n="&#x2020;" type="foot" anchored="yes">
                  <p pn="5">Isaiah, lii. 10.</p>
               </note>

               <pb n="6"/>
               <p pn="6">
                  <figure entity="jeffery6">
                     <figDesc>6th page of R. Jeffery's
The Mission of Abraham Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <p pn="6">Let us illustrate and confirm these positions by
considering,</p>
               <p pn="6">I. The manifest results of such a time as marked the
administration of our departed President.</p>
               <p pn="6">1. In the first place we have a confirmation of the status
of our American Nationality. Hitherto its character has been
undetermined and problematical. The past ninety years of our history
have been embryotic and formative. The founders of our nation wisely
agreeing and providentially led to accept events only as they unfolded
themselves, did not attempt to bring up the actual condition of the
nation to the <hi rend="italic">ideal</hi> standard which many of them
had formed of true national life. In the Declaration of Independence
they simply intimated their conceptions of the genius and spirit of a
right government. But their initiation of an attempt at achieving the
independence of the colonies from foreign control, was the first
necessary and practicable step in attaining it. Leaving all questions
concerning the structure of a new government in abeyance, the colonies
at first simply combined in the endeavor to secure to each and all,
the right to govern themselves. Had they before-hand undertaken to
unite upon a plan of government, and proposed a revolution as a means
of effecting it, it is probable that differences of opinion regarding
abstract theories would have become so positive, as to have rendered
even a union for the purpose of gaining their independence,
impracticable.</p>
               <p pn="6">But after the independence of the colonies was
accomplished, the next great question which naturally presented
itself, was as to the kind of compact by which the
<pb n="7"/>
                  <figure entity="jeffery7">
                     <figDesc>7th page of R. Jeffery's
The Mission of Abraham Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
colonies should be associated together. The time, however, for the
adoption of ultimate views had not then come. But agreeing in the
conviction that the welfare of all concerned would be better promoted
by some sort of association, however imperfect, than by the issolated
independency of each, a compact was agreed upon, by which they became
known, thenceforth, as The United States of America. A few years,
however, sufficed to convince all that the Articles of Confederation
were too loose, too indefinite, and too inefficient to constitute the
basis of a permanent and progressive nationality. They left each State
at liberty to withdraw from the compact at pleasure, and gave to no
centralized form of authority, power to enforce obedience to the
General Government.</p>
               <p pn="7">This exigency was met by the subsequent adoption of the
present Constitution, whose object is avowed in its own terms: "We,
the People of the United States, in order to form <hi rend="italic">a
more perfect Union, &amp;c.</hi>, do ordain and establish this
Constitution of the United States."</p>
               <p pn="7">Since that time until the present, the subtile forces of
two opposite elements of organization have been at work in the
formation of the character of the American nation. Embarrassment and
conflict have arisen in the various attempts to define and prescribe
their separate, and yet harmonious spheres of action. The difficulty
has been in endeavoring to adjust the relations of the several States
to the General Government.</p>
               <p pn="7">Learning from the examples of the old world to dread
centralization of power, desirous of retaining that original
sovereignty which each State enjoyed in the achievement of its
colonial independence, our fathers were disposed to allow only so much
power to the General Government
<pb n="8"/>
                  <figure entity="jeffery8">
                     <figDesc>8th page of R. Jeffery's
The Mission of Abraham Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
as was needful for the preservation of the Union. And concessions,
even for this purpose, were cautiously and guardedly bestowed. And
events which for a long time followed, have tended to give popularity
and power to the doctrine of State Rights, until now it has come to be
accepted as an axiom in American politics, guarantied by the
Constitution, confirmed by successive Administrations, and reaffirmed
by the popular sentiment, that each State is indisputably and sacredly
sovereign in all those things that are local to itself, and that do
not conflict with the express provisions of the Constitution. This
view is not a sentiment; it is not an abstraction; it is not a
philosophy; it is an actuality in the character of American
nationality. All the preceding events of our history have conspired to
educate the people into the conception, acceptance and defence of this
declaration. So that now it would be impossible to bring the American
people to consent to any infringement on the smallest constitutional
right of a State.</p>
               <p pn="8">And yet the doctrine of State Rights, like the centrifugal
force in nature, needful in its place, if left to its unrestrained
action, would drive the State off from its orbit and involve the whole
structure of the Government in anarchy. While it was needful to guard
the General Government from any encroachment on the rights of a State,
it was never intended to give to any one State, nor to a combination
of States, the right and power to encroach on the rights of all the
States, or to deprive the General Government of the powers to preserve
unbroken, the organic unity of the United States. It was not designed
to allow a State to withdraw from the Union at its own sovereign
pleasure. And the events of the last four years
<pb n="9"/>
                  <figure entity="jeffery9">
                     <figDesc>9th page of R. Jeffery's
The Mission of Abraham Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
have settled it beyond all controversy, that no State can withdraw
from the Union. So that now we present the sublime spectacle of an
organic and unique nationality. The United States is not a congerie of
independencies, but one American State. Controlled by one central
source of unity, and distributed into so many sections for local
development, the United States of America forms a unique and glorious
system of stars, each describing its own orbit, all revolving round
one common centre; each reflecting a distinct radiance, and all lit up
by a common sun. It constitutes a galaxy of nations in one
nationality, indestructible by assault and indissoluble by
secession.</p>
               <p pn="9">Now, heretofore, one phase of the national life was an
actuality; the other was a problem. Other nations knew that the
sovereignty of the States was an accepted thesis in American politics,
but neither they nor ourselves were agreed as to the possibility, or
method of harmonizing this fact with the sovereignty of the General
Government. Many profound thinkers had pronounced the adjustment
impossible, and predicted the destruction of the Republic by the
encroachments of State demands on the central authority, or the
annihilation of the rights of a State by the usurpations of the
National Government.</p>
               <p pn="9">It has been so ordered that this question has been settled
by the adjudication of the sword. All other issues were incidental to
this grand issue. The right of a State to secede was affirmed; the
right of a State to secede was denied. The decision was left to the
dread arbitrament of war. The result is the triumph of the national
sovereignty, not over State rights, but over State
assumptions. Henceforth it is decreed, that grievances arising 
<pb n="10"/>
                  <figure entity="jeffery10">
                     <figDesc>10th page of
R. Jeffery's The Mission of Abraham Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
within the Union, must be settled within the Union. Yet,
notwithstanding the successful assertion of the National supremacy,
the sovereignty of the States is unimpaired. The war was not needful
to curtail the constitutional rights of a State, but to define and
enforce them; not to make the sovereignty of the State less, but the
supremacy of the Nation more. Heretofore some extremists have boasted
that they were citizens of a particular State of the United States;
henceforth the glory of an American will be that though a resident of
a particular State, he is a citizen of the United States.</p>
               <p pn="10">2. But the war has not merely defined the genius of
American Nationality. It has also demonstrated the practicability of
American Republicanism. The structure of our Government is complex. It
is not a simple democracy, any more than it is a simple oligarchy. It
is a composite of these apparently conflicting elements, and forms a
resultant that is distinct from both. This we call Republicanism. It
is a democracy, because every citizen has a vote in the choice of
officers, and in the determination of policies. It is an oligarchy,
because the people are bound to obey the constitutional enactments of
their chosen rulers.</p>
               <p pn="10">But the success of such Government was an experiment. It
had never been fairly tried. There had been Democracies, but they had
wrought out their own destruction; there had been attempts to form
Republics, but they had failed. The Monarchists of the Old World had
predicted and hoped for the disaster of the trans-Atlantic experiment;
the down trodden of Europe had feared it, while they prayed that it
might not be. The nationalties of Europe and Asia had succeeded in per-
<pb n="11"/>
                  <figure entity="jeffery11">
                     <figDesc>11th page of
R. Jeffery's The Mission of Abraham Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
petuating their organizations by exacting obedience to authority, by
the power of brute force. They kept up military establishments,
restrained the freedom of the press, and encroached on the rights of
conscience. They said that men were not capable of self-government,
and that a nation based on that assumption provided in the terms of
its being for its own destruction. And among ourselves, there have
been sincere men who apprehended that the people might be unequal to
the task of enforcing themselves to obedience to the laws of their
constituted rulers; while bad men have not hesitated to avail
themselves of this possibility, in order to ensure the Nation's
overthrow.</p>
               <p pn="11">Thus it has come to pass, that for years, a restless,
turbulent and ambitious portion of our own people have clamored for
favors, and demanded privileges, while others, actuated by a love of
peace, and fearing the threats of rebellion and secession, have weakly
and wickedly yielded to these insolent demands, until those who made
them began to imagine themselves the autocrats of the nation, and
their brethren and equals mercenary vassals,--men, who for the pottage
of commercial gain, were willing to sell their freedom and the
sovereignty of the nation.</p>
               <p pn="11">But evidently this way of preserving the Union was a
confession of its weakness and a precursor of its ruin. It invited
combinations for the usurpation of power, and encouraged conspiracies
for the destruction of liberty. And accordingly it was coming to
appear, that every boasted light of American citizenship was being
sacrificed on the altar of pitiful and dishonorable compromises. When
the dominations of an imposing aristocracy
<pb n="12"/>
                  <figure entity="jeffery12">
                     <figDesc>12th page of
R. Jeffery's The Mission of Abraham Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
said that freedom of speech was inimical to its interests, American
freemen were muzzled. When it demanded that requited labor should not
be tolerated on its domain, American freemen were compelled to look
elsewhere for homes. When it said that its interests required the
occupancy of the unoccupied territories, American citizens who settled
therein in defiance of their schemes, were expelled, imprisoned, or
shot. And finally, when the assumption, rendered audacious by its
success, maintained that its local interests were entitled to
universal supremacy, to which every other interest was subordinate, it
was seriously attempted to induce the freemen of America to vote
themselves the vassals of the arrogant pretension. And what was the
plea by which this base subserviency was urged? The preservation of
the Union!! If these demands are not met by concessions, the Union
will be destroyed!!</p>
               <p pn="12">Now, it is possible to urge and gain measures by
intimidations of this kind up to a certain point. Most men are
disposed to be peaceful, and are willing to make considerable
compromises for the sake of their interests; but it is possible to
demand the surrender of principles that are more sacred than
interests, and to threaten until self-respect is a stronger force than
love of peace. Besides the intimidation was itself a two-edged
sword. If it were practicable and desirable for one party to secede if
its demands were not granted, it began to be questioned whether it
would not be likewise desirable and practicable for the other party to
secede if these demands were granted. So that the very process of the
discussion of such an alternative, was educating the nation to
estimate the value of the Republic in the scales of profit and loss,
<pb n="13"/>
                  <figure entity="jeffery13">
                     <figDesc>13th page of
R. Jeffery's The Mission of Abraham Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
and to overlook that great and eternal fact which God has made to
inhere in the simplest structure of Government. The fundamental idea
of Government is <hi rend="italic">Law</hi>-- law promulgated, law
enforced. Any Government that has not authority to enforce the
obedience of its subjects to the demands of its laws, is incapable of
preserving itself from destruction; and if that Government be
Republican, it must necessarily prove and maintain its perpetuity by
demonstrating the willingness of the people to obey their own laws,
and their readiness to co-operate in compelling to submission, the
turbulent and unruly. Any organization that cannot maintain its
authority over its own members, may be an association, it may be a
compact, it may be a society, but it is not a Government. Governments
are ordained of God. Obedience to their authority is obedience to God,
and rebellion against them is rebellion against God. And the disregard
by a free people of these fundamental facts, is more than a mistake or
a blunder. It is self-repudiation. It is national suicide.</p>
               <p pn="13">The existence of a wide spread and terrible rebellion, and
the exigencies of the Government in attempting to put it down, have
conspired to evoke and test the sincerity and strength of the people's
regard for the sanctity of law. It was possible for the people to have
refused its assent to the proposition of the executive to put down the
rebellion. It was possible for them to have refuse to volunteer or to
be conscripted. It was possible for them to have withheld supplies. It
was possible for them to have decreed still further compromises, to
have ordered an armistice and to have recognized the independence of
the traitors. And throughout the progress of the conflict,
<pb n="14"/>
                  <figure entity="jeffery14">
                     <figDesc>14th page of
R. Jeffery's The Mission of Abraham Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
there have not been wanting those who were ready to urge such a base
surrender of the majesty of a great people to the behests of
rebellion. But nobly, gloriously did the people sustain the Executive
in its measures to uphold the authority of the law, and preserve the
dignity and integrity of the nation. No sacrifice of treasure or of
blood was deemed too costly for the preservation of the Republic, and
no settlement was deemed admissible that did not assert the supreme
authority of the Constitution and the Laws.</p>
               <p pn="14">And do you not see, that if the people had willed
otherwise; if by a resort to compromises and concessions the war had
been brought to a close, even though the Union had been preserved
thereby, that the result would have been accomplished by the surrender
of the high dignity of the national authority, and have been regarded
by other nations as a disgraceful confession of the inability of
American Republicanism, to enforce the obedience of its citizens to
their own laws? It would have proclaimed that in this country,
obedience to authority is optional, rebellion is a political trick,
and treason is a reserved prerogative of minorities.</p>
               <p pn="14">It has been said, and that too by men whose statesmanship
we are wont to respect, that revolution even in a Republican
Government is the right of a minority. But this position we venture to
deny. It is a contradiction in terms and an absurdity in
conception. Such a right only belongs to the oppressed subjects of a
Monarchy or irresponsible Oligarchy. But in a Republic the majority
must rule; the minority must submit. The minority may discuss, may
agitate, may protest, may revolutionize popular sentiment, but
revolutionize the
<pb n="15"/>
                  <figure entity="jeffery15">
                     <figDesc>15th page of
R. Jeffery's The Mission of Abraham Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
Government, it must not. Grant that it and every minority might claim
the right of revolution.  Resistance of it would be tyranny, and its
success would be the overthrow of the Republican principle.</p>
               <p pn="15">During the progress of the conflict, we were told that this
war was an attempt on the part of the North to subjugate the South,
and were assured that the South could never be subjugated. The first
of these assertions was a falsehood, the second, an empty boast. The
issue has not been between the North and the South, but between
national authority and rebellion. In conquering the South, we have not
subjugated one section of the country to the domination of another,
but have demonstrated the grand fact, that this Republic is able to
vindicate and maintain the majesty of its authority against rebellion,
whether that rebellion arise in the South or the North, in the East or
the West.</p>
               <p pn="15">A few years ago, Congress passed the Fugitive Slave Law,--a
law, odious to the moral convictions of the great body of the northern
people. And yet, the North did not propose to rebel. And if any
portion of their people had undertaken to inaugurate a rebellion, not
only would the National Government have been bound to enforce the
authority of the law, but every loyal man would have given to the
Government his cordial support; not because he approved of the law,
but because the Constitution is the supreme law of the land; because
the constitutionality of any measure could be tested by an appeal to
the recognized tribunal; because submission to an unjust law is a less
sin than the overthrowing of the Government for the sake of evading
the law; and because subjection to the powers that be is an ordinance
of the Almighty,
<pb n="16"/>
                  <figure entity="jeffery16">
                     <figDesc>16th page of
R. Jeffery's The Mission of Abraham Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
which no thesis of Republicanism, no pretext of Democracy, can set
aside without incurring the highest guilt of rebellion "against the
throne and monarchy of God."</p>
               <p pn="16">But to-day and henceforth, the ability of this Republic to
maintain its authority against the assaults of rebellion, is a
demonstrated fact. All those delicate questions which affected the
reaching of this consummation are settled for all time. And the people
have now learned, that the proper way in which to prevent and subdue a
rebellion, is not to propose compromises with traitors, but to insist
on the unqualified submission of all the people, in all parts of the
land, to the majesty of the Constitution and the enactments of
Congress; and to dispose of treason not by wheedling with traitors,
but by meting out to them the stern demerit of their awful crime.</p>
               <p pn="16">3. A third result of this war is the Emancipation of
Labor. It is to be regretted that in this Christian land there have
been those who, without even the apology of self-interest, could argue
for the righteousness of an institution which was based on the
principle of ownership in the manhood of man, which sold him as a
beast of the field, which denied him a right to the sanctities of
marriage, which robbed woman of her chastity, and deprived mothers of
their offspring. And even of those who deplored it as an evil, many
were at a loss how to dispose of it. But it was so ordered in the
Providence of God, that they who demanded concessions for the sake of
slavery, inaugurated rebellion against the Government because it
refused to grant them. So it came to pass, that in putting down the
rebellion it was
<pb n="17"/>
                  <figure entity="jeffery17">
                     <figDesc>17th page of
R. Jeffery's The Mission of Abraham Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
found necessary to destroy its cause. God himself put the trumpet of
his Providence to the lips of the nation, and bade it "proclaim
liberty throughout all the land, and to all the inhabitants thereof."
The sound went forth, and from that moment the smile of heaven rested
upon our efforts. And to-day we rejoice that authority is restored,
and that slavery is dead. Freedom has been given to four millions of
human beings. We have vindicated our declaration of the equality of
all men. The highway of liberty is cast up for the redeemed nation to
walk in, our victorious soldiers are returning with joy upon their
heads, and before all the people is opened up a pathway of unexampled
prosperity.</p>
               <p pn="17">For after all, to speak of the destruction of slavery,
though itself an institution cruel to the enslaved, is only to state
the blessing in a negative form. The abolition of slavery was not only
an act of justice to the slave, but, an act of justice to the
freeman. For by reason of our sympathy with, or indifference to it, we
were fostering amongst us an institution which came to us as the worst
and most repugnant element of a barbarous feudalism, and sought to be
perpetuated as an essential antagonism to the law of our own national
development. Unable to maintain a conflict with the innate force of
the principles of free labor, slavery was compelled to make special
demands in its behalf And consequently, such was the illogical and
suicidal policy it was inducing us to pursue, the Government was
forced to make discriminations that were unjust to free labor and
partial to slavery. Slaves exhausted territory, freemen cultivated
it. Slavery must have more territory, freedom must have less. Slavery
could not thrive by the
<pb n="18"/>
                  <figure entity="jeffery18">
                     <figDesc>18th page of
R. Jeffery's The Mission of Abraham Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
side of free labor, free labor must not cross geographical lines
except at its peril. To slavery must be guarantied the undisturbed
possession of its prescribed territory, free labor must shift for
itself. So that it happened, such evermore are the compensations of
Providence, that slaves were the only class who held a first mortgage
on the land, and whose homes and support were assured without effort
and anxiety from themselves, by the provisions of the Government that
enslaved them.</p>
               <p pn="18">Hence in destroying slavery, the nation really knocked off
the chains from free labor, and broke down the middle wall of
partition between free labor and the fairest portion of our vast
domain. Now white men are free, free to traverse the length and
breadth of the land, free to think, speak and act as becomes freemen
without fear of lynch law, banishment or death, free to pursue any
honorable avocation, without coming in contact with an institution
that asserted an advantage which precluded the possibility of a
business competition, or that pronounced the sweat of honest and
requited toil, a brand of infamy. It is needless to speculate as to
what a revolution of advantage and prosperity to trade, to intercourse
and intelligence, this wondrous change must make. Already the
advantages of free labor are beginning to be confessed by those who,
only a short time ago, were in rebellion for the sake of perpetuating
slavery. And only a few years will elapse before the wilderness of the
South will be populated with a hardy, industrious and enlightened
people. Their demands and necessities will react upon the North, to
the quickening and enlarging of industry and commerce, to the
increasing of wealth and the diffusion of knowledge, and to the
elevating of all to
<pb n="19"/>
                  <figure entity="jeffery19">
                     <figDesc>19th page of
R. Jeffery's The Mission of Abraham Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
that position of prosperity and intelligence, which shall constitute
the high argument of the folly and sin of slavery, and the
unanswerable illustration of the superiority of that civilization
which gives every man "an equal chance" in life, and makes requited
and unrestricted labor the birthright of all, and the precursor of
individual well being and national greatness. And in view of these
glorious results, the time is not far distant when the white and the
black men of the South will join in mutual acknowledgements of
gratitude and honor, to those who, by the sacrifice of their treasure
and lives, disenthralled them both, and consecrated our entire domain
to liberty, law and labor.</p>
               <p pn="19">II. Now in considering the agencies by which these grand
results have been achieved, we assert that the nation is specially
indebted to the services of our departed President. Four years ago,
who could tell whether ABRAHAM LINCOLN was called to the kingdom for
such a time as then burst upon us? But are any at a loss to answer the
question now?</p>
               <p pn="19">1. We are able to say that he was brought to the kingdom
for such a time, in view of the circumstances of his nomination and
election. Though presented to the suffrage of the people on a distinct
and new issue, yet it was not seriously believed by many, that his
election would prove the occasion for raising the standard of
revolt. And if the nomination and election of a President had been
with a view to such a contingency, it is by no means probable that the
choice of the convention, or of the people, would have fallen upon
him. He was an untried man. He was an unambitious man. He
<pb n="20"/>
                  <figure entity="jeffery20">
                     <figDesc>20th page of
R. Jeffery's The Mission of Abraham Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
did not belong to the coterie of presidential aspirants. And even his
nomination, as it was, appears to have been a political resort,
rendered necessary because of the inability of rival factions to unite
upon any of the acknowledged candidates for the office. And when at
length civil war came upon us, many doubted whether our untried
President was the man for the crisis, while some, even of his
supporters, clamored for his supersedure by the appointment of a
dictator. But when in the light of the experience of more than three
years of war, the people were called upon to choose a President for
another term, with what unexampled unanimity did they interpret the
will of God, that ABRAHAM LINCOLN had been called to the Presidency
for such a time as this?</p>
               <p pn="20">Yes for just such a time as this. Suppose one of <hi rend="italic">some</hi> of the men who have been Presidents, had been
President when Fort Sumpter was attacked, should we occupy the
position we hold to-day? Ah, no. In that event we might have had
reason for thinking that God was designing to work out our
destruction. But He was intending, not as some have said to punish us,
but to purify and ennoble us, so he did not give us an instrument of
his displeasure, but he placed over us "a man after his own heart." We
see it now; he was defeated as a candidate for the office of United
States Senator, that he might be elected President. The American
people chose ABRAHAM LINCOLN to be their National President; God chose
him to be their National Saviour.</p>
               <p pn="20">2. In the second place, observe the general fitness of
ABRAHAM LINCOLN for just such a time. God, when selecting an
instrument for the accomplishment of his purposes, always has a regard
to the law of adaptation. 
<pb n="21"/>
                  <figure entity="jeffery21">
                     <figDesc>21st page of
R. Jeffery's The Mission of Abraham Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
The original traits of Moses qualified him to be the leader and
law-giver of the Israelites. David was possessed of elements suited to
the part in the kingdom of Israel he was called upon to act. And all
the characteristics of Paul's nature, fitted him to be the Apostle to
the Gentiles. And so it was in regard to ABRAHAM LINCOLN. The American
people blundered upon him. God chose him with special reference to
coming events.</p>
               <p pn="21">He entered upon untried difficulties. No precedents were
before him:--for such a rebellion, so vast, so comprehensive, so
formidable, so vindictive, so contrary to liberty, so dishonoring to
human nature, so defiant of the laws of Providence, against a
Government, so generous, so just, so lenient, had never occurred in
the history of the race. Its only counterpart, was that revolt among
the angels against the supremacy of God.</p>
               <p pn="21">Now, ABRAHAM LINCOLN entered upon his perilous task with a
profound and humble trust in the superintending Providence of God in
the affairs of men. He seemed to feel, and without presumption or
affectation, that he was the appointed instrument for working out the
mystery of the will of God. He did not seek to control events, but to
be controlled by them. And yet, he was not a fanatic. On the contrary,
he brought to the consideration of every question, the cautiousness
and promptness of a well-balanced and acute mind. He was able to
grapple with the most imposing difficulties, to analyze the most
subtle principles, to disentangle the most perplexing circumstances,
to reach conclusions with a slowness which showed his appreciation of
their importance, to announce them with a firmness which indicated his
confidence, to abide by them with an assur-
<pb n="22"/>
                  <figure entity="jeffery22">
                     <figDesc>22nd page of
R. Jeffery's The Mission of Abraham Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
ance that his positions would be justified by events. And yet, unlike
a weak or vain man, he had no pride of opinions to preserve. He was
ready to change his plans, to modify his measures, to retrace his
steps, to own his mistakes and to receive advice. And withal he was
possessed of such an honesty of purpose, that even those who differed
from him trusted him, and such a benevolence of heart, that his
bitterest enemies were those who hated him because he gave them no
occasion for their malignity. This rare combination of traits
qualified and proved him to be the man for the time.</p>
               <p pn="22">3. In addition to these general traits, there were peculiar
elements in the character of ABRAHAM LINCOLN, that specially proved
his fitness for the Presidency at such a time. In the first place: He
clearly comprehended the fundamental law of American Nationality. Some
statesmen are like certain religionists, who, in their anxiety to
model their church organizations after the pattern of the New
Testament, confound the formative with the normal condition of the
primitive church, and insist that some of its incipient elements were
ultimate principles. But ABRAHAM LINCOLN, saw that the past of our
national history was only a period of assimilation and development,
and that the organic and essential idea of our nationality could only
be asserted and received when the logic of events demonstrated its
consummation. In the exigencies of civil war, our nationality attained
a symmetry and concentration of its several forces, which proved that
its organic law was unity, and that the operation of its parts was not
the action of confederated agencies, but the expansion and development
of an organic entity. Hence, in the beginning of the war he asserted
the im-
<pb n="23"/>
                  <figure entity="jeffery23">
                     <figDesc>23rd page of
R. Jeffery's The Mission of Abraham Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
possibility of the division and dissolution of the Union, because of
the essential unity which inhered in the law of its being.</p>
               <p pn="23">Secondly: He clearly understood the nature of the issue
involved in the contest. Men of narrow views have ascribed this war to
the bitterness of sectional hate, but wiser men saw that it was the
action of an inevitable conflict between opposing systems of
civilization. And, with a characteristic sententiousness he applied to
it the aphorism of the Saviour, "'A house divided against itself
cannot stand.' I believe this Government cannot endure permanently,
half slave and half free. I do not expect the house to fall; but I do
expect it will cease to be divided. It will become all one thing or
the other." Accordingly from the first he entertained no sympathy with
compromises with slavery. It would not admit of compromises. It had
broken all previous ones, and made new and encroaching
demands. ABRAHAM LINCOLN saw that if this process went on, the nation
would become "all slave," and that freedom would become an outcast
from its last asylum.</p>
               <p pn="23">Again: His early training had impressed him with a high
sense of the dignity and value of labor. While many young men of his
age thought it manly to affect a gentility which exhausts itself in
smoking cigars, drinking wine, aping exquisite fashions, playing the
gallant to silly girls, ABRAHAM LINCOLN was clearing up the Western
forest, felling trees, ploughing around stumps, splitting rails, and
navigating flat-boats on the waters of the Ohio and Mississippi. Thus
his sympathy with toil was genuine. He knew its disadvantages, its
needs, and its glory; and his experience was intensified
<pb n="24"/>
                  <figure entity="jeffery24">
                     <figDesc>24th page of
R. Jeffery's The Mission of Abraham Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
by personal and constant observation of the unjust discriminations
which the feudalism of the slave system imposed upon free labor. As
God trained David to be king while in his father's sheepfolds, so he
was fitting ABRAHAM LINCOLN, in this rugged, simple, sturdy Western
life, to be the coming man, who should give freedom to a race and
salvation to a nation.</p>
               <p pn="24">Still further: ABRAHAM LINCOLN had a nature which was
intuitively actuated by the impulses of a broad philanthropy. In the
narrow, technical sense of the word, he was not an abolitionist. He
was not specially and exclusively a friend of the negro. He loved the
human race. He believed in the brotherhood of man, and allowed no
differences in constitution, color, culture or country, to commit him
to unjust discriminations against the manhood of man. He sought to
make every man better and happier. He delighted in opportunities to
sympathise with the suffering and the sorrowing. And in smoothing the
pillow of a dying soldier, in listening to the griefs of a stricken
mother, in helping a little boy, in giving a smile or word of cheer to
an aged negro, or in searching for the nest of a fallen bird, ABRAHAM
LINCOLN gave as true an expression of his simple and full-hearted
benevolence, and experienced a pleasure as genuine as when he signed
the Proclamation of Emancipation.</p>
               <p pn="24">So that, while he met the issues of this great conflict,
with a firmness that did not flinch, and a justice that did not yield
to intimidation, he resisted rebellion without resentment, he endured
detraction without impatience, punished treason without cruelty,
emancipated a race without vanity, and carried the nation unto victory
without arrogance. And when all these things were
<pb n="25"/>
                  <figure entity="jeffery25">
                     <figDesc>25th page of
R. Jeffery's The Mission of Abraham Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
done, "with charity for all and malice towards none," he at once
turned towards his deluded and disappointed countrymen, not to triumph
over their mortification, but to assure them of the sincerity of a
brother's love.</p>
               <p pn="25">4. Finally: The special Providence of God in the
administration of ABRAHAM LINCOLN, is seen in the circumstances and
time of his death. The slave demon was not to be conciliated by the
overtures of goodness. The same spirit which had for centuries fed on
cruelties, and which sought to gain its present ends by perverting the
plainest truths, by subjecting captured soldiers to tortures that
transcended the barbarisms of the ages, and by flaunting defiance in
the face of God's clearest Providences, true to its instincts, could
not die without striking its envenomed fang into the heel of the man
who had struck its head. But in this, slavery overreached itself. It
not only did not save itself, but it consecrated the name of its
destroyer to freedom, and freedom to the future generations of
mankind.</p>
               <p pn="25">Men have regretfully wondered why ABRAHAM LINCOLN was not
spared to finish the work he had undertaken. They forget
themselves. He had finished it. Attempts to assassinate him had been
made before; but they had failed. His hour had not come; his work was
not completed. It was decreed that the fourteenth day of April, 1865,
should be an era in the annals of history, an epoch in the cycles of
time, the Good Friday of American Redemption. Four years before, on
that very day, rebellion committed its first overt act. It fired on
the American flag that floated over Fort Sumter. Four years had
elapsed,--years of carnage, of cruelties, of hopes and fears; but all
this time what moral changes were
<pb n="26"/>
                  <figure entity="jeffery26">
                     <figDesc>26th page of
R. Jeffery's The Mission of Abraham Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
going on! The genius of the American nationality was developing
itself. Republicanism was proving its vitality. A race of slaves was
being made free, and a nation of freemen was being brought up to the
measure of their high vocation, in deeds of unexampled sacrifices,
wondrous charities, valiant courage and enlightened justice. God
permitted the rebellion to be strong enough and blind enough, to last
long enough, to exhaust itself and die. So that just at the end of
four years to the very day, the flag that was shot down from Fort
Sumter was restored to its place, the proud symbol of a restored,
disenthralled and victorious nationality.</p>
               <p pn="26">This done, and the mission of ABRAHAM LINCOLN was
accomplished. And strange, marvellous coincidence! On that very day,
not in the morning before the Stars and Stripes had been raised over
Sumter, but in the evening, after the glorious deed was done, ABRAHAM
LINCOLN received his summons to resign his trust. He had done his
work. He had done it well. And the universal verdict of mankind is the
counterpart of the Divine award, "Well done, good and faithful
servant, enter thou into the joy of thy Lord."</p>
               <p pn="26">Besides, the manner of his death is another element in the
speciality of his calling. If his death had occurred from natural
causes, his character would have been no less genuine, his work no
less complete, our regrets no less sincere, but it would have lacked
that finish which was needed to give uniqueness to his mission and
effect to his life. Slavery wanted a victim. Liberty needed a
martyr. Despairing of destroying the life of the nation, in its dying
frenzy slavery took the life of the nation's preserver. But it little
thought that in this it was
<pb n="27"/>
                  <figure entity="jeffery27">
                     <figDesc>27th page of
R. Jeffery's The Mission of Abraham Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
answering the purpose of God. Jewish hate gave to the world a
Redeemer; slaveholding malignity gave to Liberty a Martyr.</p>
               <p pn="27">Now we know why ABRAHAM LINCOLN lived, why he was made the
President of the United States, why he was re-elected for a second
term, why he lived out only so small a portion of that second term,
why he did not die sooner, why he did not live longer. The work to
which he was called required the lapse of just four years for its
accomplishment. On the fourteenth day of April, 1861, Slavery,
vigorous and defiant, struck down the American flag; on the fourteenth
day of April, 1865, Slavery, dying and damned, struck down the
American President. But the rebellion was crushed, slavery destroyed,
and the nation redeemed. The fifteenth day of April dawned upon a new
era in our national existence. The sun as it rose that morning, gazed
for the first time upon our nation radiant in its new-born liberty,
joyous in its assured integrity, and jubilant in the prospects of its
opening career of prosperity and peace. The Spirit of ABRAHAM lingered
just long enough on earth to cross the line of the dispensation, "when
the chariot and the horsemen thereof" came down and took him from the
scenes of his toil to the rest and reward of heaven. It was expedient
that he should die, and that he should die for the nation. It was
fitting that his blood should mingle with that of the thousands who
had fallen before him. It was fitting that he lived to cross the
boundary of our Canaan, for now his grave is the monument of our
transition, and his "soul marching along," in the carreer of our
progress, is the inspiration of our hopes, the guardian of our
liberties, and the harbinger our destiny.</p>
               <pb n="28"/>
               <p pn="28">
                  <figure entity="jeffery28">
                     <figDesc>28th page of
R. Jeffery's The Mission of Abraham Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <p pn="28">As he stood on the battle-field of Gettysburg with graves
of the fallen brave around him, he used these memorable words: "We
cannot dedicate, we cannot consecrate, we cannot hallow this
ground. The brave men who struggled here have consecrated it, far
beyond our power to add or detract. The world will little note, nor
long remember what we say here, but it can never forget what they did
here. It is for us, the living, rather to be dedicated to the
unfinished work which they who fought here have so nobly advanced. It
is rather for us to be here dedicated to the great task remaining
before us, that from these honored dead we take increased devotion to
that cause for which they gave the last full measure of devotion, that
we here highly resolve that these dead shall not have died in vain;
that this nation, under God, shall have a new birth of freedom, and
that Government of the people, by the people, and for the people,
shall not perish from the earth."</p>
               <p pn="28">So say we to-day. Let the death of our great and good
President consecrate us, to the realization in ourselves of the spirit
which animated him. Let us dedicate ourselves to keeping that which he
has given us. Let us forget past differences. Let us hate slavery. Let
us love freedom. Let us honor labor. Let us respect the rights of the
humblest and weakest and meanest of God's creatures. Let us go on to
fulfill the mission to which God has called us of being the model of a
pure and ennobling civilization. Let us prove worthy of ABRAHAM
LINCOLN.</p>
            </div2>
         </div1>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI.2>
