<?xml version="1.0"?>
<TEI.2>
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt n="Discourse the Day After the Reception of the Tidings of the Assassination of President Lincoln">
            <title>  Discourse the Day
After the Reception of the Tidings of the Assassination of President
Lincoln </title>
            <author>Parker, Rev. Henry E.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Compiled and edited by</resp>
               <name>Beck
Center</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent/>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Lewis H. Beck Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Emory University</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Atlanta,
Georgia</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>1996 Emory
University. Permission is granted to download, transmit, or otherwise
reproduce, distribute or display the contributions to the work claimed
by Emory University for non-profit educational purposes, provided
this header is included in its entirety.  For inquiries about
commercial uses, contact the Director, 
Pitts Theology Library, Emory
University, Atlanta, Georgia 30322</p>
            </availability>
            <date>1999</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Lincoln
Sermons Project</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Parker,
Rev. Henry E. Discourse the Day After the Reception of the Tidings of
the Assassination of President Lincoln, Preached in the South
Congregational Church, Concord, N. H., April 16, 1865.  Concord:
Printed by McFarland &amp; Jenks.  1865 </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This text derives from the Special Collections 
of Pitts Theology Library, Emory University, and is produced in 
collaboration with the Lewis H. Beck Center a, the Emory 
Preservation Office, and Pitts Theology Library.</p>
            <p>TRANSCRIBER: Lewis H. Beck Center and Emory University 
Preservation Office.</p>
            <p>PRODUCER:  BookLab, Inc., 1606 Headway Circle, 
Suite 100, Austin, TX 78754</p>
            <p>CAPTURE DEVICE: XEROX DocuImage 620S flatbed scanner</p>
            <p>CAPTURE DETAILS: Scanner software: XEROX ScanTool 
version 4.2.3; no gamma correction; images are all bitonal.</p>
            <p>CHANGE HISTORY: Using the Adobe Photoshop Batch Processor, 
we interpolated  the original TIFF files to 8-bit grays, 
and altered the resolution to 144 dpi, producing screen 
images twice the original size.  We then saved them in 
JPEG format.  We produced GIF thumbnails from the JPEG files.</p>
            <p>RESOLUTION: 600 ppi</p>
            <p>COMPRESSION: Resolution 144 per inch with Constrain 
Properties to 72 per inch.</p>
            <p>SOURCE: Original documents.</p>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>1999</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Scott Ellis</name>
               <resp>Staff</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <item>SGML tags inserted in compliance
with TEI guidelines using TEILITE</item>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div1 id="parker.001" n="Discourse the Day After the Reception of the Tidings of the Assassination of President Lincoln" type="text">
            <head pn="1"> 
               <bibl> 
                  <title>Discourse the
Day After the Reception of the Tidings of the Assassination of
President Lincoln</title> 
                  <date>April 16, 1865</date>
                  <pubPlace>Concord, N. H.</pubPlace> 
                  <author>Parker, Rev. Henry
E.</author> 
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Concord</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Printed
by McFarland &amp; Jenks</publisher>
                     <date>1865</date>
                  </imprint>
               <idno type="ark">http://pid.emory.edu/ark:/25593/15qrk</idno></bibl> 
            </head>
            <p pn="1">
               <figure entity="parker1">
                  <figDesc>1st page of Rev. Henry
E. Parker's Discourse the Day After the Reception of the Tidings of
the Assassination of President Lincoln.</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <p pn="1">DISCOURSE</p>
            <p pn="1">THE DAY AFTER THE</p>
            <p pn="1">RECEPTION OF THE TIDINGS</p>
            <p pn="1">OF THE ASSASSINATION OF</p>
            <p pn="1">PRESIDENT LINCOLN,</p>
            <p pn="1">PREACHED IN THE</p>
            <p pn="1">South Congregational Church,</p>
            <p pn="1">CONCORD, N.H., APRIL 16, 1865.</p>
            <p pn="1">BY THE PASTOR,</p>
            <p pn="1">REV. HENRY E. PARKER.</p>
            <p pn="1">CONCORD:</p>
            <p pn="1">PRINTED BY McFARLAND &amp; JENKS.</p>
            <p pn="1">1865.</p>
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p pn="2">
               <figure entity="parker2">
                  <figDesc>2nd page of
Rev. Henry E. Parker's Discourse the Day After the Reception of the
Tidings of the Assassination of President
Lincoln.</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p pn="3">
               <figure entity="parker3">
                  <figDesc>3rd page of
Rev. Henry E. Parker's Discourse the Day After the Reception of the
Tidings of the Assassination of President
Lincoln.</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <div2 id="parker.002" n="DISCOURSE" type="sermon">
               <head pn="3">DISCOURSE.</head>
               <epigraph pn="3">
                  <p pn="3">JOHN 11: 53. 
	<lb/>"Then from that day forth they took counsel together for
to put him to death."</p>
               </epigraph>
               <p pn="3">It is no new thing for the good to be hated, and to be
martyred. Eighteen hundred years ago a Divine One walked the earth;
yet he had bitter enemies, who foully plotted against his life; nor
did their malice subside till their fiendish machinations were
successful; with a traitor's aid they compassed his death one Friday
afternoon in April, or the month most nearly corresponding to it in
the Jewish Calendar. That day has been remembered. A large part of the
Christian world annually commemorate it with enjoined fastings and
penitential sorrow. Day before yesterday was its anniversary; the day
once made dark with the crucifixion. It is by a strange permission of
Providence that henceforth the American mind will associate with Good
Friday and its dying Lord, the death of our honored
President. Providence has permitted the singular coincidence, sad and
sacred. Nor was it any dishonor to thee, President Lincoln, to have
fallen by the hand of such an assassin--the victim of such malice. The
friendship of such men would have been a dishonor--men in whose hearts
was still rampant the demon of secession and rebellion. This is not the
<pb n="4"/>
                  <figure entity="parker4">
                     <figDesc>4th page of Rev. Henry
E. Parker's Discourse the Day After the Reception of the Tidings of
the Assassination of President Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
first case where hatred, and wrong, and violence, have been an eternal
honor to him who has experienced them. Thine assassination by
Secessia's hand is the very crown of thy patriotism and worth!</p>
               <p pn="4">And murder, murder just like this, horrible as hell could
conceive, which has stunned the nation this day, which will shock the
world, we had, perhaps, full reason to expect. When, four years ago
this last fall, the votes of the nation declared to the South that
they could no longer rule the country, that their power had departed,
then were formed plots to seize upon the government by violence, and
prevent the rightful occupant from ever reaching the Presidential
Chair. "Then from that day forth they took counsel together for to put
him to death." We well remember how, only through the adroit
management of friendly railroad officials, the President reached
Washington at all. We could not believe it till the fact was forced
upon us, that there was a definite, well-laid plan to assassinate him
on the way; and that leading southern men were both cognizant of the
plot and accessory to it. We know, however, that for a long time
guards were felt to be necessary about the Presidential mansion. We
know how that, from time to time, discoveries were made of new plots,
requiring new precautions. We remember how, when for health's sake the
President had retired to the "Soldiers' Retreat" as a summer
residence, it was found requisite for his safety that he should be
daily accompanied in and out from Washington with a mounted
escort. The threats of the dangers of assassination thus have always
hung about him.</p>
               <p pn="4">Or is it surprising that the black heart and bloody
<pb n="5"/>
                  <figure entity="parker5">
                     <figDesc>5th page of Rev. Henry
E. Parker's Discourse the Day After the Reception of the Tidings of
the Assassination of President Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
hand of the genius of slavery and rebellion should have been equal to
an act like this; the pitiless heart, the savage hand, long familiar
with lacerating the naked bodies of bondmen and bondwomen, tearing
husbands and wives asunder, parents and children;--that black heart
which could nourish treason such as this rebellion has brought forth,
how natural a nest for such a project of assassination! That
matricidal hand lifted against the mother-country of us all --how
slight a thing for it to wield the assassin's weapons! And when, by
the recent victories, it had at last become evident to the blindest
southern pride and hate that the miserable cause of the Confederacy
was meeting its miserable end, then, stung to madness in its
disappointed rage, this act is most naturally committed: like the
devils of the bottomless pit, ruined themselves, their only remaining
care to ruin as much with them as possible. I know of no parallel out
of hell. The nearest to it in human history is the act of Herod, who,
when he knew that he must die, incarcerated the most eminent citizens
of the realm, with strict orders for their assassination at the moment
of his death, that there might be some mourning in the land. Oh that
it had been the will of heaven in like manner to have frustrated this
infernalism as it did that!</p>
               <p pn="5">Yes, we had reason enough to infer this act, but it had
been deferred so long we fondly hoped that safety was secured. Alas!
how terribly were we mistaken! Oh, my country, my country! How have I,
in these late years, mourned for thee in thy prostration in the
dust!--at the humiliating spectacle thou has made for the derision of
the nations--who have scoffed at
<pb n="6"/>
                  <figure entity="parker6">
                     <figDesc>6th page of Rev. Henry
E. Parker's Discourse the Day After the Reception of the Tidings of
the Assassination of President Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
thy struggles and thy sorrows--who have mocked at thy departing
greatness and glories, as they hoped; who have looked upon thy
gigantic efforts against thy foe, thy wounds and thy blood, as the
degenerate thousands of the ancient amphitheater stretched their eager
necks, and with fiendish satisfaction gloated over the struggling
gladiators of the arena,</p>
               <lg type="stanza">
                  <l>"Butchered to make a Roman holiday!"</l>
               </lg>
               <p pn="6">And now, when at last I saw thee, my noble country, emerging from
thy humiliation and disgrace, and springing to shine old position of
influence and renown, and more,--Oh, to see thee present this most
humbling sight of all before the world, of having nourished such a
monster, capable of such an act, and of having such a deed committed
upon thy soil! for, excepting <hi rend="italic">the</hi> murder of the
ages, the crucifixion itself, human history seems not to have
furnished its parallel.</p>
               <p pn="6">But, my hearers, are there any words to be uttered this
hour, beside those of bitter lamentation for the act and execration of
it? Can I to-day perform my usual duty of uttering God's lessons to
you, as suggested by the volume of his word or the book of his
providence? Sufficient time has not yet elapsed to enable us to
recover from the appalling, bewildering effects of the tidings. We can
not yet look upon the matter with a clear and steady eye. Still, I
feel there are some things I can even now say.</p>
               <p pn="6">And, first: I feel that we are more than ever in God's
hands; that he is most directly and conspicuously dealing with
us. Think of our feelings the
<pb n="7"/>
                  <figure entity="parker7">
                     <figDesc>7th page of Rev. Henry
E. Parker's Discourse the Day After the Reception of the Tidings of
the Assassination of President Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
past two weeks till yesterday. There were no bounds to our joy--we
could not express it! And how that joy brought the nation in gratitude
to God; the nation never so acknowledged him in any joy. Every speech
that was made did it; men did it one with another; men who seldom
spoke his name felt then they must speak of him; where men gathered in
the business mart, and on the exchange, doxologies must be sung, and
prayer and the devout offering of thanksgiving be made. I am so glad
God was thus acknowledged; not indeed as he ought to have been, but
yet as he never was before, it gives us such ground for trusting that
this terrible thing is something other than a divine rebuke. And now
our sorrow is as great as was then our joy. The very greatness of
these extremes in the permissions of God's providence, are a proof
that he is as signally with us. It is not in wrath, it is not in
divine desertion that we are experiencing this. The magnitude of the
previous mercy shows this. That was in one sense a gracious
preparation for this; and we have still all our late successes and
victories to lean upon to strengthen and support us.</p>
               <p pn="7">It is possible that without great and increasing elation,
there may have been some danger that we should come to lose our sense
of dependence--come to feel as though all our troubles were past, no
more dangers to fear, and so soon become God-forgetting and
self-sufficient. I do not know; perhaps God saw this was about to
be--and he anew humbled us, and taught us, right in the midst of our
highest joy, that without his preservation, every cup of our hopes and
satisfactions will be dashed.</p>
               <pb n="8"/>
               <p pn="8">
                  <figure entity="parker8">
                     <figDesc>8th page of
Rev. Henry E. Parker's Discourse the Day After the Reception of the
Tidings of the Assassination of President
Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <p pn="8">Long ago I learned to feel that the more striking the
events in our personal experience, the more evidently God is dealing
with us as individuals. I do not know why I should have any less
strong convictions when applying the rule to national events.</p>
               <p pn="8">II. But I see more clearly the hand and the mercy of God in
not allowing this event to occur until it did. Had the first
intentions of assassination, and the first attempts four years ago
been successful, it is difficult to say how dire might have been the
results. Anarchy, very likely, would have sprung upon us at once. Our
institutions, our circumstances, certainly then could not have borne
such a trial, so critical a test as they can now; or if the event had
occurred at any time subsequently until the present. And think what an
interposition of the divine goodness we ought to call it, and most in
the loyal States will call it, that the President was not taken away
before completing the great acts of his administration, especially the
two which have most signalized it, the bringing an end to slavery and
to the rebellion.</p>
               <p pn="8">III. Another thought which presents itself is, that perhaps
this last act was needed to complete the infamy of the rebellion and
secession, and of that nefarious system of human servitude out of
which secession and rebellion grew. Such an act as this is the
legitimate offspring of those monsters, and nothing else. It is the
very hard-hearted pitilessness and savagery of slavery which can thus
wrest the life of the devoted husband from directly beneath the eyes
of the loving wife, and tear the life of the fond father directly from
<pb n="9"/>
                  <figure entity="parker9">
                     <figDesc>9th page of Rev. Henry
E. Parker's Discourse the Day After the Reception of the Tidings of
the Assassination of President Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
the embraces of dear children; slavery can educate to such bloody
heartlessness. It was the hand of rebellion and secession that first
recklessly and ruthlessly snatched war's flaming brand and waved it
challengingly and defiantly in the eyes of this government and this
nation; and it is the same hand of revolting and appalling
recklessness and crime which has now seized the assassin's weapons,
and, after with one of them murdering the defenseless man, the
husband, the father, the President, waved the other with that tragedic
style and devil's heroism which have characterized the actors in the
rebellion all along. Perhaps this last consummating act was needed to
open fully the eyes of foreign nations sympathizing with secession to
the true animus of the rebellion. I doubt if we hear any more
commendations of it, or apologies for it; it will at last have
succeeded in awakening the detestation and abhorrence of the civilized
world, as it long ago should have done.</p>
               <p pn="9">And I am not sure but that we too needed this further deed
of horror to be done, that we might be preserved from all false
leniency toward that trio of abominations, slavery, secession, and
rebellion; that we might at once proceed with unsparing and speedy
hand to root out every vestige of them. I have of late feared much
lest their downfall should not be stamped with sufficient ignominy for
the best instruction and safeguard of coming generations. There is
little fear now, however.</p>
               <p pn="9">At the outset of this rebellion I, in this house, laid the
charge and crime of it at the door of slavery! Little did I think,
that in its closing hours such a final illustration of its general
character and leadings would
<pb n="10"/>
                  <figure entity="parker10">
                     <figDesc>10th page of Rev. Henry
E. Parker's Discourse the Day After the Reception of the Tidings of
the Assassination of President Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
be furnished. But this foul, fell act comes from the same influences
which could lead, ten years ago, to that brutal, murderous beating of
the Massachusetts senator, defenseless in his legislative seat; which
four years ago could fiendishly fling the horrors of civil war into
this land of happiness and peace; which afterward could wretchedly
imitate that miserable villain of two hundred and sixty years ago, Guy
Faux, and mine the Libby Prison to destroy, at a single explosion, our
prisoners, if Capt. Dahlgren should seek to liberate them, and then,
subsequently, without shame, justify the act; and which could
deliberately starve so many thousands of our poor captive soldiers, if
to death they did not care, out of all possible future serviceableness
to their country they meant, if not to death; this last work of horrid
assassination is but the latest. God grant it the final flowering of
the same hellish plant!</p>
               <p pn="10">IV. And not only may this foul deed have been needed to put the
last possible brand of infamy upon the rebellion and its primal cause,
but it also may have been desirable as the final, highest test of the
strength of our institutions and form of government. The rebellion and
its subjugation have been a fearful but most triumphant test; this is
a further, in the view of some it would be even a severer. In other
lands the assassination of the chief ruler has perhaps usually been
the precursor of anarchy and revolution. Wisely was it that not four
hours were suffered to elapse before our Vice-President was sworn into
the office of President. As foreign nations see us pass through the
ordeal of the termination of one Presi-
<pb n="11"/>
                  <figure entity="parker11">
                     <figDesc>11th page of Rev. Henry
E. Parker's Discourse the Day After the Reception of the Tidings of
the Assassination of President Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
dent's career by violence, and the immediate introduction to the
office of his successor, without commotion, and the continuance of
each department and office of the government without any infringement
upon the usual order and routine, it may be regarded as under God the
last, highest test of the sufficiency of our Republican form of
institutions for any and all emergencies.</p>
               <p pn="11">V. Again, it may be observed, that very possibly the work of
President Lincoln was now done, so far as he could complete it. Very
possibly another could better take it up and carry it on. He has done
a great work--a marvelous work; history will record it as of
unsurpassed magnitude and honor. He could not have added to his
fame. The remaining work is now that of reconstruction, and the meting
out the best measure of blended clemency and justice to those who have
been traitors and rebels. Very possibly a southern loyal man may know
better their true spirit and deserts, and decide upon the better
course of treatment with respect to them. To us, indeed, it seems as
though Mr. Lincoln could carry on the remaining work better than any
other; yet it may be otherwise. To us, it seems, at the least, a
fearful experiment to turn from the always discreet, self-poised,
temperate and sober man, to put the highest authority of this
government into the hands of a man who has so recently and unutterably
disgraced himself and us through him. But if the imposing upon him
this great burden of responsibility shall have the same effect the
similar imposing of a similarly weighty responsibility is said to have
had upon the great
<pb n="12"/>
                  <figure entity="parker12">
                     <figDesc>12th page of Rev. Henry
E. Parker's Discourse the Day After the Reception of the Tidings of
the Assassination of President Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
Lieutenant-General of our armies, he has abundant talents, knowledge
and experience for the position. God keep him and bless him. God bless
President Johnson! My own conviction is that he will better complete
what Mr. Lincoln has so incomparably thus far carried on, than even
our lamented late President himself, if spared, would.</p>
               <p pn="12">VI. Yet again, it may be observed, that this fearful event
will have a mighty and happy tendency to unite our people. It is not
going to have the effect of throwing us into anarchy, or of confusing
any of the operations of our government, or retarding at all the
progress of our triumphant quelling of the rebellion, as perhaps the
perpetrator of this crime and his associates imagined. It will be a
new and signal illustration of the folly of revenge. This act will
utterly destroy what little remaining sympathy there was in any
quarter for the falling cause of the confederacy. It will establish an
ineradicable aversion toward it in the breasts of all right-minded
men, of all patriots, of all lovers of law and order, of all friends
of their fellow-men, of all desiring the welfare of mankind. He had
<hi rend="italic">centered</hi> upon him those animosities every where
felt toward those who stood by our government; those animosities, to a
great extent, will be buried with him;--while even where, to any
extent, they may partially or temporarily remain, his sad and wicked
end will greatly soften and ameliorate them. Diversities of political
views and feelings can be no longer violently cherished over such a
grave; we shall all together deprecate the deed; and the causes which
led to it. There are none of us, I think, who
<pb n="13"/>
                  <figure entity="parker13">
                     <figDesc>13th page of Rev. Henry
E. Parker's Discourse the Day After the Reception of the Tidings of
the Assassination of President Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
will go forward to our work and duties as citizens of this Republic
any the worse for going on more soberly and sadly. This event falls
most exactly in the line of God's dealing with us ever since the
commencement of our difficulties, by never letting us long rest in our
dependence on any individual. He has signally disappointed us in this
respect, by death and otherwise, and utterly defeated all our
tendencies to the adulation of any one. It seems to be his great
purpose thus, as in other ways, that, under him, our people must look
to themselves for the accomplishing what they need and desire. It is a
great effort of his providence to elevate and strengthen the
individual sense of duty and obligation among all the people. It is a
republicanizing and democratizing of the people on a plane of
elevation and importance in advance of every thing thus far in our
national experience and character.</p>
               <p pn="13">But most imperfectly can our poor discernment now interpret
the lessons of this event. Let us at least "humble ourselves under the
mighty hand of God, that he may exalt us in due time" from the dust of
our present abasement and sorrow. Let us together give our united,
undying enmity to those great causes and evils which have culminated
in this final crime. Let us give ourselves anew to the love and
service of our country, on whose altar such sacrifices have been
laid. Let us in the presence of such a death realize anew the
old-urged truth that no position gives immunity from the grave, and
that every life hastens speedily to render its account to God.</p>
               <pb n="14"/>
               <p pn="14">
                  <figure entity="parker14">
                     <figDesc>14th page of
Rev. Henry E. Parker's Discourse the Day After the Reception of the
Tidings of the Assassination of President
Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <p pn="14">And now rest thee, thou man beloved by more hearts and more
beloved than any man in this nation before, and by none more than the
dusky race, who will ever hail thee as their deliverer from bondage;
thou man--mercifully raised up by heaven for the fearful crisis of our
times--singularly endowed, doubtless, with the qualities most needed
for the peculiar and arduous position to which thou wast called--by
turns doubted of by every class and party, but in the end centering
upon thyself more regard and confidence by far than any other;--thou
kindly-hearted man, incapable of malice or ill-will long retained, thy
very genialness and humor, a gift sustaining thee, perhaps, when
others would have sunk beneath depression and care;--thou man of the
people--thou perfect representative of the character and the
admirableness of our institutions, which can elevate the humblest and
the poorest to the loftiest position among us, and fit worthily and
well to fill it; thou wouldst not thyself have regretted that thy
blood should mingle with that of the myriad patriot heroes, the
victims of the spirit and deed of this rebellion--one affluent more of
that mighty tide of blood ransoming our land;--how much better thy
dead and mutilated form to the living form of the now fugitive head of
the rebellion;--thou diest, a nation bending over thee in sorrow and
in love;--he lives, a nation's execrations following him for
evermore!--rest thee, worn and weary with the cares of State in most
unprecedented burden, our need and our perils imposed on thee--well
and bravely hast thou borne the burden, untiringly, uncomplainingly;
and now thou hast laid it off; not too soon for thee, we pray it may
not
<pb n="15"/>
                  <figure entity="parker15">
                     <figDesc>15th page of Rev. Henry
E. Parker's Discourse the Day After the Reception of the Tidings of
the Assassination of President Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
be too soon for us!--the last, greatest murder of the rebellion, the
last, greatest sacrifice for us;--the hatred of our enemies toward us
laid on thee--their venom concentrated upon thee--their malice, by the
most detestable of crimes, wreaking a coveted, cowardly
vengeance;--bearing so much, suffering so much, and at last thus
murdered, simply because thou wert <hi rend="italic">our</hi> President,
sustaining, directing, defending, delivering <hi rend="italic">our</hi>
government;--rest thee now from thy great and weary world! history
will give thee a high and spotless fame; it will record thee as one of
the most amiable and unexceptionable of men, as one of the truest and
noblest of patriots, as one of the wisest and ablest of
Presidents,--rest thee in the Republic's undying honor, reverence,
gratitude and love--and may a Redeemer's advocacy and blood crown thy
soul with celestial glory, immortal happiness, and everlasting
life!</p>
            </div2>
         </div1>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI.2>
