<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader><fileDesc>
         <titleStmt n="The Great Funeral Oration on Abraham Lincoln">
            <title>The Great Funeral Oration on Abraham Lincoln</title>
            <author>Hardinge, Emma</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Compiled and edited by</resp>
               <name>Beck
Center</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent/>
         <publicationStmt><publisher>Lewis H. Beck Center</publisher><pubPlace>Emory University</pubPlace><address>
               <addrLine>Atlanta,
Georgia</addrLine>
            </address><availability>
               <p>1996 Emory
University. Permission is granted to download, transmit, or otherwise
reproduce, distribute or display the contributions to the work claimed
by Emory University for non-profit educational purposes, provided
this header is included in its entirety.  For inquiries about
commercial uses, contact the Director, 
Pitts Theology Library, Emory
University, Atlanta, Georgia 30322</p>
            </availability><date>1999</date></publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Lincoln
Sermons Project</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Hardinge,
Emma. The Great Funeral Oration on Abraham Lincoln.  Delivered Sunday,
April 16, 1865, at Cooper Institute, New York, Before Upwards of Three
Thousand Persons.  New York: American News Company, Nassau
Street.</bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc><encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This text derives from the Special Collections 
of Pitts Theology Library, Emory University, and is produced in 
collaboration with the Lewis H. Beck Center a, the Emory 
Preservation Office, and Pitts Theology Library.</p>
            <p>TRANSCRIBER: Lewis H. Beck Center and Emory University Preservation Office.</p>
            <p>PRODUCER:  BookLab, Inc., 1606 Headway Circle, Suite 100, Austin, TX 78754</p>
            <p>CAPTURE DEVICE: XEROX DocuImage 620S flatbed scanner</p>
            <p>CAPTURE DETAILS: Scanner software: XEROX ScanTool version 4.2.3; no gamma correction; images are all bitonal.</p>
            <p>CHANGE HISTORY: Using the Adobe Photoshop Batch Processor, we interpolated  the original TIFF files to 8-bit grays, and altered the resolution to 144 dpi, producing screen images twice the original size.  We then saved them in JPEG format.  We produced GIF thumbnails from the JPEG files.</p>
            <p>RESOLUTION: 600 ppi</p>
            <p>COMPRESSION: Resolution 144 per inch with Constrain Properties to 72 per inch.</p>
            <p>SOURCE: Original documents.</p>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc><revisionDesc><change><name>Stewart Varner</name> transformed this document from p4 to p5 on <date when="2010-03-22">March 22, 2010</date></change><change xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><date>1999</date><label>Staff</label><name>Scott Ellis</name>SGML tags inserted in compliance
with TEI guidelines using TEILITE</change></revisionDesc></teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
***NOTE: at the beginning of this file, I removed some (seemingly) extraneous <p></p> tags. Could you double check that none of these were, in fact, crucial? The numbering also skips from hardinge11 to hardinge13 (there is no hardinge12): OK or oversight?
         <div1 xml:id="britten.001" n="The Great Funeral Oration on Abraham Lincoln" type="text">
            <head> 
               <bibl> 
                  <title>The Great
Funeral Oration on Abraham Lincoln</title> 
                  <date>April 16, 1865</date>
                  <pubPlace>Cooper Institute, New York</pubPlace> 
                  <author>Hardinge,
Emma</author> 
                  
                     <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>American News Company</publisher>
                     <date>1865</date>
                   
               <idno type="ark">http://pid.emory.edu/ark:/25593/15ptr</idno></bibl> 
            </head>
            <pb facs="hardinge1.jpg"/>
            <p>THE GREAT</p>
            <p>FUNERAL ORATION</p>
            <p>ON</p>
            <p>ABRAHAM LINCOLN,</p>
            <p>BY</p>
            <p>MISS EMMA HARDINGE.</p>
            <p>DELIVERED SUNDAY, APRIL 16, 1865, AT COOPER INSTITUTE,</p>
            <p>NEW
YORK, BEFORE UPWARDS OF THREE</p>
            <p>THOUSAND PERSONS.</p>
            <p>NEW YORK:</p>
            <p>AMERICAN NEWS COMPANY</p>
            <p>NASSAU STREET.</p>
            <p>TWENTY-FIVE CENTS.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="hardinge2.jpg"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="hardinge3.jpg"/>
            <p>PREFACE.</p>
            <p>The news of the death of Abraham Lincoln, President of the United
States, was telegraphed to New York on Saturday morning, April
15. Toward the close of the day, Miss Emma Hardinge received an
invitation from several influential citizens to deliver an oration
upon the lamented Chief Magistrate of the nation. The invitation was
accepted, and the time agreed upon for its delivery was the next day,
Sunday, at three o'clock, P. M., at Cooper Institute. There was no
time for preparing an address of so important a character, and the
effort was entirely extemporaneous.  The attention with which the
speaker was listened to, the deep interest aroused, and the
irrepressible applause with which an assembly of upward of three
thousand persons interrupted her discourse, sufficiently testified not
less to the earnestness and justice of the tribute paid to the
illustrious martyr than to the eloquence that characterized this most
valuable oration.</p>
            <p>The oration having fortunately been phonographically reported, is
now published in response to a very generally expressed desire on the
part of citizens of all shades of political belief, who are solicitous
that so fitting, a memento of the virtues of Abraham Lincoln should be
read by every American patriot.</p>
            <pb n="4"/>
<!-- blank page -->
<!--            <p>
               <figure entity="hardinge4">
                  <figDesc>4th page of
Emma Hardinge's The Great Funeral Oration on Abraham
Lincoln.</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p> -->
            <pb n="5" facs="hardinge5.jpg"/>
            <p>INVOCATION.</p>
            <p>0 Thou that hearest prayer! Look upon us, Thy children, in this
hour of deepest soul-affliction! Lord of the sunshine and the storm,
God of the starry night and sunlit day, Thou who art our joy, our
grief, our all! teach us to remember, in the darkness as the light,
that 'tis our Father's hand that's dealing with us; our Father's
footsteps leading us, through mystery and gloom, to pierce the
ever-brightening path of His omniscient goodness. Eighteen hundred
years ago Thy best beloved meekly stood to bear the roaring multitude
reject him for Barabbas. Eighteen hundred years ago and the rocking
earth sustained a dying Angel on the cross of shame, while a murderer
went forth free. Once more we see Thy son beloved, Thy child of light,
and faithful servant, struck down beneath the hand of guilt and crime,
a sacrifice to the lost and darkened souls that choose a Barabbas and
reject a Jesus! 0 Thou whose still small voice we wait to hear when
the whirlwind of our grief sweeps by, and the tempest of our anguish
is sobbed out! Teach us, as we mourn the day of Crucifixion, to turn
with brightening memory to the hopes of Easter. Teach us to recollect
that, if the best and purest that ever walked the earth must needs be
lifted up on the cross of death, all earth might rejoice in a
resurrecting Easter, so has the martyr whom we mourn this hour gone
from our mortal eyes, a sign, to all mankind of this day of
Resurrection--a bright and strong assurance for us, who so dearly
loved him, that as the Master so the servant rises, and, like the
blessed Nazarene, His follower in life, His prototype in death, he has
joined the sons of light, the hosts of victory crowned, and wears the
palm of a glorious immortality, arisen, arisen! to his Father's home,
and ours.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="hardinge6.jpg"/>
            <div2 xml:id="booth.002" n="ORATION." type="sermon">
               <head>ORATION.</head>
               <p>It seems to me as if I heard a tone, borne on the wings of time and
sounding through the corridors of space, sweeping the earth like a
breeze, from the shores of the remotest East to this land of the
distant West--a voice that for eighteen hundred years has pleaded
before the throne of Almighty Justice in the only strain that can
solve the dire and dreadful problem of red murder saying, "Father,
forgive them, <hi rend="italic">they know not what they do</hi>."
Friends, this voice most surely speaks, both to you and me, in this
hour of awful grief. There seems no other utterance fit to explain its
meaning, or able to pronounce sentence on the terrible cause, of pain
that afflicts us in this most unparalleled and sublime national woe. I
recall the page of history in vain to find any precedent (save the one
which laid the foundations of your religion) for this foul and
monstrous act of guilt which forms the record of this solemn hour.</p>
               <p>When I remember the circumstances, time, and personages of this
tragic history, all attempts at parallel grow pale and fail us
utterly. Rome's Caesar pleads to us with the dumb but most eloquent
voices of "his bleeding wounds;" but before that piteous sacrifice
stand the avenging forms of patriots. France points to a Louis Capet,
and the execrating hiss of abashed posterity pronounces his doom was
martyrdom; but even then his guiltless life was yielded up to time and
preparation, a show of justice, and the sanction of a multitude. The
wrongs of an oppressed people and the ruin of a nation were on the
heads of both the Roman and French rulers.</p>
               <p>The shadow, if not the substance, of justice condemned
<pb n="7" facs="hardinge7.jpg"/>
them, and the contagious barbarism of the times exceeds in each case
the atrocity of the murderous act. But where is the plea which we can
hand down to a candid posterity in exculpation, wholly or partially,
of the parricidal act which has robbed the American nation of a
father, every American citizen of a friend, factious parties of their
most generous judge, a relentless enemy of their best protector, and
the whole world of an HONEST MAN? Where is the precedent in history
for the insanity which destroys in a nation's preserver a nation's
institutions; in a nation's noblest man her brightest jewel; and in
the hour of his noblest recorded acts inflicts on him the blow that
recoils in an immortal stain upon a nation's honor?</p>
               <p>Pass over the perilous scenes of strife, political hatred, and
factional discord, that might have drawn lines of separation between
himself and those who could not appreciate his acts of policy, and
follow him to the time when he stands the central figure of the dark
and distracting scenes of war. Behold him there in the midst of
contending armies, confronting the friends who were so often
unfaithful and cold, and the enemy that was always pitiless and cruel;
see him extending the blessed flag of peace and reconciliation over
all alike; stretching his paternal arm over every American, and, like
the almighty and merciful father of the parable, receiving the
prodigal back to his heart with a magnanimity and beneficence that
challenges the deepest gratitude of the wrong-doer, the fealty of
friends, and the admiration of the whole world.  Strong, brave, and
immovable in the hour of trial and calamity, Abraham Lincoln practiced
the last crowning virtue of a great man's life, the divine attribute
of mercy; and after having gallantly conquered, generously forgave the
foe, uniting again in one fraternal clasp the severed hands of North
and South, and silenced every jealous
<pb n="8" facs="hardinge8.jpg"/>
lip or rebellious tongue by a clemency calculated to win more hearts
by his kindness than the invincible armies of the North have subdued
by their arms. In all his public acts, even <hi rend="italic">to the
very last</hi>, we see him ever casting himself trustingly and nobly
on the fealty of the people. Surely he must have loved them, for who
ever before so trusted them?</p>
               <p>Despite of the fearful storm which treason had conjured up around
him, in defiance of the insolent presence of the rebellion and the
infamous serpent-trail of conspiracy, the generous, unselfish heart of
the man still confided in the people, and he went among them with none
of the panoply of state, none of the assumptions of power or place,
common to others of his position; he went without guard or protection
but in the people's fealty and love; and it was even for their sakes,
to please the people, nor suffer a shade of disappointment to
embitter, by his absence, their hours of recreation, that the noble
heart went forth to its death, the tender father to cast himself into
the arms of the parricide that struck him down. Oh! what an hour, and
under what a sacred trust, to consummate this deep and burning stain
upon humanity! Accursed be the hand, the time, the place, that wrote
upon the page of history the foulest blot that page has ever borne.</p>
               <p>'Tis well the dying Master on the cross plead, in his pitying love,
for the children of perdition. Our lips are too unchristlike, face to
face with such an act as this, to say amen for the prayer of mercy on
this wretch.</p>
               <p>In view of the special infamy which time, circumstance, and person
all so fearfully aggravate, permit me here to speak my deep conviction
that this act, however fatally we know it is the work of plot and
rebellion, still cannot be, for the honor of humanity, the organized
act of any great section of the land we call <hi rend="italic">American</hi>. I cannot believe it the work
<pb n="9" facs="hardinge9.jpg"/>
Of South, North, West, the common enemy, or even a foreign foe. The
act of a demon scarcely suffices to brand a whole humanity; and we
should pause long ere we accept, as conclusive, evidence to show that
a knot of inhuman serpents wearing the shape of men, or a coil of
conspirators doing the deeds of demons, should represent the country
of our birth and manhood. Of this I shall speak more hereafter, but
having entered my protest against the belief that an enemy we once
called brother, still Americans, and always men, could have wrought
the deed which none but earth's Cains are capable of doing. I propose
to extract whatever remains of use or instruction in this hour of
gloom by tracing, as we may, the deep, mysterious purposes of God
disclosed in this solemn lesson. First, then, we are called upon to
review the noble teaching in our lost friend's history; next, to
scrutinize the deed which closed it; and then determine what the
trumpet-voice of this dread hour demands of us as <hi rend="italic">duty</hi>.</p>
               <p>I cannot think it is out of place
to-day to retrace "those shining foot-prints on the sands of time"
which he we mourn has left behind him, although they are, as they
justly should be, already household words among the people of his
love.</p>
               <p>Now, will you deem it less in order that I should presume to be
your memento of this sacred page? Month after month it has seemed my
special inspiration to call upon the people, whom it was my privilege
to address, to study out and comprehend the acts of him whom I felt
and named as the true  "PRESERVER OF HIS COUNTRY."</p>
               <p>Scarcely ten days have passed since these walls, re-echoed to the
gallant cheer that hailed my voice when I told you of the sterling
worth, the loyal faith, and providential wisdom of this noble
incarnation of earth's best republicanism--the man of the people, the
PEOPLE'S ABRAHAM LINCOLN.  Some
<pb n="10" facs="hardinge10.jpg"/>
of you heard me then, but none of you know that the highest hope that
my ambition cherished was that some future day should see me clasp his
honest hand in mine, as the noblest meed I ever could receive for
unpaid and zealous service. My hope is quenched, and the kind paternal
hand is marble now; nor YOU nor I shall clasp it, until that day when
we stand with him "where the sun goes down no more; where the mourners
cease to weep; and the just rejoice forever."</p>
               <p>What a retrospect of a splendid career developed, if not wholly
fashioned, by the fostering sun of American republicanism, does our
great chief magistrate's history present us with! Fifty-six years ago,
and the low sigh of the breeze stirring the trees of old Kentucky, the
song of the lonely woodbird, and the chirp of the tenants of the
wildest solitudes were the natal songs that welcomed into life the
child whose name has to reverberate through the earth in the clarion
tones of a worldwide fame; born to the inheritance of stern poverty
and rude toil, a log-cabin was his only shelter, the cathedral arches
of the green forest his baptismal roof, and the lonely stars and
voiceless flowers, the backwoodsman father and humble mother, his only
friends and teachers; and yet we trace the germs of Nature's truest
nobility unfolding themselves in every year of his faithful life;
always the good and dutiful child, the industrious little aid of the
toiling father, the willing little drudge of the patient mother.</p>
               <p>At seven years he goes forth with the spelling-book, one of the
three volumes that constitute the family library. At eight he learns
the first dread lesson of slavery, namely, that free white labor has
no chance in competition with captive black; that the condition of a
poor white laborer in a slave State is more hopeless than the slave
himself; and hence himself and little household endure the toil and
hardship of a weary pioneer journey from Kentucky slavery and darkness,
<pb n="11" facs="hardinge11.jpg"/>
to, Indiana freedom and light. Remember, thus early, did Abraham
Lincoln learn his first practical lessons of the corrupting and
festering influences of slavery. At ten years old the little
backwoodsman's boy, by industry and (for time and condition) most
arduous study, had. become the wonder of the scattered population in
which he dwelt for his skill in reading, and his yet more astonishing
faculty for writing, only equaled by the kindness which urged him to
become the scribe of all who sought the good boy's service in this
humble way. At nineteen he is the Mississippi boat-man, intrusted with
wealth and others' welfare, honored and sought for himself and. his
honest manhood.</p>
               <p>At twenty-one he first set foot in that Illinois whose proudest
boast to-day is to call him hers. Here he makes his father's home,
helps build his house, and fence his farm, and immortalized that
humble form of labor which renders the title of the "rail-splitter" a
patent of America's nobility. From this we trace him from his final
exodus from the paternal roof, now the hired farm hand, the clerk in
the petty store, the agent, buyer, scribe, postmaster, captain in the
Black Hawk war, surveyor, lawyer, legislator, but ever the same, good,
self-made, self-taught, toiling, honest, truthful, studious man. 0
earthly potentates! proud European princes! fortune's favored
children! how would you smile to be bid to school in the forest
log-hut; to study, the ragged page of one single volume; to learn of
the teachers grinding poverty and toil, and prepare for a rule more
large, more onerous and high in import, than Asia or Europe's greatest
monarchs know in the farmer's barn, the boat-man's raft, the village
store, or, the poor clerk's office! Bright, beautiful, and just
republicanism, thou knowest thy kings, and never can mistake thy
princes! And in every step of this great magic ladder cut by his
hands, erected by
<pb n="13" facs="hardinge13.jpg"/>
found in his famous senatorial contest with Judge Douglas. No one can
fail to perceive, from the entire tenor of Mr. Lincoln's remarkable
life, that he fully understood and completely loathed the monstrous
blot that had crept into the national legislation in the form of
legalized slavery.</p>
               <p>He was its open and avowed enemy, ever voting in his place,
whenever occasion served, against its extension in any form; the
contest I have alluded to, enabled him to bring all the powers of his
acute and logical mind and forcible nervous oratory, to bear on the
monstrous evil of its extension into the Territories, or the
perpetuation of the gigantic wrong in any form outside of its then
existing State limits. And yet, despite the unequivocal opposition
which he maintained so constantly to the character, political
influence, and destructive nature of this suicidal institution, we
find Mr. Lincoln just as firm in his defense of that State-right
sovereignty which granted the constitutional privilege of retaining
slavery in each State's precinct unrestrained by the interference of
the central government. I do not propose in this place to discuss the
vexed problem of the just equilibrium to be attained between the
powers of the States as petty sovereignties and the central government
as a whole. I notice the subject here to point to the fact, that while
the known beneficence and wisdom of' Mr. Lincoln's character inclined
us to expect of him an uncompromising war on slavery, by what I
believe to be the providential character of his mind, anticipating the
irrepressible conflict in which the nation's life was yet to be
involved, he was ever led to refuse his sanction to a single, act, by
which (as we now perceive) in after years the rebellious South could
have founded a plea upon, to excuse their base secession.</p>
               <p>That rash and hasty zeal that would have hurried the nation's Chief
Magistrate into acts which ignored the letter
<pb n="14" facs="hardinge14.jpg"/>
of the Constitution, infringed on the guarantees it offered to
Southern slavery, or recklessly cast the West and border States in the
eager arms of a half justifiable rebellion, the wise and deep-sighted
policy of the noble statesman never suffered him to adopt; and either
to a human wisdom beyond the ken of too many one-idead politicians, or
a divine inspiration providing against the inevitable hour of coming
woe, we owe it that the country's best defender left the traitor South
no shadow of excuse, nor ray of plea, for resistance to his wise
paternal rule. Such was the politician and the man--equal to all
emergencies and times. Behold him next assuming the reins of
government at a time when every other mind on earth would have shrunk
aghast from the fearful task, or sunk beneath its complicated
perils.</p>
               <p>Surrounded by treason, environed by secret foes, the ground beneath
him undermined by plots, a vast and relentless offensive war already
thundering at the nation's gate, while the thews and sinews of defense
were stolen, removed, and broken; ships, arsenals, forts, treasuries
despoiled and plundered; a navy to create, an army to raise, a
treasury to improvise; a people, all unused to war and taxes, to bend
and discipline, to both equip and provide for all; no section of a
continent, like European lands, to garrison or conquer, but a vast New
World to cover, guard, and conquer with great armies, any one of which
would eat up or destroy a country of any other quarter of the globe;
the taunts of enemies to bear; the fearful changes and chances of a
gigantic war to calculate upon and provide for; foes to repel, treason
to subdue; clamorous harpies to satisfy, presumptuous friends to
check; the whole seaboard of the wide Atlantic coast, a highway for
treacherous foreign despot powers, all waiting, longing greedily to
aid the ruin of the earth's democracy, their own most dreaded foe--and
yet, in any of these
<pb n="15" facs="hardinge15.jpg"/>
vast and momentous issues, where are the acts or words, the noble
State papers, brilliant messages, or clear and unwavering deeds of
Abraham Lincoln ever found at fault? I answer, boldly challenging
earth's statesmen to disprove my words--<hi rend="italic">not in one
single instance!</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There's not a statesman of the age but might read a lesson in the
firm and lofty dignity of tone in which the nation's status was
defined, aye, and maintained, too, in all his foreign messages and
ministerial instructions. When dark, impending ruin shook the earth
beneath his feet, where wilt you find the evidence of weakness in one
single word to any foreign power?  Where one jot of yielding of' the
nation's undivided dignity? Where one base concession to the despot's
aim to force him to submission through the country's real internal
weakness? He took with the oath of office the nation's weal or woe
upon his shoulders; wore it as a mantle; girdled it about his towering
form with his heart-strings; and wraps it now around the lifeless ruin
of his still and pulseless heart as a winding-sheet of glory. To him
you owe it that the name and dignity of the still united States
towered like a monitor above the wreck and ruin, so high and grand and
threatening, that in no hand but an armed American's dare rise in
presumptuous threat against the Stars and Stripes. One of the noblest
State papers that the records of any nation can show is, to my
thinking, to be found in Mr. Lincoln's first inaugural address to this
nation. There the entire question of the Protean Problem--Slavery--in
connection with its legalized existence in the States as guaranteed by
the Constitution, is fairly and fully laid out, the suicidal character
of secession unvailed, and the magnificent proportions of a united
American republicanism grandly depicted. A mind capable of analyzing
with such irresistible and clear deductions the entangled meshes of
treason in which
<pb n="16" facs="hardinge16.jpg"/>
the nation's life was involved, never could fail in steering the ship
of State through all the shoals and reefs in which she was
subsequently to struggle for the port of safety. The prescient wisdom
of the many great statesmen who had preceded him seemed to culminate
in his simple yet lucid definition of the nation's situation, in a
speech made by him, as early as 1858, on the occasion of his
nomination as candidate for senator in Illinois, when he says: "A
house divided against itself cannot stand; I believe this government
cannot endure permanently half slave and half free. I do not expect
the Union to be dissolved; I do not expect the house to fall; but I do
expect it will cease to be divided. It will become all one thing or
all the other." These and many other such utterances of his public
life conclusively prove not only his perfect understanding of the
vexed questions that were agitating the land, but also give the key to
that policy which his opponents have so often and so rashly denounced
as "time-serving," but which now looms up as the providential wisdom
which not only foresees, but knows how to await the ripening of the
proper time for action. And when that time came, was Mr. Lincoln slow,
fearful, or disobedient to "the higher law" that ever ruled his life
in availing himself of it? I allude to the enunciation of the immortal
proclamation of emancipation, the deed which, beyond all others of his
life, crowns him with eternal honor, and will hand his name down to an
immortal glory through all posterity. Up to the end of the first three
years of the war Mr. Lincoln had robbed the rebellious foe of every
shadow of plea against his administration by a guard over the very
rights they had forfeited, as jealous as themselves could have
exercised, retaining by his wise policy the strength of the
vacillating western and border States still attached to the Union.</p>
               <pb n="17" facs="hardinge17.jpg"/>
               <p>Assailed by unwise friends and bitter foes, with taunts and
revilings on every hand, still he moved not; but when the crisis came
in which the nation's life was balanced against protective southern
policy, how long did the noble statesman hesitate? The cry of the
discontented and disloyal raised its accustomed wail against freedom
and howled out "abolitionism;" but above the murmur of the storm arose
in his ear the grand Mosaic cry of "Let my people go!" and although
that voice has been thundering down the ages, and a burning bush and a
fire -crowned Sinai has flashed before the eyes of despots in every
century of time, whenever God's oppressed and captive people cried to
Him for deliverance, three thousand years has seen that awful charge
hold disregarded, mocked, and spit upon, until good  Abraham Lincoln,
in 1863, proclaimed it in "Liberty throughout the land, to every
inhabitant thereof!" God bless him for it!</p>
               <p>I was present in San Francisco one year after this memorable deed,
and, in company with the only other white orator who could be found to
take part on such an occasion, helped the enfranchised race to honor
the glorious anniversary.</p>
               <p>The memory of the sable martyrs that had perished at Port Hudson
and Fort Pillow was still green in memory; they told of the black
regiments, formed of men whose ancestors' unpaid. toil had made the
country rich, whose backs were still seamed with lashes, and whose
limbs still gashed with the mark of fetters, but whose freed lives
were now devoted to the salvation of the land that had enslaved
them. These pictures were vividly portrayed in of their own peculiar,
wild, and touching eloquence; but all was forgotten, all forgiven when
the name of their modern Moses was pronounced, and then it was that a
shout went
<pb n="18" facs="hardinge18.jpg"/>
up to God, chorused by four millions of glad, rejoicing voices, echoed
by the white slaves of despotism and tyranny all over the world--a
shout of  "God bless Abraham Lincoln!" That cry will be a passport to
his soul through the courts of heaven, in all eternity, did it stand
alone as the only record of his pure and spotless life.</p>
               <p>But wherever I turn my eyes in his unprecedented career I find some
fresh challenge to my wonder and admiration. No man in history was
ever before, intrusted with the charge of such vast armies, the
disbursements of such enormous sums of money, or the exercise of such
stupendous powers. Mr. Lincoln modestly professed himself unequal to
the task of directing the military situations of his vast armies, yet
his correspondence with General McClellan proves that either his clear
intuitions or his real ability always dictated the wisest and most
able instructions to his generals, the only real failure of which was
the disregard with which they were received. No scrutiny however
searching, has yet disclosed one jot of selfishness, dishonesty, or
aught but generous singleness of purpose in the use of all the power,
finance, and vast resources intrusted to his charge. Oh people of the
land he blessed and saved! can I deal justly with his sacred name,
unless I present it to your undivided admiration as your "Father
Abraham Lincoln!"--a man whose page of history stands without a
blemish, whose bright escutcheon will shine through all futurity
without one single spot. My retrospect of this noble life is almost
ended. It but remains in this place to remind you that if our Chief
Magistrate was, in his own unassuming phrase, "too deficient in
military experience to general the situation," he was amply supplied
with that moral fitness for command which has made the world's most
potent conquests and furnished in history its brightest wreaths of
victory. From the very
<pb n="19" facs="hardinge19.jpg"/>
hour when lie gave to the armies of the North, a moral watchword and
the glorious war-cry "Liberty" the most genuine and unequivocal
success has marked their every action. From point to point, their
march has been a triumph. They swept the border States; opened twelve
hundred miles of highway on the grand old Father of Waters; pierced
every gate of life in the quivering body of the confederate South;
drew their girdle of irresistible conquest around the vast chain of
territorial lands, East, West, and South, back to the North again, and
paused not until they had torn the heart of rebeldom throbbing from
the midst of the Old Dominion, and placed Richmond, a votive offering
on the shrine of that glorious Union that bent beneath the storm only
to rise in more glorious majesty again on the shattered walls of
Sumter--and the crowning acts of all were the last of this strange
eventful history.</p>
               <p>True to the genius of the opposing sections, behold the pampered
aristocrats of the South, made rich on stolen labor <hi rend="italic">sending their</hi> "<hi rend="italic">Commissioners</hi>" to
treat with the nation they had so recklessly sought to destroy; on the
other hand, see the man who held the highest dignity the earth could
confer on man going, in his simple presence, almost unattended--with
none of the guards his sacred life required, none of the outward shows
of form his stupendous charge might sanction, going himself, in
person, father-like, to receive and welcome back his prodigal
child.</p>
               <p>What a contrast does the simple, unassuming presence of the man,
conferring with the rebel emissaries, present to the lofty and
unflinching tone of the President when he spoke for the nation! He was
nothing for himself, all for the people; he went forth, the unassuming
backwoodsman's boy, to meet his southern brothers; he stood, the chief
of the great New World, to speak of the terms on which its peace
<pb n="20" facs="hardinge20.jpg"/>
could be insured; nor, when treating for its people, abated one jot of
the unconditional submission of every soul beneath the shelter of the
American Constitution, the just but literal letter of its laws.</p>
               <p>We have traced him as the incarnate spirit of true republicanism,
the self-made boy, the unimpeachable youth, the noble man, the
legislator, statesman, orator, chief magistrate, and father of a
mighty people, their staff in the earthquake's shock, their anchor in
the storm. What more remains than to contemplate him obeying the
behests of his Almighty Father, killing the fatted calf to welcome
back the returning prodigal, following the foot- of his Christian
Master, returning good for evil, dispensing blessings for curses, and
conquering foes more surely with his generous acts of mercy than all
the armies of the earth could do with sword and cannon. Did be forget
the miserable wrecks of manhood incarcerated in Libby prison and
Castle Thunder? Did he cease to mourn the heroes slain, the homes made
desolate, the hearts bereaved, the thousands fiercely massacred? Had
he forgotten the emaciated shadows of what once were men returned from
the fiendish grasp of demon captors ? Or had his ear grown dull to the
dying shrieks from Fort Pillow and many a battlefield? He forgot
nothing, this brave, great heart! but he forgave far more than he
forgot. And however WE MAY KNOW in the awful lesson of his shameful
murder that his magnanimity upreared his own funeral pyre, I do
believe, when this dark record of the great American conflict and its
termination shall pierce the astounded ears of foreign nations, all
other acts will be forgotten, all other blood-stained memories wiped
away, and all other stormy passages of this tempestuous time be
obliterated in the triumph of that Christ-like spirit which opened its
arms of welcome to the fallen
<pb n="21" facs="hardinge21.jpg"/>
and penitent General Robert E. Lee. Would that the story ended here!
Would that the hero-life filled up the glittering page ere the
martyr's doom blots out the light in blood! Oh, that our eyes might
have followed those brightening footprints through the earth made
holier by his presence, rather than, turning as they do this day
through falling tears, to seek him midst the martyred hosts of light
in the far, far distant skies! But I fence with the dreadful truth
that shuts out the glorious life and quenches the lamp which so
brightly shone for us, leaving, our land and our hearts, our homes and
hearths, so very, very dark! I pause on the threshold of that fearful
gate through which our strength and our hope went out, scarcely daring
to cast our mourning eyes to the dreadful <hi rend="italic">beyond</hi>
which has left our country desolate! But I must redeem the promise of
the hour, and speak to the very deed, the fearful act of murder, whose
harsh, dissonant voice rings in the requiem notes of the very bells
that to-day should have sounded out the glad rejoicing tones of
peace. I have but a few words to say concerning this deed, but a
passing glance to cast upon its already doomed and inhuman authors!</p>
               <p>He who knows the secrets of all hearts can best decide how many of
His creatures sink so low beneath the human image of Himself as to be
concerned in the act that struck down the noblest in his very noblest
hour, and added to the impious crime of parricidal murder the wanton,
miserable waste of golden opportunities, the only ones that could save
the fallen South or rejoice the conquering North. I still hope, for
the honor of humanity, for the name of free America, for the sake of
judgment, reason, sanity, and manhood, that this deed does not
represent more than a petty band of Cains. But while the hiss of a
whole earth's execration hoots the wretch from life who was the
foremost hand to strike the
<pb n="22" facs="hardinge22.jpg"/>
blow; while we acquit a large humanity or any section of God's earth
we call <hi rend="italic">a country</hi> from complicity in the monster
deed, should we forget the upas-tree which bears such dismal fruits as
this assassin? Shall we forget the accursed cause, the hateful,
poisonous cause, that makes a country pamper to its slaves, feeds up
and pampers on the shameful gains of others' labor a whole community
in idleness, builds up a rank, degraded aristocracy, living by theft
of men, ruling, by force of blows and stripes and bullying tones,
weakness and ignorance, and bearing inevitably (from a brutal source)
the rank and hideous weeds secession, savage war, and treacherous
murder.</p>
               <p>There are men now who sit beneath the southern orange and magnolia
and weep for him as we weep; hearts in the unhappy South as sorrowful
as ours; heads bowed with shame, and many a one who would--as I or
many of you would--cheerfully lay down his life to recall the precious
one the country mourns.</p>
               <p>Thousands of southern Rachels weep this day for our dead chief; and
wide, clear-sighted men in the furthest South know their best friend
and the country's true preserver will lie low in the grave of
Lincoln.</p>
               <p>But what is that to the past? Who can recall it? God's footsteps
never return upon themselves. The southern institution, enemy alike of
God and man, has slain the South, and as the monstrous blossom of a
poison-tree, has slain its friend and honor in Abraham Lincoln. For
never man would have dared to raise his wicked band to slay a good man
in the very hour when his goodness shone most brightly; never coward
stolen to the helpless bed of an almost dying creature to cut and back
the unresisting form of sickness--but those who had learned to love
the traffic in human life; but those whom the groans of lacerated
black men had made callous,
<pb n="23" facs="hardinge23.jpg"/>
and who, having seen the murderous knife of treason whetted for the
nation's life, scrupled not to sharpen it for fathers and for
brothers. I do not tax this deed upon the South <hi rend="italic">but on
its spirit</hi>; if not upon the men of the South, <hi rend="italic">yet
on its institutions</hi>; and if not the act in very person of
slave-owners, the <hi rend="italic">blood of Lincoln lies at the door
of</hi> SLAVERY!</p>
               <p>Oh, friends! the prayer of the gentle Master, "Father, forgive
them, <hi rend="italic">they know not what they do</hi>," constitutes
the history of this dreadful wrong, but nevertheless it must not close
our ears to the mighty right. We know that the cause that makes men
forget their humanity; the mean and truckling spirit that lives on
others' labor; the greedy and insatiate purpose that determines to
govern others without their consent, and compels all men to bow to
them; the aristocratic spirit that can never be satisfied, and cries
"Give, give," incessantly; the dark and terrible necessity that
demands more territory for its growing millions, more lands, more
States, more funds, more power; that fatal institution that dare not
trust the spelling-book and Bible, that gags free speech and keeps
back the light of intelligence from the darkened minds of
ignorance--must culminate at last in the arm of force and murder; must
throw away the ballot and take instead the bullet, and send its worst
fanatics forth to do deeds that recoil in nameless horror on
itself. And thus believing, I do dismiss the hideous contemplation of
the deed. And for the doer, what is he now but Cain?--a fugitive and a
vagabond, henceforth he'll live till the earth shall weary of him, yet
the terrible hereafter refuse to give him shelter. The sobs of the
widow and the orphan his noble victim cheered, the hiss of a loathing
world whose every heart is closed against him, shall murder his sleep
for evermore; the gates of every home on earth all violated by his
parricidal act, shall close against him; the curse of every fettered
captive 
<pb n="24" facs="hardinge24.jpg"/>
on the earth, who looked to Abraham Lincoln as their Moses, shall bow
his head beneath their bitter load; and the dying eyes of the
crucified One of old, and the gentle modern martyr, shall be the only
prayers the human family shall dare put up to God for him, who cannot
utter with his guilty lips one prayer for himself. Our tears fall fast
this hour in shame for him and his loathed deed; in pity for
ourselves, in our heavy loss, and our land's dimmed glory. But who
weeps for him? Who pities him? or what hand of man can outstretch to
save the wretch, who himself knew naught of pity! The hour is even now
upon him when be must cry, though mortal may never hear him, "My
punishment is heavier than I can bear." Let Him who judges heed
him. Man answers not, except in the fearful chorus, Justice herself
must swell, "<hi rend="italic">Death to Lincoln's murderer!</hi>" No
more of him, but wake from the fearful palsy fallen upon you people,
and answer to yourselves and to your country. What is now your duty?
what the demands of the hour, if any, on your individual action?</p>
               <p>Friends, the hour has come to try men's souls. The country waits
for you, with arm and heart and bead, to rebuild its shattered altars,
remould its glory, and restore or reconstruct, if need be, the charter
of its life and all your liberties--your national Constitution. Permit
me, then, to close up this address by a brief reference to this
absorbing subject of your duties.</p>
               <p>The very night before that fatal one that robbed us of our nation's
strong right arm, the people's voice demanded of me, in the city of
Philadelphia, suggestive words on the theme of reconstruction.</p>
               <p>I then said what I now repeat--that the question of reconstruction
depends almost solely ON THE TIME that is chosen, an THE CONDITIONS
under which the work commences
<pb n="25" facs="hardinge25.jpg"/>
The true time is not yet, or can or will be, until the Government, by
the war power by which it is clothed in the sacred Constitution,
restores intact, in peace and in full integrity, every one of the
thirty-six States which constitute the Union, to the people, who
intrust that Union to the Government. The States are the people's, the
Government their guardians, the war power the means by which the
government restores the States in their full proportion unto the
people and never until such full and entire restoration is fully made
should the war power cease, or the people (the true legislators of the
country) pretend to reconstruct the laws, which are made FOR, THE
UNION AND THE PEOPLE, NOT THE PEOPLE FOR THE UNION AND THE LAWS. It is
plain, then, that reconstruction signifies, first, the restoration of
peace in every State of the Union; the Union then itself is
reconstructed. The States are one and at their former status, restored
there by the way, and only need that legislative wisdom shall deal
with, execute, and annihilate the fatal thing that was the cause of
war. And if the legislative wisdom of the people cannot in solemn
council agree to accuse and condemn the monster Slavery as cause
enough--if some lingering remnants of the suicidal folly which
cherished the serpent, in whose foul embrace the land has well-nigh
died, should still, in blind infatuation, refuse its sanction to an
amended charter, killing the nation's cause of death to save its life
what then? Why, reconstruction will come from the same source that
made construction--THE PEOPLE! The Constitution was the creation of
the people; and shall it destroy its author? Or are those who made it,
and find it protects the nation's death instead of the nation's life,
incapable of making another and a better one? Nations grow and
parchments don't; and if a nation's growth is to be hindered to suit
the narrow limits of its laws, let <hi rend="italic">them grow too;</hi>
or if they can
<pb n="26" facs="hardinge26.jpg"/>
not, KILL THEM, and save the nation's life! Or if you hesitate to add
to or amend the law which you've outgrown, let the heart speak what
the timid tongue fears to pronounce, and "He, being dead, yet
speaketh." Let the glorious voice of Freedom, calling in
trumpet-tongue from the grave of Abraham Lincoln, and ascending, in
the immortal proclamation of emancipation, to the very heavens with
his marching soul--let this speak for you, and, in the name of the
"higher law," God's law, and Abraham Lincoln's own most godlike act,
decide your problem, and reconstruct your laws on the rock which
death, nor hell, nor time, nor human trespass can ever touch with
fingers of decay--the eternal rock of JUSTICE! You say you love your
"Father Abraham"--prove it by swearing over his martyr-grave not to
dishonor the grandest of his deeds by a base repudiation of its
legality. That charter which will not sanction liberty in the land of
the Stars and Stripes, and nullifies the brightest act of Abraham
Lincoln's life, is itself the fittest subject in the land for the
scalpel-knife of reconstruction. As for the rest, your duty's very
simple. The first that presses home on every living creature in this
land is a firm and devoted heart of loyalty tendered to your new
President. Did not the enormous exigencies of his momentous situation
appeal to every better feeling in man's nature for faithful service?
Andy Johnson of Tennessee deserves it of you--another self-made man;
another man of the people; another grand Republican ladder, on which
the mudsills rise to the highest rounds of nature's loyalty; another
living protest against the destroying influence of slavery on whites
as well as blacks.</p>
               <p>Rally around your President with heart and head and hand, and be
sure of this, that, if the mantle of the too-merciful Lincoln has not
fallen upon his shoulders, that of bold Andrew Jackson has, and that
in these troublous times,
<pb n="27" facs="hardinge27.jpg"/>
when mercy is requited with assassination, the spirit of the immortal
Andrew Jackson and the mortal Andrew Johnson can better deal with
treason and murder than the saintlike form whose, arms enfold its
destroyer.</p>
               <p>Mourn for Abraham Lincoln with your hearts, but prove your love to
him by taking up the burden he's laid down and finishing the noble
purposes of his great life so untimely quenched. For you, his country,
and the holy cause of patriotism, he perished. He spoke no word, he
made no sign, nor left a single charge on mortal man; but, oh, if ever
silence was most eloquent, if speechless, dying martyrdom. pleads now,
as in the days of' "righteous Stephen," with an angel light upon its
blood-stained brow, obey that dumb behest, and do his work, and break
the last blood-crusted link of those iron bonds that have well-nigh
killed the earth's last, best republic. We must have no treasonable
words; no more disloyal murmurs; no more pretense of plain, blunt
speech to stab the government, ruin the nation, and kill its best
defenders. Crush out the serpent in the egg, the henbane in the seed,
and we'll have no more such bitter fruit as murder and rebellion.</p>
               <p>Trust to the man of the people, raised up, in this hour of sudden
need and strange calamity, like a God-given answer to a prayer our
lips have not had time to fashion. Question not his faults, but regard
his sterling qualities. Follow his brave, strong footsteps in his
great ascent of life; his noble words and pledges of good faith ere
the nation's need had come, and be sure that God has sent him to our
rescue, and your part is to give him added strength in a nation's
united heart and faith,</p>
               <p>What matters it, then, that he we love and so bitterly deplore has
gone before us? Sooner or later, for us all, his summons will be
ours. God only give us grace to follow him to
<pb n="28" facs="hardinge28.jpg"/>
the land of light and never-setting sun, to clasp his immortal band
again in eternal fellowship in our own Easter resurrecting day, and
hear the glorious greeting that, with the arisen sun of his bright
eternity, has welcomed him to the home he's so justly earned: "Well
done, thou good and faithful servant, enter thou into the joy of thy
Lord."</p>
            </div2>
         </div1>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>