<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader><fileDesc>
         <titleStmt n="The Assassination of President Lincoln">
            <title>The Assassination of President Lincoln</title>
            <author>Chamberlain, N. H.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Compiled and edited by</resp>
               <name>Beck
Center</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent/>
         <publicationStmt><publisher>Lewis H. Beck Center</publisher><pubPlace>Emory University</pubPlace><address>
               <addrLine>Atlanta,
Georgia</addrLine>
            </address><availability>
               <p>1996 Emory
University. Permission is granted to download, transmit, or otherwise
reproduce, distribute or display the contributions to the work claimed
by Emory University for non-profit educational purposes, provided
this header is included in its entirety.  For inquiries about
commercial uses, contact the Director, 
Pitts Theology Library, Emory
University, Atlanta, Georgia 30322</p>
            </availability><date>1999</date></publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Lincoln
Sermons Project</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Chamberlain,
N. H. The Assassination of President Lincoln. A Sermon Preached in
St. James Church, Birmingham, CT, April 19th, 1865. New York:
Published by G. W. Carleton, 413 Broadway. 1865.</bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc><encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This text
derives 
from the Special Collections 
of Pitts Theology Library, Emory University, and is produced in 
collaboration with the Lewis H. Beck Center a, the Emory 
Preservation Office, and Pitts Theology Library.</p>
            <p>TRANSCRIBER: Lewis H. Beck Center and Emory University Preservation Office.</p>
            <p>PRODUCER:  BookLab, Inc., 1606 Headway Circle, Suite 100, Austin, TX 78754</p>
            <p>CAPTURE DEVICE: XEROX DocuImage 620S flatbed scanner</p>
            <p>CAPTURE DETAILS: Scanner software: XEROX ScanTool version 4.2.3; no gamma correction; images are all bitonal.</p>
            <p>CHANGE HISTORY: Using the Adobe Photoshop Batch Processor, we interpolated  the original TIFF files to 8-bit grays, and altered the resolution to 144 dpi, producing screen images twice the original size.  We then saved them in JPEG format.  We produced GIF thumbnails from the JPEG files.</p>
            <p>RESOLUTION: 600 ppi</p>
            <p>COMPRESSION: Resolution 144 per inch with Constrain Properties to 72 per inch.</p>
            <p>SOURCE: Original documents.</p>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc><revisionDesc><change><name>Stewart Varner</name> transformed this document from p4 to p5 on <date when="2010-03-22">March 22, 2010</date></change><change xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><date>1999</date><label>Staff</label><name>Scott Ellis</name>SGML tags inserted in compliance
with TEI guidelines using TEILITE</change></revisionDesc></teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div1 xml:id="chamberlain.001" n="The Assassination of President Lincoln" type="text">
            <head> 
               <bibl> 
                  <title>The
Assassination of President Lincoln</title> 
                  <date>April 19th,
1865</date> 
                  <pubPlace>St. James Church, Birmingham, CT</pubPlace>
                  <author>Chamberlain, N. H.</author> 
                  
                     <pubPlace>New
York</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>G. W. Carleton</publisher>
                     <date>1865</date>
                   
               <idno type="ark">http://pid.emory.edu/ark:/25593/15px5</idno></bibl> 
            </head>
            <pb facs="chamberlain1.jpg"/>
            <p>The Assassination of President Lincoln.</p>
            <p>A</p>
            <p>SERMON</p>
            <p>PREACHED IN</p>
            <p>St. James Church, Birmingham, Ct.,</p>
            <p>April 19th, 1865.</p>
            <p>BY</p>
            <p>REV. N. H. CHAMBERLAIN.</p>
            <p>NEW YORK.</p>
            <p>PUBLISHED BY G.W. CARLETON,</p>
            <p>413
BROADWAY.</p>
            <p>1865.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="chamberlain2.jpg"/>
            <p>BIRMINGHAM, April
19th, 1865.</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italic">Reverend and Dear Sir:</hi>--</p>
            <p>The undersigned, members of your Parish, having listened
with great interest to your Sermon, delivered this day, on the death
of PRESIDENT LINCOLN, earnestly solicit of you a copy for
publication. Deeming this request in keeping with the wishes of the
great body of those who heard it, and hoping the same will be granted,
we remain</p>
            <p>Sincerely yours, &amp;c.,<lb/>
A. BEARDSLEY, <lb/>CHARLES A. STERLING, <lb/>EDWIN WOOSTER,<lb/>
EDWARD LEWIS, <lb/>WILLIAM M. HULL, <lb/>FITCH SMITH,<lb/>
G. H. PECK, <lb/>EDWARD N. SHELTON,</p>
            <p>To the
REV. N. H. CHAMBERLAIN,
                   <hi rend="italic">Rector of St. James.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="3" facs="chamberlain3.jpg"/>
            <p>O, merciful God, and heavenly Father, who hast taught us in
thy holy Word, that thou Dost not willingly afflict or grieve the
children of men; Look with pity, we beseech thee, upon the sorrows of
thy servants, the family of the late President of the United States,
for whom our prayers are desired. In thy wisdom thou hast seen fit to
visit them with trouble, and to bring distress upon them. Remember
them, O Lord, in mercy; sanctify thy fatherly correction to them;
endue their souls with patience under their affliction, and with
resignation to thy blessed will; comfort them with a sense of thy
goodness; lift up thy countenance upon them, and give them peace;
through Jesus Christ, our Lord.  <hi rend="italic">Amen</hi>.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="chamberlain4.jpg"/>
            <p>O, God, the King of Glory, who hast exalted Thine only Son, Jesus
Christ, with great triumph, unto Thy Kingdom in Heaven, we beseech
Thee leave us not comfortless, but send to us Thine Holy Ghost, to
comfort us and exalt us unto the same place whither our Savior,
Christ, is gone before, Who liveth and reigneth with Thee and the Holy
Ghost, one God, world without end.</p>
            <p> 
               <hi rend="italic">Collect for the Sunday
after Ascension day.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="5" facs="chamberlain5.jpg"/>
            <div2 xml:id="chamberlain.002" n="SERMON" type="sermon">
               <head>SERMON.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <p>LET EVERY SOUL BE SUBJECT UNTO THE HIGHER POWERS.  FOR
THERE IS NO POWER BUT OF GOD; THE POWERS THAT BE ARE ORDAINED OF GOD.
WHOSOEVER THEREFORE RESISTETH THE POWER, RESISTETH THE ORDINANCE OF
GOD, AND THEY THAT RESIST, SHALL RECEIVE TO THEMSELVES DAMNATION.-<hi rend="italic">Epistle to the Romans</hi>, xii. 1,2.</p>
               </epigraph>
               <p>WHEN the angel of death, who is also the angel of God,
enters our homes, beloved, the Christian heart receives his advent in
silence; both because words cannot express the agony, and silence is
the most befitting fashion of souls that receive the solemn
message. Today it is no private griefs that call us together. It is a
nation's sorrow, a nation's agony. The whole body politic is sick, the
whole heart is faint. It is the mourning of a nation for its Chief
Magistrate, assassinated by the hand of treason. What words can
express our loss, our sorrow.</p>
               <p>Behold the spectacle! Here was a man, remarkable not only
for his high office, but also for the solemn times in which he was
called to fill that office; a man summoned to the administration of
affairs in troubled times, who so kept the middle path of justice,
unswerved by 
<pb n="6" facs="chamberlain6.jpg"/>
friend or foe, that men of very diverse theories came, gradually, to
see that here, somehow, was a providential man, raised up to save the
nation; a man elected to be the pilot of the ship of State, who, in a
storm as it were of blood, when, sometimes, the very stars of hope
seemed lost, and every chart of guidance wanting, in silence held the
helm with a hand so firm and steady, as to win plaudits from men on
two continents: a man not over polished in the etiquette of Courts,
perhaps, and yet with a certain inner loyalty to Liberty, to Right and
Justice, with a certain strong, unswerving honesty of life, that set
him, by the natural justice of things, among royal hearted men. And he
died by the assassin's hand! The chief captain of a thousand
victorious banners that could not shelter him, and the leader of a
hundred legions of bronzed and steady soldiers who could not save him,
lies stark and cold in the Capitol, and a great nation weeps for its
foremost man in honor. This is, perhaps, under all the circumstances,
the most solemn day of the Republic.</p>
               <p>"The powers that be are ordained of God." To this man
belonged the headship of the Republic, both by divine and human
right. He was your President. You, by the operation of that
Constitution under which you live, had, of your own free will, lifted
him to that great eminence. As your civic head, henceforth his honor
became your own. As the President of your nation, whatever affected
him, pertained to you. The assassin who smote your President, smote
also the nation's head and
<pb n="7" facs="chamberlain7.jpg"/>
heart. Why was it that he died? Was it because he had forfeited his
life to violated law? He was preeminent as sustaining law. Was it
because he was such a monster in cruelty or crime, that by the common
consent of outraged human nature, he deserved to perish? He was known
to have been as tender-hearted as a woman; sparing, to his gentle
instincts, many evil doers, and millions honored and trusted and
reverenced him, the day he died. No; it was because he was your
President, and as the President, he had executed the people's will;
because, being elevated to the chair of Washington, he had dared, like
Washington, to love and save his country; because he had kept his most
solemn oath of office, and saw that the Republic received no detriment
at his hands; because he dared to stand between treason and its
success, and withstood, by his official powers, the attempt to slay a
nation and destroy a destiny; because he had been loyal to the
traditions, the hopes, the promises, and the genius of a great
republic.</p>
               <p>You have heard it said, perhaps, in times past, (the grave
has wisely silenced all criticism of him whatever,) that he was
responsible for the loss, the burden, and the agony, that for the last
four years has crushed and smote the nation's heart. But how? National
policy is by the national vote; and the nation voted to govern itself,
and finally to save itself by war. He had but one vote among millions,
and he obeyed the people when he prosecuted war. Was he a man of
blood, rejoicing in battle? That cold, unmoving hand of our dead Presi-
<pb n="8" facs="chamberlain8.jpg"/>
dent, was worn by holding out the olive breach of peace to the men who
drew the sword against our nationality, beseeching them to have mercy
on themselves and yield. No; it is the men who smote against the flag;
the men who would destroy our nationality; the men who would overturn,
by insurrection, the very foundations of our liberties; the men who
repudiated our national traditions and glories; who insulted the
graves of our martyrs, and declared before the world that equal rights
were miasma and delusion, and popular liberty a myth; who have made
this nation blind with sorrow, and faint with the sacred offering of
its reddest blood, that the Republic might live in peace.</p>
               <p>The conspirators against unity and nationality are
responsible, I say. They sowed the wind only to reap the
whirlwind. The dragon's teeth which they scattered on the nation's
soil, wounded the hands that strewed. They spoke to a loyal people
with the voice of cannon, and cannon answered them; they insulted
loyal ears with beating drums, and they have grown familiar with the
sound of muffled drums; they marshalled legions, and were trampled
down of legions; they proffered, with proud hand, a bitter cup to the
nation's lips, and they themselves drank the very dregs thereof. They
appealed to God, and His decision was their defeat. They took the
sword, and they perished by the sword. "The powers that be are
ordained of God. Whosoever, therefore, resisteth the power, resisteth
the ordinance of
<pb n="9" facs="chamberlain9.jpg"/>
God; and they that resist, shall receive to themselves damnation."</p>
               <p>In this Church to-day are the symbols of human power and
the divine power, in which all that can be rightly called authority
exists. The flag of your country is the symbol of "the powers that are
ordained of God." The altar is the symbol of that God by whose will
human law exists. The flag you have draped in mourning, for it is the
emblem of an earthly sovereignty. The altar is never draped, because
it is the emblem of the immutable sovereignty of God. The President
dies; the Christ of the altar never dies. Cabinets are changed; but
the counsels of God never change. Nations mourn; but in Heaven they
never mourn. The great captains of human destinies fall and fail; but
the Captain of our Salvation is always strong and sure. Here human
passions and the assassin's dagger change our thanksgivings into
funeral knells, and a nation is confused by a sudden and ghastly
crime; but in the Father land of our resurrection, the light is never
shadowed, the song is never silenced, the love and peace of God can
never fail.</p>
               <p>The nation's sorrow is uttered in its draped flags; its
solace and its strength are spoken in the undraped altar, that tells
us of the all-sufficing and changeless power of God.</p>
               <p>I turn to consider for a moment, in the attempt to quicken
our Christian patriotism in this, our nation's sorrow, which is meant
to deepen our love for father-
<pb n="10" facs="chamberlain10.jpg"/>
land, to notice the meaning of that word nation, to the clear-sighted
and Christian heart. A nationality is a sublime, a solemn, a saved
thing. It has its history, its prophecy, its destiny. It is always
built upon solemn sacrifices; it is a compact always sealed with
blood. It is a purchase made with loyal and self-surrendered lives. It
is a patrimony watered with tears, preserved by faithful and patriotic
labors, and steadied and maintained, sooner or later, by men who dare
to be just, in the face of imminent perils, and citizens constant, at
a great cost, to its interests and needs.</p>
               <p>Our nationality, like every other, is sacred to us, with
the memory of dead heroes, and fragrant with the perfume of pure, and
stainless, and patriotic lives, who wrought and died for it. Our flag,
as I have said, is the symbol of our nationality, and is sacred with
its history. As a nation changes or advances, so does its flag, which
wraps in its folds its story. A nation's shame or glory dims or
brightens its flag. When, four years ago, our flag went down in an
unequal conflict in Charleston harbor, it was an honored flag. It was
our fathers' flag. Stout hands, moved of stout hearts, had carried it
on battle fields and on the seas to victory. It was the flag of a free
people, and it meant liberty. It sheltered its citizens in every
clime, and it was saluted of many peoples, who saw in it the
sovereignty of a free, a powerful nation. The last four years have
encircled it with a new halo of glory. It hath endured a new baptism,
wherein the smoke of battle
<pb n="11" facs="chamberlain11.jpg"/>
stained not and the fire consumed not. It carries in its folds the
illustrious record of all who died for it, and of all who strove for
it, that no star should fall from it, and no stain rest on
it. Henceforth that flag is the legend which we bequeath to future
generations, of that severe and solemn struggle for the nation's life,
in which we endured so much, and conquered,--not so much our enemies,
our countrymen,--as our own right to live and be a nation. Henceforth
the red on it is deeper, for the crimson with which the blood of
countless martyrs has colored it; the white on it is purer, for the
pure sacrifice and self-surrender of those who went to their graves
upbearing it; the blue on it is heavenlier, for the great constancy of
those dead heroes, whose memory becomes henceforth as the immutable
upper skies that canopy our land, gleaming with stars wherein we read
their glory and our duty. Yea, now behold a deeper crimson, a purer
white, a heavenlier blue. A President's blood is on it, who died
because he dared to hold it in the forefront of the nation. Henceforth
it bears in its folds the memory of the Chief Magistrate of the
Republic, who died because he had planned that the State should
live. Henceforth, where-ever that flag is carried; when it is canopied
again, of battle waged for human liberties, throughout the ages;
wherever our navies bear it in under the frowning battlements of
kingly realms, and in the presence of the silent or loud-mouthed
cannon of ancient citadels, stationed on any sea; under all skies, in
the immortal
<pb n="12" facs="chamberlain12.jpg"/>
constellation of its stars that represent its martyrs, shall be
blazoned forth the fame of our dead chief, who died in his great
office, sealing his record with his blood, that the one flag, cleansed
of all shadow of unequal rights for any race or color, may be the flag
of one nation, of one privilege, of one justice, of one liberty for
all men, forevermore.</p>
               <p>Remember, then, the text, "The powers that be are ordained
of God." So far I have spoken of those matters which naturally suggest
themselves in these unusual and solemn furnishings of our Church. I
address myself to the re-kindling in your hearts of that Christian
patriotism which these solemn services encourage, when I invite your
notice to the fact of the intimate relations and the mutual offices
which exist between Church and State. It is the quality of high
office, that the man who fills it cannot even die without giving a
very positive direction and influence to the minds of those over whom
he is called to preside. Certain am I that no President of this
Republic has ever died, who by the manner of his death has ever taught
us all such impressive and solemn lessons as those of this present
hour. And the lessons which he teaches are in behalf of liberty, law
and nationality. I beg you to observe, then, the relation between
church and State in the Republic. For that they are somehow bound
together, is proved from this unusual spectacle around me. If not,
tell me why, as Churchmen, you have hung these flags in this place,
which you have consecrated to the wor-
<pb n="13" facs="chamberlain13.jpg"/>
ship of Almighty God, through Jesus Christ, His Son, and in the very
presence of so many memorials of the Lord's Cross and Passion? Have
you not placed these symbols of the State so near the altar because,
somehow, these two have intimate relations? The question has but one
answer. They exist together.</p>
               <p>The duty of the Church to the State is, first of all,
obedience in things temporal. The correlated duty of the State is
protection: The Church is a spiritual kingdom. She cannot assume to
herself the power of the sword, and is strong only in her humilities,
her charities and life of the Holy Ghost. But then she nurtures in the
heart of the State that spiritual life and sense of holy things,
without which states perish. Her contributions to the public weal are
in things spiritual and eternal. Pursuing her holy avocations in godly
quietness, her first instinct is that of submission to civil
authority. Obedient, she asks only to be protected in her inoffensive
and blessed avocations. She shelters herself beneath the strong arm of
public authority, and in return for her shelter, as her bounder duty,
she teaches reverence, obedience, submission to "the powers that be."
This she is taught to do, by the whole strain and tenor of the
teaching of Her blessed Lord. She hears Him say, "Render unto Caesar
the things that be Caesar's, and unto God the things that be God's,"
and renders them accordingly. She finds the same lesson in those holy
Scriptures, whose teaching she obeys. She finds the same practice in
all the ages
<pb n="14" facs="chamberlain14.jpg"/>
of an uncorrupt and apostolic faith. She hath suffered great wrongs,
during long, weary days of dishonor and reviling, at the hands of
unjust rulers, and refused either to rebel or disobey. She hath once,
at least, in this Republic, periled her very existence, by her
persistency in obeying constituted and established law. The very
genius of the Church is that of subordination and obedience. Her
ancient hierarchy and order, wherein every man, having his own rights
in his own place, is yet under fixed law and rule, begets the same
sentiment of submission. Most emphatically does she teach obedience
and reverence to the civil magistrate. Twice a day, whenever her daily
service is celebrated, every priest is bound to offer before the
people a prayer for "the President of the United States and all others
in authority." In her Litany she prays for "all Christian rulers and
magistrates," and to be delivered from "all sedition, privy conspiracy
and rebellion." Throughout her Liturgy and in her occasional services,
she inculcates obedience to "the powers that be." Her utterance is no
uncertain sound. Avoiding, on principle, and from a fixed policy
transmitted to her from primitive time, all confusion, she shuns all
intermixing of politics or temporalities with her sacred offices; but
as a matter above and beyond all such things, she teaches as an
integral part of her religion, patriotism, loyalty and obedience to
constituted authority. If you allege, in answer, that her children
have sometimes been disloyal, I answer, the disciples have sometimes
betrayed
<pb n="15" facs="chamberlain15.jpg"/>
or forsook their Master. Their sin makes against themselves. It is
nothing against the holy things which they forsake.</p>
               <p>On this day of our solemn sorrow, the Church, finding her
words enforced by a great calamity, speaks to you both as citizens and
as Churchmen, and the lesson taught is this: She says, "In a republic,
majorities must rule, and minorities submit. Republicanism is only
possible so. When any man is elected to the Presidency, he becomes
your President,--the President of every citizen of the Republic. Then
whatever honors him, honors you; whatever injures him, injures
you. The man elected may not be a great man, or a good man, but when
elected, he becomes the chosen civic head of many great and good men,
and of the whole Republic. Honor him for his office. It is not your
charity, it is your duty." The Church says, moreover, to her children,
"You are to speak reverently of the President; not bitterly, nor
passionately, nor uncharitably, but reverently, if you speak at all."
To-day, reverence for our dead President is not difficult, for he hath
won it, or wrested it from millions of hearts. But the lesson which
the Church teaches to-day, she will teach in all future
time. "Reverence the powers that be; obey, be loyal, be patriotic, and
deal very reverently with whoever may chance to be the Chief
Magistrate of the Republic, in all coming time." I do not ask how far
any of us have done this. But remember this in the time to come, when
in the altering fortunes
<pb n="16" facs="chamberlain16.jpg"/>
of parties, some man may chance to be your President, whom it is not
the fashion to admire. The Church knows no party but her own blessed
mission and salvation, through Jesus Christ. Her words cannot
alter. "Honor the President and all civil magistrates and rulers."
"The powers that be are ordained of God."</p>
               <p>I turn now from the more general to the special lessons of
the hour, to notice a few of the many that suggest themselves. In the
first place, we observe that all our griefs come more or less directly
from sin. True, this is a most ghastly sin and grime against a nation,
and a people suffer; but whether in the race or the individual, sin in
all its accidents and consequences is sharp, bitter, biting. It has
about it the sting of the serpent and the faintness and bewilderment
of a most active poison. Great crimes like this involve innocence with
guilt in the suffering which they entail. When Caesar died beneath the
daggers of the conspirators, the Tiber ran red therefor with noble
blood, and the Empire felt to its utmost bounds the sorrow that
followed the stroke of the assassins. The blow that struck down Henry
IV. of France, reechoed through all his realm, in the cry of Rachaels
weeping for their children whom it had thrust to the fore-front of a
most gruel civil war. When William of Orange perished by an assassin,
with him died the hope of Spanish rule in the Netherlands, and many a
proud house of Spain had cause to mourn for Spanish soldiers whom that
blow slew in unsuccessful, warfare. Blood, somehow, sheds blood. The
as-
<pb n="17" facs="chamberlain17.jpg"/>
sassin's knife reaches deeper than he knows. The blow that smote the
President dug graves and built gallows.</p>
               <p>The punishment of the criminal, whose only importance
arises from the magnitude of his infamy, is certain. They tell us that
as yet there has been no arrest. But how shall he escape? Shall he
hide himself among our millions? The virtuous wrath of a great people
will hunt him to his doom, Shall he seek asylum in the great cities of
the old world? European potentates are never enamoured of
assassination, and every court is bound, in self-preservation, to give
him up. Shall he fly to the isles of the sea for refuge? Our navies
float in every water, and the vigilance of justice inspects every
land. Shall he hide his infamy among barbaric and savage races of
unknown tongues? His guilt is a tongue that daily makes itself
intelligible before the throne of God. Shall he cower in the caverns
of the earth? Their portals are very broad to the messengers of
retribution. Shall he call upon the mountains to cover him? The
mountains cannot cover. Will he turn suicide? Whether it be by steel
or poison or any element, they only unlock the doors of his most
miserable doom. Shall he trust himself to the fire? The very fire will
surrender him to the bar of the everlasting justice, and declare who
it was that died by it. Shall he cast himself into the depths of the
sea, praying the high waves to cover him, and its most shadowy and
silent gulfs to hide him? The very sea gives up its dead to God; and
there is no escape.</p>
               <pb n="18" facs="chamberlain18.jpg"/>
               <p>I have spoken of a great criminal. All sin is crime, and
hath no refuge but in penitence and the One Atonement of the
Redeemer.</p>
               <p>You will observe in the next place, the uselessness of the
monstrous crime that hath covered our land with mourning. It is the
testimony of all history, that assassination hath never outmatched a
true cause or broken a nation's will whose heart was vital with a
great aspiration. The aspiration of this nation was and is for liberty
and unity. Contrawise, examples teach how assassination recoils with
untold miseries upon the cause in behalf of which it was invoked. The
nature of the moral government of God necessitates the history which
proves the statement. Were a just cause in the keeping of the
assassin's pistol, matter would have wrested the supremacy from
God. Were the Right subject to Brutus' dagger, it would be unworthy to
wear a kinglier than Caesar's crown. The feet of the legions that
march against Liberty only trample down the earth firmer on which her
pedestal is reared.</p>
               <p>What hath this assassin of our Chief Magistrate
accomplished? How has he aided those whom he aspired to vindicate? He
has struck down their most powerful and generous friend. How has he
improved their fortunes? A great nation this day bows itself in agony,
blind, bewildered, astounded by the cruel blow, but, taking to its
heart an oath, shaped in the very audience chamber of the illustrious
dead, that henceforth, in all matters pertaining to its own existence,
simple justice
<pb n="19" facs="chamberlain19.jpg"/>
shall be done, though the very heavens fall. What hath he wrought upon
the nation whose chief he slew? Have the wheels of the public
administration been blocked? They move on without a jar. Has the hand
that held the sword been palsied? It holds the sword more firmly. Has
the fabric of our liberties been rudely shaken? They are henceforth
cemented more firmly in the blood of the President of the Republic.</p>
               <p>Here hath been a State crime, indeed. Remember, all sin is
useless!</p>
               <p>But after all, I suppose, beloved, that in the hearts of
the millions who assemble themselves this day in solemn commemorative
services in honor of our dead President, the foremost thought is of
the loss which this nation has sustained. In the truest sense, in the
universe of God, things are not lost, but changed. Things become
invisible, not seldom grow to be more powerful. The dew-drop,
glittering on the spring violet, dried up of the thirsty sun, is lost
to sight only, to be lifted in the upper air, to deepen the blue of
the spring heavens. The snow-flake fallen upon the river is lost to
sight only to become the crimson and gold of the lifted clouds, or to
fill up the glory of the sunset skies. The flower that you trample
under foot, has perished only to breathe out its fragrance to purify
the air by which we live. The sacrifices offered for a thousand years
under the golden roof of Solomon's temple, disappeared indeed, in
smoke and vapor, from the vision of the priest who offered them, but
somewhere the world still holds every parti-
<pb n="20" facs="chamberlain20.jpg"/>
cle thereof. In a subtle but holy Providence, the quality of human
sacrifice is to quicken life. A great offering of blood, for instance,
made in behalf of a right cause, bears in its red hand a great
blessing. The fragrance of an heroic life, perished, as we say, under
the lictor's axe or the assassin's dagger, for Liberty or Right,
purifies and vitalizes, henceforth, the life of nations and
individuals. The blood of the martyrs of the Church has been the
whiteness of her robes and the glory of her Crown. The life of the
President, who died in the nation's Capitol, becomes, henceforth, an
integral part of the life of the Republic. In Him the accidents of the
visible flesh are changed to the permanence of an invisible and heroic
spirit. Martyrdom for duty lifts a man out of days, to become a
citizen of the ages. Had not this man been great, (as in many ways
great he was,) the fashion of his dying would have elevated him
amongst the most venerated sons of the Republic. Assassination hath
embalmed his fame and memory with his own blood.</p>
               <p>I point you to the same truth concerning the martyrs of a
four years war, of whom our dead President hath now become the
chief. I think of them at rest; some laid in sudden graves, with the
requiem of the cannon's roar or of muffled drums, and some with gentle
shrouding, by kindred hands, among their kindred dead; of those who
went down in the red tide of battle, in the hot strife of arms, in
sudden overthrow; of those who died in prisons, or wasted away with
pale famine, or
<pb n="21" facs="chamberlain21.jpg"/>
perished with disease or wounds,--all fallen for Fatherland. These
cannot perish. They live in the new life of the Republic, which God
hath grassed us in answer to such bounden, such precious
sacrifices. To Christian faith the martyrs never die. They tell us how
the peasants who live on the plains of Marathon, think they still
hear, on stormy nights, the onset of Mardonius and his fleshless
legions, and the cry of Grecian valor, though it be two thousand years
since the Hellenic race trampled down, in blood, the proud banners of
Medes and Persians, that Hellenic nationality might live. Henceforth
the flag of our Republic hath a new championship and
retinue. Hereafter, whereever that flag is lifted in red battle in
behalf of justice, of nationality, of liberty, the invisible spirits
of those ascended from beneath its folds, in a chariot of
battle-flame, to an immortal honor, gather about it, to strengthen the
arms of those who strike for it, and to steady the hearts that honor
it, and follow it.</p>
               <p>It was, you know, on that most strange and solemn Easter
Sunday, which the American Church will long remember, with the Easter
flowers to speak of the new life through the risen Christ, and our own
agony to remind us how all flesh is "like the grass," that our pious
thought and wish for our dead President was, that when he went out
from under all his burdens, having laid aside his high office, humbly
trusting to the one Atonement once made for him and all men, freed
forever from the assassin's blow and the traitor's contumely, in a
land where malice and foul passions come not, his soul might rest in
peace.</p>
               <pb n="22" facs="chamberlain22.jpg"/>
               <p>It may be a very human thought, which somehow connects the
passage of our President into the spirit-land with that solemn story
of the prophet, who tells us that when the king of Babylon came
amongst the company of royal spirits, the kings of the whole earth
rose up from their shadowy thrones, and met him with solemn
greetings. I think of our dead Chief; of his patience, his endurance,
his great burdens, his great achievements, his most solemn and tragic
death for Fatherland; and, somehow, I seem to see, as he enters the
shadowy land of the Hereafter, the dead heroes and patriots of the
Republic,--foremost among them the great Captain of our war of
Independence, whose ashes they laid in rest by the blue waters of that
Potomac so often reddened now of patriots' blood,--rising up and
coming forth to greet our Chief, as their peer and brother; as one
who, for the Republic, followed through four years of solemn and able
services, the oath which he had sworn to save it, and sealed it with
his blood.</p>
            </div2>
         </div1>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>