<TEI.2>
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt n="Sermon on the Occasion of the Death of President Lincoln.">
            <title>  Sermon on the Occasion of the Death of President
Lincoln.</title>
            <author>Crane, Rev. C. B.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Compiled and edited by</resp>
               <name>Beck
Center</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent/>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Lewis H. Beck Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Emory
University</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Atlanta,
Georgia</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>1996 Emory
University. Permission is granted to download, transmit, or otherwise
reproduce, distribute or display the contributions to the work claimed
by Emory University for non-profit educational purposes, provided
this header is included in its entirety.  For inquiries about
commercial uses, contact the Director, 
Pitts Theology Library, Emory
University, Atlanta, Georgia 30322</p>
            </availability>
            <date>1999</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Lincoln Sermons Project</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl> Crane, Rev. C. B. Sermon on the Occasion of the Death of
President Lincoln. Preached in the South Baptist Church, Hartford,
Conn. Sunday, April 16, 1865.  Hartford: Press of Case, Lockwood and
Company. 1865. </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This text derives from the Special Collections 
of Pitts Theology Library, Emory University, and is produced in 
collaboration with the Lewis H. Beck Center a, the Emory 
Preservation Office, and Pitts Theology Library.</p>
            <p>TRANSCRIBER: Lewis H. Beck Center and Emory University Preservation Office.</p>
            <p>PRODUCER:  BookLab, Inc., 1606 Headway Circle, Suite 100, Austin, TX 78754</p>
            <p>CAPTURE DEVICE: XEROX DocuImage 620S flatbed scanner</p>
            <p>CAPTURE DETAILS: Scanner software: XEROX ScanTool version 4.2.3; no gamma correction; images are all bitonal.</p>
            <p>CHANGE HISTORY: Using the Adobe Photoshop Batch Processor, we interpolated  the original TIFF files to 8-bit grays, and altered the resolution to 144 dpi, producing screen images twice the original size.  We then saved them in JPEG format.  We produced GIF thumbnails from the JPEG files.</p>
            <p>RESOLUTION: 600 ppi</p>
            <p>COMPRESSION: Resolution 144 per inch with Constrain Properties to 72 per inch.</p>
            <p>SOURCE: Original documents.</p>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>1999</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Scott Ellis</name>
               <resp>Staff</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <item>SGML tags
inserted in compliance with TEI guidelines using TEILITE</item>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div1 id="crane.001" n="Sermon on the Occasion of the Death of President Lincoln." type="text">
            <head>
               <bibl>
                  <title>Sermon on the Occasion of the Death of President
Lincoln.</title> 
                  <date> Sunday, April 16th, 1865.</date>
                  <pubPlace>South Baptist Church, Hartford, Conn.</pubPlace>
                  <author>Rev. C. B. Crane.</author>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Hartford, Conn.</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Press of Case,
Lockwood and Company.</publisher>
                     <date>1865</date>
                  </imprint>
               </bibl>
            </head>
            <p>
               <figure entity="crane1">
                  <figDesc>1st page of Rev. C. B. Crane's Sermon
on the Occasion of the Death of President Lincoln.</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <p>S E R M O N</p>
            <p>ON THE</p>
            <p>OCCASION OF THE</p>
            <p>DEATH OF PRESIDENT LINCOLN.</p>
            <p>PREACHED IN THE</p>
            <p>SOUTH BAPTIST CHURCH, HARTFORD, CONN.,</p>
            <p>SUNDAY, APRIL 16, 1865.</p>
            <p>BY REV. C. B. CRANE.</p>
            <p>HARTFORD:</p>
            <p>PRESS OF CASE, LOCKWOOD AND COMPANY.</p>
            <p>1865.</p>
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>
               <figure entity="crane2">
                  <figDesc>2nd page of
Rev. C. B. Crane's Sermon on the Occasion of the Death of President
Lincoln.</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>
               <figure entity="crane3">
                  <figDesc>3rd page of
Rev. C. B. Crane's Sermon on the Occasion of the Death of President
Lincoln.</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <p>HARTFORD, APRIL,
17,1865 <lb/>REV. C B. CRANE. 
	<lb/>Dear Sir: Having listened to your sermon yesterday, upon
the sad event of the death of our late President, and fully endorsing
the sentiments of the discourse, we respectfully solicit a copy for
the press, believing that its circulation in a permanent form will
subserve the interests of justice and freedom. 
		 <lb/>We are truly yours,
				<lb/>ALBERT DAY,
				 <lb/>JAS. G. BATTERSON,
				 <lb/>HORACE J. MORSE,
				 <lb/>DANIEL F. SEYMOUR,
				 <lb/>E. OVERAND,
				 <lb/>JOSEPH L. BENNETT,
				 <lb/>A.M. SMITH,
				 <lb/>R. S. LAWRENCE.</p>
            <p>HARTFORD, April 18,
1865.  <lb/> Hon. ALBERT DAY, JAMES G. BATTERS0N, Esq.,
			<lb/>Gen. Horace J. Morse, and others:
	<lb/>The sermon which you request for publication, owing to its
necessarily hasty preparation, greatly needs revision; but since its
circulation should be immediate, if ever, I hereby submit it to your
disposal. 
					<lb/>I. am most truly yours,
								<lb/>C. B. CRANE.</p>
            <pb n="4"/>
<!-- blank page -->
<!--
            <p>
               <figure entity="crane4">
                  <figDesc>4th page of
Rev. C. B. Crane's Sermon on the Occasion of the Death of President
Lincoln.</figDesc>
               </figure> 
            </p> -->
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>
               <figure entity="crane5">
                  <figDesc>4th page of
Rev. C. B. Crane's Sermon on the Occasion of the Death of President
Lincoln.</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <div2 id="crane.002" n="SERMON" type="sermon">
               <head>SERMON.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <p>2 SAMUEL, 1: 19. 
<lb/>
"THE BEAUTY OF ISRAEL IS SLAIN UPON THE HIGH PLACES;
		HOW ARE THE MIGHTY FALLEN!"</p>
               </epigraph>
               <p>The nation is weeping to-day; and its temples and homes and places
of business and public edifices are draped in mourning. Strong men,
who could endure the shock of personal calamity and the pangs of
personal bereavement with uncomplaining fortitude, are shaken by the
violence of their emotions, and their tears fall upon the pavement of
the crowded street. Gentle women, secluding themselves at home, mourn
as for a husband or a lover. The festivities of society are checked,
and plans for future gayety are stopped in their process of
relaxation. Over the whole American sky are clouds and thick
darkness. Threnodies are sung by quivering lips and wail from
melancholy organs. All sounds are dirges, and the countenance of
sorrow is adorned with the jewelry of tears.</p>
               <pb n="6"/>
               <p>
                  <figure entity="crane6">
                     <figDesc>6th page of
Rev. C. B. Crane's Sermon on the Occasion of the Death of President
Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <p>Oh, friends, on the evening of Good Friday, the memorial
day of the crucifixion of our Lord, our good, true-hearted,
magnanimous, supremely loyal, great President was smitten down by the
hand of the assassin; and yester morn, at twenty-two minutes past
seven of the clock, his noble and holy soul went up from its shattered
and desecrated tabernacle to its God.</p>
               <p>The terrible tragedy is consummated, its heartrending
denoument has transpired, there can be no revision of it, it stands
the blackest page save one in the history of the world. It is the
after-type of the tragedy which was accomplished on the first Good
Friday, more than eighteen centuries ago, upon the eminence of Calvary
in Judea.</p>
               <p>Yes, it was meet that the martyrdom should occur on Good
Friday. It is no blasphemy against the Son of God and the Savior of
men that we declare the fitness of the slaying of the Second Father of
our Republic on the anniversary of the day on which he was
slain. Jesus Christ died for the world; Abraham Lincoln died for his
country. The consecration of Jesus to humanity began in the antiquity
of eternity, and found its culmination when he cried with white, yet
triumphant, lips, on the cross, "it is finished." The consecration of
Abraham Lincoln to the American people had its phenomenal and most
<pb n="7"/>
                  <figure entity="crane7">
                     <figDesc>7th page of
Rev. C. B. Crane's Sermon on the Occasion of the Death of President
Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
manifest beginning in the summer of 1858, when he entered upon that
memorable Senatorial Campaign in which, while he sustained a technical
defeat, he gained a substantial victory; it found its culmination on
the evening of the fourteenth day of April, 1865, when the sharp
pistol report announced with terrible inarticulateness, "it is
finished."</p>
               <p>And let it not grieve us overmuch, beloved brethren that
the conscious life of our late honored President ceased in the <hi rend="italic">theatre</hi> of our National Capital. He was there, not
for the purpose of gratifying himself, but at a personal sacrifice,
and for the sake of the people whom he loved. For this is the
statement of the public prints: "The President and Mrs. Lincoln did
not start for the theatre until fifteen minutes after eight
o'clock. Speaker Colfax was at the White House at the time, and the
President stated to him that he was going; although Mrs. Lincoln had
not been well, because the papers had announced that General Grant and
they would be present, and as General Grant had gone North he did not
wish the audience to be disappointed. He went with apparent
reluctance, and urged Mr. Colfax to go with him; but that gentleman
had made other arrangements, and, with Mr. Ashmun of Massachusetts,
bade him Good Bye." He did not wish the audience to be
disappointed,"--this was the
<pb n="8"/>
                  <figure entity="crane8">
                     <figDesc>8th page of
Rev. C. B. Crane's Sermon on the Occasion of the Death of President
Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
reason of his presence at the theatre on that fateful evening; and the
sentiment which dictated the words has given character to all his
private and public life.</p>
               <p>One year ago the eighteenth day of next month it was my
privilege to meet President Lincoln in the executive chamber of the
White House, in company with a delegation from the Methodist General
Conference, then in session in Philadelphia. I remember that in
replying to the address which was read to him he expressed in a most
devout manner his gratitude to God for giving to the government the
sympathy and support of the churches. And here are words which I wrote
soon after the interview, and which I repeat to you in order that you
may know the impression which the personal presence of the man
produced upon me: "The President looks thin and care-worn. I believe
with all my heart that he bears this great nation like a burden on his
life. God strengthen and guide him!"</p>
               <p>I saw many senators at that time, and many of the
representatives in Congress, and the heads of some of the departments;
and I recollect that while many of them were rubicund and jovial, and
others showed in their countenances only the resultant fatigue of
their labor,-the form of the President was bowed as by the
superimposition of a crushing
<pb n="9"/>
                  <figure entity="crane9">
                     <figDesc>9th page of
Rev. C. B. Crane's Sermon on the Occasion of the Death of President
Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
load, his flesh was wasted as by the consuming flames of incessant
solicitude, and his face was thin and furrowed and pale as though it
had become spiritualized by the vicarious pain which he endured in
bearing in himself the calamities of his country.</p>
               <p>And just that suffering, worn, martyr-like form and face of
his which I looked upon a little less than one year ago; just that
unselfish love and sympathy for others which expressed itself in every
lineament and gesture;-interpret to me the self-denying presence at
the theatre, on the night of his immolation, of the noble Atlas on
whose shoulders for four bloody years our political world has
rested.</p>
               <p>Oh memorable Good Friday, henceforth a day of sad
reminiscences in the calendar of country as well as church! While I
was walking the last evening but one under the solemn stars, all
ignorant of the disastrous presence of the destroying angel in the
land, and the tardy moon was peering over the eastern horizon as if
reluctant to look upon the infernal deed which was accomplishing, two
fiends in the guise of men, or two maniacs whose insanity is a crime,
the creatures of the ghastly rebellion which has reared its horrid
front in the South and has had shameful affiliation with dastardly
reptiles of the North, were finishing, each his own hideous work, in
our nation's capital The one was permitted by an
&#x003C;<pb n="10"/> 
                  <figure entity="crane10">
                     <figDesc>10th page of
Rev. C. B. Crane's Sermon on the Occasion of the Death of President
Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
inscrutable Providence in the presence of a crowded assembly to
consummate his purpose upon the life of him whom the world was
delighting to honor. The other, with a daring which is well-nigh
unparalleled, overthrowing all who resisted his progress, forced his
way into the chamber of the Secretary of State who was slowly
recovering from recent injuries, and plunged the fierce knife again
and again into his neck, that column which sustained as royal a brain
as the present age possesses.</p>
               <p>God's lightning, speeding along the wires, has since told
us that the President is dead; and that the life of Secretary Seward
hangs upon a thread which the gentlest strain would break.</p>
               <p>Night of crime and horrors! what pen can write thy cursed
record!</p>
               <p>Friends, we will not forget to pray to God for the life of
our Secretary of State; we will not forget to implore God to be a
Husband to the widow and a Father to the fatherless; -but there is one
form, lying in state in the nation's chamber of love, upon which all
our eyes do bend in inexpressible grief.</p>
               <p>Ah, how does the splendid life of him who was the beauty of
our national Israel, unveil itself now before us, that we may
appreciate how much we have lost.</p>
               <p>We remember his obscure birth in Hardin
<pb n="11"/>
                  <figure entity="crane11">
                     <figDesc>11th page of
Rev. C. B. Crane's Sermon on the Occasion of the Death of President
Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
County, Kentucky. We remember how at eight years of age his sturdy
arms swung the axe in the forests of Indiana; and how the next ten
years of his life were mostly occupied in hard labor on his father's
farm, and how he attended school at intervals, amounting in the
aggregate to only a year, which was all the school education he ever
received. We remember how at the age of nineteen he floated down the
Mississippi river on a flat-boat to New Orleans. We remember his
removal with his father, at the age of twenty-one, to Illinois, and
his helping to build a log cabin for the family home, and his making
enough rails to fence ten acres of land. We hear the sounding strokes
of his hammer as he assisted in the building of a flat-boat which he
afterwards navigated down the "Father of waters" to its mouth. We see
him superintending a store and a mill, alert to improve every
opportunity for advancement in life. We remember his volunteering for
the Black Hawk war and his unexpected election to the captaincy of his
company. We remember his borrowing law-books from a neighboring
attorney which he took in the evening and returned in the morning,
studying while others slept. We remember how the surveyor of his
county offered to depute to him a portion of his work, and how he
procured a treatise on surveying and a compass and
<pb n="12"/>
                  <figure entity="crane12">
                     <figDesc>12th page of
Rev. C. B. Crane's Sermon on the Occasion of the Death of President
Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
chain, and did the work. We remember his rapid rise to distinction in
the profession which he had chosen. We remember his election to the
lower house of Congress in 1846, and his inflexible, though not
factious, opposition to slavery during his entire term of service. We
remember his magnificent Senatorial Campaign against Mr. Douglass, and
his advocacy of truths which became thenceforth clearer and dearer to
every lover of human freedom. We remember his election to the chief
magistracy of the American republic in the fall of 1860. We remember
the earnest and tender appeals which he made to his misguided brethren
of the South in his first inaugural address. We remember the sagacity
which has uniformly characterized his conduct of the government
through the past four years of its peril. We remember how long he
subordinated his instincts against oppression to his convictions of
constitutional guarantees. We remember his reluctance to issue the
proclamation of Emancipation, and the entire fidelity with which he
has since adhered to its provisions. We remember the magnanimous words
which he spoke to those who announced to him his nomination for the
Presidency. We remember the total absence of personal triumph and of
malevolence against his foes and ours, which distinguished his second
inaugural. And we remem-
<pb n="13"/>
                  <figure entity="crane13">
                     <figDesc>13th page of
Rev. C. B. Crane's Sermon on the Occasion of the Death of President
Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
ber--for it is a thing of yesterday--the yearning of his great,
brotherly heart toward the people of the insurgent states so soon as
their capital was taken and their only formidable army was either
captured or destroyed.</p>
               <p>Oh, friends, our loss is irreparable. His heart was a
woman's heart. His genius belonged to the philosopher; his intellect
belonged to the statesman. The caution which used to vex us who were
more eager than wise, was the child of a tender heart and a sagacious
brain. When in the depot of his own city, whence he was just setting
forth to enter upon the duties of his high office, he asked for the
prayers of his townsmen, he gave token of being possessed of that kind
of soul which is receptive of the inspiration of the Almighty; and
that God who raised him up for this critical period of our national
history <hi rend="italic">has</hi> inspired him for the successful
accomplishment of the stupendous work which was committed to his
hands.</p>
               <p>A rare man was our martyred President, a rare character was
his. Such was his greatness, that our wisest men are fearful of
trusting any other hands than his at the helm of our ship of
state. Such was the affection which his gentleness awakened, that
women wept yesterday as though their babes had
<pb n="14"/>
                  <figure entity="crane14">
                     <figDesc>14th page of
Rev. C. B. Crane's Sermon on the Occasion of the Death of President
Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
perished, and little children bore the news of his death to their
parents in tears.</p>
               <p>And can not we say together to-day: more blessed is Abraham
Lincoln, who was slain on Friday night, than is Jefferson Davis, who,
if he escape the hand of human justice, must skulk through the world
with the crime of treason upon his heart and the mark of Cain upon his
brow and the maledictions of futurity upon his memory forever.</p>
               <p>Wherever the body of Abraham Lincoln shall be buried, there
will be established a national shrine which shall share the honor of
pilgrimages with the tomb of the illustrious hero who sleeps his long
sleep amid the classic shades of Mount Vernon. Rest henceforth in
peace ye ashes of our glorified patriots! Commune ye now in the land
of spirits, oh elected souls of God!</p>
               <p>But, friends, it is time that I should turn away from him
who has so long fascinated to himself my thoughts and words. The
eulogy of our departed father and friend which you required of me, has
been pronounced. My grief which yesterday found only partial
gratification in my tears, is further soothed by the tribute of
affection which I have now publicly paid to the beloved and honored
dead.</p>
               <p>But there remains for me a duty to you who hear me. God
visits no such providence, smites with no
<pb n="15"/>
                  <figure entity="crane15">
                     <figDesc>15th page of
Rev. C. B. Crane's Sermon on the Occasion of the Death of President
Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
such smiting, as this, without a reason and purpose. Is it immodest in
me to assume that it is my office to voice your inquiries after the
meaning of this mournful event?</p>
               <p>(1.)  Observe, then, that we needed just this, perhaps, not
only to learn the hideous enormity of the slave-holders' rebellion and
of all sympathy with it from every quarter, but also for the
sufficient atonement for it and proper settlement of it. Treason,
murder, assassination, and all mentionable crimes, are the woof which
has from the first been woven into the warp of this gigantic and
infernal rebellion. Disregard of human life, contempt for the divine
authority which is vested in human rulers, supreme disdain of one who
has risen from the obscurest condition to the highest office of state,
eagerness to smite down the man who has been smitten by the bullet of
the desperado,--all these are the legitimate fruitage of the barbarous
institution of slavery which has risen against the national life. The
horrible crime of Friday night has taught us that root and stem and
branch of the rebellion are accursed, that there is nothing supremely
abominable and devilish of which it is not capable. Every man,
together with every woman, of the North, who has hitherto launched
fiercer invectives against the government and its friends than against
the spurious
<pb n="16"/>
                  <figure entity="crane16">
                     <figDesc>16th page of
Rev. C. B. Crane's Sermon on the Occasion of the Death of President
Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
confederacy and its friends, and who does not from this day eat the
hellish words which he has spoken and repent of his well-nigh
unpardonable sin, is an abandoned traitor, and deserves to be hanged
ten thousand times higher than Haman, and to sink ten thousand times
deeper into the pit than he. His sin, if it shall continue, is sin
against light clearer than noon-day, and is capable of no
extenuation.</p>
               <p>But not only does the tragic event which we are
commemorating betoken the fiendish nature of the rebellion; it was
needed also, perchance, for the sufficient atonement for it, and
proper settlement of it. If I am unwittingly blasphemous, forgive
me,--but when God would bring an apostate humanity into reconciliation
with himself, the sacrifice of his only and well-beloved Son was
requisite to the realization of his purpose and desire.</p>
               <p>So, when our national government would bring back to
allegiance to itself its millions of apostate subjects, it was
requisite that he who was dearest to all loyal hearts should be
offered in sacrifice. We .had already given our treasure, and our
husbands and fathers and brothers and sons. They had been laid upon
the altar and were consumed. We thought our offering was costly
enough, and that none costlier would be demanded. But there was a man,
occupying the highest office of state, dear to all loyal
<pb n="17"/>
                  <figure entity="crane17">
                     <figDesc>17th page of
Rev. C. B. Crane's Sermon on the Occasion of the Death of President
Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
hearts, the nation's father and brother and son, more anointed than
any other with the holy chrism of a great people's love. The
government was upon his shoulders, but he must be, nevertheless, yea,
because of his office, the lamb of sacrifice.</p>
               <p>There is a Roman legend that the ground in the middle of
the Forum sank down to an immense depth, leaving a chasm which could
not be filled. At last the soothsayers declared that if the Roman
empire was to endure, that must be devoted to the chasm which
constituted the principal strength of the Roman people. When all
shrank back aghast, Marcus Curtius, a noble youth, knowing that
courage and consecration to country were the strength of the empire,
armed himself in complete armor, mounted his horse, and leaped into
the abyss. Lo, the yawning jaws of the earth came together with a
shock and Rome was saved.</p>
               <p>Is it hard for you to believe, my friends, that if we could
have overheard the secret prayers of Abraham Lincoln, we might have
listened to such words as these, "Oh, God, use me as thou wilt for the
salvation of my beloved country?" Just that prayer from the best
beloved man of the nation God may have waited for long: just that
prayer he answered on Good Friday night. God accepted the costly and
self-devoted sacrifice which we had not dreamed of
<pb n="18"/>
                  <figure entity="crane18">
                     <figDesc>18th page of
Rev. C. B. Crane's Sermon on the Occasion of the Death of President
Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
offering. The "Lo I come to do thy will, oh God," which fell from the
lips of Jesus when he made himself the Lamb of sacrifice for the
restoration of an apostate humanity to allegiance to the divine
government, fell not sacrilegiously from the lips of our late heroic
President when he consecrated himself to his country and became the
requisite sacrifice for the restoration of rebellious citizens to
allegiance to just authority.</p>
               <p>And as the tragedy of the cross has startled tens of
thousands of sinners into a recognition of their sins, while it
expressed the inflexibility of God's law and authority, so we may hope
that the tragedy of last Friday night will startle multitudes of
rebels, North as well as South, into a recognition of their crime,
stiffen the government, which might otherwise bend, into requisite
rigidness, and hasten the consummation of peace for which we devoutly
pray.</p>
               <p>The last and costliest offering which God demanded has been
taken; and as on the first Good Friday peace was secured between an
apostate race and God, so we will trust that on the last Good Friday
peace was secured between the contending regions of our distracted
country.</p>
               <p>(2.) If your meditations have been like mine, friends, you
have already framed a second inquiry. Who are <hi rend="italic">responsible</hi> for the assassination of Abraham
<pb n="19"/>
                  <figure entity="crane19">
                     <figDesc>19th page of
Rev. C. B. Crane's Sermon on the Occasion of the Death of President
Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
Lincoln, and who share the guilt? The question which I have asked, I
dare answer. I have already shown that the open enemy are responsible,
and share the guilt. But this is not the whole answer. The event about
which our thoughts and regrets cluster was, partly at least, the
result of a false opinion which has been industriously promulgated,
and of a diabolical sentiment which has been generated, in almost
every community of the North. That opinion is that the President of
the Republic was a tyrant who ought to be resisted and
overthrown. That sentiment is unappeasable and pitiless hatred of
him.</p>
               <p>Now it will doubtless prove that the assassin of Abraham
Lincoln, although used as a tool by our Southern enemies, was not
merely a hireling, but one who had been brought to believe that the
execution of his purpose would be an act alike of patriotism and
piety. When he leaped upon the stage of the theatre, crying "sic
semper tyrannis," "be it ever thus with tyrants," it was evident that
he believed himself to have accomplished a truly just and heroic
deed.</p>
               <p>If, now, you inquire who is directly responsible for the
assassination of Good Friday night, I answer, that in addition to our
enemies in the South, it is those men of the North who promulgated the
false
<pb n="20"/>
                  <figure entity="crane20">
                     <figDesc>20th page of
Rev. C. B. Crane's Sermon on the Occasion of the Death of President
Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
opinion and generated the infernal sentiment to which I have alluded
above, and which made the assassin the fanatic and monomaniac that he
is. And if you ask who share the <hi rend="italic">guilt</hi> of the
horrible crime which we are considering, I answer, that it is every
man and woman who has shared the above mentioned opinion and
sentiment. They share the guilt, though their influence may not have
extended far enough to participate in the criminal act, just as
sinners to-day share the guilt of the crucifixion of Christ.</p>
               <p>Let me particularize. All those editors of political papers
who during the last Presidential campaign declared over and over again
that Abraham Lincoln was a tyrant worthy of universal execration: all
those demagogues who trumpeted the same falsehood in the ears of
fierce and ignorant mobs: that man of New Haven, who asked in a public
harangue, "who is the greatest traitor, Jefferson Davis or Abraham
Lincoln?" that man of Hartford, who, if rumor be true, at the breaking
out of the rebellion invested a thousand dollars in South Carolina
bonds, in token of his sympathy with the crime of treason: that man
who once held office in the President's cabinet, and who has never
since broken his infamous silence except to malign the government
which protected instead of hanging him: these are the men who
<pb n="21"/>
                  <figure entity="crane21">
                     <figDesc>21st page of
Rev. C. B. Crane's Sermon on the Occasion of the Death of President
Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
share the <hi rend="italic">responsibility</hi> of the murder of Abraham
Lincoln. They helped to produce the opinion and sentiment which
produced the man who did the deed. Blood is upon their souls. Wash
they their hands never so much, as did Pontius Pilate, they can never
be made clean.</p>
               <p>Shall I also particularize those who share, not the <hi rend="italic">responsibility</hi>, but the <hi rend="italic">guilt</hi>,
of the murder of Good Friday night? I answer, all those obscure and
uninfluential men who have shared the opinion and sentiment which I
have mentioned, but who have not been capable of extensively
promulgating them. That alderman in our city government who said
yesterday, "I have been waiting four years for some damned black
republican bones, to make bone dust to put around my vines, and I dont
know but there is a prospect of my getting some now." That man, those
men indeed, who were guilty of the substantial, if not the identical,
expression, "I am glad that Abraham Lincoln was shot, and I would like
to go down and dance on his coffin." That employee of the Springfield
and New Haven railroad who expressed joy at the murder of Mr. Lincoln,
and remarked that "he ought to have been shot four years ago." Every
man who has felt a secret joy at the horrible tragedy of the night
before the last. 
<pb n="22"/>
                  <figure entity="crane22">
                     <figDesc>22nd page of
Rev. C. B. Crane's Sermon on the Occasion of the Death of President
Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
Every man who has not been carrying a mourning heart all yesterday and
to-day.</p>
               <p>Shall I include any <hi rend="italic">women</hi> in this
infamous catalogue? women who ought to share the sweetness and
tenderness of womanhood? I will not dishonor the mother who bore me by
bringing so horrible a charge against her sex. But if I could speak to
all the women of the land I would say, if you have ever <hi rend="italic">thought</hi> or <hi rend="italic">felt</hi> murder against
Abraham Lincoln, the event of last Friday night is the voice of God
calling you to repent in dust and ashes. And if it be true, as is
reported, that a woman, whose name I do not know, said yesterday, that
"she was glad Abraham Lincoln was shot, and she hoped Jefferson Davis
might assume his place," I can say that rather than meet her in the
way I would be confronted by all the raging Furies of Tartarus. Oh,
woman! as thou canst be most tender and forgiving, so canst thou be
most vindictive and implacable.</p>
               <p>Thus I have shown you who they are who share the <hi rend="italic">responsibility</hi> of the assassination of Abraham
Lincoln, and who they are who share only the <hi rend="italic">guilt</hi>. There is a proper attitude toward these men
which we have not yet assumed. Friendship, fraternization, forbearance
with them, should cease till they purge themselves of their crime. The
lines must be drawn, and even households be divided if necessary, as
our
<pb n="23"/>
                  <figure entity="crane23">
                     <figDesc>23rd page of
Rev. C. B. Crane's Sermon on the Occasion of the Death of President
Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
Savior has predicted. Toleration of traitors and murderers and makers
of murderers is not a virtue, it is a vice. The wine of our national
life must become pure by separating itself from the lees of
disloyalty. I have shown you the men, friends, deal with them as you
will.</p>
               <p>(3.) One other thought remains to be expressed, a thought
of consolation for the future.</p>
               <p>We have lost our Palinurus, our helmsman, and our ship of
state is adrift on a stormy sea. Has God no greater Elisha to succeed
the departed Elijah? Must we despair of reaching the haven of a
victorious and holy peace?</p>
               <p>All yesterday and to-day I have been comforting myself with
the reflection that God is alive and on the throne. The christian men
and women whom I have met have lifted faces to heaven upon which was
the expression of holy trust and serenity.</p>
               <p>Although we were not aware of it, we have been for a
considerable time past placing our confidence in our lamented
President rather than in our God. And since his second inauguration,
on which occasion Andrew Johnson brought shame upon himself and the
nation, we have come almost to believe that the destiny of our country
was suspended upon the single life of Abraham Lincoln.</p>
               <p>God has smitten down him upon whom our faith
<pb n="24"/>
                  <figure entity="crane24">
                     <figDesc>24th page of
Rev. C. B. Crane's Sermon on the Occasion of the Death of President
Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
was impiously reposed, in order that he might transfer our faith to
himself. And in one short hour he has accomplished what he
undertook. There is not a christian man before me, nor in the whole
broad land, who has not leaned more heavily upon God, and been more
consciously sustained, during yesterday and today, than for months
before. We recognize our need of the divine arm, and lo, we feel
ourselves embraced by it and upheld.</p>
               <p>More than this, I believe that God purposes to bring final
deliverance to the republic by the same Andrew Johnson in whom on the
fourth day of last March we lost faith. Not only was the man whom we
trusted taken away, but the man whom we distrusted is made the captain
of our hosts. Him will God anoint for our salvation.</p>
               <p>For, friends, I know that God will save this nation. Our
whole history, and especially the history of the last four years,
would be nothing else than an excrescence upon the trunk of time, if
we should not reach a higher national perfection and prosperity than
we have yet realized.</p>
               <p>And since I know that the republic will be delivered, I
have all faith that Andrew Johnson will be used for the accomplishment
of our deliverance.</p>
               <p>True, he stumbled fearfully at the start. But there has
been wrought a marvelous change in the
<pb n="25"/>
                  <figure entity="crane25">
                     <figDesc>25th page of
Rev. C. B. Crane's Sermon on the Occasion of the Death of President
Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
man during the forty-one days which have since elapsed. If that
maudlin speech of his in the Senate chamber on the fourth of March was
a disgrace to himself and to the nation, his speech yesterday on the
occasion of taking the oath of the Presidential office, and his manly,
yet humble and devout bearing, more than atoned for the earlier
folly.</p>
               <p>Do you not remember how we lost faith in Gen. Ulysses Grant
at the bloody battle of Pittsburg Landing, and afterward during the
siege of Vicksburg? But he was God's anointed man, and to-day we
esteem him second to no captain whom the world has produced.</p>
               <p>Do you not remember how our confidence in Abraham Lincoln
was shaken when he went from Springfield to Washington, making little
speeches from the platform of the car all the way. To-day we lament
him as one of the greatest statesmen whom history celebrates.</p>
               <p>And it is a singular fact that during this great conflict
those men of whom we had the highest hopes at the beginning of their
career, have signally failed; while they whom at the outset we
distrusted, have attained to preeminent success.</p>
               <p>And so my faith in God's using of Andrew Johnson for our
national salvation is all the greater be-
<pb n="26"/>
                  <figure entity="crane26">
                     <figDesc>26th page of
Rev. C. B. Crane's Sermon on the Occasion of the Death of President
Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
cause the beginning of his more exalted career was so inauspicious.</p>
               <p>But there is another phase of the general thought which we
are considering to which I invite your attention. Abraham Lincoln's
work is done. Therefore, we can say, since God is in this thing, that
on the evening of the fourteenth day of the present April his work <hi rend="italic">was</hi> done. From that time God had no further use for
him in the position which he held. <hi rend="italic">At</hi> that time
God had use for Andrew Johnson in the place which was left vacant.</p>
               <p>Can we not detect some reasons for this providence of
God?</p>
               <p>It seems plain to me that our late President was peculiarly
adapted to the work which he has accomplished, and to the past phases
of the great conflict which is now approaching its end. His tenderness
and spirit of conciliation at the beginning, which left no excuse to
the rebels for a resort to arms; his wonderful caution, which did not
permit him to pass beyond the sympathy and support of the people; his
humaneness which forbade his starving the prisoners of the rebels
because they starved ours;--these were qualities which eminently
fitted him for the conduct of the war.</p>
               <p>But it is more than possible, it is even more than
probable, that just these qualities unfitted him for
<pb n="27"/>
                  <figure entity="crane27">
                     <figDesc>27th page of
Rev. C. B. Crane's Sermon on the Occasion of the Death of President
Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
the final settlement of this conflict. There was danger that he would
subordinate his executive functions to his personal sympathies; that
he would forget that God had placed the sword of retributive justice
in his hands to be used; that he would feel that the traitors had
suffered enough already, and needed no further punishment; that he
would even pardon Davis and Stephens and Johnston and Lee if they
should come into his power. He was drifting in that direction, and
most of us were drifting with him.</p>
               <p>But, friends, the vindication of this outraged government,
and its dignity and safety for the future, demand that treason be
judicially punished in the persons of the chief traitors. Treason has
not been punished yet; the losses its authors and abettors have
suffered have been the natural consequences alone of our own efforts
for self-defense. Just and formal punishment demands the conviction of
the criminal by due process of law. As the proportions of the
rebellion wane the time approaches when retributive justice can
execute itself. And it must be that retributive justice be executed,
or our conceptions of government and law will become totally
debauched.</p>
               <p>I say, then, there was danger that the late President, by
reason of his kindness of heart, would not be equal to the retributive
work which was soon to
<pb n="28"/>
                  <figure entity="crane28">
                     <figDesc>28th page of
Rev. C. B. Crane's Sermon on the Occasion of the Death of President
Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
be required of him; that pardoning the very arch-rebels themselves he
would fail to place upon the crime of treason its appropriate stigma,
and thus encouraging future rebellion, endanger the future of the
republic. If he was in danger of this mistake, then his work was done;
and therefore God translated him, having already so nobly done, to
glory.</p>
               <p>But Andrew Johnson, a man of nerve, has had his heart under
the iron heel of this rebellion. He appreciates treason. His sense of
justice is paramount to his tender sensibilities. He holds a
double-edged and keen-edged sword which reaches to the southermost
point of Florida. Therefore I believe that God has raised him up to
bring this rebellion to the consummation of just retribution. It is
not private revenge that he will wreak, but the vengeance of God,
whose anointed minister he is. And so God has given him to the nation
when the nation needed him. And we will lift our reverent eyes to
heaven to-day, and, gazing through our tears, say, "Thou doest all
things well."</p>
               <p>Abraham Lincoln's memory will be greener forever that he
did the work he did, and finished it when he did. The nation will
understand ere long that the dark Providence of last Friday night was
a merciful Providence. Andrew Johnson is the Joshua
<pb n="29"/>
                  <figure entity="crane29">
                     <figDesc>29th page of
Rev. C. B. Crane's Sermon on the Occasion of the Death of President
Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
whom God has appointed to consummate the work which our dead Moses so
nobly commenced.</p>
               <p>And so, on this Easter Sunday, the anniversary of our
Lord's resurrection, we cross the threshold which introduces us as a
nation to a career of unexampled victory and puissance and glory. And
though the body of our late honored President reposes to-day in
melancholy state, and we weep as we look upon it, yet as Christian men
and women we will cry one to another, "Rejoice, for the Lord God
omnipotent reigneth; and he will save the people whom he has redeemed
with the precious blood of his only Son."</p>
            </div2>
         </div1>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI.2>