<TEI.2>
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt n="The Lord Reigneth">
            <title>The Lord Reignith</title>
            <author>DeNormandie, James</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Compiled
and edited by</resp>
               <name>Beck Center</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent/>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Lewis H. Beck
Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Emory University</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Atlanta, Georgia</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>1996 Emory University. Permission is granted to
download, transmit, or otherwise reproduce, distribute or display the
contributions to the work claimed by Emory University for non-profit
educational purposes, provided  this header is included in its
entirety.  For inquiries about commercial uses, contact the Director, 
Pitts Theology Library, Emory University, Atlanta, Georgia
30322</p>
            </availability>
            <date>1999</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Lincoln Sermons Project</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl> DeNormandie, James. The Lord Reigneth.  A Few
Words on Sunday Morning, April 16th, 1865, After the Assassination of
Abraham Lincoln.  </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This text derives from the Special Collections 
of Pitts Theology Library, Emory University, and is produced in 
collaboration with the Lewis H. Beck Center a, the Emory 
Preservation Office, and Pitts Theology Library.</p>
            <p>TRANSCRIBER: Lewis H. Beck Center and Emory University Preservation Office.</p>
            <p>PRODUCER:  BookLab, Inc., 1606 Headway Circle, Suite 100, Austin, TX 78754</p>
            <p>CAPTURE DEVICE: XEROX DocuImage 620S flatbed scanner</p>
            <p>CAPTURE DETAILS: Scanner software: XEROX ScanTool version 4.2.3; no gamma correction; images are all bitonal.</p>
            <p>CHANGE HISTORY: Using the Adobe Photoshop Batch Processor, we interpolated  the original TIFF files to 8-bit grays, and altered the resolution to 144 dpi, producing screen images twice the original size.  We then saved them in JPEG format.  We produced GIF thumbnails from the JPEG files.</p>
            <p>RESOLUTION: 600 ppi</p>
            <p>COMPRESSION: Resolution 144 per inch with Constrain Properties to 72 per inch.</p>
            <p>SOURCE: Original documents.</p>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>1999</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Scott Ellis</name>
               <resp>Staff</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <item>SGML tags inserted in compliance
with TEI guidelines using TEILITE</item>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div1 id="denormandie.001" n="The Lord Reigneth" type="text">
            <head pn="1"> 
               <bibl> 
                  <title>The Lord
Reigneth</title> 
                  <date>April 16th, 1865</date> 
                  <pubPlace>Portsmouth,
N. H.</pubPlace> 
                  <author>DeNormandie, James</author> 
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>[unknown]</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>[unknown]</publisher>
                     <date>1865</date>
                  </imprint> 
               </bibl> 
            </head>
            <p pn="1">
               <figure entity="denormandie1">
                  <figDesc>1st page of James
DeNormandie's The Lord Reigneth.</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <p pn="1">THE LORD REIGNETH.</p>
            <p pn="1">A</p>
            <p pn="1">FEW WORDS</p>
            <p pn="1">ON</p>
            <p pn="1">SUNDAY MORNING, April 16, 1865,</p>
            <p pn="1">AFTER THE ASASSINATION OF</p>
            <p pn="1">ABRAHAM LINCOLN.</p>
            <p pn="1">BY</p>
            <p pn="1">JAMES DeNORMANDIE,</p>
            <p pn="1">Minister of the South Parish, Portsmouth,
N.H.</p>
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p pn="2">
               <figure entity="denormandie2">
                  <figDesc>2nd page
of James DeNormandie's The Lord Reigneth.</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <div2 id="denormandie.002" n="text of message" type="sermon">
               <p pn="2">MY CHRISTIAN FRIENDS,--I have no sermon, and there will be
no preaching here to-day.  For the first time I confess I wish I were
not your minister, expected to say a word of consolation or help,
which word I have not. Whenever I seek words, there come only tears;
but I could wish to be one of you meeting here to weep out our common
grief, while in the sacred silence of this temple of God we re-assure
ourselves that the Lord reigneth. Sometime when we are more calm I
shall speak to you at length of our sorrow, our loss and our duty.</p>
               <p pn="2">What means this overflow of tears wide as a continent? What
mean these bells answering bells in solemn dirge all over our land?
What mean these graspings of hand with hand when no word escapes the
lips?  What mean these anxious inquiries, these mute looks, this hope
against hope for some denial of our sad news, these mutterings of
vengeance, the streets lined with black, the air filled with
murmurings, the very heavens joining in our tears? What voice have
these strange drapings in our house of worship,--this emblem of our
national glory, which at our last meeting told such a tale of joy, now
too heavy with sorrow to speak at all--these flowers, which came to
join in our thanksgiving for the immortal life brought to light to
day, breathing their fragrance over an invisible bier, on which rests
an invisible body? "He is not here, he is risen."</p>
               <pb n="3"/>
               <p pn="3">
                  <figure entity="denormandie3">
                     <figDesc>3rd page of
James DeNormandie's The Lord Reigneth.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <p pn="3">
                  <hi rend="italic">Our President has been murdered!</hi> What made us
love him, so that the humble citizen, taken by God from a western
cabin, had well nigh won the image of the world? What makes each one
of us feel a personal grief, such as no ruler has ever called forth
before? It was this simply: This man of God was true to the noblest
principles which warm human breasts. Untaught in schools, but wise for
any emergency; unskilled in diplomacy, but more than a match for any
intrigue; temperate in the midst of every temptation; fearless in the
presence of any danger; hopeful under every defeat; calm in every
success; humble in every exaltation; powerful and yet prudent; firm
and yet lenient; patriotic and yet humane; liberal and yet just;
humorous and yet solemn--Abraham Lincoln walked by faith and not by
sight, and he was not, for God took him.</p>
               <p pn="3">There is but one word of hope or trust. The Lord
reigneth. Do not let us forget or doubt that, my friends, for one
moment, or everything is gone. You will hear this question asked by
some in utter despair. What are we all coming to? Let not us ask it,
or harbor the despair. What are we coming to? Why my christian friends
we are just following out the results of a cause which is sufficient
for all these things, and a great deal more; for all that has
happened, and a great deal still to happen. It is all coming about as
naturally as the warm sun is calling all nature into life to-day. You
may think it severe, you may think it strange, you may think it
narrow, you may think
<pb n="4"/>
                  <figure entity="denormandie4">
                     <figDesc>4th page of James
DeNormandie's The Lord Reigneth.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
it paritzan, you may think of it as you will--but remember this; the
time will come when you look at it in the light of Christian principle
and Christian retribution, and say with me, not a single thing has
happened for which we have not had <hi rend="italic">in slavery</hi> a
sufficient and plain cause.</p>
               <p pn="4">
                  <hi rend="italic">Our President has been murdered!</hi> Who
murdered him? That is something for you to consider in your hearts,
else we learn nothing from our calamity. Who murdered him? They tell
us it is Booth, an actor. No, it was not Booth. He was only an
instrument of others. They tell us it was a maniac in a moment of
frenzy. No, it was not a maniac. <hi rend="italic">It was the calmest
deliberation of the most reflecting and honorable supporters of
slavery for the last two hundred years</hi>. The maturity and
culmination, I trust, of this iniquity. Every man who has ever said a
word in defence, or extenuation of this, helped murder our
President. Every man who has ever said a word in defence or sympathy
with the confederacy based on this iniquity, helped murder our
President. Every man who has withheld his word of support or sympathy
for this nation struggling for a broader freedom, helped murder our
President. Every minister who has stifled his prayer, or forborne the
utterance of his heart's conviction, or permitted his sanctuary to be
a refuge for the nation's destroyers, has helped murder our
President.</p>
               <p pn="4">Abraham Lincoln was a noble man. Noble his life--forever
sacred be his memory. He was all American; a true representative of
what this peo-
<pb n="5"/>
                  <figure entity="denormandie5">
                     <figDesc>5th page of James
DeNormandie's The Lord Reigneth.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
ple may become. He was not my choice for President the first time, but
he soon won my heart. I have read somewhat of the history of the past
four thousand years, and I find the record of no nobler truer,
simpler, grander man. <hi rend="italic">But he is dead.</hi>
               </p>
               <p pn="5">The Lord reigneth. God be thanked. He has not permitted
very much of the world's progress to rest upon any one man. The very
highest, the very greatest are quite insignificant when we think of
this mighty march of the soul of humanity. We think otherwise. We
think it all depended upon one man we call Leader, General, Emperor,
King, President, Minister, Pope. It did not. We call his death
untimely. Nothing is untimely, from the quiet and unseen opening of
yonder leaf, and its fall some day next autumn when a gentle wind
shakes the bough, all along up the series of events to where a demon
robs a nation of its choicest treasure. Everything comes in the
fulness of time, from the blessing of yesterday to the Resurrection of
the world's Redeemer. It is all of God. God gave us our Chief
Magistrate, God preserved his life until he did his work; and think
what a work it was! Who shal1 say it was not done, and well done? But
most certainly there was something for another to do. Perhaps in that
great heart which knew no jealousy, no envy, no bitterness, and could
harbor no unkind feeling, and no shadow of revenge towards one of the
human kind, there was also wanting some of that quality which measures
out
<pb n="6"/>
                  <figure entity="denormandie6">
                     <figDesc>6th page of James
DeNormandie's The Lord Reigneth.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
justice to the guilty. What that work was, the days will fast reveal;
and whatever it was, God kept it for others to do.</p>
               <p pn="6">God gave him, God took him. Yea, my friends most sacredly
remember both. We are too apt to think that it is only by a lingering
death, by a long or severe sickness, or in a good old age, that God
takes one away. The other deaths we sometimes thoughtlessly call
untimely and unnatural. But God works by miracles sometimes, and then
we do not stop to read the natural laws under which they come. I am
very sure it was his Providence, that called our President away from
that Washington Theatre, as truly as if he had fallen quietly asleep
in a good old age. One man dies; but in God's way; and by God's hand
another is raised up, and the principle lives on. Each man fills a
place no other can. We ought not to want him to; but from all these
myriads, God will show us one or many to carry on His work; and if
this struggle be not His work, it matters little whether we have
another President or not.</p>
               <p pn="6">I spoke last Thursday of the Christian doctrine of
retribution, and said a cry for it would come up from the friends of
the prisoners, from the bereaved and sorrowing hearts, from the
freedmen. That cry to-day is wide as the nation. I loved our President
as I have never loved any public man, and yet, now that he has been
murdered, I have not a single feeling of revenge. I call for no
vengeance, but we must demand punishment. Not for the murderer
merely. Why,
<pb n="7"/>
                  <figure entity="denormandie7">
                     <figDesc>7th page of James
DeNormandie's The Lord Reigneth.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
I would not have even him hanged. There are many thousands all through
our land far more to blame than he. I do not ask for their blood. I
pray to day that not a drop of blood may be shed, though life is not
much; but I call for punishment, for Christian punishment, for
punishment, for past transgressions, for present rebelliousness, for
the sake of future safety; and let punishment fall wherever it
belongs, North or South. Let a cry for justice go up which shall make
this continent ring, and the guilty tremble. Justice which none but
the guilty ever fear. Law which none but the law-breakers ever
dread.</p>
               <p pn="7">
                  <hi rend="italic">Our President is dead</hi>. He rests from
his labors, and his works do follow him. Rest in peace, thou noble
martyr, while every heart hastens to pay a son of America, while thy
land learns the lesson tribute and drop a tear on thy grave. Rest in
peace of thy life. Rest in peace, child of liberty, while her anthem
swells to a purer strain over thy memory. Rest in peace, child of the
Infinite, with all the immortal company.</p>
               <p pn="7">
                  <hi rend="italic">Our President is NOT dead</hi>. He still
speaks. <hi rend="italic">He is not dead</hi>, for the memory of virtue
is immortal. <hi rend="italic">He is not dead</hi> and here is our only
sufficient consolation.</p>
               <p pn="7">To-day is kept very sacred in the Christian church, as
commemorating the resurrection of Jesus, which brought life, and
immortality to light. I was intending to speak to you this morning
from that passage in Mark's gospel, xvi. chap. 4th verse,--when as the
three women were going to the sepulchre to annoint the body of their
Master with spices,--the tribute of affection
<pb n="8"/>
                  <figure entity="denormandie8">
                     <figDesc>8th page of James
DeNormandie's The Lord Reigneth.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
after the custom of the age, and as the early sun was just giving his
rays to light their way--it occurred to them that a great stone which
had been put as a guard by the door, would defeat their pious purpose;
but when they came to it, and looked up, behold! the stone was already
rolled away.</p>
               <p pn="8">A simple incident, indeed, but how deep its meaning, how
grand its truth, how universal its experience. We too, go along with
banged heads and mourning hearts, raising doubts or questioning
possibilities, or wondering whence our aid is to come, or what we
shall do when we reach the end,--when there, we lift up our eyes and
it has all vanished, the danger, the dread, like some phantom which
has taken to itself fearful proportions, like some great body of human
form, which turns out only a stone, and that, rolled away from where
our path leads. Oh! my Christian friends, a bold and trusting, and
persevering soul finds no stone against the door, but always enters
without hindrance among the guarding angels by the Saviour's side.</p>
               <p pn="8">It was a short and easy step for our departed President
from the theatre of earth to the theatre of heaven. The evening light
was mortal, but the morning light was full of immortality. It was a
short way through a green pasture, and beside a quiet stream, with the
Lord Jesus leading. We have two words to strengthen and comfort us.</p>
               <lg type="stanza">
                  <l>"The Lord is risen."</l>
                  <l>"Be still and know that I
am God."</l>
               </lg>
            </div2>
         </div1>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI.2>