<TEI.2>
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt n="The Martyr to Liberty.">
            <title>  The Martyr to
Liberty.  </title>
            <author>Eddy, Richard</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Compiled and edited by</resp>
               <name>Beck
Center</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent/>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Lewis H. Beck Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Emory University</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Atlanta,
Georgia</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>1996 Emory
University. Permission is granted to download, transmit, or otherwise
reproduce, distribute or display the contributions to the work claimed
by Emory University for non-profit educational purposes, provided
this header is included in its entirety.  For inquiries about
commercial uses, contact the Director, 
Pitts Theology Library, Emory
University, Atlanta, Georgia 30322</p>
            </availability>
            <date>1999</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Lincoln
Sermons Project</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl> Eddy,
Richard.  The Martyr to Liberty.  Three Sermons Preached in the First
Universalist Church, Philadelphia.  Sunday, April 16th, Wednesday,
April 19th, and Thursday, June 1st.  Philadelphia: Published by Horace
W. Smith.  1865.</bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This text derives from the Special Collections 
of Pitts Theology Library, Emory University, and is produced in 
collaboration with the Lewis H. Beck Center a, the Emory 
Preservation Office, and Pitts Theology Library.</p>
            <p>TRANSCRIBER: Lewis H. Beck Center and Emory University Preservation Office.</p>
            <p>PRODUCER:  BookLab, Inc., 1606 Headway Circle, Suite 100, Austin, TX 78754</p>
            <p>CAPTURE DEVICE: XEROX DocuImage 620S flatbed scanner</p>
            <p>CAPTURE DETAILS: Scanner software: XEROX ScanTool version 4.2.3; no gamma correction; images are all bitonal.</p>
            <p>CHANGE HISTORY: Using the Adobe Photoshop Batch Processor, we interpolated  the original TIFF files to 8-bit grays, and altered the resolution to 144 dpi, producing screen images twice the original size.  We then saved them in JPEG format.  We produced GIF thumbnails from the JPEG files.</p>
            <p>RESOLUTION: 600 ppi</p>
            <p>COMPRESSION: Resolution 144 per inch with Constrain Properties to 72 per inch.</p>
            <p>SOURCE: Original documents.</p>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>1999</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Scott Ellis</name>
               <resp>Staff</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <item>SGML tags inserted in compliance
with TEI guidelines using TEILITE</item>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div1 id="eddy.001" n="The Martyr to Liberty." type="text">
            <head pn="1"> 
               <bibl> 
                  <title>The Martyr to
Liberty</title> 
                  <date>Sunday, April 16th, Wednesday, April 19th, and
Thursday, June 1st.</date> 
                  <pubPlace>First Universalist Church,
Philadelphia</pubPlace> 
                  <author>Eddy, Richard</author> 
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Philadelphia</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Published by Horace
W. Smith</publisher>
                     <date>1865</date>
                  </imprint> 
               </bibl> 
            </head>
            <p pn="1">
               <figure entity="eddy1">
                  <figDesc>1st page of Richard Eddy's The
Martyr to Liberty.</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <p pn="1">"The Martyr to Liberty."</p>
            <p pn="1">THREE SERMONS</p>
            <p pn="1">PREACHED IN THE</p>
            <p pn="1">First Universalist Church,</p>
            <p pn="1">PHILADELPHIA.</p>
            <p pn="1">Sunday, April 16th, Wednesday, April 19th, and Thursday, June
1st,</p>
            <p pn="1">By RICHARD EDDY, Pastor.</p>
            <p pn="1">PHILADELPHIA:</p>
            <p pn="1">PUBLISHED BY HORACE W. SMITH</p>
            <p pn="1">1865.</p>
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p pn="2">
               <figure entity="eddy2">
                  <figDesc>2nd page of
Richard Eddy's The Martyr to Liberty.</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p pn="3">
               <figure entity="eddy3">
                  <figDesc>3rd page of
Richard Eddy's The Martyr to Liberty.</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <div2 id="eddy.002" n="AND THE VICTORY THAT DAY WAS TURNED INTO MOURNING UNTO ALL THE PEOPLE-1 Samuel, xix., 2." type="sermon">
               <epigraph pn="3">
                  <p pn="3">AND THE VICTORY THAT DAY WAS TURNED INTO MOURNING UNTO
ALL THE PEOPLE-1 Samuel, xix., 2.</p>
               </epigraph>
               <p pn="3">Until within a little more than twenty-four hours what
preparations had been made for a joyous keeping of this day and of
to-morrow. How many had rejoiced in the assurance that the brightest
Easter sun that ever shone upon the earth, would this day smile upon
happy worshippers, and witness a beautiful and harmonious blending of
political rejoicing and religious thanksgiving! Our hearts were full
of gratitude and hope on the last Christian Sabbath. It was,
opportunely and with singular felicity of appropriateness, Palm
Sunday-the Sunday of victory, and all through the preceding week we
had been filled with congratulations and rejoicings. Then we brought
all our joy to the Christian temple, and felt that it had the approval
and the benediction of God. Our cup of happiness was well nigh
full. But on the opening of the busy week, yes, before we had closed
our eyes in slumber on the Sabbath night, still more glorious tidings
had come to us, and the joyous messages increased as each day brought
us nearer to this day of blessed rest.</p>
               <p pn="3">How beautifully all material and religious influences
seemed conjoined to make this day ever memorable for its joyous,
instead of as now, alas! its sad observance!</p>
               <p pn="3">I had advertised that I would speak to you (as suggested by
this Resurrection Morn,) on the New Life for Man, through the power of
the revelation of immortal life by the Resurrection of Jesus Christ,
and on the New Life for the Nation, planted as the richest shoot of
Christian civilization, and now destined to a glorious career under
Christian guidance, and the strong fidelity of the people to Christian
principle.</p>
               <p pn="3">I had thought that we might thus honor God and profit our
own hearts, by such an observance of Easter. How much there was to
furnish analogy, illustration and suggestion, and to enable us to look
with cheerful hope on the changing condition of our Country.</p>
               <p pn="3">I thought of the beautiful illustrations, the encouragement
to confident trust, the incitements to patient and cheerful waiting,
the every day increasing beauties, and the constant preparations for
future harvests so beautifully visible in this joyous Spring-time How
grandly do nature's types now shadow forth the realities of the
Christian
<pb n="4"/>
                  <figure entity="eddy4">
                     <figDesc>4th page of Richard Eddy's
The Martyr to Liberty.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
Dispensation, and seem in most genial keeping with our national
hopes. Fruit trees loaded with pure white blossoms; forest trees that
seemed but yesterday to be bending beneath their load of chilling
snow, now unfurling their emerald leaves; the daisy and the violet
blossoming by the road side; the fresh grass decking the earth that
was but yesterday bare; how all these sympathized or seemed to
sympathize with our new and almost as sudden, though in reality quite
as long preparing, national change. Oh! what a long and dreary winter
has our beloved Country passed through. Stripped of how many comforts,
pinched by how many wants, agonized by how many chilling blasts of
adversity, crushed by how many cold and heavy troubles, our hearts
aching with their burdens.</p>
               <p pn="4">I thought, too, to have you feel a fresher and livelier
interest in that great religious event which makes this day so
glorious. How appropriate it was, that it should fall on this
Spring-time of the year,-man's resurrection symbolized by nature, and
realized by the rising of the Sun of Righteousness. What fitness there
was, that our Anglo-Saxon fathers should redeem this day from its
heathen observances-from at least its merely natural uses, and make it
evermore a religious-a Christian festival.</p>
               <p pn="4">I thought, too, to have said some word that should make it
be felt, that this day celebrates that event which more than any other
gives assurance that the Christian Religion rests not in
imagination,-a merely beautiful, but, perhaps, also, a fictitious
theory, but on an unmistakable, an undeniable fact. And that at no
time have the American people had greater reason to satisfy themselves
of the positive truthfulness, and the absolute authority of the
Christian Religion, than is now pressing upon them. A professed
Christian land, with the great task before it of reconstruction of the
Government of so many of its parts; with a crushed and hitherto
despised race to provide for; with thousands of unfortunates, and
thousands of criminals to dispose of-to conciliate-to discipline, and
to save from being utterly cast away; what momentous issues these
raise, what grave responsibilities they impose, what faithfulness and
patience, what justice and mercy they demand. The Christian Religion
alone can help us to solve the problem-to do that which is right, and
just, and true. How important, then, to know that the Christian
Religion has authority, that it proposes God's methods, that it
advocates nothing impracticable, but everywhere and always holds forth
the eternal truth. Let us but establish our hearts in this, and God
will make us equal to our work. 
<pb n="5"/>
                  <figure entity="eddy5">
                     <figDesc>5th page of Richard Eddy's
The Martyr to Liberty.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
Let us seek adjustments, settlements, reconstructions on any basis
foreign to the Christian truth, and we have all our work to undo and
can find no rest, no peace, till we set our feet on this immovable
rock.</p>
               <p pn="5">I hoped, too, to have set forth some recent indication of
the life on which the Nation is about to enter. How the downfall of
the main army of Rebellion, and the notice consequent thereon, that
there was to be no more calls for soldiers, had given all
encouragement and hope for speedy peace; how the words of President
Lincoln, on reconstruction, plain-spoken, full of good sense, evincing
so much goodness and greatness of heart, had won their way to all
men's consciences, and seemed to unite us still more closely and more
warmly in the consciousness of one citizenship, and oneness of just
pride in our honest, able, noble-hearted, patriotic President.</p>
               <p pn="5">These thoughts I had revolved in my mind; had hoped to have
presented them somewhat fully to you this morning.</p>
               <p pn="5">Rising at an early hour yesterday, that I might have time
to arrange and write out my theme, I heard the tidings of the
assassination of our Chief Magistrate, which I am sure must have
affected you as they affected me- absorbed all other thoughts, and
banished all other themes. How sudden, how terrible the calamity! What
else could have so changed the current of human thought all over our
land! What else have stayed the rejoicings whose enthusiastic waves
were mounting up to a height never before known among the American
people! What else could have induced the people to lay aside the
flowers with which they were intending to deck the pulpits of the
land, and to put in their stead the symbols of deepest gloom ! What
else could have made us feel as we enter our churches this long-looked
for morning, that we are come to the burial of our fondest love,
rather than to bask in the sunlight of an immortal day, and mounting
up on the wings of an all victorious faith to shout, "0, death, where
is thy sting? 0, grave, where is thy victory ?"</p>
               <p pn="5">Surely, "the victory of our day is turned into mourning
unto all the people."</p>
               <p pn="5">And here, under the pressure of this common, this deeply
oppressive grief, what can I say ? what can any man say this day ? I
find myself continually repeating: "The Nation is bowed heavily with
mourning. The man beloved, trusted, honored, and worthy of all trust,
honor and affection, is suddenly taken away, and we, like bewildered
travelers, are bereft of our guide; like orphaned children, we mourn
the departure of our father!"</p>
               <pb n="6"/>
               <p pn="6">
                  <figure entity="eddy6">
                     <figDesc>6th page of
Richard Eddy's The Martyr to Liberty.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <p pn="6">Surely this expresses the common sentiment; it tells for
the time being all that, humanly speaking, can be said.</p>
               <p pn="6">Was there ever since the death of the saviour of the world,
a more brutal, a more uncalled-for murder? Private ambition, or
personal hate, had nerved the hearts and hands of men in other days,
to the destruction of their ruler. Patriots risking all, and applauded
by the world, had driven the dagger to the tyrant's heart. The
profligate kings and princes of the past had fallen victims to the
lust or envy of the men whom they had corrupted; and many a people
have breathed more freely, as through such "sudden taking off," a
change of administration was provided for them. But no such
contingencies, no such circumstances distract our thoughts from the
awfulness of this murder, or alleviate the gloom of this terrible
calamity.</p>
               <p pn="6">A good man, a pure patriot, a man unselfishly devoted to
the best interests of his Country; a man who was carried by the voice
of millions to the highest point of earthly trust and honor; who bore
himself meekly; who never failed to favorably impress either friend or
foe brought in personal contact with him; who seldom, though
staggering under a burden of difficult duty, such as never was laid on
any mortal man before, made a mistake in his policy, but came to be
regarded more and more as the one truly wise man of the land, and to
be loved and trusted by the common people with an affection and
reverence hardly second to that which a grateful Country cherishes
towards its Founder and Father, George Washington.</p>
               <p pn="6">And here, in the midst of a career so glorious, while
standing on the height from which he could survey the promised future
of a united and free people, just as the words of peace were to drop
from his lips, and the promises of still greater mercy were about to
be made to the guilty, he is taken from his work and from his earthly
reward.</p>
               <p pn="6">Strange infatuation of his enemies, that they did not see
that he was their best and truest friend, who with truly Christian
virtue was meditating their good.</p>
               <p pn="6">Fatal blindness that struck so murderously against the two
men of the Nation, who more than all others in power and influence,
were subduing the vindictiveness which war creates, and leading the
people step by step to a willingness for this most kind and most
merciful treatment of those who have sinned so deeply against the
welfare of our land, and the interests of humanity. Woe unto them!
Alas for us!</p>
               <p pn="6">Great need have we to strive and pray, that this wrong of
theirs does not fill us with vindictiveness and hate; and for him who
thus
<pb n="7"/>
                  <figure entity="eddy7">
                     <figDesc>7th page of Richard Eddy's
The Martyr to Liberty.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
suddenly steps into the place where one so loved and so worthily
honored stood, that Divine wisdom would be given him, and the mantle
of his great predecessor fall amply around him. Nor let us cease to
hope and to pray for the recovery of that wise and able Statesman,
whose judicious counsels, whose able diplomacy, whose farseeing
sagacity have kept us from trouble with foreign powers, and made us
even in the day of our weakness and our trial, to be feared and
respected among all the nations. May God be pleased to spare our
Secretary of State to us!</p>
               <p pn="7">My friends, though the pressure of a great calamity rest
upon our hearts, and we know not what counsels may now prevail, let us
not be discouraged. As on all future issues of our coin there is to be
stamped the words, "In God we trust," so let us grave them upon our
hearts. Our destiny is still in the hands of the Ever Living, though
all trusted mortals fall and die. Though our victory is turned into
mourning, yet let us not forget that he who this day rose from the
dead, has pronounced all mourners blessed, and promises them
comfort. He lives forever, and His truth is alone the salvation of man
and of the Nation. Let us accept it, heed it, seek its influence, walk
in the path which it marks out.</p>
               <p pn="7">To be a Christian people, and a Christian Nation, is ever
possible to us; and now more than ever its importance presses on our
hearts.</p>
               <p pn="7">The Rebellion against our Country is in its dying gasps;
let us not fear that this terrible woe that is upon us can at all
revive it. The policy of him who has gone, will, let us trust, be so
far commended to the judgment of his successor, that the difficulties
of final adjustment will not be insurmountable, but that out of them
we shall come forth united, free, and forever secure!</p>
               <p pn="7">And for him who has gone; for the loved ones of his home
who are bowed in anguish; for all whose tears flow that his earthly
career is closed, how abundant the comforts beaming in the rays of the
Sun of this Resurrection Morn! Our beloved President still lives in
the sight and in the enjoyment of his God. Lost to our sight, he yet
dwells among the blest. Leaving his mangled and weary body, his spirit
soared aloft, greeted by all the heavenly host, with the glad
salutation, "Well done, good and faithful servant, enter into thy
eternal rest!"</p>
               <pb n="8"/>
<!-- blank page -->
<!--               <p>
                  <figure entity="eddy8">
                     <figDesc>8th page of
Richard Eddy's The Martyr to Liberty.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </p> -->
               <pb n="9"/>
               <p pn="9">
                  <figure entity="eddy9">
                     <figDesc>9th page of
Richard Eddy's The Martyr to Liberty.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 id="eddy.003" n="AND THEY BURIED HIM, AND ALL ISRAEL MOURNED FOR HIM.-1st. Kings, xiv., 18." type="sermon">
               <epigraph pn="9">
                  <p pn="9">AND THEY BURIED HIM, AND ALL ISRAEL MOURNED FOR
HIM.-1st. Kings, xiv., 18.</p>
               </epigraph>
               <p pn="9">Something less than fifty years ago, a young lad, strong,
muscular, and somewhat overgrown, spent his days, axe in hand, in
laborious work among the thick standing trees of what is now a densely
populated State; and industriously gave the leisure of his nights to
the acquisition of whatever knowledge might be gained from the few
books he was so fortunate as to borrow from the neighboring
settlers. Born in a State where honest toil was considered a
degradation, whose laborers were but chattels, purposely kept in
ignorance, his parents had sought under circumstances of poverty and
deprivation, a spot more congenial with efforts for manly
independence; and the son prizing his opportunities, but shrinking
from no duties, was their great helper in toil, while he also stored
his heart with noble principles, and his mind with every attainment
possible to one in his circumstances. How untoward were his
surroundings, we, who dwell here at ease in a metropolis surrounded by
conveniences and comforts which are the result of nearly two centuries
of Labor and intelligence, where the advantages of education are
unequaled, and where the richest fruits of civilization meet us on
every hand, can realize only in a very imperfect manner. But we know
that on many pages of our history there are glorious records of the
achievements of some of our best and mightiest, whose early home and
whose educational privileges were such as I have just intimated.</p>
               <p pn="9">In a few years, this lad, having reached the years of
manhood, qualifies himself by the study and use of rude materials for
a change in the sphere of his labor, and traverses the great river of
the West; then for a while becomes a trafficker in a small country
store; then for a few months experiences the adventures incident to
soldier-life; then, by the use of borrowed books, prepares himself for
the legal profession, and soon after enters upon a brilliant and
popular career as a pleader. Politics engage his attention, and as a
zealous partizan of Henry Clay, he seeks his promotion to the highest
position in the gift of a free people. - Soon he enters more active
life as a legislator; and ere long he stands in the hall of the
National Congress to give his voice and his vote against the
threatening flood of Slavery. As this
<pb n="10"/>
                  <figure entity="eddy10">
                     <figDesc>10th page of Richard
Eddy's The Martyr to Liberty.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
great evil becomes more insolent in its demands, and more open in the
manifestation of its brutal spirit, he steps forth into the arena of
popular debate, and taking as his antagonist the Giant of the West,
goes with him before the people, to the discussion of the great
questions of that hour.</p>
               <p pn="10">From this time he is the favorite of thousands, and yet,
the Country, as a whole, knows but little of him. A convention
assembles to put forth a candidate for the Presidency, and here, men
who knew his worth, and appreciated his strength, present his name,
and he is pronounced their choice. As the intelligence spreads among
the people. thousands confess that the name is that of a
stranger. Many express fear, doubt, distrust, and yet but few are
surprised, for the system so viciously prevalent in all parties, of
packed conventions, and the schemes of party hacks and managers, had
long before shown that, no one from among the men most widely known,
nor of greatest national reputation, would be likely to be selected as
Presidential candidate. He was accepted as the representative of a
principle, and by the exertions of a young and vigorous party, aided
in no small measure by the divisions among his political opponents, he
was elected President of the United States. And then, as the events of
most fearful significance gathered thick and in awful threatening over
the land, how eager was the curiosity, how intense the anxiety to know
more concerning the man to whom we had committed our destiny. During
the fearful months intervening between his election and his
inauguration; while treason was hatching its villainous plots in our
National Capitol; our navy being dispersed to the four quarters of the
globe; our arms, arsenals and forts put out of our hands; our treasury
emptied, and he who was then in authority either could not or would
not lift either hand or voice against it, how ardently we desired that
the President elect would take us into his confidence and tell us what
plan he was devising, what policy he proposed. His silence made us
impatient, and provoked complaint. That he had energy, his elevation
from such great obscurity gave full assurance; but how many doubted
whether the narrow sphere in which his life had been mostly passed had
given him opportunity for familiarity with the great principles and
policies of statesmanship requisite for the perils which were
gathering. That his honesty was so conspicuous as to have passed into
a proverb, was most gratifying, but who could feel assured that his
training was such as to guarantee his ability to grapple with the
sharpest difficulties that had ever beset the Nation. How eagerly, and
yet with what trembling,
<pb n="11"/>
                  <figure entity="eddy11">
                     <figDesc>11th page of Richard
Eddy's The Martyr to Liberty.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
we looked forward to the day when he should take the reins of
Government out of the weak hands in which they were then lying.</p>
               <p pn="11">The time came for him to journey towards Washington. His
beloved townsmen gathered at the railway station to bid him
Godspeed. Turning towards them, when he had stepped on the platform,
he said: "My friends, no one not in my position can appreciate the
sadness I feel at this parting. To this people I owe all that I
am. Here I have lived for more than a quarter of a century. Here my
children were born, and here one of them lies buried. I know not how
soon I shall see you again. A duty devolves upon me which is perhaps
greater than that which has devolved upon any other man since the days
of Washington. He never would have succeeded except for the aid of
Divine Providence, upon which he at all times relied. I feel that I
cannot succeed without the same Divine aid which sustained him, and in
the same Almighty Being I place my reliance for support; and I hope
you, my friends, will all pray that I may receive that Divine
assistance without which I cannot succeed, but with which success is
certain. Again, I bid you all an affectionate farewell!"</p>
               <p pn="11">These solemn and loving words were conveyed on the
lightning wings to every town and hamlet. The people felt that a good
man was indeed their leader; and in enthusiastic crowds they thronged
his way, content even with a word, and invoking the blessing of God
upon him. Everywhere, as opportunity offered, he was greeted with
speeches of welcome, each orator exhausting his ingenuity to impress
upon him the intense desire of the people to learn his policy. He saw,
but could not gratify; nor did he evade. Plainly and repeatedly he
said: "I deem that it is just to the Country, to myself, to you. that
I should see everything, hear everything, and have every light that
can possibly be brought within my reach to aid me before I shall speak
officially, in order that when I do speak, I may have the best
possible means of taking correct and true grounds. For this reason I
do not now announce anything, in the way of policy for the new
Administration. When the time comes, according to the custom of the
Government, I shall speak, and speak as well as I am able, for the
good of the present and of the future of this Country--for the good of
the North and of the South--for the good of one and of the other, and
of all sections of it."</p>
               <p pn="11">Arrived in this city, the intense desire of the people was
again communicated to him; and standing in Independence Hall, he spoke
the deep feelings of his heart. It is not unfitting, I trust,
certainly not
<pb n="12"/>
                  <figure entity="eddy12">
                     <figDesc>12th page of Richard
Eddy's The Martyr to Liberty.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
to us to whom that dear Shrine of Liberty is so easy of access, and
especially in view of the melancholy fact that all that is mortal of
him will soon be borne there, that I now repeat his words:
"Mr. Cuyler," said he, "I am filled with deep emotion in finding
myself standing here, in this place, where were collected the wisdom,
the patriotism, the devotion to principle, from which sprang the
institutions under which we live. You have kindly suggested to me that
in my hands is the task of restoring peace to the present distracted
condition of the Country. I can say, in return, sir, that all the
political sentiments I entertain, have been drawn, so far as I have
been able to draw them, from the sentiments which originated in and
were given to the world from this Hall. I have never had a feeling,
politically, that did not spring from the sentiments embodied in the
Declaration of Independence. I have often pondered over the dangers
which were incurred by the men who assembled here, and framed and
adopted that Declaration of Independence. I have pondered over the
toils that were endured by the officers and soldiers of the army who
achieved that independence. I have often inquired of myself what great
principle or idea it was that kept this Confederacy so long
together. It was not the mere matter of the separation of the colonies
from the mother-land, but that sentiment in the Declaration of
Independence which gave liberty, not alone to the people of this
Country, but, I hope, to the world for all future time. It was that
which gave promise that in due time the weight would be lifted from
the shoulders of all men. This is a sentiment embodied in the
Declaration of Independence. Now, my friends, can this country be
saved upon this basis? If it can, I will consider myself one of the
happiest men in the world if I can help to save it. If it cannot be
saved upon that principle, it will be truly awful. But if this Country
cannot be saved without giving up that principle, I was about to
say. I would rather be assassinated on the spot than surrender
it. Now, in my view of the present aspect of affairs, there need be no
bloodshed or war. There is no necessity for it. I am not in favor of
such a cause. I may say, in advance, that there will be no bloodshed
unless it be forced upon the Government, and then it will be compelled
to act in self-defence. My friends, this is wholly an unexpected
speech, and I did not expect to be called upon to say a word when I
came here. I supposed it was merely to do something towards raising
the flag. I may, therefore, have said something indiscreet. I have
said nothing but what I am willing to live by, and, if it be the
pleasure of Almighty God, to die by."</p>
               <pb n="13"/>
               <p pn="13">
                  <figure entity="eddy13">
                     <figDesc>13th page of
Richard Eddy's The Martyr to Liberty.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <p pn="13">Inaugurated as Chief Magistrate of the Nation, the
President spoke in his address the words which wakened hope and
confidence. Kind and conciliatory to the erring, and assuring them
that the door was wide open for their return; that whatever grievances
there were might easily be adjusted under the Constitution, and that
the laws under that Constitution-mainly, "on the sensitive point, the
laws of their own framing"-would be faithfully executed by him, he yet
firmly and in unmistakable tones declared that the Union was
perpetual, and that the Constitution and the laws should be enforced
at every cost. How kindly and yet how faithfully he concluded: "In
your hands, my dissatisfied fellow-countrymen, and not in mine, is the
momentous issue of civil war. The Government will not assail you. You
can have no conflict without being yourselves the aggressors. You have
no oath registered in Heaven to destroy the Government, while I shall
have the most solemn one to preserve, protect, and defend it. I am
loth to close. We are not enemies, but friends. We must not be
enemies. Though passion may have strained, it must not break our bonds
of affection. The mystic chords of memory, stretching from every
battlefield and patriot grave to every living heart and hearth-stone,
all over this broad land, will yet swell the chorus of the Union, when
again touched, as surely they will be, by the better angels of our
nature."</p>
               <p pn="13">But the pleading voice availed not. Unprincipled men had
determined that the Union should be destroyed, and they boldly went to
their murderous work. Since then they have furrowed the land with war,
shed the best blood of the Nation, carried desolation to every part of
our once happy possessions, doing their awful work with infernal
cruelty, ruining themselves, and often well nigh destroying the
nationality of our Country. Meantime we grew to know, and knowing, to
trust and love our ruler. Patient, cheerful, ever trusting in God,
making no vain boasts, careful not to commit himself to any policy
till he had seen all that could affect it on either side, and weighed
its worth in the just balances of an impartial judgment, and having
once adopted, never deviating from it, he, while seeming to follow the
popular will, ever led it, and the wisdom of his leading grew more and
more apparent as the time of the expiration of his term of office drew
near. His record was before the world, and millions of his countrymen
endorsed it in the most emphatic manner possible, replacing him, with
an enthusiasm unparalleled in our history, in the Presidential
chair. In the brief time that has elapsed since then, what glorious
results have been achieved. The stronghold of the Rebellion captured,
the grand
<pb n="14"/>
                  <figure entity="eddy14">
                     <figDesc>14th page of Richard
Eddy's The Martyr to Liberty.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
army of the insurgents dissolved, and so glorious the prospect of
speedy peace, that the word goes forth that no more are to be called
from their homes to the field of battle.</p>
               <p pn="14">And he who had waited so long and so patiently for this
day, upon whose mind and heart a great burden had lain these four long
and anxious years; he, who, as Commander-in-Chief of the forces that
had beaten down the Rebellion, possessed power never known before in
this land; how did he bear himself in this great prosperity? As
reverently as when leaving his Western home, he besought others to
assist him in seeking the Divine Blessing; as unselfishly as when
forgetful of self he declared in our midst his willingness to die, if
needs be, in defence of the great principle which underlies our
Declaration of Independence; as honestly and as convincingly in his
few brief words on reconstruction, as he had set forth at the first
his determination to "preserve, protect and defend " the Constitution
and the Laws; as kindly and as magnanimously as at the first he had
assured the dissatisfied, that the way was open for their return.</p>
               <p pn="14">How universal was the feeling that he was the one wise man
of the land to conciliate, restore and make anew. If we had
misgivings, it was not concerning his intellectual nor his executive
ability, but that his heart was too warm, too generous, his offers too
magnanimous to those who had sinned so deeply against our common
humanity. But even this, as we turned to God for guidance, and looked
towards the one and only infallible example, Jesus Christ, our
Saviour, commended itself to us as manifesting, not the President's
weakness, but in reality his strength, and that which alone can make
us all strong, the unmistakable assurance that he lived near to God,
and was a true disciple of him who prayed for the forgiveness of his
enemies. As this feeling was sinking into our hearts, and we were
giving attention to the voice of love and mercy, which pleads so
tenderly in the Gospel of Jesus Christ, and were feeling our hate
dissolve and our vindictiveness vanish away, and were hastening our
preparations for a rejoicing which should eclipse all former displays
of our delight, what awful tidings froze our hearts with horror, and
from the highest joy, cast us into the deepest gloom! The President,
whom all had so much cause to love, and most of all towards whom his
enemies should have turned with emotions of the deepest gratitude; who
should have been safe from violence anywhere and at all times, was
murderously assaulted at the least expected time and place, and the
assassin who crushed the brain that was only engaged in forming plans
of peace and good-will,
<pb n="15"/>
                  <figure entity="eddy15">
                     <figDesc>15th page of Richard
Eddy's The Martyr to Liberty.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
and stopped the beating of a heart that overflowed with human
kindness, betrayed an ignorance, and a depravity, how deplorable, by
applying to this, the gentlest and the best of men, the hateful name
of tyrant. Alas! Alas! How far removed from this was Abraham Lincoln!
Time it is, indeed, that we cannot now so estimate his characteristics
as to do justice to him by any analysis that we can offer; but surely
the bowing down of this Nation in a grief such as no private sorrow
brings to any circle, however narrow; the manifestation of universal
mourning, not alone, nor in any conceivable measure, by the weeds
which float in every breeze, and tinge all our homes and churches with
gloom, but by that deeper sympathy which rests with such oppressive
sadness on every heart, and forces the tears from every eye, testifies
that the name first given in derision is now the one which best and
alone fully expresses his relationship to us,-he was our worthy
father; and if ever the voice of the people echoes the Divine mandate,
the universal offering of our hearts and lips this day, is the voice
of God.</p>
               <p pn="15">We do not need, though we deeply feel how touchingly
appropriate it is, the great poet's command:</p>
               <lg type="stanza">
                  <l>"Bear hence his
body,</l>
                  <l>And mourn you for him. Let him be
regarded</l>
                  <l>As the noblest corpse that ever
herald!</l>
                  <l>Did follow to his urn."</l>
               </lg>
               <p pn="15">For with a spontaneousness the American people never
disclosed before, we bow our heads in sorrow in this hour of his
funeral. Death has, we know, been in our high places before, and in
sadness we now recall the memory of our honored dead; but we do not
disparage them, nor do we unduly magnify the greatness of this
affliction, when we place it first and most prominent among the
sorrows of our land. We shall never perhaps allow that any other than
Washington can be "first ever in our hearts," nor can we believe that
any light grief rolls over the hearts of our fathers when they
received the tidings of his decease. But for such an event they were
measurably prepared. He had passed on to that time of life when age
breaks down the strength, and gives assurance that death is not far
distant. Long in honored service, he has retired from its burdens and
cares, and in the quiet of private life was waiting, "the summons to
the tomb." It was sad to lose him, yet how natural, and so how
resignedly borne, that he should go. Webster and Clay, in our own
time, received national honors at their burial; but their departure
had also been expected, and though they were
<pb n="16"/>
                  <figure entity="eddy16">
                     <figDesc>16th page of Richard
Eddy's The Martyr to Liberty.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
respected and beloved by many, it cannot in truth be said that the
mourning for them was general.</p>
               <p pn="16">Death has also been once and again at the
Capitol. :Harrison and Taylor died while in the high office of
President. They were worthy men, and the nation bowed down heavily at
their death; but no great national trouble had bound either of them
with peculiar interest to the common heart. Diseases also gave warning
of their dissolution, and for the tidings of their departure we were
not unprepared.</p>
               <p pn="16">But the death which has now brought thousands to the White
House, and is filling all the churches with sincere and deeply
afflicted mourners, has its special significance, not alone in its
suddenness and the appalling circumstances of crime connected with it,
but chiefly in the fact, that he who has fallen. had by the peculiarly
trying circumstances of the times, been more constantly before the
people than any of his predecessors, (Washington alone excepted) had
been; that his measures had more directly and more immediately
interested them; that under his judicious lead great changes had been
wrought in opinion on the great questions of American politics; great
changes in the organic law of many of the states, as well as in the
National Constitution; and that he had shown himself worthy of trust
as the friend, not of classes and of parties, but of the great
American People; and that he was successfully and speedily leading the
Nation out of its great troubles, forever redeemed from the one great
antagonism of liberty, which had been the fruitful source of all our
political woes. The people knew him as they had never known
another. They felt the beatings of his manly heart, and their owe
pulses moved in unison with his. His voice was familiar to them; his
words ever accepted as the words of honest truth; his call to duty and
to danger was gladly obeyed; his cheerful trust had captivated and
toned their spirits, and a never-betrayed cause or confidence had led
to implicit trust in all his words and acts.</p>
               <lg type="stanza">
                  <l>"Among innumerable false, unmoved,</l>
                  <l>Unshaken, unseduced, unterrified,</l>
                  <l> His loyalty he kept, his love, his
zeal;</l>
                  <l>Nor number, nor example with him
wrought</l>
                  <l>To swerve from truth or change his constant
mind,</l>
                  <l>Though single."</l>
               </lg>
               <lg type="stanza">
                  <l>"The
elements</l>
                  <l>So <hi rend="italic">mixed</hi> in him, that
nature might stand up</l>
                  <l>And say to all the world-this is a
MAN."</l>
               </lg>
               <p pn="16">The President was loved and honored, and he is now so
deeply mourned, because the trying years of his public service had
revealed
<pb n="17"/>
                  <figure entity="eddy17">
                     <figDesc>17th page of Richard
Eddy's The Martyr to Liberty.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
those qualities which ever command universal love and respect. His
strength lay in his being honest, true, right-minded, great-hearted. To
these qualities human nature always pays its homage, and the universal
conscience stamps them as the elements of human perfection. Frank,
direct, humane, yet firm of purpose, he brought to the consideration
of the greatest questions of difficulty ever presented to any ruler, a
clear and unbiased judgment, a decision which slowly but fairly made,
he never deviated from, and in which it is no exaggeration to say, the
Country, with greater unanimity than it ever evinced on any other
national topics, gladly and gratefully coincides, and the world will
forever honor and admire. He never deceived, nor did he attempt
deception; silent, when he could not speak with directness, yet never
evading the demands for thought and for utterance, his words were
always direct and eminently comprehensive. Whatever the occasion of
public display, though Statesmen of unrivaled power, and mighty
victors from the field of strife, and orators of matchless eloquence
thronged around him,</p>
               <lg type="stanza">
                  <l>"He above the rest,</l>
                  <l>In shape and gesture proudly eminent,</l>
                  <l>Stood like a tower."</l>
               </lg>
               <p pn="17">Some of the grandest flights of oratory the world has ever
witnessed, have been manifest on the great occasions which called men
together during our great war, and noblest sentiments have</p>
               <lg type="stanza">
                  <l>"Flowed from lips wet with Castilian
dew;"</l>
               </lg>
               <p pn="17">but none of them have so taken the popular heart as the homely
phrases of Abraham Lincoln, and not one of these would the common
people now exchange for the most classic oration that has been
made. Ever appealing to the judgment of mankind, the responsive
approval has always followed, though sometimes tardily. But he could
afford to wait even for the slowest assent, for he had studied, not
the tricks of scheming policy, not the deceptive forms of
high-sounding words, but conscience, duty, and the eternal right. And
this characterized his great public documents as well as his brief
speeches to the crowds. That great Proclamation of January 1st, 1863,
in which he "avers and declares that all persons held as slaves within
designated States and parts of States, are, and henceforward shall be
free," he concludes in this solemn manner: "Upon this act I invoke the
considerate judgment of mankind, and the gracious favor of Almighty
God." Clearly the favor of God has been manifest and no more approving
page will be
<pb n="18"/>
                  <figure entity="eddy18">
                     <figDesc>18th page of Richard
Eddy's The Martyr to Liberty.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
written in the history of the world than that which records this just
and solemn act. For this, if he had never done more, the name of
Abraham Lincoln would shine with glorious immortality! Yet once again
he spake, for men were wavering and despondent; timid fear inspired a
momentary hope in some that the edict might be revoked; others, noting
the vacillation of politicians, their seeming willingness to sacrifice
everything for the immediate present, were doubting if even the honest
ruler would stand fast; but biding his own time he spoke out at last
in his message to Congress, "the promise having been made, it must be
kept." For this, and for his steadfast integrity to it, what was said
long ago of Wilberforce, now applies with intenser emphasis to
President Lincoln: "He ascended to the throne of God with a million of
broken shackles in his hands as the evidence of a life well spent ! "
And now, from henceforth, forever, while his memory will be embalmed
in all hearts, one race of men rising from the degradation, ignorance
and crimes of their former servile condition, shall feel their manhood
enobled, and their position glorious, as they remember this one
President-their life-long friend-the martyr to their liberty. And as
the Moslem to Mecca; as the Hebrew to Mt. Sion; as the Christian to
Gethsemane, so shall the black man turn to the grave of Abraham
Lincoln, and say with deep emotion, "There lie the ashes of our Moses,
of our good Father Abraham, our Emancipator!" and shall tell to their
children, as the badges which they this day wear tell to all
observers, "Abraham Lincoln, the black man's friend, was murdered by
the black man's enemy."</p>
               <p pn="18">Nor they alone shall shrine him in their hearts. Once we
were content to have him named "the man of our party;" once we
rejoiced that he was hailed as "the man of the Nation," but now he is
the man universally beloved. Death has cut the tie which bound him to
a political sect, or to a single nation, and in its place has forged
an adamantine chain that links his memory with our common humanity.</p>
               <lg type="stanza">
                  <l>"His name</l>
                  <l>Is Freedom's
now, and Fame's,--</l>
                  <l>One of the few, the immortal names</l>
                  <l>That wore not born to die."</l>
               </lg>
               <p pn="18">His memory is safe. No human events now can affect it,
other than to add to its already unrivaled lustre. The great
qualities, the private virtues, the noble and magnanimous bearing, the
loving heart,--all that is precious, has received the seal of
death.</p>
               <pb n="19"/>
               <p pn="19">
                  <figure entity="eddy19">
                     <figDesc>19th page of
Richard Eddy's The Martyr to Liberty.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <lg type="stanza">
                  <l>"The love where death has set his seal,</l>
                  <l>Nor age can
chill, nor rival steal,</l>
                  <l>Nor falsehood disavow."</l>
               </lg>
               <p pn="19">We may picture him, and we shall for the admiration of the
world, as that</p>
               <lg type="stanza">
                  <l>"Divinely gifted man,</l>
                  <l>Whose life in low estate
began;</l>
                  <l>Who grasped the skirts of happy chance,</l>
                  <l>Breasted
the blows of circumstance,</l>
                  <l>And made by force his merit
known;</l>
                  <l>And lived to clutch the golden keys,</l>
                  <l>To mould a
mighty State's decrees,</l>
                  <l>And shape the whisper of the
throne;</l>
                  <l>And moving up from high to higher,</l>
                  <l>Became, on
fortune's crowning slope,</l>
                  <l>The pillar of a people's hope,</l>
                  <l>The centre of a world's desire!"</l>
               </lg>
               <p pn="19">Good man, dear, warm-hearted lover of the race, farewell!
For thee the paean yields to the dirge, and the heart-horrors of the
Nation prepare the solemn funeral pageant. For thee the requiem is
sung with deepest pathos, its plaintive music rolling up from a
thousand vocal temples from countless throbbing hearts. Beneath it all
thy unconcious dust sleeps well, hallowing and hallowed, while thy
free spirit-the spirit of a "just man made perfect"-dwells forever
with the Lord! To Him we turn for comfort, and trusting in His mercy,
believing in His gracious Providence, we joy that He gives us strength
to say:</p>
               <lg type="stanza">
                  <l>"In the blank silence of the narrow tomb,</l>
                  <l>The clay may rest which wrapped thy
human birth,</l>
                  <l>But all unconquered by that silent doom,</l>
                  <l>The spirit of thy thought shall
walk the earth</l>
                  <l>In glory and in light!"</l>
               </lg>
               <pb n="20"/>
<!-- blank page -->
<!--               <p>
                  <figure entity="eddy4">
                     <figDesc>20th page of
Richard Eddy's The Martyr to Liberty.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </p> -->
               <pb n="21"/>
               <p pn="21">
                  <figure entity="eddy21">
                     <figDesc>21st page of
Richard Eddy's The Martyr to Liberty.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 id="eddy.004" n="THE RIGHTEOUS SHALL BE IN EVERLASTING REMEMBRANCE.-Psalm cxii., 6." type="sermon">
               <epigraph pn="21">
                  <p pn="21">THE RIGHTEOUS SHALL BE IN EVERLASTING REMEMBRANCE.-Psalm
cxii., 6.</p>
               </epigraph>
               <p pn="21">It is too soon for any man to attempt a comprehensive
analysis of the life of him, to whose memory this day is set apart;
and it is already too late to revive that intense sorrow which bowed
us all to the dust during the days which elapsed between his death and
his burial.</p>
               <p pn="21">In the one case, we must wait for the revelation of the
secrets faithfully deposited with those who stood near him, bearing
the heat and the burden of our long and weary day of war; and in the
other, we already see the hand of God so clearly manifest in bringing
good out of evil, that though we lose none of our horror for the
assassination, we are comforted by the assurance that even the wrath
of man praises God, and, banding the people together in more
determined purpose for righteousness, is overruled for the greater
attainment and security of the best things possible to the Nation and
to the world.</p>
               <p pn="21">What, then, can we do this day, except to repeat the lesson
of the text, and to seek a clear understanding and a faithful use of
some of the duties and obligations which it imposes. The dead do not
pass into oblivion. Each family has its memory of those whose goodness
of heart, and integrity of purpose, endeared them to the narrow circle
in which alone they moved; each community of men treasures with
heartfelt reverence those who' by true living, have been its
benefactors and its guides; and every Nation, pointing back to its
heroic ages, testifies that it has engraver in enduring characters,
the names of those whose purity of purpose and sacrifice of all
private aims entitled them to an exalted place among the benefactors
of the race. And when families are broken up, communities dispersed,
and Nations passed into oblivion, He with whom alone there is no
change makes the memory of the eminently righteous the heritage of the
world, to be a beacon and a teacher to all the ages. And when, one
after another, the memories of the humbler ones of earth fade away in
this changing and mortal state, they endure in heaven more lasting
than the stars, and have their record kept by Him who only hath
immortality. " Our days are gone like a shadow, and we are withered
like grass; but Thou, O Lord, shalt endure forever, and Thy
remembrance throughout all generations."</p>
               <pb n="22"/>
               <p pn="22">
                  <figure entity="eddy22">
                     <figDesc>22nd page of
Richard Eddy's The Martyr to Liberty.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <p pn="22">From this consideration, we are led to feel not alone that
we cannot overrate the power and the worth of moral influence, but,
also, that it is the highest wisdom in us to imitate that which we so
much admire, and which has the promise of endurance. It is this lesson
which seems to me most pertinent to this hour, and obedience to which
will help us to honor most worthily our departed President. It is, I
am sure, the lesson which he desires us to accept and to
heed. Standing over the remains of the thousands who had fallen on the
soil of this State, President Lincoln thus spoke at Gettysburg:</p>
               <p pn="22">"We are met on a great battle-field of this war. We have
come to dedicate a portion of this field as a final resting place for
those who here gave their lives that the Nation might live. It is
altogether fitting and proper that we should do this. But in a larger
sense we cannot dedicate, we cannot hallow this ground. The brave men,
living and dead, who struggled here, have consecrated it far above our
power to add or detract. The world will little note, nor long remember
what we say here, but it can never forget what they did here. It is
for us, the living, rather to be dedicated here to the unfinished work
which they who fought here have thus far so nobly advanced. It is
rather for us to be here dedicated to the great task remaining before
us, that from these honored dead we take increased devotion to that
cause for which they gave the last full measure of devotion; that we
here highly resolve that these dead shall not have died in vain; that
this Nation, under God, shall have a new birth of freedom, and that
government of the people, by the people, and for the people, shall not
perish from the earth."</p>
               <p pn="22">There is energy in these words; there is majesty in the
thought they express; and in some of the sentences there is most
exquisite felicity of expression. Is there not now most singular
appropriateness to himself, and to us who mourn for him? Standing, as
he did, like the Prophet of old, between the living and the dead, he
held up the banner of right and honesty, charmed by the utterances of
truth, captivated by the nobleness of true good-will to man, not for
our admiration alone, but also for our imitation. To accept and heed
this will be the noblest tribute we can offer to his memory. It will
manifest our highest appreciation of his life, and our most hearty
assent to the principles for which we most admire him. It will be most
in agreement with his last official utterances in that Inaugural
Address, concerning which the British press has said: "It contains a
grasp of principle, a dignity of manner, and a solemnity of purpose,
which
<pb n="23"/>
                  <figure entity="eddy23">
                     <figDesc>23rd page of Richard
Eddy's The Martyr to Liberty.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
would have been unworthy of neither Hampden nor of Cromwell, while his
gentleness and generosity of feeling towards his foes was almost
greater than we should expect from either of them."</p>
               <p pn="23">How solemnly grand do the closing words of that Inaugural
appear, now that he has passed away:</p>
               <p pn="23">"Fondly do we hope, fervently do we pray, that this mighty
scourge of war may soon pass away. Yet, if God wills that it continue
until all the wealth piled by the bondman's two hundred years of
unrequited toil shall be sunk, and until every drop of blood drawn
with the lash shall be paid with another drawn with the sword, as was
said three thousand years ago, so still it must be said, 'the
judgments of the Lord are true and righteous altogether."</p>
               <p pn="23">"With malice toward none; with charity for all; with
firmness in the right, as God gives us to see the right, let us strive
on to finish the work we are in; to bind up the Nation's wounds; to
care for him who shall have borne the battle, and for his widow and
his orphans; to do all which may achieve and cherish a just and
lasting peace among ourselves and with all nations."</p>
               <p pn="23">As he who uttered these words was righteous, because he was
true to the right which God gave him to see, let us as earnestly
desire to know and do our duty.</p>
               <p pn="23">There are three things, which it seems to me eminently
fitting, just and right, that we who love and honor the illustrious
dead, and who love the cause and the country for which he gave his
life, should demand and secure:</p>
               <p pn="23">1. That justice shall have its course with those who
instigated and led in this Rebellion. I speak: not of revenge,
certainly not of wild and furious retaliation, urging to mob force and
to indiscriminate horrors which attend on personal hate. I clamor not
for blood, nor would I countenance a resting in torture. I would have
no unlawful exactions, no mere vengence; but the justice which comes
from judicial trial, the execution of the penalty which the law has
provided for treason. This, justice, which in a perfect government is
but another name for mercy, demands; demands not for my gratification,
nor for yours, but for the public safety and for the good of the
race. It can, indeed, do nothing for the past; bring back none of our
slaughtered thousands; relieve nothing from the burden of taxation;
make no restitution for the loss which pinches every one, but it can
give us assurance for the future, check the mad and evil ambition
which turns liberty into license, and save us from the repetition of
the
<pb n="24"/>
                  <figure entity="eddy24">
                     <figDesc>24th page of Richard
Eddy's The Martyr to Liberty.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
fearful agonies through which we have now passed. For this, worth all
that we can imagine, and beyond all price, let the guilty be tried,
and according as the law pronounces on their deserts, let them be
punished. And let us by our speech and through the influence of the
public opinion which we may create, educate our people to just thought
of the characters and deeds of those who have brought such ruin and
distress upon us. Let us have done with the folly of praising Southern
Statesmanship, and especially put from us the foolish thought, that as
a people we shall yet be proud of the talents and skill, the daring
and sacrifice, or even of the military genius and skill of the
managers of the Rebellion.</p>
               <p pn="24">I regard him as a corrupter of our public morals, an enemy
to our good, an unsafe and ruinous teacher of our young, who couples
the names of Davis, Stephens, Stonewall Jackson and Robert E. Lee, or
any of their associates, with anything that can appeal to American
pride and honor. Let <hi rend="italic">them</hi> have place with Haman
of old, with Benedict Arnold of modern times, whose example offers
nothing but warning, whose names are synonyms for all ignominy and
baseness. Let their name, as "the name of the wicked, <hi rend="italic">rot</hi>." Justice to the memory of those noble ones,
whose earthly existence was put out by their sins against the Nation
and the race, demands that they go into the catalogue of the enemies
of man.</p>
               <p pn="24">2. Justice also demands of us the utter extinction of that
great evil from which our troubles sprung. Rebellion, which killed its
thousands upon the battle field, and starved and murdered its
thousands in prisons; which was nourished by perjury, and culminated
its horrors in assassination, ever manifesting</p>
               <lg type="stanza">
                  <l>"Unconquerable will,</l>
                  <l>And study of revenge, immortal hate,</l>
                  <l>And courage never to
submit nor yield,"</l>
               </lg>
               <p pn="24">had its birth in slavery-the vilest and the blackest slavery ever
known on God's earth; "founded," so said Abraham Lincoln, twenty-eight
years ago, "on both injustice and bad policy." None so blind now that
they cannot see that this curse created the Rebellion; none should
fail to note the warning,, voice of Mr. Lincoln, as he said to the
convention which put him in nomination for the United States Senate:
"This government cannot endure permanently half slave and half
free. It will become all the one thing, or all the other."</p>
               <p pn="24">And now, if justice demands the crushing out of the
Rebellion, the punishment of its leaders, and the entire submission to
the law, of all
<pb n="25"/>
                  <figure entity="eddy25">
                     <figDesc>25th page of Richard
Eddy's The Martyr to Liberty.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
who have in any way aided and abetted it, with what equal force does
it also demand that the accursed root from which this deadly tree
grew, shall be plucked up and utterly destroyed. Let it alone and you
cannot prevent its growth. As in time passed it will control trade,
commerce, offices, presses, pulpits, politics, and rule them all in
the interests of unrighteousness, and whatever we may now do to the
wicked wretches which it has created, it cannot fail, soon or late, to
give birth to n kindred brood whose career will be run on a plane of
equally atrocious depravity. Let the accursed thing die! No
compromise, no covenant, no concession or conciliation should save
it. President Johnson, all honor to him! treats it in his Proclamation
as a thing utterly annihilated in the States which have been in
rebellion. Let us so second his efforts, that it may soon be dead
everywhere. We are not guiltless in regard to its existence or its
spread, and on us rests many of the consequences of its growth, to us
much responsibility must attach for the fruits which it has borne. We
have need to repent of our sins in regard to it; and while our
condemnation of others must in a great measure react and fall back on
ourselves, our way out of the trouble lies only in our doing the works
of righteousness, confessing our folly and sin, and bringing forth "
the fruits of repentance."</p>
               <p pn="25">3. And this leads me to a brief mention, in conclusion, of
the third great demand of justice upon us, which is, that we bring the
State and the Nation to a recognition and maintenance of the equality
of all men before the law. Slavery has not only ruled us in making us
unjust towards those who were held in bondage, but it has filled us
with vile and bitter prejudices against all whom it pleased God to
create with a different complexion from ourselves. It has us taught to
regard them as so far our inferiors, that on account of their color we
have shut them out from the right of suffrage, driven them from our
institutions of learning, expelled them from our public
conveyances. In all this we have been and we continue to be the
perpetrators of outrage and wrong. We have been governed not by
reason, but by blind and stupid prejudice. We have forgotten all the
dictates of Christianity, all the lessons of history, and given the
most emphatic lie to our national boast of universal suffrage, and
that "governments derive their just power from the consent of the
governed."</p>
               <p pn="25">Now in rebuking this, I am not asking for sympathy for the
negroes, nor intimating what charity and good will ought to lead us to
do in their behalf; but I make an appeal to your moral sense, to what
<pb n="26"/>
                  <figure entity="eddy26">
                     <figDesc>26th page of Richard
Eddy's The Martyr to Liberty.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
righteousness demands, and to what we must do in order to be just. Let
us look back and see what we sprung from, and what a despicable thing
our prejudice against race is. Six hundred years ago our fathers, the
blue-eyed and fair-haired Anglo-Saxons, who were trampled into the
dust by their Norman conquerors, were regarded as of coarser clay, and
far inferior to the haughty ones who trampled them down; our ancestor,
yours and mine, was regarded as so low and so mean, that he might be
found in the highways of England laboring with a brass collar on his
neck, and the name of his master marked upon it. That is where we came
from; and it ought to smite us to the dust, that the prejudice which
the Norman then had against the Saxon, we the children of slaves have
dared to transfer to others.</p>
               <p pn="26">Our assertion of the inferiority of the races is all a lie,
falsified by all history, condemned by all the inspired testimony of
God. And the very moment we attempt to say that the negro, trampled
upon for ages, accursed, despised by the proud, made the slave of the
cruel, and the victim of prejudice without reason, is naturally
inferior to the men of all other nations who have their homes and
their voice here, we place ourselves in a position where fact cannot
be our basis, but where prejudice alone can serve for our unwarranted
assertion. As another has well asked, "Will you exchange the negro for
the Esquimaux--for the Pacific Islander--for the South American
tribes?" An unqualified negative will be our answer to this, and in
our answer behold the reproach of our foolish prejudice.</p>
               <p pn="26">Now our wickedness lies in this, that boasting of universal
suffrage and of universal right, we suffer mere prejudice to give the
lie to our pretensions. The question of universal suffrage I do not
debate here, neither its use nor its dangers. I merely state our
national boast as it is made, our political practice which gives to
the stupid German and the ignorant Irishman the right to a voice in
determining our affairs, on condition of a short term of residence,
and denies that right to those born on the soil, but whom it pleased
God to give a different color from what he gave ourselves. In all this
we are doing unrighteously. If we make other conditions of suffrage,
very well; but no future conditions can excuse our present
inconsistencies. and yet, how the events of this war caution us to
care in placing the right to a voice in the Government on any grounds
other than that broad one-the rights of man as a man. No mere property
qualification is safe, for how wealthy were the rebel leaders; and for
the same reason no high standard of intellectual attainment can be set
up, for as a class they had all the
<pb n="27"/>
                  <figure entity="eddy27">
                     <figDesc>27th page of Richard
Eddy's The Martyr to Liberty.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
culture of the schools, while in manhood, devotion to right, loyalty,
integrity, the poorest and the humblest poor have stood above them
all; and the accumulated power of those simple-minded, true-hearted,
inflexibly loyal negroes, who have bared their breasts to the Southern
fire and steel, have been mightier and worth more than the heaviest
brain that plotted treason against the land.</p>
               <p pn="27">No tribute to liberty, no homage to the Stars and Stripes
has been more impressive and magnanimous than that offered by the
despised ones who owed the Nation nothing; but who freely gave their
all, that the traitors who owed the Nation everything might not
succeed in its overthrow. To these men and to their children we must
be just. They must all stand equal in the law. In intelligence,
industry, and all outward attainment, they already compare favorably
and are more than equal to the mass of our foreign voters. In loyalty
they are unsurpassed by none who tread our soil. Righteousness
requires that for them we establish justice and secure liberty. Let us
meet the demand.</p>
               <p pn="27">In hints, rather than by labored argument, still less of
exhaustive presentation, I have given you, my brethren, these
thoughts. I trust they have not been inappropriate in the memorial
service of Him who has taught us that it is by following the right,
and thus completing the work which others have begun, rather than by
words of eulogy and praise, that we shall honor the memory of those
who have died for us. He was faithful to his duty, obedient "to the
right as God gave him to see the right," and the work which he left
unfinished, we, if we love the memory of the righteous, will carry
forward to successful completion. Let, I beseech you, his memory prove
an incentive to the love of truth, to consecration of heart and life
to righteousness, and to harmony of effect with the demands of eternal
justice; then shall we see what he so much desired, the Nation firmly
and permanently established by Mercy and Truth meeting together, and
Righteousness and Peace embracing each other.</p>
            </div2>
         </div1>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI.2>