<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader><fileDesc>
         <titleStmt n="Character and Death of Abraham Lincoln">
            <title>  Character and
Death of Abraham Lincoln </title>
            <author>Fowler, Henry</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Compiled and edited by</resp>
               <name>Beck
Center</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent/>
         <publicationStmt><publisher>Lewis H. Beck Center</publisher><pubPlace>Emory University</pubPlace><address>
               <addrLine>Atlanta,
Georgia</addrLine>
            </address><availability>
               <p>1996 Emory
University. Permission is granted to download, transmit, or otherwise
reproduce, distribute or display the contributions to the work claimed
by Emory University for non-profit educational purposes, provided
this header is included in its entirety.  For inquiries about
commercial uses, contact the Director, 
Pitts Theology Library, Emory
University, Atlanta, Georgia 30322</p>
            </availability><date>1999</date></publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Lincoln
Sermons Project</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl> Fowler,
Henry.  Character and Death of Abraham Lincoln.  A Discourse Preached
at Auburn, N. Y., April 23, 1865.  Auburn, N. Y.: Wm. J. Moses' Steam
Press Establishment, No. 16 Clark Street.  New-York; Shelden &amp; Co.
1865.</bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc><encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This text derives from the Special Collections 
of Pitts Theology Library, Emory University, and is produced in 
collaboration with the Lewis H. Beck Center a, the Emory 
Preservation Office, and Pitts Theology Library.</p>
            <p>TRANSCRIBER: Lewis H. Beck Center and Emory University Preservation Office.</p>
            <p>PRODUCER:  BookLab, Inc., 1606 Headway Circle, Suite 100, Austin, TX 78754</p>
            <p>CAPTURE DEVICE: XEROX DocuImage 620S flatbed scanner</p>
            <p>CAPTURE DETAILS: Scanner software: XEROX ScanTool version 4.2.3; no gamma correction; images are all bitonal.</p>
            <p>CHANGE HISTORY: Using the Adobe Photoshop Batch Processor, we interpolated  the original TIFF files to 8-bit grays, and altered the resolution to 144 dpi, producing screen images twice the original size.  We then saved them in JPEG format.  We produced GIF thumbnails from the JPEG files.</p>
            <p>RESOLUTION: 600 ppi</p>
            <p>COMPRESSION: Resolution 144 per inch with Constrain Properties to 72 per inch.</p>
            <p>SOURCE: Original documents.</p>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc><revisionDesc><change><name>Stewart Varner</name> transformed this document from p4 to p5 on <date when="2010-03-22">March 22, 2010</date></change><change xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><date>1999</date><label>Staff</label><name>Scott Ellis</name>SGML tags inserted in compliance
with TEI guidelines using TEILITE</change></revisionDesc></teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div1 xml:id="fowler.001" n="Character and Death of Abraham Lincoln" type="text">
            <head> 
               <bibl> 
                  <title>Character and
Death of Abraham Lincoln</title> 
                  <date>April 23, 1865</date>
                  <pubPlace>Auburn, NY</pubPlace> 
                  <author>Fowler, Henry</author>
                  
                     <pubPlace>Auburn, NY; New York</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Wm. J. Moses' Steam Press Establishment, No. 16 Clark
Street; Shelden &amp; Co.</publisher>
                     <date>1865</date>
                  
               <idno type="ark">http://pid.emory.edu/ark:/25593/15q6c</idno></bibl> 
            </head>
            <pb facs="fowler1.jpg"/>
            <p>Character and Death of Abraham Lincoln.</p>
            <p>A DISCOURSE</p>
            <p>PREACHED AT</p>
            <p>AUBURN, N.Y., APRIL 23, 1865.</p>
            <p>BY</p>
            <p>REV. HENRY
FOWLER,</p>
            <p>PASTOR OF THE PRESBYTERIAN CHURCH.</p>
            <p>PUBLISHED BY REQUEST.</p>
            <p>AUBURN, N. Y.:</p>
            <p>WM. J. MOSES' STEAM PRESS ESTABLISHMENT,</p>
            <p>NO. 16 CLARK STREET.</p>
            <p>NEW YORK; SHELDON &amp; CO.</p>
            <p>1865.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="fowler2.jpg"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="fowler3.jpg"/>
            <div2 xml:id="fowler.002" n="DISCOURSE" type="sermon">
               <head>DISCOURSE.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <p>"AND THE ANGEL OF THE LORD CALLED UNTO ABRAHAM OUT OF
HEAVEN THE SECOND TIME."<hi rend="italic">Genesis</hi>
xxii,15.</p>
               </epigraph>
               <p>IN the midst of unequaled rejoicings, we are called to
unequaled sorrow. The certainty of Peace was revealed to us as a
bright vision; peace won by victories, not bought by conditions; peace
the seal of an indissoluble Union, not the treacherous truce of
independent sovereignties; peace the virtuous bride of liberty, not
the mistress of oppression; peace,</p>
               <lg type="stanza">
                  <l>"Whole as the marble, founded as the rock,</l>
                  <l>As broad and general as the casing air,"</l>
               </lg>
               <p>in fulfilment of the prophecy, "when mercy and truth meet together,
righteousness and peace kiss each other." Exalted by the certainty, we
raised our hallelujahs till they touched the skies. Their echo but met
our ears, when the words of a grimmer prophet are fulfilled: "Our
feasts are turned into mourning, and our songs into lamentations, as
the mourning of an only son, and the end thereof as a bitter day."
This country never saw such grief as marked the Ides of April, 1865,
when all men lifted up their voices and wept, and the Rachels refused
to be comforted. That grief abides to-day. The
<pb n="4" facs="fowler4.jpg"/>
Sabbath has tempered the sorrow with its teachings of faith. The
dismay which follows a first outburst of ambushed evil is past;
anxiety felt for the Republic is allayed, as we observe the unmoved
stability of affairs; but the mourning continues, and we gather now to
express and explain our bereavement, and to learn from each others'
hearts the lesson of the hour.</p>
               <p>"FATHER ABRAHAM."</p>
               <p>Our grief is both national and personal. When the President
of these United States was murdered, the shot was aimed at our
Country. The Republic shivered with the shock; each American seemed
called to avenge the blood; for, when Abraham Lincoln fell, "then you
and I and all of us fell down, whilst bloody treason flourished over
us."</p>
               <p>But our grief has its tenderer as well as sterner aspect,
its personal as well as its national elements. The Filial has taken
possession of our souls. Not only had the President's administration
constructed, in the heart of the nation, the confidence which upbuilds
between honest citizens, but his character had won the peculiar trust
felt by the son for a wise and good father. We were not afraid to ask
his reasons, and we were willing that he should not without giving
reasons. We received his explanations, and with faith alike
unquestioning, we accepted his reticence. His wisdom seemed to us
great, but not remote; his greatness upbore all the nation with him as
one family. He was, and always will be--"Father Abraham."</p>
               <p>HIS MORAL QUALITIES.</p>
               <p>In discussing his character, I do not dwell upon the
attainment of the Presidential chair, from humblest beginnings,
because in this, Abraham Lincoln is not remarkable. It is our
Institutions which are remarkable. Andrew Jackson, James K. Polk,
Millard Fillmore, and now Andrew Johnson, have become Presidents,
though beginning life in straitened circumstances; while Henry Clay
and Daniel Webster, with similar biography, have been greater than
Presidents. I ask you to consider the HONESTY of Abraham Lincoln,
although you
<pb n="5" facs="fowler5.jpg"/>
have mentioned it a thousand times, for it is too remarkable a quality
ever to be passed in silence. It was a grace of singular virtue, and
rare attainment. It not only essayed to speak the truth, but it
succeeded in speaking the truth. Its statements were free from
perplexing adumbras, and from Janus-faced meanings. You could always
tell what Abraham Lincoln meant to say. And he not only spoke, but
acted honestly. His words and his deeds were one. The grand unity of
truth wrought them into its clear consistency. Few men have lived who
held over the people, by simple integrity, such prevailing power, or
demonstrated to the world with such conclusiveness, the transcendent
scope of uprightness. While conceding that in common life, "honesty is
the best policy," some have imagined that on the broader field of
State or National politics, success could be best attained by the
subtlety of the politician, or the arts of the demagogue. But this
life tells us that integrity wins, when artifice fails. The President
did not waste the forces of intellect in cunning devices; he was not
wearying himself with anxieties about the consistency of his record;
he trusted the Truth, and she took care of him; her way out of
political labyrinths was short. Thus it was that in the lists of
diplomacy the President was never ensnared, confused, or doubled
on. He was more than a match for professional partisans, and for
Southern leaders, trained in the dialectics of the Conclave. I do not
affirm that honesty was the only source of this superiority; we must
give full credit to a sterling sense; but honesty was the main, as it
was the moral, head of that fountain of power which enabled Abraham
Lincoln to govern the Republic in these years of trial. A trait as
difficult of retention as of attainment, it was held by him sacred to
the last, a lustrous jewel; and as the American people cherish his
memory, they will repeat to coming generations the familiar title
which embalms his honesty.</p>
               <p>With this upright speech was
united</p>
               <p>THE HEARING EAR.</p>
               <p>The President listened to all comers. He
exercised a patient absorp-
<pb n="6" facs="fowler6.jpg"/>
tion. His long suffering was never exhausted. With equipoise he
listened not only to all statements of each applicant, but to each
statement of all applicants. He entertained and considered many
sides. Coming into the Presidential chair without investiture of a
clique, he held himself untrammeled by exclusiveness or even
partizanship. He was accessible to any and all the people; border
state men, peace men, war men, conservatives, radicals, religious men,
practical men, theorists, were received, and their arguments
weighed. His greatness lay in this all-comprehensive receptivity, He
belittled nothing, ignored nothing; he had that "wisdom from above
which is easy to be entreated, gentle, without partiality, and without
hypocrisy." No ruler has lived who kept his ear closer to the motions
of the popular thought, and to the pulsations of the American
heart. The voice of the people penetrated his soul with a sacred
welcome only second to the voice of God.</p>
               <p>Accompanying this trait appears</p>
               <p>HIS CLEMENCY</p>
               <p>He was so long-suffering, so forgiving, "not willing that
any should perish." The governmental power of pardon was used more
readily than the governmental power of execution. He sought to
reprieve, rather than to condemn. Mercy overruled justice. He was the
father rather than the judge of the people. He went to meet the
prodigal while he was yet a great way off, sometimes while
unrepentant. We have blamed him for this. We have been anxious at what
seemed an undue leniency which encouraged crime. But so he was! and
now that his work is done, we discern, not without satisfaction, the
handwriting of history, as it inscribes MERCY in crowning letters
above the record of his life. No man living could have won, or would
have won, from the American people, easier terms for traitors. To
gratify his purpose of mercy, we would have sacrificed our sense of
justice; and rebellion revealed the depths of its malignity when it
called Abraham Lincoln a tyrant, and the height of its folly when it
slew
<pb n="7" facs="fowler7.jpg"/>
him. Tyrant? Yes! as Moses was a tyrant to the Israelites--as David
was a man of Belial to the cursing Shimei--as Paul was a revolutionist
to the Ephesians--aye, as Jesus was a wine bibber and a publican to
Scribes and Pharisees.</p>
               <p>HIS INTELLECTUAL QUALITIES.</p>
               <p>In thus analyzing the moral qualities of the President, I
have touched upon the intellectual characteristics, for moral and
intellectual, in his nature, interwove their threads as warp and
woof. His mind was honest as his heart. It received and discerned the
truth. It never failed, however slowly, at last to grasp and hold the
essence of the thing. Laying off on either side extraneous
circumstances, filtrating out the worthless, it gathered the gold,
laboriously, yet completely, in one nugget, which it held triumphantly
up to the reflecting light. The President hesitated much before
deciding, but none after; flexible then, immovable now! This
discerning power enabled him, at crises in the war's history, to show
the American people its way of wisdom. You recall those letters, which
he at intervals wrote, of such singular insight, simplicity, and
logic. He is the only American statesman who could handle the edged
tool of a letter without self-injury; but every one he wielded,
carried conviction to the nation. His choice of occasion was as
felicitous as his selection of truth. He never wrote too soon; the
impatient now say that he wrote soon enough. As upon a flood tide,
even whose ebb-waves each marked higher upon the measure of his
influence, did he launch the ballasted vessel, freighted with the
precious cargo of his thought.</p>
               <p>The President was remarkable for not attempting to solve
problems sooner than Providence demanded. He made time his right hand
ally, neither wasting nor crowding her; he made no drafts on the
Future; he lived morally and intellectually, as it were, within his
income; he made no promises for next year; the work of each day was
all-sufficient, and he kept himself sufficient for the work. So he
toiled on, industriously, temperately, never flagging and never
hurrying, beneath the mighty burden which God had laid, unasked, upon
<pb n="8" facs="fowler8.jpg"/>
his shoulders. Holding himself as the servant of the people, and the
instrument of the Most High, he waited with docility on the logic of
events, as unrolling the decrees of God.</p>
               <p>HIS STORIES.</p>
               <p>To relieve Himself in the midst of labors which could not
stop, he used, with admirable success, a rare gift of humor and
illustration. He answered manifold applications with as many
stories. He replied to unsound arguments with jokes which dissolved
them. He cheered others and himself with anecdotes. He met the
incessant demands of society with reminiscences. He never could have
lived through the four years, if God had not endowed him with this
mental idiosyncracy. No public man resembles him in this. Many have
regarded his "little stories" as a littleness, but history will
treasure them as handmaidens of greatness, more helpful than games,
more instructive than songs. The clearer we apprehend the present era,
the plainer we may see the need of just such men at the head of
affairs. If he had been sedate like Washington, or partisan like
Jefferson, or opinionative like Adams, or imperious like Jackson, or
diplomatic like Van Buren, or impatient like Taylor, could he have
saved the American Union? May we not conclude that, in a superior
sense, to meet an extraordinary emergency, he was called to his work
"by the angel of the Lord," as Abraham, and Moses, and David were
called in old times, as Cromwell, and William of Orange, and
Washington in modern times, whose calling is seen through the special
traits with which God endowed them, and the controlling circumstances
with which Providence invested them?</p>
               <p>I am not willing to be borne by the occasion beyond the
calm judgment of history, and yet I do not hesitate to declare that
the people yet have not appreciated the greatness of Abraham
Lincoln. So modest, so unassuming, in manner so unaffected, never
elated by his elevation, never imperious because of his re-election,
ever so respectful to the opinions of others, without dogmatism, pride
or vanity,--these undoubted evidences of greatness have veiled rather
than re-
<pb n="9" facs="fowler9.jpg"/>
vealed the greatness itself, as at noonday grateful clouds hide the
power that produced them. But as future generations review the
gentleness, honesty, calmness, wisdom, endurance and buoyancy of the
man; as they note the conclusive fact, that the more we knew, the more
we trusted him, that the heavier grew his burdens, the stronger grew
the man, they will place him at the head of the nineteenth century. He
issued from the Nazareth of Central Illinois, and we esteemed him
not. He has been our teacher and ruler for four years, and we had come
to realize that we could lean on him as on no other man among twenty
millions, who would stand so firm. Suddenly he has been slain by those
for whom he was pleading, not only before Heaven, but before the
American people,--"Forgive them, for they know not what they do,"--and
we begin to suspect, we begin to feel, that the truest of patriots has
fallen, that the costliest sacrifice has been laid upon the altar of
country. He follows the heroes of the war, glorifying each in this
long line of martyrs to Constitutional Liberty; the greatest, and God
grant the last!</p>
               <p>BETWEEN THE OLD AND THE NEW.</p>
               <p>The character with which Arthur Stanley invests the prophet
Samuel, we may apply to the President. He was the mediator between the
old and the new. His two-sided sympathy enabled him to unite the
passing and the coming epoch, an epoch of surpassing perplexity,
transition, revolution. In every such passage of a nation, such a man
is needed. He may be misunderstood and misrepresented at the time,
attacked from both sides, charged with not going far enough, and with
going too far; charged with saying too much, and with saying too
little; yet he slowly, conscientiously works out the mighty
problem. Mr. Lincoln was not the founder of a new state of things,
like Washington. He was not the champion of the existing order of
things, like Webster. He stood between the old Union and the new,
between the past and future, between the dead and living, with that
sympathy for each, which, at such a period, is the best hope for any
permanent solution of the questions which torment it. His duty was
<pb n="10" facs="fowler10.jpg"/>
carefully to distinguish between that which was temporal and that
which is eternal. He might have but little praise from partisans, but
he was the careful healer, binding up the wounds of the age in spite
of itself; the good surgeon, knitting together the dislocated bones of
the disjointed times.</p>
               <p>SYNOPSIS OF CHARACTER.</p>
               <p>Sixteen months ago, I used the following language in
addressing you, which I repeat, in order to make an important
addition: "The explanation for the President's every act is this: He
executes the will of the people; he represents a controlling
majority. If he be slow, it is because the people are slow. If he have
done a foolish act, it was the stupidity of the people which impelled
it. His wisdom consists in carrying out the good sense of the
nation. His growth in political knowledge, his steady movement towards
emancipation, are but the growth and movement of the national
mind. Indeed, in character and culture he is a fair representative of
the average American. His awkward speech and yet more awkward silence;
his uncouth manners; his style miscellaneous, concreted from the best
authors, and yet oftentimes of Saxon force and classic purity; his
humor an argument, and his logic a joke, both unseasonable at times
and irresistible always; his questions answers, and his answers
questions; his guesses prophecies, and fulfilment ever beyond his
promise; honest yet shrewd, simple yet reticent; heavy and yet
energetic; never despairing, and never sanguine; careless in forms,
conscientious in essentials; never sacrificing a good servant, once
trusted, never deserting a sound principle, once adopted; not afraid
of new ideas, not despising old ones; improving opportunities to
confess mistakes, ready to learn, getting at facts; doing nothing when
he knows not what to do; hesitating at nothing when he sees the right;
lacking the recognized qualifications of a party leader, and yet
leading his party as no other man can; sustaining his political
enemies in Missouri to their defeat; sustaining his political friends
in Maryland to their victory; conservative in his sympathies, and
radical in his acts; Socratic in
<pb n="11" facs="fowler11.jpg"/>
his style, and Baconian in his method; his religion consisting in
truthfulness, temperance, asking good people to pray for him, and
publicly acknowledging in events the hand of God; he stands before you
as the type of 'Brother Jonathan,' a not perfect man, and yet 'more
precious than fine gold.'"</p>
               <p>To this statement something should now be added in regard
to the President's</p>
               <p>CHRISTIAN CHARACTER.</p>
               <p>While experience had cultured his language, style and
manners, so as to supply the defects of early education, it is his
Christian character which, during the last year, had specially
unfolded and perfected. Truthfulness had developed into love of Him
who is the Truth; temperance had become Christian self-control; the
solicited prayers of the good had been accompanied by his own prayers;
and the acknowledgment of Providence had ripened into the dedication
of himself to Jesus.</p>
               <p>He will never be identified with any one denomination. He
enlisted the fellowship of all Christians. His convictions betook
somewhat of every school. He was educated both by Friends and
Presbyterians. In a profound belief in the sovereignty of God, he was
Calvinistic; in partiality for mercy, even to the neglect of justice,
he was Socinian; but we may speak of him as at once orthodox and
liberal, devout and humanitarian; to whom the kingdom of heaven came
without observation, and was not declared in the usual phrases, but
whose "CALLING was of God." So that, remembering how without
self-seeking, by a singular concurrence of events, which we now see
were providential, he came, first, to be President, and knowing how,
by the felt necessities of help from God and by the sorrows of
Gettysburg, he was led, next, to a Christian consecration, we may
apply to him the words of the text: "And the angel of the Lord called
unto Abraham out of heaven <hi rend="italic">the second time</hi>."</p>
               <p>How, fifty months ago, those parting words to his townsmen touched
the sympathies of the country! How the request for prayer
<pb n="12" facs="fowler12.jpg"/>
roused the Church of Christ! Since, how easy to pray for Abraham
Lincoln! We do not hesitate to believe that God's answer to the
prayers thus elicited, have made the President what he was, holding
him from disastrous blunders, leading him in the path of wisdom.</p>
               <p>But what progress from this primal request does the second
INAUGURAL show. This remarkable state paper is not a political
manifesto, but a Christian exposition. It is the words of a man of
God, instructing the people of his charge. It presents the
sovereignty, wisdom, and justice of God, the sinfulness of slavery,
the faith, perseverance, and charity which become the people. It is
the farewell address of the Restorer of the Union. It will be read
unceasingly, and its Christian doctrine, its ripeness, simplicity,
pathos and profound sentiment, will make it a sacred Epistle to the
American people.</p>
               <p>HIS WORK.</p>
               <p>Having thus presented his character, we observe that the
President's work was done just as his death came. Posterity will
regard the emancipation proclamation as the great act of his life, but
his great work was the saving of the Union. The emancipation
proclamation was a means to this end, used with hesitation, lest,
unsustained by the people, it might miscarry, and issued with a prayer
that the act of freedom, justice, and mercy might receive "the
considerate judgment of mankind, and the gracious favor of Almighty
God." The means proved efficient. At first it encountered bitter
opposition, but it was our safeguard against foreign intervention, our
helper in the enlistment of colored troops. And so the great work went
on of restoring the Union, until when Lee surrendered, we may say the
work was done. Whatever else fails, the Union <hi rend="italic">cannot
be dissolved</hi>.</p>
               <p>The proposal made in the President's first inaugural, "to
hold, occupy, and possess the property and places belonging to the
Government," had been fulfilled; the ports and chief cities of
Rebellion had surrendered; their armies were scattered, captured, or
demoralized; their chiefs were either slain, paroled, imprisoned, or
fugitive; the President had visited their stronghold; the flag had
been raised on
<pb n="13" facs="fowler13.jpg"/>
Fort Sumter; the appeal in behalf of a liberal re-adjustment had been
made; the last day of the four years since the first humbling of the
flag was drawing to its close amidst the joy of a great people,
victorious over disunion, ready to forgive the traitors, proposing to
receive back to all the rights and privileges of citizenship, any who
would take the oath of allegiance, and then, amidst the joy, and hope,
and peace, and amnesty, the tools of slavery plot for the murder of
all the rulers--President, Vice-President, Cabinet-Secretaries,
Lieutenant-General. The Secretary of State, our honored townsman, is
stabbed as he lies helpless upon a bed of pain, his sons and defenders
are disabled, the Chief of all is slain, and the nation cries out in
agony!</p>
               <p>JUSTICE</p>
               <p>But the cry is not alone of agony. It is also a cry for
justice. It is uttered not against the miserable, dissolute assassins,
but against the guilty Power that hies them on. It speaks to that
conspiracy which includes this and any infernal plot--the gigantic
conspiracy against human nature, which sought to carry oppression
wherever the flag of our country rules; which corrupted our national
politics, and debauched the public conscience; which forced the
country into compromises, only that it might trample them under foot
as stepping-stones to more arrogant domination; which made war upon a
neighboring Republic, that it might extend the area of slavery; which
struck down a distinguished Senator in his place, and gloried in the
act; which forbade free speech throughout its domain, and mobbed or
hung whomever the love of liberty forbade to keep silence; which
wasted the Free State men of our border territories; which sold its
own flesh and blood with fiendish greed for gold, breeding for the
auction block; which waxed arrogant and brutal, till it refused to
submit to the constitutional election of Abraham Lincoln, impiously
insisting that he retire from the Presidential chair, and a
secessionist, by general consent, occupy his place, as the only escape
from national disruption;
<pb n="14" facs="fowler14.jpg"/>
which demanded that we all bow down to Moloch, or pass through the
flame and blood of sacrifice, to the hideous idol; which plotted to
assassinate the President elect on his way to Washington, fired on
Fort Sumter, sought to seize the capital by a <hi rend="italic">coup
d'etat</hi>, voted States out of the Union, concentrated armies,
possessed itself of forts, arsenals, ships, and other properties of
the United States; in the midst of profound peace, flung abroad the
firebrands of civil strife, involved a nation of thirty millions in a
continental war, consuming thousands of millions of substance, and
slaying hundreds of thousands of our sons and brothers; which has
sought by subtle plot, to involve our cities in midnight
conflagration, to desolate our towns with sudden raids, and by the
help of decoyed England, has burned our ships on the high seas with
pirate craft; which has murdered, by wanton exposure and designed
starvation, thousands of our brave soldiers, prisoners of war,
reducing many to an idiocy worse than death; which has mutilated the
bodies of our slain heroes, scattering their flesh and shaping their
bones into trinkets; butchered hundreds of our black soldiers after
surrender, and those white soldiers who escaped from its infernal
prisons hunted with blood-hounds; which has visited thousands of
Southern homes with fire and sword, hanging many a true man before the
eyes of wife or sister, for the sole crime of loving his country's
flag too well; which has sought for four years, by inflammatory
appeals and offers of large rewards, to compass the assassination of
our chief officers: and which, at last, its armies beaten, its foreign
help paralyzed, its cities captured, its power exhausted, its hopes
demolished, with nothing to gain by the cowardly and infamous deed,
sends the assassin's bullet from behind through the head of the
nation, and culminates all crimes against humanity by this last
crowning villany, fitting close to the horrible record of human
slavery!</p>
               <lg type="stanza">
                  <l>"Treason has done his worst; nor steel, nor poison,</l>
                  <l>Malice domestic, foreign levy, nothing</l>
                  <l>Can touch him further."</l>
               </lg>
               <p>There is such a thing as vengeance; I do not advocate it; but is
<pb n="15" facs="fowler15.jpg"/>
there not such a thing as justice? Is law never to be vindicated? Is
government not ordained of God, as a terror to the evil doer? Is there
no such a thing as a righteous retribution? Are we to see the plotters
and engineers of this great conspiracy, reinstated in their
properties, places, and families? Is Robert E. Lee to be cheered by
Americans, because as a Virginia aristocrat he fought desperately
against his country? Is treason only a difference of political
sentiments? What lesson have we to learn? The President, living,
teaches us mercy, and we listen with consent to amnesty and
re-construction; but the President murdered, teaches us retribution,
and we swear above his open grave, extermination against treason and
its plotters. As a Christian man and a Christian teacher, I ever
inculcate mercy for the penitent, but for the reprobate, for traitors
to the last, for those who will murder from behind, when they can no
longer fight in front--I call upon government to unsheath the sword of
justice, and I do it in the name of moral law and of Infinite
Righteousness.</p>
               <p>But you say, "extermination is impossible."</p>
               <p>Let us analyze the population of the South.</p>
               <p>Before the war there were (in round numbers) three hundred
and fifty thousand oligarchists; one million poor whites, their tools;
four millions of Africans, their slaves; five millions of
yeomanry. These last were for the most part persons of industry and
self supporting; some owned one, two, or three slaves apiece; a few
were educated; all preferred the Union, and as a class believed in
free institutions. The survivors of these five millions, with few
exceptions, we may trust. Many have died for the country, or are now
in our armies; those who fought against us, were either deceived or
conscripted; they will take the oath of allegiance in good faith, and
return to the Union and honest labor. Of the poor whites, many have
died in the rebel armies; some will wander off to Mexico; some will
become guerrillas and be shot; the few remaining will be of less
account. Of the oligarchists, many have been slain in battle; some are
in Canada, or Europe; a few are true Union men; the balance will be
banished from the land
<pb n="16" facs="fowler16.jpg"/>
they have betrayed, or be condemned to death. There remain four
millions of Africans, laborers in the planting States. Who can surpass
the African in loyalty, in love for the flag, in bravery, in a desire
for education, in Bible faith, <hi rend="italic">in love for Abraham
Lincoln</hi>? Shall they who weep the saddest tears by the national
bier, be denied citizenship, and smiling rebels re-construct the
Union? Shall you and I never learn to look below the skin? Yes, we
shall! Though they murdered Abraham Lincoln, his work they cannot
murder! Now is the Union cemented, and the Emancipation Proclamation
sealed with his blood! Yea, we may say that the work to which he was
"called by the angel of the Lord," was but a part of God's great plan
for this country. We may not discern the plan in its fulness and
beauty, but we see already outlined the equal protection of all races,
the fraternity of peoples, the unhindered and universal dissemination
of social, political, and Christian truth. Abraham Lincoln has led out
of Egypt, and from Pisgah's top has passed to heaven. "Well done, good
and faithful servant," sobs the nation! Andrew Johnson will lead us
into the promised land!</p>
               <p>We may be called to added sacrifices, but sacrifice has
vicarious power; our children and humanity will reap the
blessing. God's furnace of affliction may again be hot, but the fire
will purify and save. If we only win the End, we will bear the
pain. It is the blessed purpose of heaven we fulfil. We are the keys
of the great instrument, from which an Almighty hand reveals the
anthem. Last week it was the paean of praise. To-day it is the
dirge. Soon may it be the hallelujah of salvation! God's will be done!
AMEN!</p>
            </div2>
         </div1>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>