<TEI.2>
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt n="The Teachings of the Crisis">
            <title>The Teachings of the
Crisis</title>
            <author>Garrison, Rev. J. F.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Compiled and edited by</resp>
               <name>Beck
Center</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent/>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Lewis H. Beck Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Emory University</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Atlanta,
Georgia</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>1996 Emory
University. Permission is granted to download, transmit, or otherwise
reproduce, distribute or display the contributions to the work claimed
by Emory University for non-profit educational purposes, provided
this header is included in its entirety.  For inquiries about
commercial uses, contact the Director, 
Pitts Theology Library, Emory
University, Atlanta, Georgia 30322</p>
            </availability>
            <date>1999</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Lincoln
Sermons Project</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Garrison,
Rev. J. F. The Teachings of the Crisis. Address Delivered in
St. Paul's Church, Camden, N. J., on the Occasion of The Funeral of
Abraham Lincoln, April 19, 1865.  Camden, N. J.: Printed by S. Chew,
at the Office of the "West Jersey Press." 1865.</bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This text derives from the Special Collections 
of Pitts Theology Library, Emory University, and is produced in 
collaboration with the Lewis H. Beck Center a, the Emory 
Preservation Office, and Pitts Theology Library.</p>
            <p>TRANSCRIBER: Lewis H. Beck Center and Emory University Preservation Office.</p>
            <p>PRODUCER:  BookLab, Inc., 1606 Headway Circle, Suite 100, Austin, TX 78754</p>
            <p>CAPTURE DEVICE: XEROX DocuImage 620S flatbed scanner</p>
            <p>CAPTURE DETAILS: Scanner software: XEROX ScanTool version 4.2.3; no gamma correction; images are all bitonal.</p>
            <p>CHANGE HISTORY: Using the Adobe Photoshop Batch Processor, we interpolated  the original TIFF files to 8-bit grays, and altered the resolution to 144 dpi, producing screen images twice the original size.  We then saved them in JPEG format.  We produced GIF thumbnails from the JPEG files.</p>
            <p>RESOLUTION: 600 ppi</p>
            <p>COMPRESSION: Resolution 144 per inch with Constrain Properties to 72 per inch.</p>
            <p>SOURCE: Original documents.</p>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>1999</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Scott Ellis</name>
               <resp>Staff</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <item>SGML tags inserted in compliance
with TEI guidelines using TEILITE</item>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div1 id="garrison.001" n="The Teachings of the Crisis" type="text">
            <head pn="1"> 
               <bibl> 
                  <title>The Teachings
of the Crisis</title> 
                  <date>April 19, 1865</date> 
                  <pubPlace>St. Paul's
Church, Camden, N. J.</pubPlace> 
                  <author>Garrison, Rev. J. F.</author>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Camden, N. J.</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Printed by
S. Chew, at the Office of the "West Jersey Press"</publisher>
                     <date>1865</date>
                  </imprint> 
               </bibl> 
            </head>
            <p pn="1">
               <figure entity="garrison1">
                  <figDesc>1st page of
Rev. J. F. Garrison's The Teachings of the
Crisis.</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <p pn="1">The Teachings of the Crisis.</p>
            <p pn="1">ADDRESS</p>
            <p pn="1">DELIVERED IN</p>
            <p pn="1">ST. PAUL'S CHURCH, CAMDEN, N.J.,</p>
            <p pn="1">THE FUNERAL</p>
            <p pn="1">OF</p>
            <p pn="1">ABRAHAM LINCOLN,</p>
            <p pn="1">April 19, 1865,</p>
            <p pn="1">REV. J. F. GARRISON, M. D.</p>
            <p pn="1">PUBLISED BY REQUEST</p>
            <p pn="1">CAMDEN, N.J.:</p>
            <p pn="1">PRINTED BY S. CHEW, AT THE OFFICE OF THE "WEST
JERSEY PRESS."</p>
            <p pn="1">1865.</p>
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p pn="2">
               <figure entity="garrison2">
                  <figDesc>2nd page of
Rev. J. F. Garrison's The Teachings of the
Crisis.</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <p pn="2">
               <hi rend="italic">"With malice towards none, with charity for
all, with firmness in the right as God gives us to see the right, let
us strive on to finish the work we are in, to bind up the Nation's
wounds, to care for him who shall have borne the battle, and for his
widow and orphans, to do all which may achieve and cherish a just and
lasting peace among ourselves and with all Nations." [From Abraham
Lincoln's Second Inaugural.]</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p pn="3">
               <figure entity="garrison3">
                  <figDesc>3rd page of
Rev. J. F. Garrison's The Teachings of the
Crisis.</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p pn="4">
               <figure entity="garrison4">
                  <figDesc>4th page of
Rev. J. F. Garrison's The Teachings of the
Crisis.</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <p pn="4">ST. PAUL'S CHURCH,
CAMDEN, APRIL 20, 1865.</p>
            <p pn="4">REV. J. F. GARRISON,</p>
            <p pn="4">DEAR SIR:--The subscribers, members of the
Vestry and others, listened with great satisfaction to the sermon
preached by you on the occasion of the funeral services on the death
of President LINCOLN. We but give expression to a general wish for a
wider circulation of this sermon, in asking a copy for publication.</p>
            <p pn="4">O.H. TAYLOR,			CHAS. P. STRATTON,
		<lb/>T.P. CARPENTER,			W.D. COOPER,
		<lb/>ROBT. B. POTTS,			HENRY ACKLEY,
		<lb/>P.J. GRAY,				H. GENET
TAYLOR,
		<lb/>J.R. DUNHAM,			S.H. GREY,<lb/>
AZAEL ROBERTS,			JOSHUA L. HOWELL,<lb/>
M.B. TAYLOR,			T. CHAS. MERRY,<lb/>
J.V. TROTH,				JNO. R. STEVENSON, <lb/>MAURICE
BROWNING,			CLINTON M. ACKERMAN,<lb/>
GEO. S. WARDWELL,			F.B. ODENHEIMER,<lb/>
WM. E. LAFFERTY,			S.C. HARBERT.</p>
            <p pn="4">CAMDEN,
APRIL 21, 1865.</p>
            <p pn="4">GENTLEMEN:--Your favor of the 20th inst., requesting the
publication of the address delivered on the occasion of the funeral
service of President LINCLON, is before me.</p>
            <p pn="4">Hoping that it may be useful, at this great crisis, in what
I believe to be the cause of "God and our Country," I place the
manuscript which you request, at your disposal.</p>
            <p pn="4">Very Respectfully Yours,</p>
            <p pn="4">J.F. GARRISON.</p>
            <p pn="4">Messrs. O.H. TAYLOR,
  <lb/>T.P. CARPENTER,
	  <lb/>R B. POTTS,
	  <lb/>S.H. GREY,
	  <lb/>WM. D. COOPER, &amp;C., &amp;C.</p>
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p pn="5">
               <figure entity="garrison5">
                  <figDesc>5th page of
Rev. J. F. Garrison's The Teachings of the
Crisis.</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <div2 id="garrison.002" n="The Teachings of the Crisis" type="sermon">
               <head pn="5">The Teachings of the Crisis.</head>
               <epigraph pn="5">
                  <p pn="5">HEBREWS XI: 6.</p>
                  <p pn="5">"HE BEING DEAD YET SPEAKETH."</p>
               </epigraph>
               <p pn="5">A nation is to-day assembled for a funeral. And never, save when
God himself laid Moses in the valley of Beth-Peor, had mortal man so
grand a burial. There have been larger piles of stone heaped up than
we shall rear for our murdered President; there may have been more of
the pomp and circumstance of gilded majesty around, and on the bier;
but never before was man laid in his tomb, with twenty- millions of
true hearted sorrowers standing, by to do him honor. A nation gathers
at the grave, and the sad tokens, and yet sadder ceremonials have
spread a pall of mourning over half a continent. In every Town and
City, in every Church and hamlet, there is a thronging to the funeral;
it began on the cold New England hills, where the spring violets have
not yet peeped beside the winter snow, it moves on down through the
great cities of the seaboard States, a thousand miles across the
<pb n="6"/>
                  <figure entity="garrison6">
                     <figDesc>6th page of
Rev. J. F. Garrison's The Teachings of the Crisis.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
Alleghanies, along the great Father of Waters, far away over the
distant prairies, only to cease where no flash of the magic telegraph
can carry its sad tidings farther; and then, for days, weeks after,
these will come, one by one, into the solitary homes of remote
settlers in the wilderness, and make them all the more sorrowful, that
they could not have had the sad joy of mingling their sorrow in the
great ocean of the nation's grief. But more impressive, even, than the
mighty host who gather around, is the tribute of the feeling which has
brought them here; the nation is not assembled for this vast solemnity
as a mere looker-on, to share the mourning of a stricken few; the
nation is itself the mourner. It mourns the man; it mourns the
President; men feel it as an individual sorrow, as well as a national
calamity; and they have reason to do both.</p>
               <p pn="6">Called to the Presidential Chair at the most momentous
crisis in the history of the country, ABRAHAM LINCOLN had a task
entrusted to his charge, such as God has seldom given to the lot of
man. He found the nation tottering on the verge of anarchy and
hopeless ruin; treason had paralyzed the government; its treasury was
bare; its navy scattered; its army unavailable; Rebels had already
entrenched themselves within its forts, driven out their garrisons,
seized their stores and armaments, had robbed its mints, defied its
officers, and equipped their soldiers in the plundered munitions of
its arsenals; And thus, with traitors swarming in every department,
and sympathizers with the rebels--if not with the rebellion--all over
the nation, Mr. Lincoln took on him the immense, the terrible
responsibilities of the Presidential office. Untried in higher
statesmanship, unknown among the leading, names who were regarded as
the thinkers of the nation,
<pb n="7"/>
                  <figure entity="garrison7">
                     <figDesc>7th page of
Rev. J. F. Garrison's The Teachings of the Crisis.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
with less of means, and more of peril than ever man was called to
undertake so great a work before, he set himself to enter on his
duties. The tempest which has been so long gathering burst, and what a
storm!--who that lived through it, ever can forget that fearful
morning, when the news, thrilled through the land from Sumter, that
traitor hands had plunged the nation into the fiery hell of civil
war?</p>
               <p pn="7">How eagerly, how achingly, doubtingly, almost despairingly,
all eyes were turned toward the President. Would he be equal to the
emergency? Had he the nerve? The wisdom? Was he, untried and
inexperienced, the man to guide the nation in this hour of peril? It
was a time to test the very uttermost of all that is in a character,
and Mr. Lincoln met it in a spirit equal to the time. I know not
anywhere in all the records of great governors and statesmen, a
higher, nobler sentiment, than the concluding sentence of his first
message to the special congress of 1861, and after events have shown,
that this was the spoken impress of his real nature: "Having thus
chosen our course, without guile, and with pure purpose, let us renew
our trust in God, and go forward, without fear, and with manly
hearts."</p>
               <p pn="7">On the fierce conflict raged, and he did "go forward." He
had to prepare an army, to fill a treasury, to create a navy, to hold
down factious malcontents at home, to ward off threatened intervention
from abroad, to build up credit when everything seemed crumbling into
ruin, to save the nation's life when all was dark within, and all
without was cheerless. Everything was to be done at once; each several
thing was imperatively needed at the instant; there were no
precedents; no one had any knowledge or experience: his soldiers were
undisciplined civil-
<pb n="8"/>
                  <figure entity="garrison8">
                     <figDesc>8th page of
Rev. J. F. Garrison's The Teachings of the Crisis.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
ians; his ministers untaught, and ignorant in the immense,
unprecedented duties of their new position; but in all these
discouragements, with all these dangers, he never wavered never
faltered, nor despaired: through many long, dark months--years they
appeared to us--of toil and painful agony, order began to grow out of
chaos, and light to break upon the darkness. And he not only built his
navy, but used it so efficiently, that before he died, it rode in
triumph over every fortressed harbor from Cape Henry to the Rio
Grande; and he so wrought his armies to the work they were to do, that
ere he passed away, he saw their banners wave victorious in the
capital of treason, and knew the mightiest forces of the Rebellion all
broken or surrendered before their serried columns. What enemies had
long pronounced impossible, was gradually done; what half, or whole
sympathizers with the rebels, had tauntingly paraded with derisive
jeers, as hopeless barriers, were swept or worn away.</p>
               <p pn="8">And although, on many points of governmental policy there
were wide differences of opinion, although, as must ever be the case
where so many and so complicated questions are at issue, his
principles of constitutional interpretation were disputed, yet day by
day his hold grew stronger on the nation's heart, his place more
settled in the people's confidence, and never did he stand so high in
almost universal estimation, as just at the moment of his death, when
in the very flush and glory of the triumphant progress of his armies,
he showed a noble magnanimity of soul towards the vanquished, which
stands as solitary in the history of rebellions, as our Republic does
among the family of nations. He needed but one honor more, to write
his name upon the topmost scroll of earthly immortality; and
<pb n="9"/>
                  <figure entity="garrison9">
                     <figDesc>9th page of
Rev. J. F. Garrison's The Teachings of the Crisis.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
when he died, a victim to the traitor's hate towards the nation he had
loved, and saved, that honor was awarded; and he who ranked before
among the high historic names of human glory, will henceforth stand
among that higher, chosen few, who are deemed worthy to be martyrs for
the cause of right. It robs him of a few short years of troubled
life. It consecrates him to the never-dying reverence of a nation's
loving honor.</p>
               <p pn="9">But great as was the work performed by ABRAHAM LINCOLN in
the deliverance of this nation from the threatened danger of its
anarchy and ruin, his place in history will not be bounded by the
narrow limits of one nation's gratitude; his name will mark,
throughout all after time, one of the epochs, from which the world
will date the opening of a new era in the onward progress of God's
providential leadings of the race of man. Two facts in human history
are linked inseparably, with the name and work of ABRAHAM LINCOLN, and
by them "He being dead yet speaketh." The first was demonstrated by
his life; the second was established in his death.</p>
               <p pn="9">I. The history of this country under the Administration of
Mr. Lincoln, has demonstrated beyond reasonable cavil, the capacity
and fitness of a people for self-government. This was the problem
given our nation to decide; so we have understood it; so has it been
understood, and canvassed by the world without.</p>
               <p pn="9">Those who desired that Governments should be administered
for the blessing of the people, and not for the maintaining of a
caste, have looked to us to show the world that this was possible, and
was actually done; the burdened and starving masses who have groaned
for some
<pb n="10"/>
                  <figure entity="garrison10">
                     <figDesc>10th page of
Rev. J. F. Garrison's The Teachings of the Crisis.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
place of refuge, where they might give their children bread and feel
themselves were men, have thanked God when they heard what our land
was doing, and with one heart turn here, as to the only hope on earth,
of the oppressed and destitute; and those who have for ages ruled the
world on the acknowledged principle,</p>
               <lg type="stanza">
                  <l>"Thus it hath been, shall be, beneath the Sun,</l>
                  <l>The many still must labor for the One."</l>
               </lg>
               <p pn="10">They too looked here and hoped--but hoped that all our mighty work
for man would fail, that we should soon dissolve in anarchy, or
degenerate into despotism, have prophesied what they desired, and
prayed to have their prophecies fulfilled, have loathed our very name
and never ceased to vilify our principles and policy. And when at
length, in the embittered feud on slavery--a feud which they had fed,
and fanned, and nursed to it malign maturity--a fierce and terrible
rebellion broke upon our land, the sneering coldness, and derision of
the titled classes of all Europe, told the settled bitterness which
they had always felt towards the great experiment of governing a
nation by, and for the people; and all their hopes and prophecies were
now declared to be fulfilled; the day at last had come, when
"Democracy was proved a failure;" the troublesome and vexing cry of
suffering multitudes, was thenceforward to be stilled by the
conclusive answer, "The great Republic of your admiration, is a vile
abortion, "henceforth remember, that we rule by right divine, and
"learn to suffer, and be silent." Thus, upon every hand, the problem
was distinctly recognized, and our work was set.</p>
               <p pn="10">In our long years of peace, there was but little to decide
the question; "you have not yet," we were continually
<pb n="11"/>
                  <figure entity="garrison11">
                     <figDesc>11th page of
Rev. J. F. Garrison's The Teachings of the Crisis.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
told, "had any real testing of a people's fitness for self government;
your boundless country gives abundant room for labor, you have no need
of taxes, you make no call upon your people for self-sacrifices, you
are not even governed; wait, until some crisis when you are compelled
to these demands, and then see what a rope of sand your unrestrained
democracy will prove; then will your laws be powerless, then will your
cities flame with riot, your people rage to anarchy, and your whole
system show itself--however beautiful in theory--a practical
impossibility." We hardly dared to trust an answer, where there were
so many, and so real dangers threatened, our hope was mainly, that our
place, and territorial relations would never give us the occasion to
bring them to the trial.</p>
               <p pn="11">But our work was to decide the problem. God does not raise
up great nations without a purpose in the course of history; each has
its contribution to bestow, in the grand work of God for the advancing
education, and elevation of the race of man. And the capacity of a
people under the influence of Christianity to be free, and to maintain
their freedom as a blessing, is one of the questions to which our
nation was to give an answer; and God sent the trial which was to
force it to a solution; and it was a trial worthy of the principle at
issue. Oh! how our nation shook and reeled beneath the blinding fury
of that awful testing!--we do not wonder that the world prepared our
epitaph, and taunted us with our doom. But God had not held out the
cup of promised blessing to the people of the earth, to dash it down
in mockery.</p>
               <p pn="11">The very fearfulness of our trial was only to make its
triumph all the more apparent. The storm was met, our Government was
not a paltering inability, the loyal people
<pb n="12"/>
                  <figure entity="garrison12">
                     <figDesc>12th page of
Rev. J. F. Garrison's The Teachings of the Crisis.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
did not disintegrate to anarchy, they not only bore the burdens first
required of them, but when, in the very darkest and fiercest of the
struggle, the question was asked them, by a Presidential canvass,
"Will you, without fear, and with manly hearts go forward through
this? Will you pour out, more lavishly, your treasure? Will you lay
down upon your nation's altar, more, and more, and more, if need be,
of yourselves, and sons, and fathers?" The answer came back in a
single night, not in a voice of lawlessness and riot, not from streets
run with blood, nor cities wrapped in howling conflagration, but in
the silent majesty of a bloodless ballot-box--"So help us God we
will." It was sublime! History has no such scene! The trial had been
fearful, but the triumph was complete. A people could be free, and a
free people could maintain their own self-government.</p>
               <p pn="12">And yet, there are those, so blind to the true stake at
issue, that they see nothing ennobling or inspiring to humanity in all
this, who say there is no patriotism in our country now, that all this
is nothing, and means nothing but mere party politics, that all this
vast uprising of a continent, this giving up in agony of heart their
loved and needed, this quiet, settled purpose, calmly uttered, still
to bear and do, is only selfish, hireling work for money wages. No
patriotism in all this? only money? mere party bitterness? Oh no! Oh
no! Such have not read the nation's heart aright; they have not
rightly weighed the value of the issue, nor known how deep a hold its
vital principle had fixed upon the soul of our people. No human work
can be without some selfish and unworthy aspect, so it has always
been, is now, and will be to the end, but never did the pen of history,
<pb n="13"/>
                  <figure entity="garrison13">
                     <figDesc>13th page of
Rev. J. F. Garrison's The Teachings of the Crisis.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
in any age, portray a higher, purer love of country or a more glorious
spirit of self-sacrifice, than fill the records of our country, in
this its noble struggle for its own existence, and the universal good
of man.</p>
               <p pn="13">The living instinct of the people felt the true import of
the crisis, and with a zeal and patriotic fervor which esteemed no
price too great, for the immeasurable interests at stake, they bore,
and carried through, the contest. And we may now feel, although we
have yet much to do and learn, that by the help of God, a final and
decisive answer has been given to the question, of the capacity, and
fitness of a people for the government of a nation. I know--no one can
be more painfully alive to the conviction--that we, as a nation, have
many and grievous faults, evils in our modes of thinking, often great
wrongs in our methods of administration, that we have bad men,
unworthy legislators, many, corrupt in principle, too many, vile in
conduct, that sin abounds in our land, and wickedness brings misery to
multitudes, and I know--and with all solemn earnestness proclaim--that
if we go on in our sins, God's judgments, soon or late, will come for
our utter desolation. But with all our faults, and wrongs, when, or
where, had any nation fewer? Where one, in which there was less crime
and misery? England, Wales and Ireland with five millions less
population, report in their courts of record, ten thousand more
criminals annually, than we; their own reports announce that in a
population of twenty millions there are every year, from eight hundred
thousand, to nearly a million and a half of paupers, an average of one
individual in every twenty of the entire nation, named upon its poor
list.</p>
               <p pn="13">We have indeed, our sins and crimes, and in the present
<pb n="14"/>
                  <figure entity="garrison14">
                     <figDesc>14th page of
Rev. J. F. Garrison's The Teachings of the Crisis.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
suffering we would have you recognize, a punishment, and discipline
for our wickedness, as well as an assertion of the vital principle of
our nationality, but notwithstanding, we have an heritage, than which,
the world has never seen a nobler and a better. Thank God that I am an
American! I want no higher title, I know no higher name among the
nations of the earth, of past or present history. There was a time,
when to say "I am a Roman Citizen," was nobler honor than to be a
king; but Rome in her loftiest glory could give no title to her
citizen, so worthy to be honored, as that of "an American"
to-day. Rome claimed her greatness in making millions, slaves, and
tributaries: America is great, in  witnessing through blood and agony,
that man, as man, is able to be free.</p>
               <p pn="14">The second fact linked with the name of ABRAHAM LINCOLN,
and by which "he being dead yet speaketh," was established in his
death. And this is, that slavery no longer shall retain a place among
the institutions of a civilized community. There was, from the
beginning of our government, a glaring contradiction between the
principles which it avowed upon the subject of human rights, and human
liberty, and its actual practice. We called ourselves, and claimed it
as our highest honor, that we were a land of liberty; the birth-throe
of the nation was the declaration, which proclaimed this as our
fundamental principle; we set apart, one only day, of all the year, as
our universal and symbolic festival, and on that day we were to read,
and teach our children, as our national birth-pledge, "We hold these
truths to be self evident, that all men are endowed by their Creator,
with certain unalienable rights, that among these are life, 
<pb n="15"/>
                  <figure entity="garrison15">
                     <figDesc>15th page of
Rev. J. F. Garrison's The Teachings of the Crisis.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
"liberty, and the pursuit of happiness"--self-evident," our
Revolutionary Fathers thought them, not needing proof, too plain to
ask an argument, only to be named, to be acknowledged.</p>
               <p pn="15">No wonder, that the observance of the Fourth of July as a
national festivity had, a few years ago, well nigh died out, when we
not only held four millions men as slaves, legislated for them as mere
legal chattels, bought, sold, worked and beat them as we did our
horses and our hounds, but boasted of it as an honor, assumed for it
and its supporters, peculiar eminence of caste, and consideration, in
silence acquiesced when they were vaunted as the chivalry of our land,
and feared to talk of liberty, lest it might wake an echo in the bosom
of a slave. What a comment on our national consistency and truth! we
were a living lie, and either our principle or our practice would,
soon or late, one or the other have to be abandoned.</p>
               <p pn="15">And yet, although so flagrantly in contradiction to all
that our Fathers held as true and right, because they had from motives
of political expediency, given slavery the protection of the
government, in certain of its features, the Christian sentiment, and
law-abiding spirit of the country bore the contradiction, and accepted
the inconsistency; they maintained the institution as a part of our
constitutional requirements, checked all disturbing agitation of its
iniquities, ranked it as one of the things of Caesar, to be rendered
unto Caesar, made compromises to favor its continuance, and poured the
oil of soothing sympathy upon the angry feelings of its jealous
advocates, when searching truths fell on tile quick of their excited
sensibilities. But bye and bye it was no longer satisfied with this;
it would no longer rest content, to be regarded
<pb n="16"/>
                  <figure entity="garrison16">
                     <figDesc>16th page of
Rev. J. F. Garrison's The Teachings of the Crisis.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
as an arrangement of political expediency; it now claimed to be an
institution of divine ordainment, demanded that men should close their
eyes to all its evils, moral as well as political, should seal their
mouths against all mention of its enormities; And as the contradiction
between the truths in which the nation had its origin, and the
realities of our actual condition, pressed more and more on slavery,
the inconsistency grew unendurable; and slavery declared its purpose
to strike down the Government, to divide the nation, and to build up
another empire, in which the "unalienable right" of slavery, was to be
the vital principle, and chief corner stone--"The first" says its most
distinguished advocate "the world has ever seen, in which this was
avowed"--and in this he was right; it was the first, and it will be
the last.</p>
               <p pn="16">To carry out this hideous purpose, it arrayed itself
against the Government in armed rebellion; and at Fort Sumter threw
down the gauntlet of defiance.</p>
               <p pn="16">In this first act of mad revolt, it sealed its own
destruction; and then and there we date its fatal wound, and the
beginning of the deliverance of the nation from its curse and
ignominy. But it was to be borne with yet awhile, that it might fill
the measure of its own iniquity, and bring upon itself the ruin, which
it had thought to bring upon the nation. And we bore with it when it
stormed our forts, and murdered our soldiers; we bore with it when it
marched its troops against our Capital; and while its guns were
thundering at the very gates of our Halls of Congress, they passed a
resolution, to propose as an amendment to the Constitution, that it
should never be so altered, as "to authorize or give Congress power to
abolish, or interfere with" slavery in any State. We bore with it
<pb n="17"/>
                  <figure entity="garrison17">
                     <figDesc>17th page of
Rev. J. F. Garrison's The Teachings of the Crisis.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
in the long dark days of bloody battles; even then had it been willing
to return in peace, the brand would have been buried, and the past
forgiven. And when at length the feeling had grown rooted in the
nation's mind and heart, that slavery must come to an end, and its
destruction was officially decreed, still, many who desired its ruin
wavered, hesitated, would rather have borne on, and trusted to the
action of less stringent measures to work out the final
consummation.</p>
               <p pn="17">It starved our captive soldiers, inch by inch, and day by
day, thousands on thousands, wasting them to haggard skeletons, and
pining them to death in hopeless agony, with a brutality which has no
parallel upon so large a scale, in all the sickening records of
earth's mocking cruelty; and still we felt to it, and dealt to it a
mercy it had never shown to others.</p>
               <p pn="17">But when its spirit fired the brain of an assassin, to plan
with fanatic deliberation, and execute with fiendish calmness, the
murder of the nation's president, infused the vengeful hate, which
sought by dying fraud the chamber of a wounded, well-nigh dying
officer of State, and stabbed him in his helplessness, then the last
drop in the cup of the national forbearance was wrung out; and the cry
went up, not loud and fierce, but deep, and solemn, and inexorable as
the doom of fate, that "Slavery and treason, both and together, were
forever to be cleansed away from our land." And thus, what long years
of war had failed to do, what right and reason had not been able to
accomplish, what else--had ABRAHAM LINCOLN lived--might have been only
partially effected, was sealed and established in his dying, as
clearly as the doom of Babylon was written, by the hand of God, upon
the palace of Belshazzar.</p>
               <pb n="18"/>
               <p pn="18">
                  <figure entity="garrison18">
                     <figDesc>18th page
of Rev. J. F. Garrison's The Teachings of the
Crisis.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <p pn="18">Such we believe to be the two great facts, one demonstrated
in the life and the other established by the death of ABRAHAM
LINCOLN. And none, since the Reformation made man's conscience free,
and purified religion, will for a moment bear comparison in actual
importance, or after influence, with these, in which our Martyred
President, though "being dead, yet speaketh," and to the end of time
will speak. They tell the coming ages that the people of the nations
must be governed, not by might and tyranny, but right and justice:
they ring the knell of slavery, and wipe away its curse and stain from
our borders, and make our land in truth, as it has been in name, a
land of Liberty: And when, in after times, the thoughts of men turn
back to read the ways of God in history, the name of ABRAHAM LINCOLN
will forever stand among the high historic landmarks of the race, to
give undying witness to the precious truths for which our people
struggled and for which he died. </p>
               <p pn="18">We turn now in conclusion, for a moment, from this broader
field of national, and universal history, to note some of the lessons,
which this solemn time should teach ourselves, as individuals. We name
but two, one suggested by the nature of our government; the other by
the event which has assembled us together.</p>
               <p pn="18">I. If we are to continue as a free people, it can be only
as a moral, and religious people. The government of a free people
must, of necessity, be the expression of the prevailing principles and
character of those it represents. If our citizens are in any large
proportion dishonest, or otherwise immoral, the officers they choose,
will be the same; and such men always will abuse the government,
<pb n="19"/>
                  <figure entity="garrison19">
                     <figDesc>19th page of
Rev. J. F. Garrison's The Teachings of the Crisis.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
to further their own evil purposes, and in the end, will bring it to
inevitable ruin. And no nation will continue for a course of
generations, so generally moral as to shun these dangers, unless there
be a constant, and pervading influence of the higher power of
religion. The life of our country all depends on this. If we fail
here, our national prosperity will wither from the root; no
statesmanship can save us long; no present strength can give us any
guarantee for our future. Here is a field where every individual in
the nation, however humble, can contribute his proportion to the
permanent prosperity, and life of our Government. God lays on every
one a part of this responsibility. Mothers should train their children
to the loftiest patriotism, by founding it upon Religion, by teaching
them that the bad man cannot be the good citizen; and, as they learn
to love their country above all earthly things, making them to feel,
that they can only serve it rightly, when they are inspired and guided
by the higher love of God. And here too, young men, and old may work
together, side by side, in the same good endeavor, conducing to the
nation's health, by living as God-fearing men; and in the practice of
a christian life displaying those pure, and holy principles, which at
the same time are the truest ornament of manhood, the highest duty of
the citizen, and the most vital need of their own present and eternal
being.</p>
               <p pn="19">II. "God's ways are not as our ways." In the presence of
his judgments we can only stand in wondering silence, and sob, "Thy
will be done." In such dark hours, we feel the need of faith; and
faith is our only comfort; the wisest man, at such a time, is only</p>
               <lg type="stanza">
                  <l>"An infant crying in the night,</l>
                  <l>An infant crying for the light,</l>
                  <l>And with no language but a cry."</l>
               </lg>
               <pb n="20"/>
               <p pn="20">
                  <figure entity="garrison20">
                     <figDesc>20th page
of Rev. J. F. Garrison's The Teachings of the
Crisis.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <p pn="20">All our hope is trust in God, belief that he is wise and
good, and "doeth all things well." And though we may not see his
plans, and cannot read his purposes, yet if we trust his love,--we
know that,</p>
               <lg type="stanza">
                  <l>"Somehow good</l>
                  <l>Will be the final goal of ill "--</l>
               </lg>
               <p pn="20">and in the darkness of our ignorance, we only draw more closely to
his side, and rest more firmly on the comfort of his promises. Thus
would we feel, and thus would we have you all feel to-day; and as we
go abroad again, from these sad scenes, to mingle in the busy crowd of
men, may we bear ever with us, the abiding sense, that our only help
as individuals, or as a nation is the sustaining love of God, our
highest duty, heartfelt obedience to the Saviour: to whom be glory,
now and ever, world without end--Amen.</p>
            </div2>
         </div1>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI.2>