<TEI.2>
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt n=" The Uniter and Liberator of America">
            <title>  The Uniter and
Liberator of America </title>
            <author>Haven, Gilbert</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Compiled and edited by</resp>
               <name>Beck
Center</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent/>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Lewis H. Beck Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Emory University</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Atlanta,
Georgia</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>1996 Emory
University. Permission is granted to download, transmit, or otherwise
reproduce, distribute or display the contributions to the work claimed
by Emory University for non-profit educational purposes, provided
this header is included in its entirety.  For inquiries about
commercial uses, contact the Director, 
Pitts Theology Library, Emory
University, Atlanta, Georgia 30322</p>
            </availability>
            <date>1999</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Lincoln
Sermons Project</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Haven,
Gilbert. The Uniter and Liberator of America. A Memorial Discourse on
the Character and Career of Abraham Lincoln: Delivered in the North
Russell Street M. E. Church, Boston, Sunday, April 23, 1865.  Boston:
James P. Magee, No. 5 Cornhill. 1865.  </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This text derives from the Special Collections 
of Pitts Theology Library, Emory University, and is produced in 
collaboration with the Lewis H. Beck Center a, the Emory 
Preservation Office, and Pitts Theology Library.</p>
            <p>TRANSCRIBER: Lewis H. Beck Center and Emory University 
Preservation Office.</p>
            <p>PRODUCER:  BookLab, Inc., 1606 Headway Circle, 
Suite 100, Austin, TX 78754</p>
            <p>CAPTURE DEVICE: XEROX DocuImage 620S flatbed scanner</p>
            <p>CAPTURE DETAILS: Scanner software: XEROX ScanTool 
version 4.2.3; no gamma correction; images are all bitonal.</p>
            <p>CHANGE HISTORY: Using the Adobe Photoshop Batch Processor, 
we interpolated  the original TIFF files to 8-bit grays, 
and altered the resolution to 144 dpi, producing screen 
images twice the original size.  We then saved them in 
JPEG format.  We produced GIF thumbnails from the JPEG files.</p>
            <p>RESOLUTION: 600 ppi</p>
            <p>COMPRESSION: Resolution 144 per inch with Constrain 
Properties to 72 per inch.</p>
            <p>SOURCE: Original documents.</p>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>1999</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Scott Ellis</name>
               <resp>Staff</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <item>SGML tags inserted in compliance
with TEI guidelines using TEILITE</item>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div1 id="haven.001" n="The Uniter and Liberator of America" type="text">
            <head pn="1"> 
               <bibl> 
                  <title>The Uniter and
Liberator of America</title> 
                  <date>Sunday, April 23, 1865</date>
                  <pubPlace>North Russell Street M. E. Church, Boston</pubPlace>
                  <author>Haven, Gilbert</author> 
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Boston</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>James P. Magee</publisher>
                     <date>1865</date>
                  </imprint>
               </bibl> 
            </head>
            <p pn="1">
               <figure entity="haven1">
                  <figDesc>1st page of Gilbert Haven's The
Uniter and Liberator of America.</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <p pn="1">THE UNITER AND LIBERATOR OF AMERICA.</p>
            <p pn="1">A</p>
            <p pn="1">MEMORIAL DISCOURSE</p>
            <p pn="1">ON THE</p>
            <p pn="1">CHARACTER AND CAREER</p>
            <p pn="1">OF</p>
            <p pn="1">ABRAHAM LINCOLN:</p>
            <p pn="1">DELIVERED IN THE</p>
            <p pn="1">NORTH RUSSELL STREET M.E. CHURCH, BOSTON,</p>
            <p pn="1">SUNDAY, APRIL 28, 1865,</p>
            <p pn="1">BY</p>
            <p pn="1">GILBERT HAVEN.</p>
            <p pn="1">"A laborer with moral virtues girt, <lb/>With spiritual graces, like
a glory, crowned."</p>
            <p pn="1">BOSTON:</p>
            <p pn="1">JAMES P. MAGEE, NO. 5 CORNHILL.</p>
            <p pn="1">1865.</p>
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p pn="2">
               <figure entity="haven2">
                  <figDesc>2nd page of
Gilbert Haven's The Uniter and Liberator of
America.</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <p pn="2">AT the close of the morning service in the North Russell Street
Methodist Episcopal Church, Sunday, April 23, the undersigned was
solicited to take the chair; whereupon, on motion, it was unanimously
voted by the congregation to request the pastor, Rev. Mr. Haven, to
furnish a copy of the discourse just delivered, on the character and
career of President Lincoln, for publication.</p>
            <p pn="2">
               <lb/>JOHN H. COLLINS.<lb/>
BOSTON, May 1, 1865.</p>
            <p pn="2">Cambridge Press.</p>
            <p pn="2">DAKIN AND METCALF.</p>
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p pn="3">
               <figure entity="haven3">
                  <figDesc>3rd page of
Gilbert Haven's The Uniter and Liberator of
America.</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <div2 id="haven.002" n="SERMON" type="sermon">
               <head pn="3">SERMON.</head>
               <epigraph pn="3">
                  <p pn="3">Thy gentleness hath made me great. Ps. xviii. 35.</p>
                  <p pn="3">He saved others, himself he cannot save. Matt. xxvii. 42.</p>
                  <p pn="3">All nations shall call him blessed. Ps. lxxii. 17.</p>
               </epigraph>
               <p pn="3">The appalling deed of the last Good Friday begins to put on
the fixed lineaments of the past. As that face and form, then so full
of life, are frozen in death, so he who animated them is fast becoming
solidified and shapen in the unchanging marble of history.</p>
               <p pn="3">Still standing in the horrible shadow, how can we carve the
features of the immortal dead? The chisel shakes in our trembling
hand. The rain of sorrow blinds our eyes. In the ghastly darkness, we
but faintly discern the spiritual form that has so suddenly been
struck from its earthly home and has forever vanished from the eyes of
man. He, who but yesterday was the centre of all human observation;
whose every word, as he himself declared but three nights before his
death, was in no unimportant sense a national decree; from whom were
the issues of life and death to the imperious leaders of the rebellion
and their too willing subjects; upon whose course foreign potentates
fastened watchful eyes, and foreign peoples were yet more intent; the
foremost man in all the world;--now lies he low in his bloody
shroud. A nation weeps around his bier. The world bemoans his
fate. Never before did so wide and bitter a cry pierce the
skies. Never before were the heads of so many millions, waters, and
their eyes fountains
<pb n="4"/>
                  <figure entity="haven4">
                     <figDesc>4th page of Gilbert Haven's
The Uniter and Liberator of America.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
of tears, weeping day and night for the slain of the daughter of their
people. The great day of the Church has become yet more solemn in the
annals of America. Let not the fifteenth of April be considered the
day of his death, but let Good Friday be its anniversary. For then the
fatal blow was struck. He died to the conscious world ere the day had
died. We should make it a movable fast, and ever keep it beside the
cross and the grave of our blessed Lord, in whose service and for
whose gospel he became a victim and a martyr.</p>
               <p pn="4">That crime I cannot dwell upon in such an hour. The
criminal is not the object of my revenge. Justice will demand his
death,--to whom no less would it be a mercy; for it would shut him
from the sight of the race he had dishonored and the earth he had
polluted, and cast him into the congenial fellowship of his spiritual
and eternal companions in rebellion and in sin. Not the awful
transgressor nor his crime, not even the gigantic abomination of which
this deed was the natural and inevitable fruit, shall becloud the
hour. Let us look the rather upon him whose earthly work is done; not
upon his form, laid out in   "long-stretching death," that is slowly
moving amid tearful myriads, through mighty cities, by the side of
inland seas, across yet vaster seas of billowy or level green, to its
beloved home in the heart of the land, fit resting-place for him who
shall ever live in the heart of the nation: but upon the features of
his life, that we may learn why he grew to such a height, and how we
may, in our humbler sphere, attain an equal perfection.</p>
               <p pn="4">The Character and Career of Abraham Lincoln will therefore
be the appropriate subject of our mournful meditations. These are
harmoniously united. His career was but the flowering of his
character,--his character the seed and germ of his
career. Extraordinary circumstances gave that nature a fulness of
opportunity for its development such as has most rarely, probably
never before, fallen to the lot of man; but they did not make the
man. The
<pb n="5"/>
                  <figure entity="haven5">
                     <figDesc>5th page of Gilbert Haven's
The Uniter and Liberator of America.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
most fruitful ground does not create the character of the seed it
multiplies. It imparts a possibility of richness and fulness that
inferior earths cannot afford. Still their own nature abides, and the
oak is an oak, the ivy an ivy, in the richest as well as in the
poorest soils.</p>
               <p pn="5">His character was as complete when wrapped in the vesicle
of his early privacy as in the grand uplifts of its wonderful
consummations. As a child, a youth, an industrious, studious, obscure
workman, a lawyer, politician, and statesman of Illinois, he displayed
the peculiar qualities which in his higher sphere bore such abundant
fruit. His first speech was as brief, as witty, as compact, as
simple-minded and as good-natured as his last.</p>
               <p pn="5">For these traits he is not to be praised. He was created in
the frame of soul that he ever exhibited. For their culture he alone
merits eulogy.</p>
               <p pn="5">God needs various workmen for his varied work. And as a
wise master-builder uses a great variety of material for his manifold
edifice, and works this material into a yet greater variety of forms,
that the whole may be a unit of perfection; so does the Divine
Master-builder in his infinitely grander structures of soul, erected
on earth for time and for eternity.</p>
               <p pn="5">The stately cathedral has its messy stone, lying in huge
boulders under its visible foundations, rising in shapen blocks to its
roof and pinnacles, carved in daintiest delicacy around its pillars,
doors, and altar. This solid earth it lightens with graceful forms of
wood, as though the heart of oak blossomed like the gentlest flower
into fragrant beauty. These are yet more relieved by tints that flush
the cold face of stone with life, and this vitality puts on its
highest expression in the scenes, sacred and divine, into which the
walls change under the touch of the great masters, as the shapely face
of death becomes radiant with life and love under the inspiration of
its Creator.</p>
               <pb n="6"/>
               <p pn="6">
                  <figure entity="haven6">
                     <figDesc>6th page of
Gilbert Haven's The Uniter and Liberator of
America.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <p pn="6">Thus does God build up the nation and the world. Thus does
He use every style of character, every quality of spirit in His
sublime cathedral of man, which He is patiently and persistently
erecting, in truth and love, out of a redeemed and regenerated
humanity, on the earth and in the heavens.</p>
               <p pn="6">I. What, then, were the traits of soul which this eminent
agent in the plan divine received from God and faithfully, usefully,
and rewardfully developed?</p>
               <p pn="6">1. We should only respond to the sentiment of every heart,
hostile or friendly, when we place at the foundation of his character,
honesty. This was his familiar appellation in obscurity. It has been
none the less so in the greatness of his exaltation. Yet it fails to
express the whole idea which it strives to embody. That is the rude,
ungainly trunk, which, despite its rough exterior, is both the
upholder and the nourisher of all the attractions that rejoice above
it. It branches out in graceful boughs, with their rustling robes of
green. It turns under the smiles of spring into an orb of odorous
flowers. It depends in an autumn ripeness of golden fruit.</p>
               <p pn="6">Honesty in him was not the calculating wisdom of the world
as shown in its favorite and unworthy employment of that word. It was
not from selfish policy that he was honest. Such honesty is really
most dishonorable. It meant in him its true and original
signification. It was sincerity, simplicity, impartiality, honor; in
fine, the scriptural conception of this nature, guilelessness. If ever
a man lived of whom it could be said he was without guile, that man
was Abraham Lincoln. Look down as deep as you may into his profound
nature, you will see that it is clear as a moteless fountain. It may
seem to be shallow, it is so pure; and yet a second sight convinces
you that though your eyes are sounding deeply, they touch not the
bottom. As you look skywards on a clear day, you first fancy that you
sweep the whole depth of the
<pb n="7"/>
                  <figure entity="haven7">
                     <figDesc>7th page of Gilbert Haven's
The Uniter and Liberator of America.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
dome with your glance; a second and more penetrating gaze shows you
that you have only caught its lowest outlines. As it rises heights
above heights, you exclaim,--</p>
               <lg type="stanza">
                  <l>"The <hi rend="italic">chasm</hi> of sky above my head</l>
                  <l>Is
Heaven's profoundest azure,</l>
                  <l>	. . . . . an <hi rend="italic">abyss</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>In which the everlasting stars
abide."</l>
               </lg>
               <p pn="7">Thus do you gaze into this pellucid nature. It is as simple
and open as a child's, yet you cannot penetrate it; not because it
interposes barriers to your gaze, but because your vision fails. It is
none the less clear because it is so deep. Could you look farther, you
would find the same nature, honest, unselfish, childlike; "an
Israelite indeed, in whom is no guile."</p>
               <p pn="7">The soul of this characteristic is absence of
selfishness. That is the root of guile. Though not without the
temptations common to all men, he was remarkably free from this
propensity. This freedom from self-seeking is the more noticeable in
contrast with the characters of most great men. Milton declares
ambition "the last infirmity of noble minds." This passion implies a
subtle love of self, and frequently mars the most exalted
natures. Only one President before him seemed almost utterly free from
it. Jefferson talked indifference, but was a ceaseless schemer and
mover of political wires while professedly absorbed in his laboratory,
study, and farm. Adams, Franklin, Jackson, Clay, were men of great
parts, but a sense of their necessity to the movements of the nation
gave to their strength the weakness of men. Their personality was to
them an <hi rend="italic">essential</hi> element in the events of their
age. Not so with Washington and Lincoln. They were the priests placed
over the abyss divine. The breath of God bore them onward in the
accomplishment of his purposes. They were his willing servants, but
servants only. They were
<pb n="8"/>
                  <figure entity="haven8">
                     <figDesc>8th page of Gilbert Haven's
The Uniter and Liberator of America.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
not necessary to his success. Each looked forward to the hour when the
Master should take from them the harness and allow them to repose
peacefully in the quiet of their homes. Each felt that others had
greater wisdom than they. Each bent his ear kindly to hear what their
more creative minds should say. Each sincerely sought the truth. Other
men of might feel that they have the truth. They do not seek it. It
comes to them. It is an inspiration. They must declare it or die. "Woe
is me," cry Phillips and Everett, cry Sumner and Beecher, cry Greeley
and Weed, "if I preach not that which I feel stirring within me." The
President had no such call. He waited to hear their words. In
sincerity of heart he deliberated, decided, acted.</p>
               <p pn="8">This trait gave him that slowness of action, which was not
unlike the stammering of Moses. He must hear the voice thrice ere he
obeyed it. He must consider as he cannot create, deliberate as he does
not divine.</p>
               <p pn="8">2. But this guilelessness of heart and impartiality of
judgment were joined to great faithfulness in adhering to the truths
he had espoused. His step was as firm as it was careful. Having done
all, he stood. Hampden's motto might properly have been his,--<hi rend="italic">Nulla vestigia retrorsum</hi>. No step did he ever take
backward. Men of ideas often fail when those ideas are born into
actual life, and the Herods rise up for their destruction. They are
bold in the closet and the forum, but timid in the field. Demosthenes
was not only the greatest orator of Athens, he was her greatest
democrat; none of her men of might equalled him in courageous defence
of, and adhesion to, her central doctrine. And yet when she must
sustain her idea at Chaeronea, he fled before the legions of monarchy,
and denied in shame the faith for which he had so valiant--a Roman in
the forum, but not at the front.</p>
               <pb n="9"/>
               <p pn="9">
                  <figure entity="haven9">
                     <figDesc>9th page of
Gilbert Haven's The Uniter and Liberator of
America.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <p pn="9">So have been many idealists and reformers. Their shields
have been thrown away when the enemy assailed them. Such are not the
most renowned. They have the strength of soul both to create and to
sustain. Socrates, Huss, Luther, Paul, could fight as well as
speak,--die as heroically as they lived. Still this faithfulness is
more sure to be revealed in those who accept the truth in full view of
the perils it involves. Who takes the oath of allegiance before the
enemy's guns, will be apt to abide by it in the succeeding
charge. Lincoln believed in these truths from the beginning. But he
did not embrace them as objects of duty till he saw the whites of the
enemy's eyes, as they were rushing upon him to his evident
destruction. Then, seizing them as if they were, as they were, loaded
cannon, he henceforth used them steadily and valiantly in repelling
and discomfiting his foe.</p>
               <p pn="9">This trait was the more necessary in the tremendous
fluctuation of popular feeling and current events. When the waves
roared and were troubled, when the mountains shook with the swelling
thereof, it was well for the nation that one held the helm who steered
carefully, but calmly and steadily; who, if he did not hasten, did not
go back; if he did not so soon as we prayed make the desired haven,
never ran his vessel back upon tile breakers we had passed. His
faithfulness was one of his most admirable and most necessary
traits.</p>
               <p pn="9">3. We should be unjust to his character if we shrank from
noticing his playfulness. In common with many superior minds, he was
as sportful as a lamb. He liked a good story better than a great
honor. No one ever more enjoyed</p>
               <lg type="stanza">
                  <l>"Jests and youthful jollity, </l>
                  <l>Quips and cranks and
wanton wiles,</l>
                  <l>Nods and becks and wreathed smiles,</l>
                  <l>Sport that wrinkled care derides,</l>
                  <l>And laughter holding both
his sides."</l>
               </lg>
               <pb n="10"/>
               <p pn="10">
                  <figure entity="haven10">
                     <figDesc>10th page of
Gilbert Haven's The Uniter and Liberator of
America.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <p pn="10">A merry twinkle ever sat in his eyes. Ever when saddest
with sorrow, a ray of this sunlight played on their salt
drops. Napoleon, Luther, Socrates, Cicero, Caesar, Wesley, Franklin,
Webster, many great men, were of this nature. A jest-book attributed
to Cicero was current in Rome long after his death. Caesar was ever
pointing his speech with these glittering specialties. Napoleon was
full of mirth and jokes, even on the night before Waterloo. Their
bon-mots were as brilliant as their battles. Lincoln, next to
Franklin, if next, was the most famous jester of America. Each of
these ever used a witty story to point an argument; and many was the
laughable word uttered by the great diplomat of the Revolution, that
did the people of that sad hour good like a medicine.</p>
               <p pn="10">This playfulness was not unmanliness. It was the relief of
an intensely overstrained nature,--the pleasant bloom of childhood
dancing on the brow of age,--the reminiscence of the past, and
prophecy of the future, that kept his heart green and juicy amid the
furnace of fire, heated seven times hotter than ever before, where he
was called of God to walk. It was an important element in his
career. Without it, neither he nor the people could have walked
erect. Those mirthful, melancholic stories creeping out on the top of
great disasters, like light playing over graves, relieved the people
in their terrific gloom. Not that he did not weep. No president ever
wept so much. Not that he did not soberly gird himself to his fearful
responsibilities. None ever wrought so patiently and persistently. But
by a pleasantry he lightened his and our bursting hearts that would
otherwise have sunk like lead in the mighty waters. His most famous
story had in it the whole point of the controversy. Secretary Seward's
more statesman-like declaration of the same necessity is hardly
remembered,--that, having been elected President of the United States,
he must
<pb n="11"/>
                  <figure entity="haven11">
                     <figDesc>11th page of Gilbert
Haven's The Uniter and Liberator of America.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
be acknowledged as such by all the States; Lincoln's had not a little
to do with his triumph.</p>
               <p pn="11">4. His integrity was remarkable. In fact, all the traits we
have mentioned, save perhaps the last, may be summed up in the one
word,--Integrity. Here is his honesty, his simplicity, his
impartiality, his steadfastness. He was an integer--a unit. His soul
was one. There was no disunion there,--no conflict there. Its surface
might be tossed, not its depths. He had doubts as to what policy to
pursue, and often changed it with the changing moment; but never, did
he doubt his country, his cause, himself. It was the spinal column,
that supported not him alone but the whole land. To it, as to a mighty
tower, the people fled and felt that they were safe. Thousands of
millions passed through his hand; no itching palm caught the most
soiled fragment of the tiniest currency. He assumed the errors, even
the asserted peculations, of his subordinates as his own. The country
smiled, but laid not the assumed sin to his charge. Its faith in his
rectitude was unbounded. The most envenomed shafts were never aimed at
that mark. Here, at least, his bitterest foes confessed that he was
invulnerable.</p>
               <p pn="11">5. But even this was not the seat of his strength. That lay
in his love. His gentleness made him great. Sincere, honorable,
faithful, true, he might have been, and yet not beloved. Franklin was
as mirthful, Washington as incorruptible, Adams as just, yet for none
of them did the people shed such floods of tears. Children and
graybeards, man and woman, slave and freeman, beggar and prince, all
poured forth their tributary tides of woe. "Behold how they loved
him!" will all Europe say, as they hear this exceeding bitter
wailing. It was because he loved them. The condition of the highest
love is essential here. We loved him because he first loved us. He was
the first President of the United States who seemed to carry in his
warm-
<pb n="12"/>
                  <figure entity="haven12">
                     <figDesc>12th page of Gilbert
Haven's The Uniter and Liberator of America.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
est heart the heart of all the people. The pertinacious, cold-blooded
leech of an office-seeker did not feel that he was answered in the
selfish spirit which inspired his zeal. There was a fatherly affection
even in the refusal. The bitter secessionist, even the relentless
rebel, found only gentleness and love in his eye and voice and
grasp. They were constrained to feel that they had become prodigals
from, nay enemies to, a most tender and still affectionate father.</p>
               <p pn="12">If these selfish or hostile men found such a welcome, how
much more did the loyal. The most degraded slave felt the warm clasp
of that paterna1 hand as a benediction. The most garrulous griefs were
poured into a sympathetic ear. His most patient heart allowed every
head to lie upon its broad, soft pillow. The people felt the
throbbings of that heart warmly beating for them, and, like a tired
child on its mother's bosom, sank confidently to rest.</p>
               <p pn="12">Far more than his sagacious judgment, incorruptible
integrity, and playful humor, did his deep affection for the nation
support and carry us through this darkest night of our history. It is
not his mother's knowledge of what is best for him, not her lightsome
nature, not her unceasing faithfulness, that makes the sick child
commit himself so confidently to her arms. It is her love that makes
him trustful. Her judgment may err, strength may yield, joy may flee,
but love never faileth. Many waters cannot quench it nor floods drown
it. His greatest weakness only increases its strength. His dying makes
it live forever.</p>
               <p pn="12">So has the nation rested in his loving arms. She knew that
his judgment was often at fault, however carefully he exercised it;
that sometimes even his strength of purpose almost trembled under the
fearful pressure to which it was subjected; that his pleasant smile
became sadness, and the sunny wrinkles were channels for many
tears. He had never spoken confidently of success. The mighty struggle
he feared might result disastrously; the sick na-
<pb n="13"/>
                  <figure entity="haven13">
                     <figDesc>13th page of Gilbert
Haven's The Uniter and Liberator of America.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
tion might die; but dying or living she felt that he loved her. That
quality of his soul was undiminished. Nay, it was the soul's self and
grew the stronger when all else grew weaker.</p>
               <p pn="13">Never did a great people so universally recognize and repay
such love in its ruler. Never did a ruler so love his people. Cromwell
loved religion first; Wellington, duty; England was the second in
their heart; her people, last. Napoleon loved himself, not France;
Caesar, power, not Rome; Washington, the right and the country more
than its people. All the great leaders of the revolution, all the
great living leaders, reformatory, civil, and military, are devoted to
the idea that controls them: this to liberty, that to union; this,
America's glory, that, her destiny; this, philanthropy, that, piety;
this, justice, that, honor; this, empire, that, prosperity. Not one of
them can in a peculiar, profound, and personal sense be said to love
the American people. That grace they want. Not that they do not love
the nation; far from it. All have, all do; but it is a general, not a
special regard; an affection that reveals itself in other forms than
mere love. Not so with our great President. He held every one in his
heart of hearts; he felt a deep and individual regard for each and
all; he wept over the nation's dead boys at Gettysburg as heartily as
over his own dead boy at Washington. Their death, more than his own
child's, was the means of bringing him into an experimental
acquaintance with Christ. That sorrow wrought in him a godly sorrow,
which has become a joy forever.</p>
               <p pn="13">Here then may we properly conclude his portraiture. It
arises, like that of Him in whose image he and all of us are made,
into the heights of love. Without profanity we may say Abraham Lincoln
is love. By that nature will the future hail him. A John among the
disciples, he, of all our public men, the most truly possessed and
expressed the nature of his Lord and Master. Without revenge, without
malice, without hardness or bitterness of
<pb n="14"/>
                  <figure entity="haven14">
                     <figDesc>14th page of Gilbert
Haven's The Uniter and Liberator of America.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
heart, he held loyal and disloyal, grave and master, black and white,
rebel soldier and rebel leader, in his equal love. Had his dying lips
been allowed to utter one sentence, we think it would have been the
dying words of Christ; and for his assassin he would have prayed,
"Father, forgive him, for he knows not what he does."</p>
               <p pn="14">It was for this trait that such mourning bows the land; for
this are the streets of his funereal journey lined thick with weeds of
sorrow, thicker with mourning multitudes; for this do the subdued eyes
of millions of strong, cool men,</p>
               <lg type="stanza">
                  <l>"Albeit unused to the melting mood,</l>
                  <l>Drop tears as fast as the Arabian trees</l>
                  <l>Their medicinal gum."</l>
               </lg>
               <p pn="14">It was for this preeminently that the despised race, free
or slave, pour forth their most piteous lamentations. Their tears of
joy but yesterday are almost tears of blood to-day. He was the first
President that took one of them kindly by the hand; the first that
acknowledged their equal right with every other citizen to his
official recognition. He was not merely their military liberator,
breaking their bonds only because he could thus deliver himself from
his enemies; but he was their friend and their father, carrying them
in the same paternal arms in which he bore the rest of his
children. Well may they cry out, as they see him thus suddenly leap
into a chariot of fire and ascend to his reward, "My father! my
father!" Well may they bewail because of him!</p>
               <p pn="14">For this do ten thousand steeples knell their pathetic
minor, while all listening hearts, as never before, beat
responsive:</p>
               <lg type="stanza">
                  <l>"Keeping time, time, time,</l>
                  <l>In a sort of Runic rhyme</l>
                  <l>To the throbbing of the bells,</l>
                  <l> Of the bells, bells, bells,</l>
                  <l>To the sobbing of the bells:</l>
               </lg>
               <pb n="15"/>
               <p pn="15">
                  <figure entity="haven15">
                     <figDesc>15th page of Gilbert
Haven's The Uniter and Liberator of America.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <lg type="stanza">
                  <l>Keeping time, time, time</l>
                  <l>To the rolling of the bells,</l>
                  <l>Of the bells, bells, bells,</l>
                  <l>To the tolling of the bells,</l>
                  <l>Of the bells, bells, bells, bells,</l>
                  <l>Bells, bells, bells,</l>
                  <l>To the moaning and the groaning of the
bells."</l>
               </lg>
               <p pn="15">Thus stands forth the character of this great man: of
unblanched and unbending soul; without selfishness, yet full of
feeling; without pride, yet ever regardful of the dignities of his
position; without ambition, yet ascending to the topmost heights of
sovereignty, and absorbing into himself more than dictatorial, far
more than imperial and kingly powers, without the least malice, yet
waging the bloodiest of wars; without boastful bitterness, yet making
myriads of his enemies lick the dust; whose most loving heart ever
irrigated, yet never drowned, his wise brain, making that, which is
often in others a verdureless summit, in him a well-watered garden,
full of choicest life.</p>
               <p pn="15">Such was the nature of him to whom the heart of the people
has gone out as never before to any ruler. They revered Washington,
they respected Adams, they believed Jefferson, they admired Jackson,
they loved Lincoln. God's gentleness had made him great.</p>
               <p pn="15">II. How this character revealed itself in his career, there
is no need that I should relate unto you. The details of that life
will be the theme for many a historian. Irvings will yet arise who
will devote their most graceful pen to the portraiture of this second
Washington. Carlyles will make the splendor of their genius glow
around the head of this greater than Frederic or Cromwell. Napoleons
will make him a more faithful study and model than Caesar. With every
luxury of art and wealth shall the grand career of the cabin-boy of
Kentucky, the Uniter and Liberator of America, stand in the libraries
of kings and statesmen, in
<pb n="16"/>
                  <figure entity="haven16">
                     <figDesc>16th page of Gilbert
Haven's The Uniter and Liberator of America.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
humbler shape and larger love, on the shelves of all their people
whose future that life both illustrated and assured.</p>
               <p pn="16">1. Two dangers threatened the land when he assumed the
reins of government,--disunion and slavery. The Scylla and Charybdis
were on either side of the tossed and leaky vessel, when he took the
helm. Fierce broke the waves on the rocky Scylla of disunion; fiercely
did the Charybdian sands of slavery threaten to suck the ship in their
shifting and ceaseless maelström. Both in influence invaded the
whole land. A great party in the North supported disunion under the
specious phrases of State sovereignty and no coercion; while all the
land alike hated the slave and his kindred, and refused to touch, in
the least, the iniquity or its victims. The President shared the
feelings of the last, if not the sentiments of the first. His
predecessor yet occupying the seat of government, if government it
might be called which he had ceased to govern, was calling on the
people to fast and pray, that the wayward sisters might return. Great
men carried monstrous petitions wrapped in the powerless American flag
and laid them before Congress, entreating that body to consent to the
nationalizing of slavery by giving it the best half of our territory
and all our constitution. The most widely circulated paper in the land
declared for the Montgomery constitution, and had its rebel rag
already to fling to the breeze when Fort Sumter should be attacked,
the nation utterly cowed, the government overthrown, and Jefferson
Davis made president of the twenty-seven Confederate States of
America,--New England alone being excluded from the general
league. She might be permitted, if she chose, to retain the belittled
title of the United States, with its plucked eagle and lowered
flag,--the Switzerland of America,--safe only in the contempt of her
tyrannous neighbors, wide ruling the continent.</p>
               <p pn="16">Beneath all this turbulence was the crowded dungeon of
slavery. Its imprisoned millions toiled and suffered, and sighed and
prayed,
<pb n="17"/>
                  <figure entity="haven17">
                     <figDesc>17th page of Gilbert
Haven's The Uniter and Liberator of America.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
and saw visions and dreamed dreams such as the despised Galileans saw
in Jerusalem when prelate and Pilate, ignorant and scornful, were
seeking, by reconciliation and compromises, the union of the God of
the Hebrews with the idols of Rome. What cared we for these? "Touch
slavery where it is?" Never! "Free the slaves?" "Hang him who dreams
that dream." "Up with John Brown and his crazy gang, who fancied
himself the Moses of this abominable Israel."--How that first martyr
but now welcomed the last to the rest and reward of the faithful!
Brothers in this service, they shal1 be brothers in heavenly fruition
and eternal renown.--"Abolish slavery instantly and forever?"
"Impossible. The slaves will cut their master's throats, will invade
the North and expel our laboring population, will be the vagabonds of
the continent."</p>
               <p pn="17">Thus warred the elements.</p>
               <lg type="stanza">
                  <l>"Who shall calm the angry storm?</l>
                  <l>Who the mighty task perform</l>
                  <l>And bid the raging tumult cease?"</l>
               </lg>
               <p pn="17">We pay no unwarranted eulogy to President Lincoln when we
declare that the peculiar qualities of his nature adapted him to this
especial work. We well understand that God was beneath and above all
this chaos, breaking the grievous yoke of his children and moving this
unwilling nation into higher spheres of life and duty. But he works
ever through instruments, and as we properly study the relation of the
human nature of Moses, of David, of Paul, to the work he laid upon
them, so may we that of our leader to what he was set to do.</p>
               <p pn="17">(1.) We see how admirably that nature was fitted for its
first and most important work,--the uniting the North. Whatever other
duties should arise ere the gigantic task was completed, the first
duty evidently was to make the loyal States one. They were weakened by
the severing of Southern ties. The whole structure
<pb n="18"/>
                  <figure entity="haven18">
                     <figDesc>18th page of Gilbert
Haven's The Uniter and Liberator of America.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
rocked to its base. North-western, Pacific, Central, and North-eastern
confederacies were projected. Even cities threatened to assume their
independence. The Mayor of New York publicly declared that no troops
should pass through her streets, no cannon leave her wharves for the
coercion of the rebellious States. Unless we could be united, the
whole was lost. There was otherwise no fulcrum upon which to plant the
lever of emancipation,--no means of staying the movement of disunion;
while to secure the Union was to destroy slavery, as every rebel
knew. Therefore this must be done.</p>
               <p pn="18">His conciliatory character, joined with his perfect
simplicity and integrity, was the centre around which the Union
sentiment rallied. The people felt that they could trust him with
their liberties, for he would not abuse the trust. The hostile party
found it hard to complain of so paternal a despot. They might rave at
his acts, but not at him. They saw that the salvation of the country
was his first and last concern; that he had no private or party ends
to serve, but only those of God, his country's, and truth's. He
addressed them kindly and generously, as in his letter to the
democrats of New York,--being, we presume, the first great ruler in
this or any land who wrote letters to his people as frankly as to his
family. He thus brought many of their leaders to his side, so that in
his army and in his cabinet, as well as in less prominent but hardly
less important fields, many of these earnest foes of his party became
his warmest supporters. General Butler and General Dix, Senator
Dickinson and Edward Everett, Secretary Stanton and Senator Douglas,
with thousands of others, gave him their earnest and cordial
support.</p>
               <p pn="18">His conciliatory nature is strikingly seen in the
composition of his first cabinet. It contained all of his rivals for
the nomination, with one exception, that of General Banks, and he
would undoubtedly have had the bureau for New England, had he not taken
<pb n="19"/>
                  <figure entity="haven19">
                     <figDesc>19th page of Gilbert
Haven's The Uniter and Liberator of America.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
up his residence in the West. Such a combination of independent and
leading minds, rivals of each other and their head, has never been
seen in this land since the first cabinet of Washington, which
embraced in it three rivals of each other, if not of him,--three
favorites of the nation for his chair; two of whom sat in it, and the
constitution was modified solely that the third could also,--an event
which might have happened but for his assassination by Aaron Burr.</p>
               <p pn="19">This course had the desired effect. The country rallied
round so gentle a leader, and the union of the yet undismembered
fragments was secured. The feeling of the land found expression in its
chief, and the various orders and mighty number of traitors yet with
us were compelled by popular sentiment, and sometimes by popular
violence, to conform to the general will.</p>
               <p pn="19">(2.) Then came the second step,--the conciliation of the
border. Each side essayed this work. Their sympathies and their sins
inclined them to the rebels, their instincts and obligations to the
nation. The presence of our army constrained its Eastern edge to our
side, the influence of ideas, its Western. The line swayed low in the
centre, and Kentucky became the battle-ground of this
sentiment. Slowly and surely the truth prevailed there. Against their
prejudices, their education, their habits, their institutions, they
ranged themselves under the flag.</p>
               <p pn="19">The openly rebellious region must be reduced only with
arms. How these fluctuated, and how they triumphed only when fortified
with the other and greater idea of the war, history will faithfully
show. Here his nature had no chance to exert its
influence. Generalship, not statesmanship, was what that work
demanded. It was, however, beginning to do so when his career
closed. He had other material than a discontented North or a divided
border to operate upon, and might have failed as completely there as
he had succeeded wonderfully before. Through his armies there, through
<pb n="20"/>
                  <figure entity="haven20">
                     <figDesc>20th page of Gilbert
Haven's The Uniter and Liberator of America.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
himself here, he had closed up the hideous rent secession had made,
and beheld North and South, East and West, again and forever, one. He
was the uniter of America.</p>
               <p pn="20">2. But a still greater danger, duty, and glory were before
him. We were an enslaved as well as a sundered people. The sighing of
the captive had upheaved the nation from its foundations. The closing
quotation of Mr. Sumner's first speech against our national sin was
being awfully fulfilled: "Beware of the groans of the wounded souls;
oppress not to the utmost a single heart; for a solitary sigh has
power to overset a whole world." We disregarded those sighs, not
solitary, but multitudinous and perpetual as the heavings of the sea,
and we were fast reeling to our downfall. To be set aright, this
dungeon must be opened. Its millions of innocent captives must go
free. This people must be our people, their God our God. How terrible
this task! It is ever easier to conquer our judgment than our
prejudice. We surrender our reason sooner than our heart. We hated, we
despised, we detested, the black man. We preferred slavery, with all
its horrors, to immediate and unconditional emancipation. So did
Mr. Lincoln. But God is greater than man, and to our martyred leader's
eternal honor shall it ever be said, God found him willing in the day
of his power. How slowly these steps were taken, how reluctantly, how
unbelievingly even, we all know. Yet taken they were. Like Jacob,
having so many feeble ones to carry, he must needs travel slowly, yet
he moved forward. Every day found him farther than before.</p>
               <p pn="20">Conciliation was his favorite feeling and policy. But that
cannot be adjusted to this most embittering duty. It must stand aside
for a season, and deeper traits must be brought into service. His
sense of right, the backbone of his nature, which alone made him
strong in the fearful strife, saw that there was no other path than
this. His training and his feelings
<pb n="21"/>
                  <figure entity="haven21">
                     <figDesc>21st page of Gilbert
Haven's The Uniter and Liberator of America.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
shrank from the negro; his desire to shun distracting elements made
him shrink from him yet the more; but duty said, "Go forward!
Pronounce the decree of emancipation! Let my people go! Take them by
your official hand and recognize them as yours!" And he obeyed.</p>
               <p pn="21">There was another great conciliator by his side, the head
of his armies, the worshipped of the land. He heard the like voice,
but refused to listen. Reconciliation and emancipation he declared
were impossible. He had the ear and the heart of the President. He
warned him, he threatened, he besought. Kentucky begged him to
desist. He would mar all her prospects of Union if he pursued that
course. The influential half of Missouri entreated. Many wise friends
from the North entreated. He hesitated till disaster overwhelmed the
chief adviser of this delay, till the volunteer inspiration had gone
out in blood, and the suggestion of a draft was met with scowls and
threats of defiance from every quarter. The ship was lying on her
beam-ends. All God's waves and billows were going over her. The rocks
of anarchy were thrusting their sharp fangs into her. Only the
throwing overboard of this demon can save her. He clung to the idol
yet a little, and made one more prayer to its worshippers to come into
the ship and save their god. They heard and jeered. They had a better
craft, built for the sole worship of their deity. They entered no
amalgamating vessel of freedom and slavery. He kept his word. Slavery
was tumbled into the bottomless gulf. The waves roared and hissed the
fiercer. Disunion broke its bands among us, and raged in the streets
of Northern cities. But all in vain. The ship of State began to right
itself. The voice of Christ calmed the sea. The rocks of disunion were
submerged, and the quicksands of slavery disappeared forever from the
view. The slave became a man, a warrior,--will soon be a citizen, and,
merged in the currents of society, be lost in the indistinguishable
throng that,
<pb n="22"/>
                  <figure entity="haven22">
                     <figDesc>22nd page of Gilbert
Haven's The Uniter and Liberator of America.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
from all nations and lands, rejoice in the common blood and name of
America.</p>
               <p pn="22">Thus will he stand forth in all coming time. To him was
decreed the greatest honor history has conferred on man. His sole peer
is the father of our country; and he is not his superior. Alike in
many traits of character, alike in many points of career, they will
share together the reverent gratitude of succeeding generations. Their
statues will rise in every city, before every eye. The one delivered
the nation from the yoke of vassalage to a once paternal, but then
tyrannical power; the other released her from the deadlier grasp of a
once fraternal, but then far more tyrannical dominion. The one
organized her embryotic communities into States and a nation. The
other reorganized these belligerent republics into a solid and
perpetual union. The one liberated three millions of his own race from
foreign despotism; the other liberated another people than his
own--four millions of bound and bleeding victims--from a despotism
infinitely more horrible. The influence of both shall go forth for the
redemption and regeneration of all lands. The whole world shal1 sit
rejoicingly at the feet of Washington and Lincoln. Happy, proud
America! that from her soil sprang, over her soil reigned, in her soil
sleep, the two creators and redeemers, under God, of her land and of
the world.</p>
               <p pn="22">We will not dwell upon the defects in this character; for
the service it was set to do, it was fully competent: from other
service God has mercifully relieved it. As his prototype failed to see
and to carry out the full workings of the principle he
inaugurated,--as another Virginian was to be the perfecter of the
doctrine of democracy which God intended should here have complete
expression, and the great leader was removed so that his influence
might not embarrass this movement of Providence,--even so may this
second Washington have been summoned to his reward, in order that the
perfection of that democracy may the more speedily
<pb n="23"/>
                  <figure entity="haven23">
                     <figDesc>23rd page of Gilbert
Haven's The Uniter and Liberator of America.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
hasten forward. It could not perhaps have been done before. The
country had been so reduced by previous theories of State rights and
of long submission to an oligarchy of human flesh, that it could not
instantly know, much less discharge, its full duty. The web of the new
era might have been rent, had it been then subjected to severer
strain. But this crime has made its lace iron,--the Northern iron and
the steel,--and we shall henceforth be strong enough, we hope just
enough, to confer equal citizenship upon all the nation. We must not
only nor chiefly punish the rebellious leaders. This may be our
primary, though not our principal duty. The loyal freedman must have
his full rights as a man. For this is the new President raised up;
not, as most say, to be the juster judge, but to be the truer
democrat. The last involves the first. The conditions of the rebel and
his former slave, excepting slavery, must be reversed. No citizenship
for the rebel leader; perfect citizenship for his slave. No land for
the chiefs of the rebellion, homesteads for his loyal
bondmen. Expatriation, which was urged upon the negro, not three years
ago, must be enforced upon his master. The African had no rights these
would respect. These must have none the nation will respect. Outlawed,
homeless, exiled, let these once mighty rulers of the land thus
expiate their crime of treason, while their victims take their homes
and their crowns. The first shall be last, and the last, first.</p>
               <p pn="23">Whatever be the fate of the rebel, the enfranchisement of
the negro alone can renew that land. We have found that our salvation
could not be effected without the aid of their bullet. We shall yet
find that it cannot be preserved without the aid of their ballot. It
is impossible to hang, banish, or disfranchise the half a million
former aristocrats of the South. Neither confiscation of their lands
nor emancipation of their slaves can annihilate their power. They
cannot thus be prevented from vaulting into authority again. The white
serfs who have so faithfully fought their battles will assuredly
<pb n="24"/>
                  <figure entity="haven24">
                     <figDesc>24th page of Gilbert
Haven's The Uniter and Liberator of America.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
honor their military commanders with civic power. What can make and
keep them powerless? Negro suffrage. Nothing less, nothing more. Set
the four millions of the freedmen over against the six millions of
white peasantry, and let them grapple. We shall soon see who are the
real men of that region. These loyal masses will see to it that the
disloyal tyrants do not trouble the nation farther. They will be the
owners of the soil, and the masters of their masters. They shall rule
over their oppressors, and preserve thus the liberty, the unity, the
peace of America.</p>
               <p pn="24">To this consistent and complete democracy the new Jefferson
is summoned. If true to his principles, and triumphant over the base
prejudices of birth and breeding, he will shine by the side of his
forerunner, equal in service, gratitude, and fame. We trust that he
will be thus faithful, and that we shall grow as steadily after the
divine pattern in the healthful sunshine of a hastening peace as in
the fearful midnight of the most bloody of wars.</p>
               <p pn="24">Let us not be blinded from higher duties by our just
vengeance against the assassin. His sin will quickly find him
out. That sin no death can adequately punish. Yet Booth is but a babe
in iniquity compared with Lee. The assassin never reigns in history by
the side of the rebellious chief. He has secured a horrible
notoriety. With Clytemnestra the assassinator of Agamemnon, king of
men; with Ravaillac, who slew the best king that France ever knew;
with "him who fired Ephesian's dome;" with the murderers of our
Lord,--he shall hang forever on the gibbet of infamy.</p>
               <p pn="24">Yet he was but the dagger's point; Lee is its polished
handle; slavery the force that drove it home. Shall we wreak our
vengeance on the bullet, and let him that fired it go free? The
miserable felon assassinated our leader. The yet unharmed general
attempted to assassinate the nation. We have been wrestling in his
murderous clutch for four years, and received innumerable
<pb n="25"/>
                  <figure entity="haven25">
                     <figDesc>25th page of Gilbert
Haven's The Uniter and Liberator of America.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
stabs in our attempts to prevent our destruction. Is the nation less
than one of its citizens? Shall we fawn upon her would-be murderer,
and tear his, in our rage, into a thousand atoms? Nay, he too is a
murderer. Not alone of the hundreds of thousands whom he has slain in
battle, but of the multitudes that he has starved to death in his
prisons. He has ridden daily under the walls of these charnel-houses
where they were perishing for a crust of bread, and never relented for
an instant at the piteous moanings that almost made the walls to
groan. When the bony arm of one of our boys was thrust between the
bars, he not daring to put his face there, knowing that the sentinel's
bullet would strike him dead, and a poor slave-woman thrusts a crust
of bread into his hand, that sentinel's bullet instantly spatters her
brains upon the sidewalk. And that guard was a soldier of Robert
E. Lee, a traitor colonel of the army of the United States, who,
despite of his barbarities to our men in the field, our captured
soldiers and these lowly creatures, whom we are, by the command of
God, especially required to protect, dwells among us unharmed, almost
in honor. What was the miserable actor's crime to his? Let us do
justice to the greatest traitors in our hand, as we shall to him if
Providence shall place him in our power.</p>
               <p pn="25">But whether we are firm or feeble, God will make both to
praise him. How marvellous are His ways! Out of unspeakable crimes He
has revealed his glory. Out of the violence of the slave-master has
come liberty to all he held in bondage; out of the attempted murderers
of the nation, a more perfect nationality; out of the successful
murder of its head, a sterner justice, a more thorough and speedy
regeneration. Thus has it been most strangely verified before all
nations, and in the experience of these transgressors, that</p>
               <lg type="stanza">
                  <l>"Power to the Oppressors of the world is
given,</l>
                  <l>A might of which they dream not. Oh, the curse,</l>
               </lg>
               <pb n="26"/>
               <p pn="26">
                  <figure entity="haven26">
                     <figDesc>26th page of Gilbert
Haven's The Uniter and Liberator of America.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <lg type="stanza">
                  <l>To be the awakener of divinest thoughts,</l>
                  <l>Father and Founder of exerted deeds,</l>
                  <l>And to whole nations, bound in servile straits,</l>
                  <l>The liberal Donor of capacities</l>
                  <l>More than heroic! This to be, nor yet</l>
                  <l>Have sense of one connatural wish, nor yet</l>
                  <l>Deserve the least return of human thanks;</l>
                  <l>Winning no recompense but deadly hate</l>
                  <l>With pity mixed, astonishment with scorn."</l>
               </lg>
               <p pn="26">Such is the fate of Davis, Lee, and Booth. Living or dead,
among men or devils, they have the painful consciousness of having
been the unwilling instruments of the very ends they strove to
frustrate. They have united, liberated, fraternized America, and yet
are and ever shall be linked with Pharaoh, and Judas, and Caiaphas,
and Pilate, the most execrated and execrable of men.</p>
               <p pn="26">Thus have all things worked together for our good, so far
as we have loved God. From the beginning has he held us in his
hand. He has ever prevented our sins from destroying us. Good and evil
were in our earliest history, as in our latest. Raleigh and the
slave-trade gave their contrary impress to Virginia; the pilgrims and
persecution to Massachusetts; Huguenots and slavery to South Carolina;
the Dutch greed of gain and love of liberty to New York. The wheat and
the tares have grown together until now. Yet always has he been
guarding the wheat from utter spoliation. He has eliminated the evil,
and educed the good; he has made our sins and our sufferings go hand
in hand, our penitence and our progress; he has changed New England
intolerance into firmness for the right, New York greediness of wealth
into rivers of beneficence. He will change Virginia slave-trade into
righteous traffic, and South Carolina slavery into the grandest
liberty of this continent. The conscientious contraries shall also
become a harmonious whole. The Huguenot of Carolina and the Puritan of
New England, the Catholic of Mary-
<pb n="27"/>
                  <figure entity="haven27">
                     <figDesc>27th page of Gilbert
Haven's The Uniter and Liberator of America.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
land and Episcopalian of Virginia, the Quaker of Pennsylvania and
Dutch Protestant of New York, the Baptist of Rhode Island and
Methodist of the prairies, shall yet form, not the broad, but the true
church of our Lord and Saviour Jesus Christ, on whose divine
foundation the nation shall stand in perpetual unity, holiness, and
love. Thus may we learn to more perfectly confide in His guidance and
grace who has so wonderfully revealed His constant presence in our
planting and our growth, and who has shown here, as elsewhere in His
kingdom,</p>
               <lg type="stanza">
                  <l>"That many things, having full
reference</l>
                  <l>To one consent, may work contrariously;</l>
                  <l>As many arrows, loosed several ways,</l>
                  <l>Come to one mark, as many ways meet in one
town,</l>
                  <l>As many fresh streams meet in one salt sea,</l>
                  <l>As many lives close in the dial's centre,</l>
                  <l>So may a thousand actions, once afoot,</l>
                  <l>End in one purpose."</l>
               </lg>
               <p pn="27">Let us then show our grief for our loss by greater
faithfulness to the cause for which he died. The grandeur of this
cause, in its past, present, and future, was remarkably revealed in
his most memorable word and most memorable deed, with which his career
was properly crowned. The last inaugural is that word,--the entry into
Richmond, the deed. That word is the most truthful, humble, and
Christian, that a ruler ever addressed to his people. There is the
clearest recognition of the divine will, the humblest prostration
before His offended goodness, the amplest confession of the
righteousness of His punishments, the largest beneficence to his own
most deadly foes.</p>
               <p pn="27">How sadly it prophesies his own fate! His too must be of
the blood which God requires from the sword to repay that drawn by the
lash, for two hundred years, from the shrinking flesh of His innocent
children.</p>
               <pb n="28"/>
               <p pn="28">
                  <figure entity="haven28">
                     <figDesc>28th page of
Gilbert Haven's The Uniter and Liberator of
America.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <p pn="28">His dying speech from the national throne will be read with
wet eyes by our children's children. As the farewell address of
Washington will ever be cherished by the nation, much more will this
more profound and pathetic confession of our sins, more resolute
expression of our duty and purpose to eradicate them, be admiringly
read by remotest generations. It lacks no element of perfection. So
short that he that runs may read it; so simple that the most childish
can understand it; so statesmanlike in its enunciation of principles
that the rulers of the world can profitably study it; so religious
that the most pious can find in it the holiest nutriment; so
philanthropic that largest souls can grow larger in its air; so
clement that the hardest heart cannot but melt in its perusal,--it is
the consummate dower of executive orations. Jeremiah could not wish it
more penitential, Ezekiel more resolute, John more affectionate.<ref target="haven.002.n01">*</ref></p>
               <p pn="28">It was a worthy requiem. He sung his swan's song, sad,
sacred, solemn, sweet. The voice of the ages from David to Christ went
wailing through the strain. It will yet be, as it should be, the most
popular and powerful word of America.</p>
               <p pn="28">But if the last inaugural was his litany, the advent into
Richmond was his jubilate. No picture of the war will be so frequently
painted. It was in extraordinary agreement with his whole life and
character, in extraordinary disagreement with that of every other
eminent ruler. Here was a more than emperor, who for four years had
waged severest war with a portion of his own people that</p>
               <note pn="28" id="haven.002.n01" n="*" place="foot" anchored="yes">
                  <p pn="28">The "London Spectator" truly says of him
and it,--"He has persevered through all obstacles, without ever giving
way to anger, or despondency, or exultation, or popular annoyance, or
sectarian fanaticism, or caste prejudice, visibly growing in force of
character, in self-possession and in magnanimity, till in his last
short message of the Fourth of March we can detect no longer the rude
and illiterate mould of a village lawyer's thought, but find it
replaced by a grasp of principle, a dignity of manner, and a solemnity
of purpose which would have been unworthy neither of Hampden nor of
Cromwell, while his gentleness and generosity of feeling towards his
foes are almost greater than we should expect of either of them."</p>
               </note>
               <pb n="29"/>
               <p pn="29">
                  <figure entity="haven29">
                     <figDesc>29th page of
Gilbert Haven's The Uniter and Liberator of
America.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <p pn="29">had made this their capital. Under many generals had he essayed its
capture. Blood had flowed around it like water. Yet it had still
proudly resisted the whole strength of his armies. At length, after
bloodiest encounters and almost a year of siege, it had fallen into
his hands. How should he take possession of his prize? How have all
conquerors exulted over such a conquest? When Charles the Bold
captured Liege, he compelled its citizens to batter down a new
entrance in their walls, through which he marches in triumphant pomp
and scorn. When Louis the Great's and David's generals reduced a
rebellious city, they sent for their royal masters to take stately
possession. Our grand monarch is near by when his great general, as
great as their greatest, has won for him the long-coveted prize, and
all the country is aflame with joy. Does he enter it in royal state?
He sends a grand deputation to take formal possession of rescued
Sumter. He himself walks up the streets of the capital of the
rebellion attended by twelve marines and half-a-dozen officers and
friends, without music or banners, or military or civic
pomp. Thousands of unshackled slaves dance around him in an
uncontrollable ecstasy of delight. They look upon the face of their
deliverer. To them it shines like that of Moses as he descended from
the mount. Like the lame man unchained of his life-long fetters of
infirmity, they precede and follow this to them chief of Christ's
apostles, walking and leaping and praising God. They too have been
unchained of life-long fetters, that have made them sit at the
beautiful gate of the temple of knowledge and liberty, powerless to
move, hopeless of salvation.</p>
               <p pn="29">Their sneering master and mistress (such, thank God, no
longer!) scowl from their windows upon him and the tumultuous crowd of
beggared blacks that throng him, as Saul's daughter did upon the
rejoicing David, despising him in their hearts. They do not mar his
calm content nor the delight of the noisy escort who guide 
<pb n="30"/>
                  <figure entity="haven30">
                     <figDesc>30th page of Gilbert
Haven's The Uniter and Liberator of America.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
the ruler both of them and of their masters to the residence of the
fled usurper. He is indifferent to their contempt, and only regards
the wonderful salvation of which he has been the chosen instrument,
but which Jesus of Nazareth has alone effected.</p>
               <p pn="30">As Christ entered into Jerusalem, the city that above all
others hated, rejected, and should soon slay him, attended by those,
but now lame and blind and deaf and leprous, whom he had cured, so did
this, his servant, enter the city that above all others hated and
rejected him, and would soon be the real if not intentional cause of
his death, attended by thousands who had been saved from worse
maladies than these, out of whom, in a moment, legions of devils that
had long possessed them had been instantly and forever expelled by the
same Divine Redeemer, through his appointed word. "Behold thy king
cometh, meek," is most beautifully true here and now. The haughty
tyrant is gone, the loving father is come. Well may their glad hearts
dance for joy. Well may the air ring with their jubilant
hallelujahs. Well may the paternal President feel the comfort and
strength of the hour. The blessings of those that were ready to perish
came upon him. His work draws near its close. The North is united, the
rebel subdued, the slave set free. His cup is full. He can well
exclaim, "Now, Lord, lettest thou thy servant depart in peace, for
mine eyes have seen thy salvation and the glory of thy people
Israel."</p>
               <p pn="30">How near that departure was! This was his Palm Sunday. Ten
days elapse and he follows his Divine Master, through like bloody
hands, to a like glorious eternity.</p>
               <p pn="30">Thus did our king enter his strong city. Thus did he
triumph over his Philistia. The story wil1 be wrought in song and
canvas, over the world and adown the ages, as the most beautiful and
most rare expression of a Christian triumph. John Brown's last act,
the kissing of the slave-child, will be one with Abraham Lincoln's
last walk up the streets of Richmond, attended by ten thousand of
<pb n="31"/>
                  <figure entity="haven31">
                     <figDesc>31st page of Gilbert
Haven's The Uniter and Liberator of America.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
his emancipated worshippers. With such a word as the inaugural and
such a deed as this, we may truly feel that his life was rounded to a
perfect close. He could properly hear the voice of the Master, saying,
"It is enough; come up higher! Thou hast been faithful over a few
things, I will make thee ruler over many things. Enter thou into the
joy of thy Lord."</p>
               <p pn="31">His work is done. Ours is yet unfinished. His place in
history and in heaven is sure. Ours is yet to win. We shall show our
admiration for him more by completing his work, than by standing too
long gazing steadfastly into the heavens whither he has ascended.</p>
               <p pn="31">As he constantly moved forward with the advancing hour, so
must we. To pause where he stopped is to go backward. Let us keep step
with God in every path of Christian and patriotic duty, enlarging the
bounds and upbuilding the walls of the kingdom of Christ by our faith,
our zeal, our love. Then shall we best express our sorrow over him who
fell so untimely, yet so timely, and become, if not, like him, a
martyr, at least a witness for and a worker with our God. Then shall
we be a sharer of his labor and his reward. What a reward it is to him
whose most peaceful nature was compelled to most stormy and repulsive
service! How ineffably sweet must be the quiet and repose of the banks
of the river of life, after this dark and bloody night of earth and
time! There he rests from his labors, and his works--how many and how
mighty!--do follow him and shall forever follow. There he worships the
Chief of the martyrs,--whose form like his was pierced by the
murderous stroke, whose soul like his was bowed with sorrows not his
own, whose life like his was given for the redemption of others than
himself,--with whom he may feel himself made one, in that final
confession of his enemies, "He saved others, himself he cannot save;"
as he is also one in forgiving them for their atrocious deed. Before
that Saviour does he, thoughtless of self, bow in bliss and gratitude
<pb n="32"/>
                  <figure entity="haven32">
                     <figDesc>32nd page of Gilbert
Haven's The Uniter and Liberator of America.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
unknown to earthly hearts. Through His infinitely greater service and
sacrifice has he, a poor slave of sin and hell, found everlasting
redemption and equal citizenship with the unfallen angels of God. Let
us, like him, though with eyes dimmed by tears and time, gaze, in
faith, on the illustrious martyr of the universe, our Saviour, our
Redeemer, our God. Let us consecrate ourselves, soul, body, and
spirit, to that divinest purpose, for whose establishment He poured
out His soul unto death, and to whose completion He has allowed so
many of His disciples to feebly but gratefully follow Him afar off, in
like sacrifice of themselves upon the altar of their faith,--assured
that, under His supervision, despite the seeming triumphs of men and
devils, that cause is steadily advancing to its earthly and eternal
consummation.</p>
            </div2>
         </div1>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI.2>