<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader><fileDesc>
         <titleStmt n="Three Discourses">
            <title>Three Discourses</title>
            <author>Laurie, Thomas</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Compiled and edited by</resp>
               <name>Beck
Center</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent/>
         <publicationStmt><publisher>Lewis H. Beck Center</publisher><pubPlace>Emory University</pubPlace><address>
               <addrLine>Atlanta,
Georgia</addrLine>
            </address><availability>
               <p>1996 Emory
University. Permission is granted to download, transmit, or otherwise
reproduce, distribute or display the contributions to the work claimed
by Emory University for non-profit educational purposes, provided
this header is included in its entirety.  For inquiries about
commercial uses, contact either: Lincoln Sermons Project or Lewis
H. Beck Center for Electronic collections and services, Emory
University, Atlanta, Georgia 30322</p>
            </availability><date>1999</date></publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Lincoln
Sermons Project</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Laurie,
Thomas. Three Discourses, Preached in The South Evangelical Church,
West Roxbury, Mass., April 13th, 19th, and 23d, 1865. Dedham, Mass.:
Printed by John Cox, Jr. 1865.</bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc><encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This text is produced in conjunction
with the  Women Writers Resource Project at Emory University</p>
            <p>TRANSCRIBER: Lewis H. Beck Center and Emory University 
Preservation Office.</p>
            <p>PRODUCER:  BookLab, Inc., 1606 Headway Circle, 
Suite 100, Austin, TX 78754</p>
            <p>CAPTURE DEVICE: XEROX DocuImage 620S flatbed scanner</p>
            <p>CAPTURE DETAILS: Scanner software: XEROX ScanTool 
version 4.2.3; no gamma correction; images are all bitonal.</p>
            <p>CHANGE HISTORY: Using the Adobe Photoshop Batch Processor, 
we interpolated  the original TIFF files to 8-bit grays, 
and altered the resolution to 144 dpi, producing screen 
images twice the original size.  We then saved them in 
JPEG format.  We produced GIF thumbnails from the JPEG files.</p>
            <p>RESOLUTION: 600 ppi</p>
            <p>COMPRESSION: Resolution 144 per inch with Constrain 
Properties to 72 per inch.</p>
            <p>SOURCE: Original documents.</p>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc><revisionDesc><change><name>Stewart Varner</name> transformed this document from p4 to p5 on <date when="2010-03-22">March 22, 2010</date></change><change xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><date>1999</date><label>Staff</label><name>Scott Ellis</name>SGML tags inserted in compliance
with TEI guidelines using TEILITE</change></revisionDesc></teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div1 xml:id="laurie.001" n="Three Discourses" type="text">
            <head> 
               <bibl> 
                  <title>Three
Discourses</title> 
                  <date>April 13th, 19th, and 23d, 1865.</date>
                  <pubPlace>The South Evangelical Church, West Roxbury, Mass.</pubPlace>
                  <author>Laurie, Thomas</author> 
                  
                     <pubPlace>Dedham,
Mass.</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Printed by John Cox, Jr.</publisher>
                     <date>1865</date>
                   
               <idno type="ark">http://pid.emory.edu/ark:/25593/15qhm</idno></bibl> 
            </head>
            <pb facs="laurie1.jpg"/>
            <p>THREE</p>
            <p>DISCOURSES</p>
            <p>PREACHED IN</p>
            <p>The South Evangelical Church</p>
            <p>WEST ROXBURY, MASS.,</p>
            <p>April 13th, 19th, and 23d, 1865,</p>
            <p>BY THOMAS LAURIE.</p>
            <p>Published by Request.</p>
            <p>DEDHAM, MASS.:</p>
            <p>PRINTED BY JOHN COX, Jr.</p>
            <p>1865.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="laurie2.jpg"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="laurie3.jpg"/>
            <div2 xml:id="laurie.002" n="DISCOURSE I." type="sermon">
               <head>DISCOURSE I.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Preached on Fast Day, April 13, 1865, and repeated in
Rev. Mr. Edwards's Church, Dedham in the afternoon.</p>
               </argument>
               <epigraph>
                  <p>Ezra 8, 21: Then I proclaimed a Fast there at the river
of Ahava, that we might afflict ourselves before our God, to seek of
Him a right way for us and for our little ones, and for all our
substance.</p>
               </epigraph>
               <p>IT is written in holy scripture, "Is any addicted, let him pray. Is
any merry, let him sing psalms." This is also the voice of nature. But
sometimes an occasion of great joy is only a louder call for prayer,
and such were the circumstances referred to in the text. That we may
see this more clearly, let us go back a little in the history of
Israel. For their sins they had been carried captive to Babylon. This
captivity lasted seventy years, so that very few of those who
witnessed its commencement lived to see its close. Toward the end of
it, Daniel set his face unto the Lord God, to seek by prayer and
supplication, with fasting and sackcloth and ashes, the grace which
had been promised to his people. Here was one in affliction praying,
encouraged by the promise of a divine deliverance. And soon the
deliverance came. Cyrus the Great issued a proclamation declaring that
<pb n="4" facs="laurie4.jpg"/>
the Lord God of Heaven, who had given him the kingdom, had charged him
to rebuild His Temple in Jerusalem; so he invited all Jews, so
disposed, to engage in the good work. He also encouraged such as could
not go in person to send their contributions, and it is a remarkable
fact, that in this royal edict the King of Persia acknowledged
Jehovah, God of Israel, to be <hi rend="italic">the</hi> God.</p>
               <p>In consequence of this proclamation, a company of nearly
fifty thousand went up to Jerusalem under Zerubbabel, and it is
interesting to note that out of so large a multitude only eight
thousand one hundred and thirty-six, or less than one in six, were
able to ride, though the journey occupied four months; moreover, three
out of every four who did ride were mounted on asses, the cheapest and
smallest of all beasts of burden. Yet though so poor, they carried up
with them offerings to the amount of sixty-one thousand pieces of
gold, and five thousand pounds of silver--this last worth about
seventy-five thousand dollars.</p>
               <p>Fourteen years after, a royal order was procured from
Cambyses to put a stop to the work; but only three years after that,
Darius Hystaspes commanded it to go on. He restored the sacred vessels
plundered by Nebuchadnezzar, and appropriated sufficient from the
royal tribute to meet all expenses.</p>
               <p>Surely in all this Israel had abundant occasion for
praise. But in addition to this, Ezra, a scribe well instructed in the
law, and devoted to the religious instruction of his people, received
a commission from Artaxerxes Longimanus to go up to Jerusalem and
enquire after the success of the enterprise. The king and his nobles
contributed largely
<pb n="5" facs="laurie5.jpg"/>
themselves to the object, and besides authorizing whoever wished, to
return with Ezra, and take with them all the contributions they could
procure, he donated of the royal tribute one hundred talents of
silver, equal to ninety thousand dollars, besides abundance of all
sorts of provisions for those who carried on the work. Then, every man
connected with the temple, from the high priest down to the humblest
hewer of wood and drawer of water, was exempted from taxation; and
Ezra was enjoined to enforce the law of God, in all things without let
or hindrance. In consequence of such distinguished favor, Ezra took up
with him a company of fourteen hundred and ninety-six men, with their
wives and children, making a caravan probably of about six thousand
persons. These carried with them one hundred talents and one thousand
darics of gold, and seven hundred and fifty talents of silver--the
silver alone amounting to six hundred and seventy-five thousand
dollars. Surely here was occasion for most jubilant thanksgiving, yet
right in the face of so many and so great mercies, we find Ezra
appointing a Fast, to seek the protection and blessing of God on the
way. And, my friends, he needed to do this; for that great company,
including so many defenceless women and children, and having with them
so much treasure, were going to be for four months within reach of the
Arabs of the desert, who would not fail to know of the grand
opportunity for plunder. Ordinarily such caravans needed a military
escort, as travellers through that region do to-day. Yet Ezra had
spoken to the king so confidently about the good hand of the Lord
being upon all them that seek Him, that he was ashamed to ask the
usual band of soldiers and
<pb n="6" facs="laurie6.jpg"/>
horsemen, but turned instead to that King who filled the mountain full
of chariots and horsemen round about Elisha; and God did not
disappoint his servant, but sent his angels to encamp round about him
all the way, so that neither by day nor by night did any evil befall
him, or any plague come nigh the camp. Thank God that faith is not
confined to any one age, but shines out upon us from them all; and
thank God that it still lives to the praise of Him who works in His
waiting servants the work of faith with power.</p>
               <p>My hearers, I need not tell you that to-day is a day of joy
far greater than that ancient joy in Persia, when those who carried
Israel away captive became the builders and guardians of a renovated
temple. A rebellion vaster, fiercer and more defiant than earth ever
saw before, has just received its death blow. A war unparalleled in
magnitude, whether we look at the size of its armies, or the number
and bloodiness of its battles;--a war involving the existence of our
beloved country;--a war whose opening scenes made the heart faint, and
the blood stagnate in the agony of our suspense,--such a war has just
closed with a series of victories, involving such crushing defeats to
our foes, that whether willing or unwilling, they must lay down the
sword. We do not stop to ask how the South receives them. We raise no
question about the time and manner of the proclamation of
peace. Peace, to all intents and purposes, has been wrenched from
their unwilling hands. The arm that refused it has been broken--broken
by the mightier power of Him who doeth His will in the army of heaven
and among the inhabitants of the earth.</p>
               <p>On Monday, when the news spread from city to city, and
<pb n="7" facs="laurie7.jpg"/>
from house to house, men were beside themselves with joy. Words could
not give it utterance; only the loudest music, and the thunder of
cannon, could give expression to so great gladness. Never before did I
get such an idea of mere sound as an expression of emotion, and if the
multitudes that thronged the city streets last Monday could only have
come together, and all joined in one of the grand old chorale, we
should have heard such singing as we are not likely to hear this side
of heaven. We are calmer today, though not less jubilant. If our
praises are less impulsive, they are more hearty, for we have had time
to think, to look at our mercies; and if not to grasp all their
greatness, yet to let them sink into our hearts till they are running
over.</p>
               <p>My friends, we have very great occasion for praise, and no
doubt we shall soon have an opportunity for its expression; would that
when it comes, it might find us in the spirit of him who wrote,
"Praise ye the Lord, for it is good to sing praises unto our God, for
it is pleasant, and praise is comely." Would that whenever we come
together for the worship of our Divine benefactor, we might have more
heart to make his praise glorious. But praise is not our only work
to-day. Even more than that pilgrim band at the river of Ahava, we
have occasion for prayer as well as praise, and to that need let us
now direct our thoughts, so that pleading, like that multitude by the
river of Babylonia, we may, like them, prevail.</p>
               <p>Why then, after so great victories, and in the midst of
such universal joy, should we devote ourselves to the work of fasting
and prayer? I answer, in brief, because much
<pb n="8" facs="laurie8.jpg"/>
yet remains to be done to secure the benefits of these long years of
war. The war is virtually ended, but the results to be produced by it
are not yet secured. We stand in the, very crisis of destiny. The
great questions that have so long agitated the nation are now
approaching their final settlement. They have passed out of the sphere
of force into that of debate, and not debate only, but political
management, party strife and sectional prejudice. Till now the nation
has held its breath, watching the shock of contending armies. Now
there is danger that men will feel that all is safe, and so let
traitors secure, by secret cunning, what they failed to accomplish by
open force; or at least mar our dear-bought gains, and inaugurate the
same contest under another form, and on different fields of
action. The mass so long in the furnace is now being withdrawn. To-day
it is soft and ductile. A child may make an impression on it. Tomorrow
it cools and hardens, perpetuating, it may be, for ages and
generations, the impress of to-day. When the character of a great
nation is thus in the balance; when our institutions are taking form
afresh, is it a time to give ourselves up to impassioned ecstacy? Is
it not a time for fervent intercession that God will in mercy Himself
superintend our removal from the furnace; give the results of these
protracted trials such a shape, and so stamp His own image on us as a
people, that He may be glorified in our highest prosperity, and that
we may not fail one iota of that benefit which His grace is able to
bestow upon us in this advanced stage of the history of Redemption. Is
there no danger that while good men give themselves up to the
intoxication of the hour, scheming politicians and worthless demagogues
<pb n="9" facs="laurie9.jpg"/>
may plot unhindered? Shall the golden opportunity, purchased by the
blood of so many brave men, be thus vilely cast away? Shall those
suffering heroes, now sustained in their agonies and mutilations by
the sweet thought that each pain is purchasing their country's good,
wake up to the greater agony of seeing the enemy sow tares in the
field watered by their blood, while those who ought to have sowed it
with good seed spend the time in thoughtless jubilation?</p>
               <p>But you will ask, What can we do? We are private citizens;
we fill no position of influence; we have no control over public
affairs. Permit me, in all plainness, to answer: This last is not
true. You may be private citizens; you may hold no office. But it is
just such that the country looks to for help in this time of need; and
if we do not render it, how can we answer for it to the great cloud of
witnesses who, from so many gory beds, are looking on our inaction?
How can we answer for it to their weeping friends, who gave them up to
such a death for us? Do you still stand idle, and ask, "What can we
do?" There is the mercy seat, and to-day Massachusetts calls on you to
approach it, and intercede for your country. Have you done it? Do you
intend yet to do it? All through the war, our rulers and our statesmen
have needed our prayers, but never more than now, when on them
devolves the work of securing to posterity the advantages procured at
so great a cost. Think how one mistake, one well intentioned blunder,
may mar the whole. Think how one treacherous Ahithophel may mislead an
honest heart, and perpetuate, in new forms,
<pb n="10" facs="laurie10.jpg"/>
the miseries of the past. Think how God, all through the war, has
guided and sustained our rulers in answer to prayer. And shall he find
us silent now? Babylon is not the only nation that has perished
because her people gave themselves up to revelry when they should have
been every man at his post, alert and vigilant. And if now, when our
destiny as a nation is taking new form, we be found among those who
restrain prayer, shall we be guiltless?</p>
               <p>I have already said, in various forms, that the present is
a turning point of destiny. Look for a moment at some of the things
that make it such. The fate of the leaders of this rebellion is now to
be decided. They, with others now gone to appear before a higher
tribunal, have stirred up the South to frenzy. They have diligently
fed the flame thus kindled. They have, by a worse than Parisian reign
of terror, dragged with them unwilling men, and made the life of loyal
citizens to hang on cooperation with treason. They have instigated all
this slaughter. And when the brave men who sought to defend our
country, fell into their hands, they deliberately tortured them to
death. The rack and the stake were too merciful and too slow for their
use. Famine, that could slay its thousands at a stroke; starvation in
sight of abundance, was the instrument of their careful choice. The
groaning of the prisoner came into their ears. The report of the guns
that shot men too weak to stand, because they had not power to control
the direction of their fall, echoed through the council chamber at
Richmond, and passed beyond into loyal homes, where heart-broken
relatives thanked God for the stroke which ended the long agony and
the long suspense, and still that starvation went on. 
<pb n="11" facs="laurie11.jpg"/>
These men might have stopped it. One word, one penning of a signature
had put an end to such cruelty; but the word was left unspoken, the
pen moved not, and the lingering torture went on, up to the last
moment they had power to inflict it. Shall such men be allowed to
attempt, by wiles and flattery and fraud, the destruction they failed
to effect by force? Shall they be left to muster their followers at
the ballot-box as they have done in the battle field? Shall they be
permitted to thwart the progress of freedom and free institutions, as
they have erected ramparts to arrest the progress of our armies? I
know that it is written: Vengeance is mine, I will repay, saith the
Lord;--but in such a connexion let us think not of <hi rend="italic">vengeance</hi> but <hi rend="italic">justice</hi>. Remember,
it is also written, "that the ruler is the minister of God, a revenger
to execute wrath upon him that doeth evil;" and as I think of the
unscriptural sentimentalism that makes rulers, even in New England,
bear the sword in vain, allowing condemned murderers to go unwhipt of
justice--making honest men more afraid of evil-doers than evil-doers
are of retribution; either in this world or the world to come, I
tremble when I think what judgments may yet be in store for a land
where "judgment is so turned away backward, and justice standeth afar
off."</p>
               <p>My hearers, we need prayer here to guard us on both
sides. On the one hand, from a passionate and ungodly wrath, that so
far from being religious, unfits the soul for prayer; and on the
other, from an antagonism to the demands of justice, which is, in
essence, antagonism to God. In this matter, do we not need specially
to pray that God will both keep our rulers from being opposed to
justice, and
<pb n="12" facs="laurie12.jpg"/>
from seeking the ends of justice from other motives, and in an unholy
spirit? Do we not need, also, to pray that justice may be honored with
just as little suffering as is consistent with that end? Who of us
would not shrink from the difficult questions which our rulers must
decide, and from the painful duties which they must perform? Can we do
less than help them by our prayers, and still the more as we see the
day approaching?</p>
               <p>Then, besides the leaders, there is the whole population at
the South. What dark masses of perplexity mount the sky, with the
approach of peace, like clouds driven by the storm. How can the guilty
be punished, and the innocent saved from further suffering? How can
prejudice be conciliated--prejudice, drank in at a mother's breast,
taught in the schools, strengthened by social intercourse with those
trained under like influences, and above all, sanctioned by the
teachings of the pulpit? No man can form any adequate idea of the
strength of such prejudice, and not feel that God alone can remove
it. And what shall be our future if it be not removed? There are those
in whose minds all the sufferings and bereavements of the South in
this rebellion will be invested with the halo of martyrdom in a holy
cause, putting them hopelessly beyond the reach of argument. And if we
may judge of the effect of their persecutions on the patriots of the
South, from the spirit manifested by one recently chosen to be ruler
of the State where he suffered so much, we do not see much prospect of
conciliation or of harmony, and when to this antagonism we add the
influx of greedy, unprincipled men from the free States, intent solely
on their own advantage,
<pb n="13" facs="laurie13.jpg"/>
we ask how long will it take the agitated waters to subside? As we
think of the extreme severity of military jurisdiction, and the laxity
of civil authority,--here rebels bearing  sway as the legal majority,
and there army officers, with methods of administration learned in
war;--as we think of these things, we ask who can make the wrath of
man to praise Him and restrain the remainder thereof, but God only?
Let Him deal with us as we deserve, and He might leave us to be bound
together in one bitter antagonism that should end only in mutual
destruction. But in answer to prayer, He can make our bitterest
enemies gentle as the lamb, and cause the whole land to seek those
things that consolidate peace, because they foster mutual regard,
esteem and love. Then in every portion of our now distracted land
shall each, in seeking a brother's welfare, find his own. My hearers,
God alone can bring this about, and he does this in answer to
prayer. I might easily enlarge on the complications likely to arise
among a people made up of defeated rebels, lawless robbers, loyal
sufferers, and soldiers of a victorious army, with citizens from the
free States--all brought together in closest contact, and each class,
with its partizans, quick to insult and take offence, and slow to
forget an injury. But I mean not to paint the picture in full; I only
sketch such outlines as may serve to show the urgent need of prayer
to-day.</p>
               <p>Turn to another class, hitherto kept in the background, but
now brought, by their God and ours, into unwonted prominence. Thank
God, they are bondmen no longer, but freedmen. But does the
Proclamation of Freedom complete the work? Nay, verily. The shackles
may be stricken off,
<pb n="14" facs="laurie14.jpg"/>
but the scars remain. The vices of slavery need to be rooted out. The
voluntary separation of husband and wife, and the facile formation of
a new connection growing out of that great crime, is a greater evil
than the forcible sundering of the relation, and harder to be
remedied. Its roots lie deeper, and they are stronger. One stroke of
the pen can put a stop to the one, but only a long and laborious
instruction can, by the blessing of God, remove the other. The
sentiments, the practices, the habits of slavery, need all to be
remodelled. Listless indulgence, unthinking improvidence must be
replaced by habits of steady labor and prudent forethought. The
jealousy with which the slave has hitherto regarded his white master,
rendering even well-meant counsels and efforts for his comforts of no
avail, must be replaced by a confidence which shall be given because
it is felt to be deserved--and confidence is proverbially a plant of
slow growth. And how many, think you, of those foremost in denouncing
oppression, will have the self-denying, patient love that is requisite
for this? Alas for those just out of the prison-house who fall into
the hands of unprincipled men, who love money more than they love
their neighbor. In such cases it is not impossible to secure all the
miseries of slavery without the name. These freedmen need sympathy and
kindness. They need education; above all, and more than all, they need
the gospel. Not a system of truth in which man is prominent, of which
human goodness is the starting point, and happiness the goal--a system
according to which Christ is only one teacher among many; but the
truth as it is in Jesus, based upon Him and summed up in Him, as its
alpha and omega, its essence and its life--
<pb n="15" facs="laurie15.jpg"/>
the gospel in which God stoops to the sinner in infinite love, that
through the redemption that is in Christ He may lift him up to
Heaven.</p>
               <p>This gospel, and this alone, can fit the freedman for the
right discharge of his duties; and there is no other power that can
transform rebels into loyal citizens. Armies can break their power,
but grace alone can break their hearts, and teach them to look with
love both on their former slaves--now lifted up to share their own
legal standing--and on those who, under God, have lifted them up to
this equality. The whole South must be leavened with the gospel. Its
educational and religious institutions must be reconstructed, not by
arbitrary dictation, but by a loving co-operation; and to this end our
churches--this church--each one of us who hope that we are Christians,
need a fresh baptism from on high. We need to care not only for our
own things, but also for the things of our whole land. Henceforth our
interest, our prayers, and our benefactions must be on the broad scale
of our country, what they have been for our own church. Will the
churches come up to this? Are you, my hearers, ready to stand in your
lot, and do whatsoever your hand findeth to do, as God shall give you
ability, till these reunited States shall be thoroughly supplied with
the ordinances of the worship of our God. O blessed invitation of our
Master! to return such blessings for their curses and the miseries
they sought to bring upon us! God, in his providence, calls us to this
work--shall it be done? If we prove unfaithful, there is a class--not
in the cotton-fields of South Carolina, but scattered through New
England towns, and living in our own families--a class no more
friendly to
<pb n="16" facs="laurie16.jpg"/>
either our political or religious institutions than the rebels at the
South, whom God may use to chastise His churches as He has used the
other to chastise the nation.</p>
               <p>But if we rightly discern the signs of the times; if in the
spirit of our Master we meet the demands of the hour, all the
deliverance God has wrought for us these four years on so many fields
of strife; all the answers He has given to prayer for our rulers and
our armies; the great salvation He has wrought from that gigantic
system of oppression which corrupted all it touched, and seemed to
defy our prayers; all these assure us that God will be with us and
bless us with a still greater blessing. He will subdue rebel hearts as
well as rebel armies. He will bless the negro in his new position, and
we shall be that happy people whose God is the Lord.</p>
               <pb n="17" facs="laurie17.jpg"/>
            </div2>
            <div2 xml:id="laurie.003" n="DISCOURSE II." type="sermon">
               <head>DISCOURSE II.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Preached April 19th, the day of the Funeral of Abraham
Lincoln.</p>
               </argument>
               <epigraph>
                  <p>1 Samuel 3, 18: It is the Lord. Let Him do what seemeth
Him good.</p>
               </epigraph>
               <p>WE are all mourners to-day. At ordinary funerals, we see a little
bereaved band, and a larger circle of spectators, sympathizing,
indeed, but not suffering the distress of those immediately
afflicted. On public occasions like this we are accustomed to see much
of the pageantry of sorrow, but little of the reality. It is not so
to-day. Seldom do we witness in private bereavements such grief as is
called forth by this public loss. I was walking out when the news
came, and from almost every house that I passed weeping ones came out
to meet me--not because they expected I could comfort them, but
because their grief was too great to be endured alone. The death of no
other President since the first could have awakened such emotion. He
was our father, and we were his children. It was not always so. We
need hardly go back six years to find a time when most of us did not
even know his name, for by the force of his own sterling virtue he
worked his way up from obscurity. And when, a
<pb n="18" facs="laurie18.jpg"/>
little more than four years ago, he was called to the helm just as the
ship of State plunged into the storm, amid sunken rocks, and almost
within reach of a lee shore, we had some misgivings. The crisis
demanded a man of tried ability, of commanding powers, and he was an
obscure stranger. We did not know him. His education did not command
our confidence. He came from a region whose manners are yet
unpolished, and its institutions immature. We had learned to distrust
the loud commendation of partizans in a political campaign. And is it
any wonder that when the first gun was fired in Charleston harbor, we
could not rest? Traitors had control in the capital. They filled the
national councils. Their plans were mature; ours were yet to be
formed--and who was our leader? We hoped in the God of our fathers,
and yet we feared that we had provoked Him to destroy us. So all eyes
were fixed upon our chief magistrate. One thing we were sure of -- God
had given him to the country;--but was he to be a saviour, or an
instrument of the vengeance we deserved? That touching request for our
prayers, as he turned from his western home to the scene of his
labors, was the first thing that drew him to our hearts, and at the
same time made hope to triumph over fear. Then that providential
deliverance from violence on the way, was another token for
good. Still we were troubled; but ever the more we knew him, the
brighter were our hopes. It did not take long to satisfy us of his
honesty of purpose; we endorsed the name first given him by his
western friends. But was he intelligent? Would he take broad views of
things? Would he look well before he moved? Here, too, we learned to
ad-
<pb n="19" facs="laurie19.jpg"/>
mire his child-like candor and transparency. But cautious and careful
in coming at conclusions, could he stand firm? Surrounded by
politicians, many of them unscrupulous, some of them influential,
could the magnet avoid being deflected from the pole, amid so many
counter attractions? Here, too, we learned to love, as well as
confide. Now and then things occurred to try our faith, but in the end
they only rooted it the firmer. Each blast that swept over it only
made it stronger for the next encounter with the storm.</p>
               <p>The war
lengthened out beyond all our anticipations. But still our leader
stood firm--firm in his own principles--firm in the confidence of
loyal men. Then came the time for a new election. Would not men grow
impatient under unusual burdens? Slanders were rife; and bold, bad
men, caring nothing for principles, intent only on the one end of
putting down the national government, carefully constructed a platform
most conducive to popular effect. They selected their candidate for
his availability rather than for his sympathy with themselves, and
moved earth and heaven to overthrow him who had already surmounted the
most difficult portion of the voyage toward a righteous and an
honorable peace. There was a time when it seemed as though the enemy
must succeed. It seemed as if the masses, deluded by slanders, would
certainly turn against their steadfast deliverer. But not such was the
will of God. You remember how He strengthened the heart of His
faithful servant, and confounded His enemies by a result as gratifying
as it was triumphant.</p>
               <p>Thus was our confidence in the leader God
had given us
<pb n="20" facs="laurie20.jpg"/>
made stronger, and love kept pace with our confidence. More than ever
we felt assured that God had called him to his position, and qualified
him for his work. We loved to pray for him, and watch the blessings
conferred on him in answer to prayer. So we went on; and though most
of us had never looked on his honest face, we felt toward him as a
father.</p>
               <p>When the blow fell--O, how sudden, and how sore!--we could
not work; we could not eat. We scarce knew what we did or said; one
crushing weight pressed all hearts into the dust. We had just begun to
feel at home with him; we were just tasting the sweets of unbounded
confidence and love, when that dastard crime dashed our cup of
happiness on the stones. Now that the war was past, we expected to see
him enjoy the remainder of his presidential term in reaping the
harvest ripened under his care. But his work is done, and well done;
his race is finished, and we rejoice that his character is so
universally appreciated as it is to-day.</p>
               <p>It is customary, on such an occasion, to say a word of
comfort to the bereaved,--but :what shall I say? I cannot point you to
all the reasons for such an event, for I know them not any more than
you; but we can together enjoy the consoling thought--it is not
chance; it is not accident; "It is the Lord; let Him do what seemeth
Him good." But I have heard the passionate reply--"What! such an act
from God! and such an agent!" My friend, I appreciate your
difficulty. I do not wonder that it troubles you. But as to the agent:
when would God do anything if He waited till a sinner became worthy to
be the channel of His mercy? 
<pb n="21" facs="laurie21.jpg"/>
Besides, are there not links in the chain of second causes better
supplied by villains than by honest men? Would it have been as
appropriate for the beloved disciple to have betrayed his Master, as
it was for that traitor who, after the crime, could not find one act
in the whole life of Christ to mitigate remorse, and so went and
hanged himself? Only remember that when God uses so base an
instrument, He does not make it base, nor compel,--no, not even
induce--it so to act, but only adapts His providence to bring good out
of the evil wrought. "He makes the wrath of man to praise Him,"--does
not create it--"and restrains the remainder thereof,"--not the whole,
for a portion is made to issue in a louder song of praise from all who
witness the use which God makes of human wickedness. The same sun
ripens the wheat and the tares; the same rain ministers life to the
garden and malaria to the swamp. The same soil produces the rose and
the deadly nightshade, and the different result is not owing to the
sun, or the rain, or the soil, but wholly to the evil nature of the
tares, and the swamp, and the poisonous plant. We cannot tell why God
permitted sin at first, or why He allowed such a tempter to enter
Eden. We only know that where sin abounds, grace does much more
abound; and that the visit of Satan to destroy, gave occasion to the
visit of Christ to save.</p>
               <p>But why enlarge? Such things are tests of our confidence in
God; and however clouds and darkness may for a moment hide the sun,
the Christian knows that it still shines--that there is a perfectly
holy motive at the beginning--a pure and blameless management all the
way, and an issue at the end that shall infinitely justify God in all
His acts. The
<pb n="22" facs="laurie22.jpg"/>
evil is ours--the beginning, middle and end of it are ours--but the
greater good which it is made to subserve is all from God. "He is not
tempted with evil, neither tempteth He any man; but every man is
tempted when he is drawn away of his own lust and enticed." Yet, at
the same time, the Prophet can ask, "Shall there be evil in a city,
and the Lord hath not done it?" For while man, in the exercise of
moral evil, brings physical evil to pass, God determined to make that
physical evil the occasion of both physical and moral good. So while
no greater crime was ever committed in the universe than the putting
to death of our Redeemer, yet "him being delivered by the determinate
counsel and foreknowledge of God, [men] have taken, and by wicked
hands have crucified and slain." Yea, "of a truth, against Thy holy
child Jesus, whom Thou hast anointed, both Herod and Pontius Pilate,
with the Gentiles and the people of Israel, were gathered together for
to do whatsoever Thy hand and Thy counsel determined before to be
done," but without any sinful agency of God on their minds inclining
them so to act. Then do we not see clearly why we should adopt the
language of the text, concerning this cowardly murder of our beloved
chief magistrate, in humble and holy, aye, joy-giving faith?</p>
               <p>For even if the course of events to-day, and for a long
time to come, should give no ray of light; though so far as tendencies
and manifest results of Providence were concerned, we should be left
in darkness, yet the character of God is so perfect that we cannot do
otherwise than give ourselves up confidingly to His sovereign
disposal. If while our loved President was living, we could trust him
even
<pb n="23" facs="laurie23.jpg"/>
when we did not know how he would act, how much more shall we trust
God when we see how He has acted even though we do not as yet see the
good that shall most certainly come out of it. Just as in the storm,
when the ship groans beneath us, the storm howls above us, and the
waves threaten to sweep over us, we are comforted by the sight of a
tried pilot at the helm; so here we can look all possible evil in the
face and sing, "As for God, His way is perfect; a just God, without
iniquity, just and right is He;" "Therefore will we not fear, though
the earth be removed and the mountains be cast into the midst of the
sea."</p>
               <p>But God has not shut us up to such darkness. As though He
knew us too well to trust us in such entire absence of all sensible
comfort, He has not left Himself without witness in this time of
national calamity. For He has been with us all through the war, and
led us by a way which we knew not, which nevertheless was the best and
most beneficent way to victory. So that we may boldly say, "The Lord
is our Helper, we will not fear what man can do unto us;" "Because
Thou hast been our Help, therefore in the shadow of Thy wings will we
rejoice." God has not led us all through this war to such a commanding
position only to destroy us now. He has not answered so many prayers
only to forsake us to-day. But this is one of the all things that
shall work together for our good --yea, lift us up to a serener height
of blessing. We have been accustomed to regard the rebel inhumanity to
prisoners as one of the darkest clouds in the whole horizon; but look
round you: see how that inhumanity is opening the eyes of men at home
and abroad to the true character of this rebellion. 
<pb n="24" facs="laurie24.jpg"/>
See how it consolidates the loyalty of the loyal States, and calls
forth the condemnation of Europe and the world; making men whom
nothing else could have induced to do so, to abhor the rebellion with
an unmitigated and unchangeable abhorrence; and do you not see that
not one iota of those lingering agonies of thousands of brave men has
been endured in vain? And what if this last and foulest crime clenches
the nail thus driven home? What if it makes popular
sentiment--proverbially fickle--as inflexible as the orbits of the
stars? What if it secure a condemnation of this whole rebellion as
lasting as the race?</p>
               <p>But there is another view of this matter no less
encouraging. It is not in my heart to breathe one syllable in
disparagement of the departed. I know it is the opinion of many that
the heart now forever at rest was too tender for the stern work of
punishing evil-doers. But I am not so sure of that. Never yet has he
been found wanting either in appreciating the duties of the hour, or
in meeting its demands. The great trouble has been in the popular
feeling, that if the rebellion could only be put down, it was
expedient to be generous, and forget the past. The idea has been that
it would be magnanimous to forgive, and let traitors go unwhipt of
justice. Magnanimous indeed! Is it magnanimity to efface the brand of
infamy from treason? Methinks it has not produced such pleasant fruit
these last four years as to merit a better standing than before. Is it
magnanimous to approve the effort of traitors to destroy our
country--an effort held back from success only by the lifeblood of
thousands of her bravest sons? If this be magnanimity, may God keep
you and me from so great a crime. 
<pb n="25" facs="laurie25.jpg"/>
Look around you on the multitude of the slain, from Galveston to
Gettysburg, and from Yorktown to our Western territories--see them in
the narrow beds, where they were laid tenderly by patriot hands, or
piled rudely in shallow trenches, where traitors tossed them in with
insult and reviling; and as your eye takes in the countless multitude,
tell me, "Who slew all these?" Go through the now silent
prison-houses--pardon the word--not houses, but living graves, scooped
out with their tin cups, for which, alas! they had little other
use--where, in the storms of winter, naked, starving patriots sought
in vain for shelter, and when you have repeopled them with the
shivering shadows that once were men, but now the lifeless victims of
rebellion, again I ask, Who slew all these? <hi rend="italic">and
how?</hi> And is it magnanimity to say to the next generation of
traitors, "Go on. Do the same thing over again. You will never be
called to account for it. Succeed better than these if you can, and if
you can't, you will not suffer?" For one, my hearers, I do not so
understand either duty or justice. It is one of the attributes of our
God that He will by no means acquit the wicked. It is said in His
praise, "Also unto Thee, O Lord! belongeth mercy, for Thou renderest
to every man according to his works."</p>
               <p>I said that public sentiment stood in the way of our
departed President, and hindered his performance of duty here; but his
death has transformed that public sentiment. In murdering him, rebels
removed the last barrier that stood between them and retribution. They
struck down their kindest benefactor. They turned a latitudinarian
public sentiment that cared nothing for justice, provided it enjoyed
<pb n="26" facs="laurie26.jpg"/>
present prosperity, into a stern demand for righteousness. The great
danger now is that the righteous demand for justice shall degenerate
into a ferocious cry for vengeance, and so err as far on one side as
it has done on the other.</p>
               <p>It is a significant fact that at this moment Providence has
called to the chair, so sadly vacated, a man who thus expresses his
views and purposes: "I am in favor of lenity, but in my opinion
evildoers ought to be punished." "Treason stands highest in the
catalogue of crimes." "The halter to intelligent, influential
traitors; but to the honest man, deluded into the rebel ranks, I would
show mercy." Later, "Let it be engraven on every heart, that treason
is a crime, and traitors shall suffer its penalty."</p>
               <p>Take it, my hearers, as a mark of Divine favor, that in a
day like this, He calls a man to be the President of our country who
advances sentiments like these. Let us cherish revenge towards no man;
but if blood must be shed, it is better that it should be that of the
evil-doer; better that traitors should suffer, as a warning to those
who may be hereafter tempted to tread in their steps, than that the
loyal families of our land should be devoted to another decimation. A
wiser, holier, and more loving heart than yours or mine has said, "It
must needs be that offences come, but woe unto that man by whom they
come;" let us be content to echo the words of Jesus: "Woe to the
offender, rather than to those who do not offend." God punishes
because he is holy and benevolent, and he requires rulers to do the
same, as his ministers, because that course is holy and benevolent--a
terror to evildoers, and a praise to them that do well. You and I
cannot be wiser or more
<pb n="27" facs="laurie27.jpg"/>
benevolent than God. He calls us to no spirit of vengeance, but to
such a reverent regard for right as shall make us willing to maintain
it in His appointed way.</p>
               <p>Four years ago we did not dare to hope that God would be
acknowledged in our land as He is to-day; that our coins would bear
the inscription, "In God we trust;" that our rulers would implore the
prayers of Christians; that our victories would be ascribed to
God. But see what hath God wrought! Yet one thing was lacking--a
reverent regard to justice. The current of public sentiment ran strong
in the opposite direction. It seemed as if the whole people would be
content with victory, and utter no solemn testimony against
treason. The very proposition would have been hooted down as bigoted
fanaticism. But by one touch what a change! Surely if Abraham Lincoln
looks down to-day on the change his death has wrought, he feels that
he has accomplished something by his death as well as by his life Let
us give to his successor the confidence and love that we gave to him,
and seek to turn the rushing stream out of the channel of blind
revenge into that of holy, loving loyalty to God and right.</p>
               <pb n="28" facs="laurie28.jpg"/>
            </div2>
            <div2 xml:id="laurie.004" n="DISCOURSE III." type="sermon">
               <head>DISCOURSE III.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Preached on the Sabbath after the
Assassination.</p>
               </argument>
               <epigraph>
                  <p>Gen. v, 5: And all the days that Adam lived were nine
hundred and thirty years, and he died.</p>
               </epigraph>
               <p>MAN was formed of the dust of the ground, and so was named Adam:
i.e., red earth. Was it not intended that thus his name should be a
constant memento of the word, "Dust thou art, and unto dust shalt thou
return"? It may seem inconsistent with this that he should live
through the long period of nine hundred and thirty years. Think of it,
not far from ten centuries--nearly one--sixth of the whole period from
his creation till this moment. He lived to see his posterity of the
eighth generation. Lamech, the father of Noah, was fifty-six years old
when Adam, his first parent, died. It was a long life indeed, and yet
were not the words of David true even then, that its strength was
labor and sorrow. Think of those nine hundred and thirty years,
commenced in Eden, but spent and ended in a world cursed through his
transgression. There must have been something very sad in that curse,
for even Lamech said of his little babe, "This child shall comfort us
concerning our work
<pb n="29" facs="laurie29.jpg"/>
and the toil of our hands, because of the ground which the Lord hath
cursed." We can almost hear the sigh of the old man as he unburdened
his grief and sorrow, in the dim hope of relief; and if the sin and
suffering of earth seemed so grievous to him, who had never seen
anything else, what must it have been to Adam, who could contrast it
with the glories of Paradise, and primeval holiness? Then our first
parent had witnessed all the wrong and violence with which earth was
filled, from the blood of righteous Abel down to the crimes that, in
his old age, were fast ripening a world for the Flood. Surely his nine
hundred and thirty years, spent in looking on the ruin which his sin
had wrought, are not to be envied. It almost seems like one of the
wondrous retributions of Providence in this life that he "who brought
death into the world, and all our woe," was detained here so long, ere
he could go to that world where nothing entereth that defileth, and
wherein dwelleth righteousness. But even after so long a life, Adam
died, and though Jared and Methuselah both lived longer than he, yet
of them, also, the short biography closes with the same record: "and
he died."</p>
               <p>It might not be profitable to dwell on the life and death
of our first parent. For we know so little of the incidents that
filled up those nine hundred and thirty years, that we can only
imagine what they were. But we need not go so far away. These emblems
of mourning point us to a recent bereavement. We find it difficult to
day to keep our minds away from our great loss, and so while on
Wednesday we gave ourselves up to meditation on the fact as citizens,
today let us look at it as those to whom it is appointed once
<pb n="30" facs="laurie30.jpg"/>
to die, and after death, the judgment. Yes, we shall follow after
him--every one of us in his time--and of us it shall be true, as it
now is true of him, that we shall not return.</p>
               <p>The death of our beloved President, then, admonishes us
that exalted station is no shield from death. Men sometimes have the
feeling that while ordinary mortals die, those lifted up to
responsible positions have a firmer hold on life; that Providence owes
it to such to give them a longer lease of earth; that as so much more
depends on them, so they should have a longer time in which to form
their plans and carry them out. But if any of us have indulged such
thoughts for a moment, how are we rebuked to-day! God is no respector
of persons. Both high and low, rich and poor together--the ruler and
his people--must go whenever God shall call them, and go, too, at the
moment, without delay. And if it was so with him on whom rested so
much of responsibility and such great interests, much more is it true
of us. As with a trumpet voice this Providence says to you and me,
"Prepare to meet thy God."</p>
               <p>There is another feeling somewhat akin to this, which leads
us to expect that a man zealously engaged in a good work will be
allowed to finish it; that if it involve the welfare of millions of
his fellowmen, and he prosecutes it with rare discretion or unusual
success, God will not suffer him to be interrupted, but will ward off
danger till the undertaking be complete. But does our recent
bereavement endorse such views? Does it tell us that if we would
secure long life, we must diligently engage in some work indispensable
to human wellbeing, and so secure safety till the work be carried
through? Nay, my hearers; but it tells us
<pb n="31" facs="laurie31.jpg"/>
that however important may be the work in hand, and however
successfully we may prosecute it, only the present moment is ours. The
next, God may give or withhold as He pleases. He is so rich in His own
resources that He does not need our services. And He has so many
instruments at His control that He can take the unfinished work from
one and confide it to another, as He pleases. And if it be so with the
strong ones, who use their strength so profitably, how is it with us?
Does not this Providence say to you and me, "Whatsoever thy hand
findeth to do, do it with thy might, for there is no work nor device
nor knowledge nor wisdom in the grave whither thou goest."</p>
               <p>After these things, I need not speak of that very common
but far less reasonable feeling, that when, after passing through much
tribulation, our feet are on the verge of quiet enjoyment, God will
surely suffer us to live to see it; or that when, through much toil
and suffering, we have earned the love of our fellowmen, God will
spare us to enjoy that love. Look on yon casket, containing all that
is left of the man whom the nation delighted to honor--the man of our
affections, and in whom our hearts did safely trust,--and read what it
saith concerning such hopes. After long and patient toil we may say to
our souls: "Soul! thou hast much good laid up for many years; take
shine ease." But another may say: "Thou fool, this night thy soul
shall be required of thee."</p>
               <p>So, too, we may have said, Life is indeed uncertain, but
God will give me some warning ere he takes it away. He may not allow
me to finish the undertaking in which I am engaged, but He will let me
know when He would have me
<pb n="32" facs="laurie32.jpg"/>
stop--at least He will give me time enough to attend to the one thing
needful before probation ends. My hearers, it is written of one, "I
gave her space to repent, and she repented not." God is now giving us
the same, and of how many may the recording angel write this moment,
"not repented?"</p>
               <p>But let this Providence speak--"The Lord said unto Moses,
get thee up into this Mount Abarim, and see the land which I have
given unto the children of Israel, and when thou hast seen it, thou
shalt be gathered unto thy people." But did He give any such warning
to our beloved President? Was there any hint such as was given to good
king Hezekiah, when the Lord said unto him--"Set thy house in order?"
We speak of sudden death. But think of never knowing that we are in
danger,--never being conscious of a stroke or a pain, till the soul
recovers consciousness in the presence of its Judge. Has such a
Providence no voice to you and me, and every soul in this great
nation? Oh, that it might be heeded! Oh, that along with the universal
grief might be a heart to hear the voice of Him who says, "Be ye
therefore ready also, for in such an hour as ye think not the Son of
Man cometh."</p>
               <p>And here I am constrained to turn aside a moment to another
lesson of this great national sorrow: From whatever side we view it,
we are appalled by its magnitude. Like some lofty peak that rises so
far above the rest of the mountain range that it seems to stand alone,
so does this bereavement overtop all similar distresses; but among all
its other aggravations, we cannot forget the scene where it
occurred. Fain would our affection have chosen some other
<pb n="33" facs="laurie33.jpg"/>
place for the closing scene of such a life. That agonized cry of his
bereaved companion, as dawn revealed its dim outlines, "Oh, that
dreadful house! that dreadful house!" still rings in our ears. It is a
relief to know that our beloved President went with reluctance to the
fatal spot. Even if we did not know that he went from regard to the
feelings of others, yet in such a matter Love would hope all things,
and think no evil. But we are startled to see the blow struck in such
a place, by one whose whole character was molded by its
influences. And what a revelation of those influences does that
character present! Not only reason distorted, and heart perverted, but
conscience so seared as to glory in his shame. How could he commit so
amazing a crime in so theatrical a way! That one word "theatrical"
explains it all. No other could express such commingled wickedness and
insensibility. That stupendous crime was the fitting fruit of an
education that, passing by the ordinary manifestations of depravity as
too commonplace, brings the soul into contact, and holds it in
communion, with all that is most intensely exciting in human crime. An
education that, making the heart familiar with the foulest and most
bloody deeds, bends the whole energy not to be good, but to put on its
seeming. It has nothing to do with goodness, save to ape its attitudes
and steal its words. It teaches a man to pass by genuine piety as
beneath regard, and heaps its praises on the clever counterfeit of its
most impassioned manifestations. At the same moment vice is equally
applauded, if the expression of its most violent outbreaks be only
vivid and intense. In that case, the greater the verisimilitude the
louder the applause. What education
<pb n="34" facs="laurie34.jpg"/>
could be better contrived to obliterate moral distinctions than that
which subsidizes both crime and virtue as means of amusement? Oh, if
that assassin, instead of being thus trained to counterfeit and win
applause by the perfection of the counterfeiting, had learned of Him
who teaches to make the tree good, that the fruit may be good
also--not to hang painted fruit amid painted leaves--would he ever
have committed so foul a crime? If he had sat at His feet who bids us
keep the heart with all diligence, because out of it are the issues of
life; to cultivate those inward graces, whose praise is not of men but
of God--the nation might have been spared the tears it weeps
to-day.</p>
               <p>Through such a crime, in such a place, by such a hand, God
points us to those words of Jesus: "By their fruits ye shall know
them;" and bids us decide which we shall choose for our children--the
education of the theatre or of the church: of the book of plays, or
the book of God. On this side, are clever counterfeits of vice and
virtue for amusement, thrilling scenes that move to tears, and
exhaust, in selfish excitements, the sensibility God meant should
prompt us to noble deeds. On that, is a daily taking up the cross, a
steady conflict with evil, that makes meet for an inheritance among
the saints in light. Here is the training for adultery, treason and
murder. There is the training to be like Christ, and be with Him where
He is.</p>
               <p>Some may fear that the death of so good a man in such a
place may draw multitudes within its gates. But the fact that it
trained his assassin for that deed of blood; that it blinded him to
its damning infamy so as to glory in shame, from which a good
conscience would have shrunk
<pb n="35" facs="laurie35.jpg"/>
back appalled, ought to produce the opposite effect.--Whether it will
or no depends on the character of each spectator of the crime. But its
testimony concerning the influence of the theatre is one which no good
man will fail to regard; and in this matter, as a parent soweth, so
shall not only himself but his children reap.</p>
               <p>We speak of being prepared for sudden death. It has become
a stereotyped phrase, "so to live every day as if it were our last;"
but have we a definite idea of what such a life involves? It is not a
few hasty prayers sandwiched between a life of ungodliness and our
appearance before the Judge. It is not a flood of tears shed over a
life up to that moment spent in deliberate disobedience. Nor is it a
regular round of Pharisaic devotion that leaves us where it found
us--prayer preceding, following, and enclosing round about, unvarying
sinfulness. But it is the discharge of daily duties as so much service
owed to God. It is whether we eat or drink, or whatever we do, doing
all to the glory of God. Is the merchant who indulges through the day
in what are so pertly called "the tricks of trade," but which are in
fact so many sins against God and our neighbor--is he ready at night
to hear Christ knock and open unto him immediately? Is the man who
to-day curtly refuses the claims of missions, or stops his ears to the
cry of so many millions of freedmen for the gospel, ready to give in
his account to-night to Him who knows each expenditure for luxury, and
each new investment? How easy it is to steel the heart to God's
commands in the daily life, and then in His house harden the same
heart against His truth, so as to go forth and renew the disobedience
of Saturday on Monday morning. 
<pb n="36" facs="laurie36.jpg"/>
It is easy to do this; but that is not laying up treasure in
Heaven.</p>
               <p>On this point the life of our martyred President speaks as
loudly as his death. Says one who knew him intimately ever since he
entered on the duties of the office he performed so well, and here I
condense somewhat the testimony of his pastor, Rev. Dr. Gurley:</p>
               <p>"He deserved the confidence and love of the nation by the whole
tenor and spirit of his life. Always and everywhere he endeavored to
be right and to do right. His integrity was thorough and
incorruptible, all pervading and all controlling. It was the same in
great things and in small, in every place and in every relation. When
he assumed the presidency he saw his duty as the leader of a great and
imperilled people, and determined to do the whole of it, leaning on
the arm of Him who "giveth power to the faint, and to them that have
no might increaseth strength," we admired his child-like simplicity,
his perfect freedom from guile, his forgiving temper, his persistent
devotion to every duty of his high position, his readiness to hear the
cause of the poor and the oppressed, his charity toward those who
questioned the correctness of his course; his large philanthropy, that
knew no distinction of race, but looked on all men as brethren; his
unswerving purpose that what freedom had gained should not be lost,
and that the end of war should be the end of slavery. All these things
commanded our admiration; but holier and more lovely than all of these
was his abiding confidence in God, and in final triumph, through Him
and for His sake. This was the secret alike of his strength and his
success, and by this
<pb n="37" facs="laurie37.jpg"/>
more than by any other excellence, he being dead, yet speaketh."</p>
               <p>So did President Lincoln perform the duties of each day;
and so through trust in the atoning blood of Jesus was he prepared to
die. God grant that while we seek to be found in Christ, not having
our own righteousness, but that which is through the faith of Christ,
we do not forget those words of our Great Example, "I have glorified
Thee on the earth. I have finished the work which Thou gavest me to
do." For in like manner God has given a work to every one of us. He
has not given the same to all, but to each one his own work, for which
he and not another is responsible. There is one work to the man of
property, and another to the man of mind, and to no individual in the
two classes is there precisely the same. There is one to the leader in
society and another to the follower; one to the mother and another to
the daughter. The duties of no two persons are identical, but they are
assigned by One who perfectly knows our capacities and
opportunities. Their performance is watched by One whose eye suffers
nothing to escape its notice--neither the positive transgression nor
the unperformed requirement. And judgment will be pronounced on all by
One who has left it on record, "To him that knoweth to do good, and
doeth it not, to him it is sin." Think of these things, and in the
light of that instant arrest of thought and speech and consciousness
Friday before last, see how far those of us who profess to obey Christ
are obeying his command, "Be ye therefore ready also, for in such an
hour as ye think not the Son of Man cometh." We have need to do this,
for God will not regard vain excuses. Nor will He
<pb n="38" facs="laurie38.jpg"/>
fail to render to every man according to his deeds; to them who by
patient continuance in well-doing, mark the words, not spasmodic
efforts in times of rivival, but <hi rend="italic">patient continuance
in well-doing</hi>, to those who <hi rend="italic">thus</hi> seek for
glory and honor and immortality, He will give eternal life; but unto
them that are contentious and do not obey the truth, preferring to
cavil rather than to serve --to such He will render indignation and
wrath, tribulation and anguish upon every soul of man that doeth evil,
of the Jews first and also of the Gentiles; of the two, I had rather
be an ignorant slave in Africa than a barren professor in New
England.</p>
               <p>And ye who make no profession, look after the fatal stroke,
at that heaving breast, that unconscious brain, and think what had
become of him had the work of preparation for eternity been put of
till then? And is your preparation all made? If not what security have
you that your death will not be as sudden, that your sick bed will not
be equally incapable of thought and feeling. God is not shut up to one
method of arresting mental activity. And have you any claim, that
Abraham Lincoln had not, to a continuance of consciousness even to the
last?</p>
               <p>Finally, my hearers, this event is eminently fitted to
correct some popular errors concerning death. One of these errors is,
to search the death-bed for evidences of piety rather than the
life. But where does the Bible sanction such a course? Does it
describe the death-bed of Paul, or the beloved disciple? Does it
record the dying experience of Moses on the top of Pisgah? or of
Joshua, his successor? Look at the lamp of David going out amid the
senilities of second childhood, or at the good Josiah, slain in his
chariot
<pb n="39" facs="laurie39.jpg"/>
at Megiddo. Read the short narrative of the death of our first
father. It is all contained in the brief sentence "and he died," and
not even so much is said of our first mother. How long she lived, or
when or how or where she died, who can tell? Of Samuel it is simply
said, "And Samuel died," and not even so much is said of Ezra, or
Isaiah, or any of the prophets. And was that death at Washington an
exception?</p>
               <p>Another popular error is an expectation that everything
pleasant and peaceful will attend the death of the righteous. But it
is of the wicked that it is written, "There are no bands in their
death--their strength is firm." And how many of the people of God have
perished by the hand of violence, in foul dungeons, and at fiery
stakes, and "others were tortured, not accepting deliverance; they
were stoned; they were sawn asunder; were tempted; were slain with the
sword; they wandered about in sheepskins and goatskins, being
destitute, afflicted, tormented." Go ask the noble army of martyrs
whether a death even of shame and insult be a token of perdition. Then
enter many a house of luxury, and enquire whether death in tapestried
chambers and amid all the alleviations of earthly love and wealth, be
a token of salvation.</p>
               <p>My hearers, even in death man looketh on the outward
appearance, but God looketh on the heart, and on its preparation for
heaven--not the physical comforts of a dying hour. What are all the
comforts of the home of Dives, if they end in perdition? What are all
the discomforts of the death of Lazarus--I do not say death <hi rend="italic">bed</hi>, for he may not have had one--if all ended in
Abraham's bosom? What is
<pb n="40" facs="laurie40.jpg"/>
a little more pain or a little less, if the eternity that follows be
with God? My Christian friends, that death-bed in the capital bids us
drop all anxiety about externals, and fix eye and heart on that far
more exceeding and eternal weight of glory. Leave all outward things
for Christ to order as He pleases, but be sure that ye commit your
soul into His holy keeping, till he presents it holy, unblamable and
unrebukable before the throne, and so rest, singing "The Lord is my
Shepherd, I shall not want." "Even in the valley of the shadow of
death, I will fear no evil! for Thou art with me. Thy presence is all,
all else is nothing."</p>
               <p>And you who do not call yourselves disciples--you who do
not look to Jesus as your Saviour--think what would all his
well-earned fame, what would all this affection, this universal
mourning avail for our beloved President, if he were not washed from
his sins in the blood of Jesus? And will you live longer without
coming to Him, that you too may have this life? Come to Him, and He
will give you grace to live, grace to die, and then share with you His
home and His throne in glory. Few will ever become Presidents of these
United States; very few will ever be mourned for as Abraham Lincoln is
mourned to-day. But "as many as receive Christ unto them does He give
power to become the sons of God, even to them that believe on His
name," yea, He makes every one of them kings and priests unto God, and
they shall reign with Him forever. Shall we not accept this grace, so
that, finding us ready to open unto Him immediately, He shall welcome
us into the kingdom prepared for us from the foundation of the
world?</p>
            </div2>
         </div1>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>