<TEI.2>
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt n="Strength in Sorrow">
            <title>Strength in Sorrow</title>
            <author>Leffingwell, Rev. C. S.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Compiled and edited by</resp>
               <name>Beck
Center</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent/>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Lewis H. Beck Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Emory University</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Atlanta,
Georgia</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>1996 Emory
University. Permission is granted to download, transmit, or otherwise
reproduce, distribute or display the contributions to the work claimed
by Emory University for non-profit educational purposes, provided
this header is included in its entirety.  For inquiries about
commercial uses, contact the Director, 
Pitts Theology Library, Emory
University, Atlanta, Georgia 30322</p>
            </availability>
            <date>1999</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Lincoln
Sermons Project</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Leffingwell,
Rev. C. S. Strength in Sorrow. A Sermon, Preached in St. John's Church,
Canandaigua, June 1st, 1865, on the Occasion of the National Fast,
Following Upon the Assassination of President Linclon.  Canandaigua:
Printed at C. Jobson's Office, Bemis Block, 2d Story. 1865.</bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This text derives from the Special Collections 
of Pitts Theology Library, Emory University, and is produced in 
collaboration with the Lewis H. Beck Center a, the Emory 
Preservation Office, and Pitts Theology Library.</p>
            <p>TRANSCRIBER: Lewis H. Beck Center and Emory University 
Preservation Office.</p>
            <p>PRODUCER:  BookLab, Inc., 1606 Headway Circle, 
Suite 100, Austin, TX 78754</p>
            <p>CAPTURE DEVICE: XEROX DocuImage 620S flatbed scanner</p>
            <p>CAPTURE DETAILS: Scanner software: XEROX ScanTool 
version 4.2.3; no gamma correction; images are all bitonal.</p>
            <p>CHANGE HISTORY: Using the Adobe Photoshop Batch Processor, 
we interpolated  the original TIFF files to 8-bit grays, 
and altered the resolution to 144 dpi, producing screen 
images twice the original size.  We then saved them in 
JPEG format.  We produced GIF thumbnails from the JPEG files.</p>
            <p>RESOLUTION: 600 ppi</p>
            <p>COMPRESSION: Resolution 144 per inch with Constrain 
Properties to 72 per inch.</p>
            <p>SOURCE: Original documents.</p>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>1999</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Scott Ellis</name>
               <resp>Staff</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <item>SGML tags inserted in compliance
with TEI guidelines using TEILITE</item>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div1 id="leffingwell.001" n="Strength in Sorrow" type="text">
            <head pn="1"> 
               <bibl> 
                  <title>Strength in
Sorrow</title> 
                  <date>June 1st, 1865</date> 
                  <pubPlace>St. John's
Church, Canandaigua, NY</pubPlace> 
                  <author>Leffingwell,
Rev. C. S.</author> 
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Canandaigua</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>C. Jobson's Office</publisher>
                     <date>1865</date>
                  </imprint>
               </bibl> 
            </head>
            <p pn="1">
               <figure entity="leffingwell1">
                  <figDesc>1st page of
Rev. C. S. Leffingwell's Strength in Sorrow.</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <p pn="1">STRENGTH IN SORROW.</p>
            <p pn="1">A SERMON,</p>
            <p pn="1">Preached in St. John's Church, Canandaigua,</p>
            <p pn="1">JUNE lst, 1865,</p>
            <p pn="1">ON THE OCCASION OF THE</p>
            <p pn="1">NATIONAL FAST, FOLLOWING UPON THE</p>
            <p pn="1">ASSASSINATION OF</p>
            <p pn="1">PRESIDENT LINCOLN.</p>
            <p pn="1">BY THE</p>
            <p pn="1">REV. C. S. LEFFINGWELL, M. A.,</p>
            <p pn="1">RECTOR</p>
            <p pn="1">CANANDAIGUA:</p>
            <p pn="1">Printed at C. Jobson's office, Bemis Block, 2d
story.</p>
            <p pn="1">1865.</p>
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p pn="2">
               <figure entity="leffingwell2">
                  <figDesc>2nd page
of Rev. C. S. Leffingwell's Strength in Sorrow.</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <p pn="2">CANANDAIGUA,</p>
            <p pn="2">THURSDAY, 1ST JUNE, 1865.</p>
            <p pn="2">Rev. C.S. LEFFINGWELL:--</p>
            <p pn="2">DEAR SIR:</p>
            <p pn="2">The undersigned respectfully
solicit for publication, a copy of the excellent and interesting
sermon delivered by you at St. John's Church, this morning, on the
occasion of the Fast day appointed in consequence of the assassination
of President Lincoln.</p>
            <p pn="2">Respectfully Yours,
						<lb/>JAMES C. SMITH,
						<lb/>EBENEZER HALE,
						<lb/>CHAS. B. MEEK,
						<lb/>SANDERS IRVING,
						<lb/>E.G. LAPHAM,
						<lb/>WILLIAM H. ADAMS,
						<lb/>W. FITCH CHENEY,
						<lb/>A.G. MURRAY.</p>
            <p pn="2">Hon. JAMES C. SMITH, EBENEZER HALE, Esq., and others:</p>
            <p pn="2">GENTLEMEN:--</p>
            <p pn="2">I have to acknowledge the
receipt of your complimentary favor of the 1st inst; and in acting
upon the subject matter of your note, rely upon your judgement rather
than on my own, and so, I place at your disposal the Sermon delivered
in St. John's Church, on the memorable day of our National Fast.</p>
            <p pn="2">Respectfully Yours,</p>
            <p pn="2">C.S. LEFFINGWELL.</p>
            <p pn="2">St. John's Rectory,</p>
            <p pn="2">June 3, 1865.</p>
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p pn="3">
               <figure entity="leffingwell3">
                  <figDesc>3rd page
of Rev. C. S. Leffingwell's Strength in Sorrow.</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <div2 id="leffingwell.002" n="SERMON" type="sermon">
               <head pn="3">SERMON.</head>
               <epigraph pn="3">
                  <p pn="3">What hath God wrought!"-(NUMBERS. XXIII:
23.)</p>
               </epigraph>
               <p pn="3">There is a duty laid upon me to-day from which I would
almost willingly shrink; the task of addressing you upon a subject,
concerning which, although our thoughts are all in unison, yet a
subject upon which a number of my congregation could speak with fuller
justice than myself. And for this reason, I had hoped, that one of our
own number would address our citizens this evening, from whose wisdom,
and large experience in dealing with legal and national topics, we
might have gleaned more valuable lessons than it may be in my power to
offer.</p>
               <p pn="3">But, though I feel myself incompetent to the task of the
hour, I shall gladly utter the honest convictions of my heart, and in
doing this, I feel assured from the oneness of sentiment among us,
that my words will meet a response in the breast of all.</p>
               <p pn="3">A month and a half has passed by, since the murder of
President Lincoln, but that brief period will not suffice to enable us
fully to estimate the worth of his character, or rightly to judge of
the influence which his official work and untimely death will have
upon our national future.</p>
               <pb n="4"/>
               <p pn="4">
                  <figure entity="leffingwell4">
                     <figDesc>4th page of
Rev. C. S. Leffingwell's Strength in Sorrow.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <p pn="4">Greater men, intellectually, doubtless our land could
boast. There were those of a higher culture and refinement among us;
there were men of more gracefulness and elegance of manner, and there
may have been men of a deeper toned religious life. But he had that
degree of religion which taught him to familiarize himself with the
Holy Scriptures,--to pray to the God of both princes and people,--to
infuse into his writings the spirit of our common Christianity, and to
make the rare acknowledgment in those public records and official
papers, of our utter dependence, as a nation, upon the Supreme
being.</p>
               <p pn="4">Had others a native exterior grace which he did not share,
or an acquired outward refinement which he did not reach? He had the
grace of honesty of purpose and singleness of heart, to do his duty
well in that state of life whereunto he had been called.</p>
               <p pn="4">Had
others greater charms of manner, and acceptableness of person? He had
that degree of attractiveness which has won for him a higher and more
enduring place in the national esteem,--than has been gained by any
man, since the noble form of Washington was laid clown to its quiet
rest in the hallowed shades of Mount Vernon.</p>
               <p pn="4">Could others be
found of stronger intellect or more vivid mental brilliance? He had
that degree of mental power which enabled him, under God, to
accomplish by his steady, persistent efforts, the great hope of a
nation's agonizing heart, that degree of mental energy which enabled
him, as God's instrument, to bring to a brilliant success, the last,
the
<pb n="5"/>
                  <figure entity="leffingwell5">
                     <figDesc>5th page of
Rev. C. S. Leffingwell's Strength in Sorrow.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
greatest experiment of modern history; an experiment whose momentous
issues we shall never fully realize; an undertaking whose results only
our children and our children's children will appreciate; an
experiment testing the strength,--and, thanks to our God,--proving the
stability of our republican form of government.</p>
               <p pn="5">The winds of division beat fiercely upon it; the waves of
rebellion rolled with gigantic force against it, but it stood,--and
stands to-day stronger than it stood before,--more firmly established
than ever, by earnest hearts and patriotic hands, upon the great rock
of eternal right.</p>
               <p pn="5">Friends abroad withdrew their sympathy, and foes abroad
gave aid to foes at home, but we think they would to-day gladly bury
the remembrance of their ill-judged deeds, and join with us in
rendering honor to the man who, under God, guided our nation through
those perilous times; the man who is remembered and mourned all
through our land to-day.</p>
               <p pn="5">Again, it was au experiment which forced upon our
government the final solution of the long vexing question, whether it
would continue to nurse, to feed, and fatten, with the life blood of
the nation,--that offspring of Satan, Human Slavery, or suffer it to
die a suicidal death, its hands imbrued in its own blood.</p>
               <p pn="5">For long and weary years the wisdom of our sagest
counsellors had been baffled in every plan and effort, to lift that
evil weight from the bowed head and aching shoulders of American
civilization. 
<pb n="6"/>
                  <figure entity="leffingwell6">
                     <figDesc>6th page of
Rev. C. S. Leffingwell's Strength in Sorrow.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
For long and weary years, that curse had been brooding over the land,
its ominous threats growing louder, its intimidating menaces growing
wilder and fiercer, alarming, the timorous and mocking the most
confident and brave.</p>
               <p pn="6">In an evil hour for itself, it gathered up its great
resources, and, snatching every adventitious aid, came rushing with
demoniac determination to give to the American Union the full stroke
of death.</p>
               <p pn="6">And in that sad encounter, our quiet, peaceful nation
reeled and tottered! Amazed and bewildered, is it strange that she
should have reeled? Is it marvellous that she should have stumbled?</p>
               <p pn="6">But she only stumbled. She did not fall. In her very
stumbling she learned her footing. She planted her feet more
firmly. She arose with caution, called in the strength hitherto
expended upon her accustomed peaceful acts, and renewed the contest
with valiant earnestness, while each successive struggle gave to her
the valued power of experience.</p>
               <p pn="6">She gained by continual victories and even by seeming
defeat, until now, at last, before her erect, well-knit frame and
stalwart form, the foe which sought her ruin lies lifeless at her
feet.</p>
               <p pn="6">The cloud, the veil is removed. The curse of human Slavery
is lifted from the brow of American Freedom, while the world abroad
looks on with wonder and amazement, and we at home are filled with
earnest gladness. For here, in the very home of Freedom, has Tyranny
received her greatest shock! Here in our own land, in our own time and
midst, has the greatest experiment of modern
<pb n="7"/>
                  <figure entity="leffingwell7">
                     <figDesc>7th page of
Rev. C. S. Leffingwell's Strength in Sorrow.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
history been made. Tyranny has sought the very life of Liberty and has
fallen in the act. Human Slavery has reached its possible limits, and
has perished in its own eventuatings.</p>
               <p pn="7">The reaction of this event, the influence of this great
stride of Liberty will be felt upon the world at large from this year
of grace onward.</p>
               <p pn="7">The rights of humanity have been asserted, defended and
upheld. The privileges of the few have been weighed in the balance
with the inalienable rights of the many, and, found wanting, have been
condemned, and that condemnation has been sealed,--forever sealed,--on
this continent, with the blood of the representative man of his
age,--him whom we commemorate to-day.</p>
               <p pn="7">His position as our President, during the fearful ordeal of
the Rebellion, drew upon him the steady earnest gaze of every
nation. He stood the foremost man of his time, the embodiment of the
great American idea,--"Popular rights, Freedom for all, Oppression to
none."  He caught thc clarion echo which has rung through our forests,
over our vallies and hills, which has resounded in our cities and
hamlets, until it has stamped itself upon the American Spirit--"<hi rend="italic">Liberty or Death!</hi>" Both were reached. Liberty for the
enslaved, Death for him. He fell, but his mission was accomplished,
his work was done,--and he has now been laid down to his rest,
sharing, the long sleep of those other heroes, who poured out their
life blood on the battle field, martyrs alike to the sacred work of
advancing, human civilization.</p>
               <pb n="8"/>
               <p pn="8">
                  <figure entity="leffingwell8">
                     <figDesc>8th page of
Rev. C. S. Leffingwell's Strength in Sorrow.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <p pn="8">The first words transmitted over the Magnetic Telegraph, whose
electric wires now encircle the land were these: "<hi rend="italic">What
hath God wrought!</hi>"</p>
               <p pn="8">Man, then only discovered what God had made from the
first. It was God's doing, and in his own time, he permitted the mind
of man to observe and apply the subtle element of Electricity to the
purposes and wants of civilized life, and now that mystic cord runs in
every direction over the world, and its varied uses have become a
recognized, essential element, in the work of human progress.</p>
               <p pn="8">But that first telegram,--"What hath God wrought!" has no
more appropriate application to that one advance, than to any other
great step of Civilization. The hand of God is to be recognized every
where, and at all times.</p>
               <p pn="8">Does any one ask, if I see the hand of God in the violent
scenes which were lately enacted in the city of Washington? I answer,
that I recognize the kind, overruling Providence of God in preserving
the lives of our national counsellors in their great extremity, and,
looking further back, I acknowledge the providence of God's overruling
care, in continuing him, their chief, in life, and effective health,
and strength, so long as he did,--in preserving him through all those
imminent perils, until his work was done.</p>
               <p pn="8">His life, to all human appearance, was in far greater
danger many times before. He had incurred risks which called forth the
fears of the nation.</p>
               <p pn="8">The memorable night of his inhuman slaughter, was marked by
no sign of evil. No danger ap-
<pb n="9"/>
                  <figure entity="leffingwell9">
                     <figDesc>9th page of
Rev. C. S. Leffingwell's Strength in Sorrow.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
peared in view. The great jeopardies, the apparent hazards had all
been ventured before, and in and through them a good providence had
sheltered him;--and now, when the work assigned him to be accomplished
in active life had been done,--the work assigned him to be
accomplished in death was <hi rend="italic">permitted to occur</hi>.</p>
               <p pn="9">In that event, God has taught afresh, and with an emphasis never
more thrilling, that any human arm, to which nations or individuals
may cling for defence or safety, is frail as the bending reed, and
fleeting as the passing hour.</p>
               <p pn="9">That human aid, though given by God's goodness, and
sustained by God's providence, is only human and is to be given up in
God's own time. That lesson we have been taught anew, which the
Psalmist inculcated long centuries ago: "It is better to trust in the
Lord than to put any confidence in princes." Their power is feeble and
limited. They are weak and finite. They must perish like
ourselves,--for they are subject to the same unhesitating call. The
highest form must bend. The strongest arm must yield. The wisest and
most prudent, cannot foresee, and prevent, the inevitable lot of
all. Death renders no homage to lofty place, or deference to highest
worth. All earthly powers are tributary to the King of Terrors. He
walks the palace floor, and climbs the very throne. He snatches the
sceptre from the hand of power, and tramples on goodness, and mocks at
greatness.</p>
               <p pn="9">The worthiest princes, as was said of David must, after
serving their, generation for a time, fall
<pb n="10"/>
                  <figure entity="leffingwell10">
                     <figDesc>10th page of
Rev. C. S. Leffingwell's Strength in Sorrow.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
asleep. For this reason we are to moderate our confidence in them, and
make it subordinate to the trust we should ever repose in God. Theirs,
may indeed, be wise designs, and generous purposes for the nation's
good, but when "their breath goeth forth, then all their thoughts
perish!</p>
               <p pn="10">What vain props are these, for a nation's security! What
uncertain support, what unsafe reliance, is any thing, short of God,
upon whose direct guidance we all are freshly taught to lean.</p>
               <p pn="10">In coming years, men will read the record of our late civil
strife, with a truer understanding of God's Providential guidings, and
will be able to trace the steps of his wisdom and goodness and love in
many of the complicated and trying events of the time, which we from
our nearer position, may be unable fully to decipher.</p>
               <p pn="10">But even now, blind is the eye, and unbelieving is the
heart, which does not recognize the Providence of the Lord of Hosts,
in leading this great people, through broad fields of blood toward the
quiet valley of rest, guiding our perilous march, made with agonizing
hearts, through the black night of war, and bidding us to celebrate
the dawn of peace, while gathered as one great mourning nation, even
around the new-made grave of our slaughtered leader.</p>
               <p pn="10">That death occurred with the fore-knowledge, and permission
of the omniscient God, and, as concerning our great gladness in
victory and peace, so concerning our great grief in tile loss of the
President,--we may well exclaim with wondering awe:
<pb n="11"/>
                  <figure entity="leffingwell11">
                     <figDesc>11th page of
Rev. C. S. Leffingwell's Strength in Sorrow.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
"<hi rend="italic">What hath God Wrought!</hi>" How he has allied grief
unto gladness! How he dashed our growing joy with sudden and weighty
sorrow,--and made that unforseen, abrupt commingling of smiles and
tears, a nation's emblem of human life! How he evidenced to all, that
which every christian man should remember in his private individual
life, that the hour of victory is the hour of danger!</p>
               <p pn="11">And even in minor and more personal matters, the providence
of God has been plainly apparent. How brief the victim's suffering!
How promptly the foul assassin was brought to bay, and how wisely was
his evil life disposed of! How quietly our government passed on, in
its regular functions! How quickly was the great Rebellion ended! How
rapid the events of those few days! Who can forget them!</p>
               <p pn="11">There is such a majesty, such a power in solemn universal
grief, that in those dark hours of sorrow we felt within ourselves and
in each other, a firm strength and a oneness, which gave to the
American nation a presence and a mien, approaching the sublime! In
solemn quietness we stood, and looked calmly upward to our God, though
vivid hopes and startling fears were pulsating in every vein! But
God's arm brought salvation. His providential care, bridged over the
danger. And now, as we see those fears removed, and those hopes
reaching fruition, is it too soon, even on this day of humiliation and
sadness, in view of all that has been done,--in view of all that has
been gained, and of all that has been
<pb n="12"/>
                  <figure entity="leffingwell12">
                     <figDesc>12th page of
Rev. C. S. Leffingwell's Strength in Sorrow.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
lost, is it too soon to exclaim with reverence,--"<hi rend="italic">What
hath God wrought!</hi>"</p>
               <p pn="12">Brethren, who of us hereafter will reckon upon any certain
morrow? A few weeks since,--in that holy season, when we were
reviewing the sad scenes of Calvary,--on the last morning of the week,
when as it were we watched the holy sepulchre where our Lord was
laid--there came sudden tidings! In whispered tones men told them to
each other. "Impossible!" we each one cried,--but it was true.</p>
               <p pn="12">Our president was dead!--dead, while almost countless
armies, awaited his bidding,--dead, while the great world was watching
for his next movement.</p>
               <p pn="12">Who then of us will count with certainty upon any
to-morrow!</p>
               <p pn="12">But while we do live, let us, as we now, led by the hand of
God are merging upon better and brighter times,--let us ever cherish
the memory of the patriotic dead,--the heroes who have gone forth in
our stead--who have fought our battles for us, and have perished.</p>
               <p pn="12">Let them still live. Let their names be always fresh, and
their memory ever green, that in generations to come our children may
cherish their worth, and honor their deeds,--as we have done honor to
the heroes of revolutionary fame.</p>
               <pb n="13"/>
               <p pn="13">
                  <figure entity="leffingwell13">
                     <figDesc>14th
page of Rev. C. S. Leffingwell's Strength in
Sorrow.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <p pn="13">Wherever they lie buried, in prison vault or open
field--there is a shrine for patriotic pilgrimage,--"there is a spot,
at which, for ages to come, valor shall gain fresh life, and where
freedom shall trim her torch."</p>
               <p pn="13">They have not died in vain,--their death procures for us a
lasting peace; enlarges the area of human freedom, builds up in every
corner of our land, a tower of strength impregnable to any foe abroad,
and points forever to the bloody doom of treachery at home!</p>
               <p pn="13">Shall we not then, as Christian Patriots, give unto God the
glory due for his providential care, and in view of all that we have
gained, as well as in view of all that we have lost, exclaim with
reverence,--</p>
               <p pn="13">"WHAT HATH GOD WROUGHT!"</p>
               <pb n="14"/>
               <p pn="14">
                  <figure entity="leffingwell14">
                     <figDesc>14th
page of Rev. C. S. Leffingwell's Strength in
Sorrow.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <p pn="14">THE PRAYER FOR UNITY.</p>
               <p pn="14">Almighty God, we implore Thy mercy for all the people of
this land, and more especially therein for all Christians; beseeching
Thee to give us grace, seriously to lay to heart, the great dangers we
are in, by our unhappy divisions. Take away all hatred and prejudice,
and whatever else may hinder us from godly union and concord; that, as
there is but one body and one Spirit, and one hope of our calling, one
Lord, one Faith, one Baptism, one God and Father of us all; so we may
henceforth be all of one heart and one soul, united in one holy bond
of truth, of faith and charity, and may with one mind and one mouth
glorify Thee; through Jesus Christ our Lord. Amen.</p>
            </div2>
         </div1>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI.2>