<TEI.2>
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt n="The Nation's Sacrifice">
            <title>  The Nation's
Sacrifice</title>
            <author>Mayo, A. D.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Compiled and edited by</resp>
               <name>Beck
Center</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent/>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Lewis H. Beck Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Emory University</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Atlanta,
Georgia</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>1996 Emory
University. Permission is granted to download, transmit, or otherwise
reproduce, distribute or display the contributions to the work claimed
by Emory University for non-profit educational purposes, provided
this header is included in its entirety.  For inquiries about
commercial uses, contact the Director, 
Pitts Theology Library, Emory
University, Atlanta, Georgia 30322</p>
            </availability>
            <date>1999</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Lincoln
Sermons Project</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Mayo,
A. D. The Nation's Sacrifice. Abraham Lincoln.  Two Discourses,
Delivered on Sunday Morning, April 16, and Wednesday Morning, April
19, 1865, in the Church of the Redeemer, Cincinnati, Ohio.
Cincinnati: Robert Clarke &#x0026; Co., 55 West Fourth St. 1865.  </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This text derives from the Special Collections 
of Pitts Theology Library, Emory University, and is produced in 
collaboration with the Lewis H. Beck Center a, the Emory 
Preservation Office, and Pitts Theology Library.</p>
            <p>TRANSCRIBER: Lewis H. Beck Center and Emory University 
Preservation Office.</p>
            <p>PRODUCER:  BookLab, Inc., 1606 Headway Circle, 
Suite 100, Austin, TX 78754</p>
            <p>CAPTURE DEVICE: XEROX DocuImage 620S flatbed scanner</p>
            <p>CAPTURE DETAILS: Scanner software: XEROX ScanTool 
version 4.2.3; no gamma correction; images are all bitonal.</p>
            <p>CHANGE HISTORY: Using the Adobe Photoshop Batch Processor, 
we interpolated  the original TIFF files to 8-bit grays, 
and altered the resolution to 144 dpi, producing screen 
images twice the original size.  We then saved them in 
JPEG format.  We produced GIF thumbnails from the JPEG files.</p>
            <p>RESOLUTION: 600 ppi</p>
            <p>COMPRESSION: Resolution 144 per inch with Constrain 
Properties to 72 per inch.</p>
            <p>SOURCE: Original documents.</p>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>1999</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Scott Ellis</name>
               <resp>Staff</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <item>SGML tags inserted in compliance
with TEI guidelines using TEILITE</item>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div1 id="mayo.001" n="The Nation's Sacrifice" type="text">
            <head> 
               <bibl> 
                  <title>The Nation's
Sacrifice</title> 
                  <date>Sunday Morning, April 16, and Wednesday
Morning, April 19, 1865</date> 
                  <pubPlace>Church of the Redeemer,
Cincinnati, Ohio</pubPlace> 
                  <author>Mayo, A. D.</author> 
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Cincinnati</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Robert Clarke &#x0026; Co., 55
West Fourth St.</publisher>
                     <date>1865</date>
                  </imprint> 
               </bibl>
            </head>
            <p>
               <figure entity="mayo1">
                  <figDesc>1st page A. D. Mayo's The Nation's
Sacrifice. </figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <p>THE NATION'S SACRIFICE.</p>
            <p>ABRAHAM LINCOLN.</p>
            <p>TWO DISCOURSES,</p>
            <p>Delivered on Sunday Morning, April 16, and Wednesday <lb/>Morning,
April 19, 1865,</p>
            <p>IN THE</p>
            <p>CHURCH OF TEE REDEEMER,</p>
            <p>CINCINNATI, OHIO.</p>
            <p>By A. D. MAYO, Pastor.</p>
            <p>CINCINNATI:</p>
            <p>ROBERT CLARKE &#x0026; CO., 55 WEST FOURTH ST.</p>
            <p>1865.</p>
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>
               <figure entity="mayo2">
                  <figDesc>2nd page
A. D. Mayo's The Nation's Sacrifice. </figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>
               <figure entity="mayo3">
                  <figDesc>3rd page
A. D. Mayo's The Nation's Sacrifice. </figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <div2 id="mayo.002" n="THE NATION'S SACRIFICE." type="sermon">
               <head>THE NATION'S SACRIFICE.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <p>"Without shedding of blood is no remission."-HEB. ix,
22.</p>
               </epigraph>
               <p>When God is speaking, who shall open his mouth! He speaks
to us to-day, and his word is the old voice of inspiration: "<hi rend="italic">Without shedding of b1ood is no remission</hi>.</p>
               <p>All shedding of blood is by God's permission. Not one act
of violence, not one destruction of life, not one drop of human blood
shed, without his knowledge and consent. For God is infinite love, and
in His perfect providence all things work together for good. Even the
things that seem so terrible that men tremble as if there were a
Prince of Darkness, and he were master of the universe, are compelled
to do His sovereign will. <hi rend="italic">He maketh the wrath of man
to praise him, and the remainder of wrath shall He restrain.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Ever since the beginning of the world the friends of
falsehood and sin have believed that the right could be put down by
shedding the blood of the righteous. Cain believed he could destroy
the true worship of God by slaying Abel, the servant of God. And since
his day every wicked and foolish man, every great despot, every
God-defying class, every desperate member of every party of
unrighteousness the world has seen has been crazed by this stupendous
delusion that the Truth and Justice and Holiness of God Almighty could
be driven away from the earth by killing the friends of God and
man.</p>
               <p>So the world, for four thousand years, has been full of
blood. None of it rests upon the hands of the consistent friends of
God and man, for all they have shed has been in defense of everlasting
righteousness. It all rests on the souls of the enemies of Truth and
Goodness; for they never have overcome the hideous delusion that they
could slay the Truth by slaughtering its de-
<pb n="4"/>
                  <figure entity="mayo4">
                     <figDesc>4th page A. D. Mayo's The
Nation's Sacrifice. </figDesc>
                  </figure>
fenders. Oh! what an Aceldema have they made of this fair earth by
their insanity! How many of the wisest, best, loveliest--the glory of
all ages and all lands--have they sent to their God, through
blood-stained paths! How many of the wicked, the worst of the earth,
have they also sent to judgment in blood! How many, in all conditions
of spiritual life, have they drowned in this bloody sea of wrath! But
yet, <hi rend="italic">the wrath of ma1l shall praise Him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>One would have thought that when the concentrated falsehood
and injustice of the ancient time, wielding the power of the Roman
Empire, nailed Jesus, Son of God and man, to the bloody cross, that
the wrath of man had done its worst. And when, out of the shedding of
Christ's blood came Salvation for even his own murderers, when the
Roman power that slew him at last bent before his gentle sway, so that
the very names of Rome and the cross are fixed together till the end
of time--one might have hoped that wicked men would have learned the
impotence of shedding blood to help the wrong. But wicked men do not
learn such things. And every year since the sacrifice of Christ, the
violent on earth have been peopling Heaven with martyrs and filling
all lands with tears and blood.</p>
               <p>And we have lived to behold what our eyes have seen during
the last four years, reaching its climax of horrors in that strange
deed which we can hardly yet believe has happened. We supposed, a few
years ago, that the vast majority of mankind in civilized lands had
finally learned that no great wrong could be upheld one hour by
shedding of blood. But God has called us, in this new world, to behold
what the peoples of the old world, the other side of the great waters,
have witnessed so often--the auful delusion and wrath of that
despotism which is the sum of all wrong against earth and Heaven. We
did not believe what history had told us on her every bloody page,
that a tyrant, or a class of tyranical men would commit all crimes of
which human nature is capable, under the vain fanatical belief that
they could put man down and keep him down. So God has raised up, right
among us, of our very hearts' kin, our friends, countrymen,
associates, participators with us in all the blessed privileges of
American life, a class of despots, who, within the last half century,
have committed more crimes, and worse crimes, than any great
aristocracy that yet has dominated in ancient or modern days.  For I
verily believe that when History comes to make
<pb n="5"/>
                  <figure entity="mayo5">
                     <figDesc>5th page A. D. Mayo's The
Nation's Sacrifice. </figDesc>
                  </figure>
out her awful record against the slave aristocracy of these United
States of America, it will be seen that since it appeared as a
consolidated social and civil power, half a century ago, it has done
evil to a greater number of human beings, sinned against greater
light, caused the death of more innocent men, affrighted this world
with more ghastly and singular shapes of horror and wrath, and
meanness, and cold cruelty, than any one set of wicked men has ever
yet been able to achieve.</p>
               <p>Oh, how blind we were, not to see that a class of men who
deliberately began by the blasphemy of God in the systematic
degradation of his image, man, to a brute, would do any vile or bloody
thing which human nature could devise. Yet we did not see it for so
many years. We said: no, these gentlemen and gentlewomen are our
brothers and sisters, our associates in Church, in State, in society;
they are dreadfully mistaken, and are now doing wrong to their
bondmen, but they will hear the voice of our reason, our science, our
religion; they will repent, and be reconciled, and at last do justice
to their own enslaved, to us, to themselves, and to their country. And
so we went on in our sin and blindness, strengthening their hands,
arming them with new weapons of power, forgiving them faster than they
could harm us. We might have known then they were inflicting the worst
outrages ever conceived on three millions of their unhappy subjects;
but we said: they are of another race, they are not quite men; and
went on making them stronger and stronger to slay us.</p>
               <p>And soon enough they began to shed the blood of our own
proud race, and to do to us all the dreadful things they had done to
our weaker brother. They began to insult and abuse, and murder our
people who, among themselves, lifted up their voices against this
great wrong of despotism. We loved the liberty of speech, and they
began to kill men for speaking the truth about their sin; we loved the
freedom of the press, and they destroyed the types, and assassinated
the editors; we were more gentle and reverent in our treatment of
woman than any people ever was, and they imprisoned women for teaching
children to read the Bible; we were proud of our free labor, and they
killed and drove away the emigrants to every Territory and State they
had doomed to be their own; we favored free suffrage, but they tried
to murder every man that voted for the freedom of all men; we supposed
the pulpit would be a place of safety, but they hung
<pb n="6"/>
                  <figure entity="mayo6">
                     <figDesc>6th page A. D. Mayo's The
Nation's Sacrifice. </figDesc>
                  </figure>
and shot ministers of the Gospel of the Golden Rule, and set a price
on Channing's head; we thought the scholar's gown a shield, but they
drove away, with terrible threats, every scholar who would not
prostitute his learning to the enslavement of mankind; we supposed the
Senate was an ark of safety, but they came in and half slew the
foremost of American scholars and philanthropists on the floor of the
Senate.</p>
               <p>Yet all this did not open our eyes. Then they tried their
hand on a higher thing, and resolved to drown the nation herself in
the blood of her freedom-loving citizens. Four years ago last Friday
they opened war, and for four years they have waged a conflict that
has not been so much a war as a Saturnalia of all crimes within the
record of man. They knew that if they would destroy this great
republic they must wade through oceans of blood, and do such deeds,
accursed of God and man, as would astonish mankind; but they did not
hold back.</p>
               <p>Oh, what things they have done, my friends, during these
years! They have caused to be slain in battle, or to be wounded, or to
die of sickness, or to be prostrated by anxiety and excitement, and
the terrible bewilderment of revolution, not less than a million human
beings. They have caused to be destroyed enough property to educate
every child on the globe into a Christian man or woman. They have
killed men in every variety of ways. When the Union men and women and
children of the South shall stand up in evidence against these
enemies, no one of us will have the heart to read their story. They
have redoubled their cruelty to their slaves, and forced them, at the
bayonet's point, to work, yea, to fight, for their own
enslavement. They have slaughtered women, murdered little children,
butchered prisoners of war; they have deliberately starved to death
thousands of white men taken captive in fair battle; they have
insulted the remains of our slain. They mutilated the dead body of
Dahlgren, and their best man, Robert Lee, sent to the father of the
boy, as an excuse for the bloody deed, a pretended document of most
barbaric import, said to have been found upon him, but deliberately
forged and photographed, and then they hid his body for a whole
year. They have enrolled bands of assassins, to steal upon border
villages, five hundred miles from the seat of war, and shoot our
citizens at mid-day. They have lighted up every ocean with the glare
of our unarmed merchant ships. They have tried to burn our great
cities, and involve thousands
<pb n="7"/>
                  <figure entity="mayo7">
                     <figDesc>7th page A. D. Mayo's The
Nation's Sacrifice. </figDesc>
                  </figure>
of every age and sex in wholesale destruction. Under the name of
guerrilla operations, legalized by their sham government, they have
disorganized human society itself over vast regions of our territory,
and rendered life a daily peril and curse not fifty miles from our own
doors. Sons murdering fathers, and brothers their brothers, and
neighbors shedding one another's blood, even women betraying men to
the assassin; all these things have become so common that we think of
them as every day affairs.</p>
               <p>But in spite of all this they did not prosper. Their cause
waxed weaker as their wrath increased. The more freemen they killed
the more men became freemen. They slaughtered our soldiers, but our
ranks filled up and stood more firmly. They murdered Union men, but
the Union grew, watered by their blood. They starved their prisoners,
but our cause waxed full and mighty. Stung to very madness, they
solemnly resolved at last that their black slaves should be made
soldiers, to gain their unholy ends; and before the ink was dry on
that godless statute, their sham President and their sham Congress,
their General-in-Chief and his powerful army, had disappeared by one
blow of divine justice, so that they shall no more be known as a power
on the earth, while the negro slave marched in, a conqueror and a
freeman, under the Union, and occupied Richmond and Charleston, the
Sodom and Gomorroh of their land of blood!</p>
               <p>And then we thought the end of wrath had come. We said:
these men must now see that there is no longer any hope in war, they
know their despotism is dead forever; will they not come in and be our
brethren once more? I have, during the last two weeks, travelled
through seven free States, and in all their chief cities seen great
crowds of people rejoicing over our victories, and the grandest thing
I saw was the magnanimity of the people towards these, their mortal
foes. Oh, if this Southern aristocracy, this prodigal son of the
nation, this wanderer from the flock, would now come back to us, not
in abject humiliation, but repentant, willing to be forgiven, willing
to unite with us in building up the Republic, how gladly would this
people, on its last great day of rejoicing, have gone out, like the
Father, and taken the stricken one in to the great feast of love to
God and man!</p>
               <p>But no, it was not so to be. Wicked men upon earth always
go on to the last result, and that result is <hi rend="italic">to slay
their truest</hi>
                  <pb n="8"/>
                  <figure entity="mayo8">
                     <figDesc>8th page A. D. Mayo's The
Nation's Sacrifice. </figDesc>
                  </figure>
                  <hi rend="italic">friends, and quench their blind rage in the blood of
the noblest who would die to save them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There were two men in these United States, who were, under
Providence, the most noted representatives of Human Liberty in all the
land. The elder of the two was the greatest philosophic statesman that
this or any republic has produced--a man whose vast mind beheld the
regular onward march of Liberty from age to age, and who, in the midst
of the apparent success of tyranny always percieved the coming
deliverance of man. For forty years has this great and good man,
gentle as a woman, genial as a little child, forgiving and kind and
magnanimous to a fault, calmly uttered, in words that never purposely
wounded a human being, or uttered one thought of private malignity or
personal spite, the lofty prophecy, of the passing away of the
despotism of the land. Accused of the worst motives and frailties, and
intrigues, his real power has been in his wondrous glance over the
field of our national life, so that like a watchman from a lofty
tower, he has told off the passing hours of slavery, and called the
people to welcome the morn of freedom. He never made a public mistake
that was not the weakness of a heart too benevolent to credit what his
reason told him was true of the enemies of man. He trusted so much in
great ideas--he saw so clearly the inevitable conquest of the wrong by
the right--that he was apparently careless what special measures
should be enacted, or what special offenders put to shame. He once
said to me: "We talk of vengeance upon the aristocracy of the South;
let us only protect Liberty in the Union, and that aristocracy will at
last come to us to be kept from starvation; and we, of the free
States, will be obliged to nurse the South back to life like a sick
child."</p>
               <p>Among all the statesmen of the world, there was no man who,
last Friday at sundown was at once so true a friend to the South, so
true a friend to Union and Liberty, so firm a believer in the progress
of man, so willing and eager to receive every repentant enemy of the
Republic, and rejoice over his conversion, as WM. HENRY SEWARD,
Secretary of State. He was born in the Empire State. He came on one
side, of a Welsh ancestry, and for forty years of public life has been
as inflexible in what he believed the cause of Freedom as the rocks
and mountains, and noble people of that land. On the other side he was
of Irish lineage, and no son of that afflicted race was ever more
genial,
<pb n="9"/>
                  <figure entity="mayo9">
                     <figDesc>9th page A. D. Mayo's The
Nation's Sacrifice. </figDesc>
                  </figure>
more gracious, more winning, to friend and foe. And what American ever
had a vision of the Union so lofty as his--a Union from which even her
rebellious children should not always be cast out, which should lift
up the lowliest to liberty, and teach the proudest monarchs on earth
to rejoice in the prosperity of man?</p>
               <p>And along with him I always saw his best-beloved son--a
young man who seemed the perfect embodiment of his father's
sweetness. He was so good, and simple-hearted and conscientious and
gentle, that all men loved him as he walked the streets.</p>
               <p>But there was one other in the land, greater than this
statesman--because manhood is grander than genius, and silent and
patient power nobler than the most gracious courtesy. ABRAHAM LINCOLN
was the most faithful representative of the whole people, in public
affairs, this world has yet seen. He came of a Northern Quaker
paternity, and his maternity was out of the common people of old
Virginia. He had worked through every kind of experience the people
knew, up to the Presidency of the Republic. He was neither quick, nor
brilliant, nor demonstrative; but his broad soul touched every class
and race of our strangely mingled nationality. He felt in his blood
what they were feeling and thinking; he knew what they could do, and
bear, and achieve. He knew every kind of American men better than they
knew themselves. He loved truth, and he loved man as
well. Contemporaneously with Seward he saw and declared that the
republic must be all free or all slave. Like Seward, he did not
agitate for freedom so fiercely as some, for he saw its mighty coming
afar off, and saved his strength to organize the new
Republic. Apparently by the intrigues of policy, but really by the
Providence of God, he was preferred to his great associate as
candidate for President. The people knew by instinct whom they could
trust, and chose him. He journeyed to Washington, so unpretendingly,
so carefully, saying no harsh word; full of love for all the people of
his vast domain. How he has carried the people through four years of
frightful war, so that the republic is now triumphant, and slavery
abolished, and the class that tried to destroy us going to its own
place, history will say. And oh, how compassionate, how just, how like
a father he has been to these mad children of the household. Has he
said one word in bitterness of them? Has he pushed one measure in
wrath? Has he knowingly done one deed that should prevent
<pb n="10"/>
                  <figure entity="mayo10">
                     <figDesc>10th page A. D. Mayo's
The Nation's Sacrifice. </figDesc>
                  </figure>
any rebellious man from coming to him as to a father? Read over again
that last address of his--so broad, so practical, so wise, so
magnanimous. Who ever went through such a four years so purely, so
successfully, so lovingly, as he? As he awoke last Friday morning, he
could have felt that his work was done; the army and navy of the Union
everywhere triumphant; the people united in their rulers; slavery
wounded to death; the nation ready to start anew on her glorious
career of power and freedom. Had the deadliest rebel tyrant in all
America so true a friend in the whole world that day as ABRAHAM
LINCOLN?</p>
               <p>So, here was the opportunity for this slave power to fill
up the measure of its iniquity by striking at the life of the two men,
of all others, who could have rescued it from its barbarity. And it
did not hesitate a moment. Alas! the wretch who aimed at the father of
his people did his work too well, and ABRAHAM LINCOLN has died, a
blessed martyr, that his country might live! May God spare SEWARD to
take one more observation of the political heavens and hells, and, in
his own simple and majestic language, tell us what becomes of a power
that signalizes its last occasion for repentance by the last crime of
the assassination of the only men that could save it from perdition!
May that blameless young man be spared to forgive the poor creature
that tried to kill him because he would save his sick father's
life!</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">And now-what?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Nothing new. Only the same old thing that has been going on
since the foundation of the world; all known to and approved by the
Providence that never was beaten by any enemy of God or man.</p>
               <p>One more martyr to Human Liberty. One more great and good
man exalted by bloody death to the most sacred name in this new
time. Is this a mistake of Providence? We have carelessly babbled that
we could not choose a great man for President; the people did not know
whom to trust. God has condescended to meet and dispose of that
falsehood, once and forever. Never was ruler so instinctively
recognized, so generously obeyed, so completely approved in his life
as ABRAHAM LINCO1N by the Freemen of this Republic. And now that his
great work is done, he has fitly put on the martyr's crown. WASHINGTON
was Father of his County; our country owes to him her independent
life. ABRAHAM LINCOLN was the <hi rend="italic">Father of the American
people</hi>: first
<pb n="11"/>
                  <figure entity="mayo11">
                     <figDesc>11th page A. D. Mayo's
The Nation's Sacrifice. </figDesc>
                  </figure>
under him was there one free people of the United States. Together in
sainted memory will these men abide.</p>
               <p>One more warning to the people of the nature of the power
with which they contend. As long as there is a class in America that
denies the humanity of man, it will do just what this slave
aristocracy is now doing--what its leaders still advise it to do. It
will argue till it is beaten--and then try to kill the priest, the
scholar, the statesmen who have refuted it. It will fight as long as
it can, with all the bravery and barbarity of savages, and when it
surrenders as a warrior, reappear as an assassin. I do not say that
all these rebel men and-women, that a majority of them, would
personally have done this deed. But I say that a class that begins by
denying humanity will end by doing all the infamy that was ever done,
and then invent some new curse to scourge the world. This aristocracy
has already committed all the crimes that men ever committed before;
who shall say what hideous and strange enormity may startle us
tomorrow? It will go on to its death as it has begun.</p>
               <p>One more solemn announcement--that however merciful God and
good men may be to individual sinners, yet for <hi rend="italic">every
wicked class and every unrighteous institution there is only eternal
death</hi>. We may forgive every rebel in the Union of his special
guilt, neither you, nor all men, nor God can forgive an aristocracy
that has risen on hatred and contempt for man. This mighty revolution
will go on, as every one like it has gone on, till that old slave
aristocracy is ground to finer dust than now covers the grave of the
man it slew. Last Friday it perhaps seemed that it might be saved, but
we had only seen the beginning of the end. Before midnight it had
opened between itself and modern times a gulf so deep and wide that no
human arm can reach it more! It drove at the nation's heart four years
ago, crying out: "<hi rend="italic">Let us alone!</hi>" Well, <hi rend="italic">now, at last, it is alone in God's world</hi>. It has put
itself outside the pale of human fellowship, respect,
forgiveness. When the poor slave of that proud old caste flourished
aloft his steel, and cried out, "<hi rend="italic">Sic semper
Tyrannis</hi>!" he spoke by the inspiration of God; he was the star
actor of the great tragedy of modern days, for on that stage did the
American slave aristocracy commit suicide, and pass away, forever more
to be "<hi rend="italic">let alone</hi>" by God and man. There did
tyrannical old Virginia, having gone down through every phase of
wickedness
<pb n="12"/>
                  <figure entity="mayo12">
                     <figDesc>12th page A. D. Mayo's
The Nation's Sacrifice. </figDesc>
                  </figure>
and meanness, perish, shouting her own motto and epitaph, and the
world will never behold old Virginia any more.</p>
               <p>Do you talk of vengeance! Look away across the abyss, to
that Southern aristocracy, in its silent torment; look at poor old
Virginia, and tell me what is left for you to do. We can live with
LINCOLN away from the earth. <hi rend="italic">But he was the last man
that could have persuaded this American people to try to build
anything good, out of that pile of rubbish--the slave aristocracy of
the South</hi>. Henceforth the man who seriously proposes to
resuscitate and reconstruct that old power may be permitted to go his
way, as a maniac so hopeless that he can do no man harm. God seems to
have said to us at the end of our rejoicings, last Friday night:-- All
things are possible to your great energy, hope and love, save this
one; see what this despotism will do on its way to everlasting
perdition; henceforth waste no breath in calling to life what God has
doomed to eternal death.</p>
               <p>Who shall say the price is too great to pay for such a
revelation from heaven? For now has come in the second era of this
revolution. The great enemy is destroyed; we wounded him to death, and
even while dying he clutched the pistol and through the head of our
President, blew out his own foolish brains. Once for all, the American
people understand which way lies hell. Every man not a fool can see
to-day that one thing can never again be done. Next to knowing just
what to do, it is good to know just what not to do. If ABRAHAM LINCOLN
had lived he might have failed to show us just what to do in our new
era of shaping the people's Republic. He has died to show us just what
not to do in all the generations of man. What man, by his life and
death, has decided a question so momentous before? God knows his own
ways, and has used his servant, our Father, for the best.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Without the shedding of blood is no
remission</hi>. Our blood has been poured out like water during four
dreadful years, but all the time has God been lifting us thereby out
of our sin. And now, that in our beloved President we all bleed
to-day, we know all shall be saved to Freedom and Union, and all sins
of the people be forgiven. We had said that LINCOLN must live till he
became President of all the people--the loyal, who obeyed, and the
disloyal, who defied the Republic through him. That was not to be. But
now that he has passed through bloody death to his victory, he has
gone up to his glorious inauguration in the
<pb n="13"/>
                  <figure entity="mayo13">
                     <figDesc>13th page A. D. Mayo's
The Nation's Sacrifice. </figDesc>
                  </figure>
heavens, as sovereign of the hearts of the whole American
people. There he dwells, above the rage of his enemies and the folly
of his friends; and there he will dwell in glory, till the children of
all these wrathful and bloody men, one by one, shall be subdued by his
mighty love, and come into the great Union of freedom. No one man
could unite the American people today. But ABRAHAM LINCOLN is now a
name about which all who inhabit this vast Republic shall gather in
reverence while time endures. By the shedding of this sacred blood,
our God and Saviour have told us there is remission for all the
people's sins. Under the Saviour, Christ, shall this nation, through
its chief of martyrs, be saved.</p>
               <p>And now, Friends, Countrymen, Christians, what of us?
Another true and tried man is President. Let every loyal soul rise up
and stand to-day like a wall of strength by ANDREW JOHNSON, now, by
the Providence of God, President of this Republic, regenerated and
renewed by the sacrifice of bloody war.</p>
               <p>By this event we are shown that no one man is great enough
to do this mighty work before us, neither is any one man
indispensable. Were every great man to fall to-morrow, there would
still be left the American People, whose children and servants they
are. We are that American People, God's chosen people of these modern
days to lead the world to the freedom of all mankind. Every one of us
must be somewhat nobler now that our great leader is gone. Let no
breath now be wasted in barbaric curses, no power lost in
indiscriminate vengeance. It would be childish in us to go off into a
frenzy, or drift into disorder, or try to wash out his precious blood
by spurning the corpse of the slave aristocracy! No! Let that
abomination alone! Begin, to-morrow morning, to build up the American
home, American industry, American religion, American society, the
American Republic, in all its vast extent, with that decayed
aristocracy left out and let alone. "Let alone" every man and woman
that ties to that dead body. The new age is here. Have your doings,
and sayings, and associations with living men and living
things. Everywhere do better than you have yet done. Stop not to weep;
but work and pray; and as you toil towards the new day the kindly face
of our dear, dear father shall smile upon us with the same love that
used to gleam out of those eyes, which assured us that when he did put
off that great earthy body he would put on the spiritual body of a
saint in heaven.</p>
               <pb n="14"/>
               <p>
                  <figure entity="mayo4">
                     <figDesc>4th page
A. D. Mayo's The Nation's Sacrifice. </figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <p>Oh, yes, look not down into that bloody grave, but upon
these Easter flowers, to-day. Blessed types of that immortal beauty,
which through all fleeting forms abides forever; let them teach us
that all we love still lives; that all that is good and true lives;
that God, and Christ, and martys, and "just men made perfect,"
live. Oh, yes, they live-all live who died that the Republic might
endure. Little child, tender women, obscure soldier, unknown slave,
heroic commander, priest, statesmen, President-all live more truly,
more powerfully, more divinely, than they lived on earth. Can we be
recreant with this cloud of witnesses looking on from the world of
souls; with so many yet spared to earth who will gladly die that we
may live; with God calling as he calls to-day? Oh, Thou who hast
called Thy servant home, guide this people, and lead each one of us to
his place in Thee.</p>
               <pb n="15"/>
               <p>
                  <figure entity="mayo15">
                     <figDesc>15th page
A. D. Mayo's The Nation's Sacrifice. </figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 id="mayo.003" n="ABRAHAM LINCOLN." type="sermon">
               <head>ABRAHAM LINCOLN.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <p>"The righteous shall be in everlasting
remembrance."--Ps. cxii, 6.</p>
               </epigraph>
               <p>On the night of April 14,1865--the anniversary of the
opening of the second American revolution, ABRAHAM LINCOLN, President
of the United States, was slain by an assassin. Today, on the
anniversary of the battle of Lexington, which opened the first
American revolution, also of the first bloodshed of the present war,
in the streets of Baltimore, the loyal people of the United States
observe his funeral solemnities.</p>
               <p>It was a wise thought of the venerable Mr. HUNTER, Acting
Secretary of State, to request the whole people of the Union to
assemble at the hour of these funeral services, in their churches, for
never has this people needed the lofty consolations of religion as on
this day. Never before, in the history of the Republic has the attempt
been made to involve the entire executive authorities of the nation in
indiscriminate massacre. This astounding attempt, by permission of an
inscrutable Providence, has partially succeeded; and at this solemn
hour the Chief Magistrate is borne to the grave, while the Secretary
and Assistant Secretary of State lie stricken, yet hovering on the
borders of life and death. It is a momentous day in this people's
history. Shall they, to-day, harden their hearts, breathe vows of
eternal vengeance, and become, like their wrathful foes, a race of
assassins and barbarians? Or shall this culmination of the crimes of a
rebellious class only move them to a loftier love of liberty; a firmer
resolution to extirpate human slavery; an inflexible determination to
preserve and regenerate the Union; with the exercise of such a
Christian spirit of mercy towards all repentant offenders as shall at
once establish and adorn the majesty of the nation? Oh, may the
ministers of God, who
<pb n="16"/>
                  <figure entity="mayo16">
                     <figDesc>16th page A. D. Mayo's
The Nation's Sacrifice. </figDesc>
                  </figure>
this day have the ear of the people, fail not to declare at once the
Divine justice against our national sin, and the Divine compassion for
all who repent of their complicity with it.</p>
               <p>Last Sunday I counselled my people that this blow is the
end of human slavery in this Republic, perhaps in the world; and that
an aristocracy which had committed the last crime of assassinating its
truest friends, can have no more hope of life in any world ruled by
God. It is too early to say who among the individual criminals that
have involved this Republic in war should suffer judicial punishment,
or what that punishment shall be. When that question comes up it will
be met and settled by the calm wisdom and conscience of the loyal
American people. To-day there can be nothing better done than to draw
the portrait of the great and good man, who, on the very summit of
triumph over his nation's foes, even while bending in a gracious
attitude of mercy to a subdued enemy, became a martyr to Freedom. If
we can hold in our souls a clear and full image of this noble
American, we shall carry about with us a guide through all the perils
to come. Let me, then, ask your attention to a discourse on the life
and character of ABRAHAM LINCOLN.</p>
               <p>ABRAHAM LINCOLN was born in Hardin County, Kentucky,
February 12, 1809. His paternal ancestors were from Pennsylvania, of
Quaker connection. They intermarried with Virginia women, and removed
to Kentucky in 1782, where his grandfather was killed by the Indians,
in 1784. Both his father and mother were born in Virginia. At seven
years of age his family removed to Indiana, and little ABRAHAM, being
then a large boy, was put to work with his axe to hew down the
forests. For half a century he has plied that axe, till he has hewed
his way up through the material, social, civil wilderness of our new
American life, to the millennial day of Universal Liberty, guarded by
Social Order and the People's Law.</p>
               <p>For twelve years, till he was nineteen, he toiled in the
forest, with only one year at school, and then went to New Orleans, as
a hired hand on a flat-boat. In 1830, at the age of twenty-one, he
removed to Macon County, Illinois, and, true to his filial duty,
helped build a log cabin for his father's family, and made rails
enough to fence ten acres of land. Probably about this time he offered
himself at the office of a lawyer now distinguished in Southern
Indiana, as a student, but was rejected at once, as a hopeless
subject. I doubt not God had better business for him
<pb n="17"/>
                  <figure entity="mayo17">
                     <figDesc>17th page A. D. Mayo's
The Nation's Sacrifice. </figDesc>
                  </figure>
just then, than learning Southern Indiana law. He was kept, like
Washington, where he could learn of men, study the new life of the
mighty West, and slowly mature into a noble growth of manhood. At
twenty-two he helped build a boat, at twelve dollars a month, and then
took it to New Orleans. On his return he was put in charge of a store
and mill, in Menard County, Illinois. In 1832, at the age of
twenty-three, he enlisted as a soldier in a volunteer company, going
into the Black Hawk War, and was made Captain. He served three months,
and on returning home was nominated for the Legislature, and in his
own County, strongly opposed to him in politics, received two hundred
and seventy-seven out of two hundred and eighty-four votes, though he
failed of election. Then he opened a country store, which he gave up
to take the office of Postmaster, and began to read law by borrowing
books at night, to be returned in the morning. At the same time he
bought a compass and chain, and a treatise on surveying, and became a
practical surveyor. In 1834 he was elected to the Legislature of
Illinois, at the age of twenty-five, and re-elected in 1836-38 and
1840. In 1836 he began to practice law, not a day too late for him, at
the age of twenty-seven. He had become a man before he became a
lawyer, and to that fact we owe, perhaps, the preservation, at once of
the Constitution and liberty in this Republic.</p>
               <p>In April, 1837, at the age of twenty-eight, he removed to
Springfield, the capital of Illinois, where he lived twenty-four
years, till he left it for the capital of the nation, as President of
the United States. His success in the law was immediate and eminent,
and his interest in politics did not decline. He was often candidate
for Presidential elector, and became a favorite of the people, as a
public speaker, as early as 1844. In 1846, at the age of thirty-seven,
He was elected to Congress from Illinois. In the Congress in which he
sat he was chiefly noticed for his votes in favor of liberty, and in
1849 he offered a bill for abolishing slavery in the District of
Columbia. He was a member of the Convention that nominated General
Taylor for the Presidency, 1848. In 1849 he was a candidate for United
States Senator from Illinois. He continued in the practice of his
profession till the events between 1850 and 1856 aroused him to a new
interest in national politics. He had become one of the most eminent
men of a State not poor in able men, and when, in 1858, the Republican
party of Illinois looked about for a rival
<pb n="18"/>
                  <figure entity="mayo18">
                     <figDesc>18th page A. D. Mayo's
The Nation's Sacrifice. </figDesc>
                  </figure>
worthy of Stephen A. Douglas, it unanimously nominated him for United
States Senator. On this occasion he made that remarkable speech in
which he declared that this Union must, of necessity, become "all free
or all slave"--a speech which, like the famous address of Mr. Seward,
at Rochester, New York, in 1858, announcing the 'irrepressible
conflict' between freedom and slavery, has been so wonderfully
verified by the events of the last four years. In the memorable
discussion that followed between Mr. Lincoln and Mr. Douglas, the
former was fairly placed before the American people as one of the
ablest men of the party to which he was attached. He was defeated as
candidate for the Senate, only to be nominated as candidate for
President of the United States, in 1860, and in November of that year
was fairly and triumphantly elected Chief Magistrate of the Republic,
at the age of fifty-one.</p>
               <p>And it was no illiterate, obscure, vulgar, county-court
pettifogger, that was chosen by the people of the United States to
this exalted position. Of course the enemies of the Republic, at home
and abroad, vilified and ridiculed him as they always have hated and
despised every great friend of the people. Unhappily, too many of the
friends of freedom were not clear-sighted enough to recognize at once
in this simple, unpretending, homely citizen, the Father of the
American People. Many doubted his capacity; others ridiculed his
rhetoric and manners; others slandered his character, or denounced him
as a masked friend of the despotism that was assailing the nation's
life. But if all these men had reflected, they would have suspended
their judgment. They would have seen that no university could have
been so good a school for the man who was to defend the American
People against a fierce and proud aristocracy, as just the life which
Abraham Lincoln had lived for fifty years. He had seen and he knew
well all kinds of men. He was acquainted with free labor; not alone by
writing elegant essays or committing to memory and reciting flowery
speeches upon it, but by actively working in its every important
department. He was an experienced legislator, a distinguished lawyer,
a trusted political leader, only requiring opportunity to become a
statesman. Mr. Seward declared, as early as 1844, that Abraham Lincoln
would become one of the foremost men of the country, and his judgment
was that of every man qualified to appreciate him, who was not blinded
by envy or political prejudice. He was known in
<pb n="19"/>
                  <figure entity="mayo19">
                     <figDesc>19th page A. D. Mayo's
The Nation's Sacrifice. </figDesc>
                  </figure>
public and private to be a stanch friend of universal freedom. And
better than this, he had lived through the toils and temptations of a
new country, and come out at fifty a pure, honest, religious man.</p>
               <p>I remember seeing his portrait presented by himself to a
worthy old woman in Kentucky, after he became President, with the
touching inscription, in his own hand: "<hi rend="italic">In remembrance
of a Bible presented to me twenty years ago by your pious
hands</hi>."</p>
               <p>He was a man in whom the people had learned to confide; and
experience has proved that in the long run, the people can be trusted
to select their rulers. Like the people, in all ages, his nature was
slow, many-sided, often obscure and apparently contradictory in its
motions, not brilliant or melo-dramatic, but patient, ever searching
for truth, ever opening into unexpected developments of power,
adequate for; all emergencies, created to separate wrong from right,
and plant justice and liberty on foundations as enduring as the human
race.</p>
               <p>He rose at once to the exigency of the hour. The slave
aristocracy, far more penetrating than the people, knew Abraham
Lincoln for their most formidable enemy, and revolted in fury when his
election was announced. For four dismal months had the work of
disorganization gone on, till seven States had seceded, established a
pretended government, elected a president, and enrolled an army. The
government at Washington was meanwhile but a hollow name--treasonable
in spirit, anxious only to compromise with rebels who threatened its
own existence. Already had the dread decree gone forth among the
nations, that the Union was forever gone. The North was distracted
only less than the border States, all of which were on the eve of
revolution.</p>
               <p>At this gloomy hour Abraham Lincoln began his journey, on
February 1l, 1861, from Springfield, Illinois, to the national
capital. To his friends, at parting, he said: "A duty devolves upon
me, which is perhaps greater than that which has devolved upon any
other man since the days of Washington. He never would have succeeded
except for the aid of Divine Providence, upon which he at all times
relied. I think I can not succeed without the same divine aid which
sustained him, and in the same Almighty Being I place my reliance for
support, and I hope you, my friends, will all pray that I may receive
that di-
<pb n="20"/>
                  <figure entity="mayo20">
                     <figDesc>20th page A. D. Mayo's
The Nation's Sacrifice. </figDesc>
                  </figure>
vine assistance, without which I cannot succeed, but with which
success is certain."</p>
               <p>He journeyed slowly, visiting the principal cities of
Indiana, Ohio and the Middle States, on his way, and speaking brief
words of wisdom and conciliation to the people. We thought those
little, homely, rugged speeches, unworthy then, but now we see the
admirable judgment that managed to say nothing when nothing ought to
be said, and to deliver great principles in the most familiar way.</p>
               <p>Three ideas appeared prominent through all the public and
private addresses of this journey:  First, that salvation could come
to the Republic from no man, but only from Almighty God and the
American people; second, that the Union was not a "free love"
arrangement, which could be dissolved or renewed at pleasure, and that
the so-called doctrine of State Rights meant practically the power of
any State to "rule everything below and ruin everything above it;"
third, that the object of the fathers in establishing this Union was
the freedom of mankind, and he, like them, was willing to work and to
die for that end. In his speech at Independence Hall, in Philadelphia,
as if in anticipation of his own sacrifice, he said concerning the
idea which was the center of the Revolutionary war and the Declaration
of Independence: <hi rend="italic">"It was that which gave promise that
in due time the weight should be lifted from the shoulders of all
men. If this country cannot be saved without giving up that principle,
I would rather be assassinated on this spot than surrender it!</hi>"
Noble man!  Thou hast fallen by the assassin's hand; but not till that
old bell on Independence Hall has pealed out, <hi rend="italic">"Liberty
through all the land!</hi>"</p>
               <p>On this journey, at Albany, N. Y., I first saw
Mr. Lincoln. I saw him three times in one day--first, in the morning,
in the hall of Representatives, where he delivered a few gracious
words to the assembled Legislature. I remarked chiefly during his
speech the depth of kindness in his grave and tender eyes, out of
which looked a soul large enough to enfold all mankind. Again I saw
him at noon, escorted down State street, by a great throng of
citizens, quite surrounded by a military array; he standing up at his
full hight in his carriage. Never had I seen, never shall I again see,
so majestic a sight. I felt, as I looked on him then, that there was a
man strong enough to fight secession, backed by all the powers of
earth and all the demons of the
<pb n="21"/>
                  <figure entity="mayo21">
                     <figDesc>21st page A. D. Mayo's
The Nation's Sacrifice. </figDesc>
                  </figure>
infernal world. In the evening, I was glad to take his hand, which
near midnight was not too wearied to give my own a grasp that made me
his personal friend. Once only, afterward, did I see him--one Sunday
afternoon, in Washington, the second summer of the war. He was
standing on the grass before a hospital, in the suburbs, shaking hands
with a long line of invalid soldiers, and talking like a father to his
sons. From the hour I first saw him I believed him the man he has
become.</p>
               <p>He was wise enough to avoid assassination before his work
was begun, and went to the capital in disguise. On the 4th of March,
1861, with an imposing military and civic display, amid universal
apprehension of danger, he was inaugurated sixteenth President of the
United States.</p>
               <p>It is not my purpose to follow Mr. Lincoln through the four
years of his administration, or attempt any partizan advocacy of the
civil or military policy of the Government under his lead. I know that
policy has been contested honestly as well as dishonestly, often by
political friends no less than by political enemies. We have not yet
arrived at the historical point whence an impartial estimate can be
made of its most important phases. But I may call attention to the
great distinctive features by which it will be estimated in future
times.</p>
               <p>The first characteristic feature of his administration was
his conviction that he was cast in a Providential crisis of human
affairs, and could be only a humble agent of God in a mighty work of
regeneration to the Republic. No man in the Union had, from the first,
a profounder sense of the vast and radical nature of the nation's
conflict than Abraham Lincoln. He saw, long before the breaking forth
of war, that the great American aristocracy of the South would use its
institution of slavery to rule or ruin the Government, and that the
attempt would result in its complete success or complete
destruction. He said that Washington had not so difficult a task as
himself. He saw that no party could save the Union; not even the loyal
people alone; but, as he so often said. "God Almighty and the American
people." He felt he was cast in one of the great eras of history. He
once said to some clergymen who proposed prayer that God would come on
the country's side: <hi rend="italic">"Let us get on God's side, and all
will be well.</hi>" He knew that such a movement of national forces
could neither be hastened nor hindered by mere human will, and set
himself to watching the development of the mighty
<pb n="22"/>
                  <figure entity="mayo22">
                     <figDesc>22nd page A. D. Mayo's
The Nation's Sacrifice. </figDesc>
                  </figure>
drama, and helping the American people keep step with the progress of
Providential events. Nobody can understand this four years of his life
at all who does not regard the solemn sense of being an agent of God
in a great work as the back-ground of his whole policy.</p>
               <p>The second characteristic feature of his policy was his
great and unaffected faith in the loyal American people, and his
belief that they were being led by God to a glorious end which they
did not yet apprehend. He saw that while the slave aristocracy was
fully educated down to its infamous work, the loyal American people
were not yet educated up to the glorious part they were to play in
this revolution of humanity. He knew they were divided by political
habits, social sympathies, and often by radical ideas of society, and
that no number of excellent speeches or no attempts at a dictatorship
for freedom would convert his opponents. They must be brought into
support of the great war of freedom by the inevitable progress of
events; and he knew events would come to force them over to the side
of the right. <hi rend="italic">So he waited for the people to be
educated into union for the sake of a Republic dedicated to
freedom</hi>. From March, 1861, to January, 1863, he aided the people
to wage war with a divided mind, on an enemy that knew just what he
wanted, and never wavered in its support. If the result was not
satisfactory, the fault was no imbecility in the Executive arm, but
uncertainty in the popular mind, which was the source of all power.</p>
               <p>It is only by referring to these two central ideas of
Mr. Lincoln's policy, that any fair estimate can be made of much that
has been called weak and vacillating, by those who only looked on the
surface of events. And these ideas do light up the whole course of
that administration which, beginning in apparent uncertainty, has gone
on, like the operations of nature, to its present magnificent
success.</p>
               <p>It is often asked, why did he not, at his inauguration,
call the loyal people to arms against a treason already consummated?
Because the people were not then ready to fight; but full half the
community believed war could be averted by compromise. Why, then, did
he not attempt compromise? Because he saw that none was possible,
except one which would change the Republic to a permanent
oligarchy. He waited till popular conviction demanded war, and then
compelled the aristocracy to open the conflict in the most aggravating
way.</p>
               <pb n="23"/>
               <p>
                  <figure entity="mayo23">
                     <figDesc>23rd page
A. D. Mayo's The Nation's Sacrifice. </figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <p>Why, then, did he not call out a million men, and crush the
enemy at once? Because the call for any such large number of soldiers
would have astonished and divided the people, while the call that was
made powerfully stimulated their patriotism. He determined that the
people should make their own call for armies, for navies, for the
frightful expense of war, for severe measures of martial law, for
every thing essential to success. He was their servant, not their
master. While, therefore, during the first year of the war, he was
often accused of holding the people back, he always subtly and
powerfully stimulated the public zeal, and never waited to be called
twice to do a necessary thing.</p>
               <p>Why did he appoint to the command of our largest armies,
Generals who were either incompetent or unwilling to destroy the rebel
hosts? and why did he retain them long after a large portion of the
people lost confidence in them? Because he knew that the military and
naval commanders who would finally conquer, must be educated in actual
war. Not one of them had ever commanded 10,000 men, or maneuvered a
fleet in action. He could only choose the generals who appeared best,
give them the most generous opportunity and confidence, and wait until
the real man appeared. True, some of our armies were disastrously
defeated, in the summer of '61 and '62; but does any man know that
they would not have been under any other commander likely then to be
substituted? Did the army of the Potomac immediately succeed on the
discharge of Gen. McClellan? He waited and thought and toiled, until
war had educated the great leaders and the veteran host that have,
within the last two years, swept the armed confederacy from the
earth. Take your map of the South, and consider that on April 15th,
1861, all of it was practically in rebellion; and that on the day he
died, four years later, only one small army in North Carolina stood,
shaking in its shoes, the rear guard of the rebel power on its retreat
to oblivion, and ask yourself sincerely if you believe any other man
could have done a greater work in that time than the President of the
United States? Do you say the people did it? O! that is just the
point. He had aided the people to disentangle themselves from a purely
peaceful civilization, and in four years become one of the most
formidable military and naval powers on the globe. And history will
say, never was a great people so greatly led.</p>
               <p>Why did he not choose better men for office? The proof of
his administration is before you. You may or may not think
<pb n="24"/>
                  <figure entity="mayo24">
                     <figDesc>24th page A. D. Mayo's
The Nation's Sacrifice. </figDesc>
                  </figure>
this or that civil functionary the best, but do you doubt the great
work has been done? <hi rend="italic">The people of the United States
have learned, under Abraham Lincoln, how to govern themselves without
the aid of the slave aristocracy and its satellites</hi>. Does it
matter what good man or men hold office, so that thing is done? Why
did he tolerate dissensions in his Cabinet? He had far less than
Washington, and like Washington, he tried to represent all great
sections of the loyal people in his administration, by appropriate
men. He united the people at least, whatever friction there may have
been among statesmen, and however inconsistent they may have thought
his course. There were never in public office in America, so many able
and patriotic men as now and they were all the friends and sincere
mourners of the people's President, who was the best of them all.</p>
               <p>Why did he show such a spirit of conciliation to border
States, to enemies abroad, to foes in the loyal States? Because he
knew that no man loves you so much as a regenerated enemy. Because he
often did thereby change the country's enemies to its friends. Because
he was often compelled to endure what he could not cure. It was better
to sin on the side of forbearance and patience in dealing with great
States, like Kentucky and Missouri, than on the side of impatience and
wrath. It was better to bear insult from foreign nations till we could
speak and be respected. Was it not better to endure the folly and
frenzy of sympathizers with rebellion at home than sow the seeds of
implacable hatred through every neighborhood of the loyal States?
Mr. Lincoln believed the Union was to stand and be a Union for
Liberty, and he wisely believed the less of wrath the people had to
forget the easier it would be, in the great day of reconstruction, to
close up in a fellowship that should endure.</p>
               <p>Why did he wait so long, almost two years, before he struck
the decisive blow at slavery which has gained us the victory of arms
while it has saved us a free Republic? Because the people, even in
January, 1863, were hardly prepared for so great a challenge. Consider
how you regarded slavery ten years, five years ago! It was a great
divinity, against which we all dreaded to speak. We may have feared
and hated it, but we kept ourselves respectful in its haughty
presence. I believe the Emancipation Proclamation came not one day too
late. Two years ago the children in our streets were throwing stones
at colored women. He waited till slavery had taught the people its
hideous nature
<pb n="25"/>
                  <figure entity="mayo25">
                     <figDesc>25th page A. D. Mayo's
The Nation's Sacrifice. </figDesc>
                  </figure>
by sending affliction into myriads of homes, and bringing the nation
to death's door. So, when he did speak, a black cloud seemed to lift;
and from that day our armies never lost a mile of territory really
gained, and pressed on to final victory. This giant power now lies
prostrate. A hundred and fifty thousand men who were slaves four years
ago now carry United States muskets. The Congress of the United States
has voted for, and every State will finally ratify the amendment to
the Constitution that abolishes that pest forever. Is not this a
success; to destroy such a huge and terrible power in five years; and
will not the man who helped the people do it be called by all the holy
names that mankind gives to its benefactors?</p>
               <p>I believe history will pronounce Abraham Lincoln's
administration of our Government a triumphant success. The wisest
friends of the people abroad so declare it now; the wisest men in
America have been growing into this conviction month by month, and the
people have not doubted it from the first. Thank God, he lived to be
approved by the people, and re-elected to his great station; he lived
to place Grant over the army, and Farragut over the navy, and Chase at
the head of the courts; lived till the confederacy had collapsed, and
its President, legislature, and armies were fugitives; lived to show
his enemies what he was willing to do for them. As he sat in that last
cabinet meeting, the day before his death, urging a Christian
clemency, and yearning to enfold every erring citizen in the arms of
the Union, he was the noblest figure of this century. He was ready to
be offered. Dreadful as was his departure, had it been less so, would
it have startled out the wondrous love from the hearts of all men that
now appears? Men who have spent their days and nights for three years
in bitter hostility to his person and policy were surprised into
tearful admiration and sincere eulogy. The only great State that voted
against his re-election, confesses through her Governor that she has
lost her best friend, and Kentucky will yet explore her mountains and
dive into her mammoth caves in search of marble white enough to build
his monument. Was it not better he should go on to heaven as a martyr,
like Socrates, like William of Orange, like Hampden; should be one of
the glorious army whose Leader died on the cross, than to die as a
worn-out statesman? He died when his work was done. In his death the
nation has newness of life.</p>
               <p>Abraham Lincoln has often been contrasted with Cromwell,
<pb n="26"/>
                  <figure entity="mayo26">
                     <figDesc>26th page A. D. Mayo's
The Nation's Sacrifice. </figDesc>
                  </figure>
Napoleon, Caesar, William of Orange, Washington, Luther, and other
great leaders of that stamp. He was not that kind of a leader of
men. He did not lead by a display of prodigious powers in a state of
splendid exhibition. He did not suck up all the vigor of a nation into
himself, and use the multitudes only as tools of his imperial reason
and will. The time is past, at least in this country, when such a
leader can arise. No man was ever great enough to dominate over the
twenty millions of freemen in our loyal States, as even Washington
ruled the three millions of the first revolution. A few men during the
last four years have tried to do it, but where are these men to-day?
Jefferson Davis was the ablest leader of that sort on this
continent. He succeeded in enslaving twelve millions of people for one
year, and then his power began to decline, and what can he do now with
his confederacy? Nothing, but get out of it as fast as steam or
horse-flesh can carry him. Only a profound ignorance of the character
of our people and the nature of our institutions would look for a
leader of this character in a revolution like the present.</p>
               <p>But he was a leader in the people's new and improved
meaning of that word. His was a vast soul all attuned to receive the
noblest inspiration of a great nation's life; apt to reconcile,
comprehend, combine, suggest, secure all that can be gained, strive
after what should be attainable, guide and be guided by the march of
events, lie open on one side to God, and on the other to the people,
till the greatest ends are achieved, and all men rejoice, and each man
honestly thinks himself has done it all. Is not this the perfect proof
of the matchless leadership of our Lincoln, that under him the Union
and freedom have been saved, and many an able, and how many an unable
man shirks himself the saviour? Many a great commander thinks the army
and navy have saved us? But who has been the father of all these great
commanders, born like Providence with their weaknesses, healed their
feuds, reconciled their quarrels, inspired them and the soldiers with
increased devotion to the cause, and left us, at the end of a four
years' war, with less danger of a military despotism than when it
began?</p>
               <p>Many a great statesman thinks himself and his clique have
saved the country! But who has kept all these statesmen up to their
duty, set them an example of self-sacrifice, purity of life,
catholicity, patience, love of truth and justice? Who has cheer-
<pb n="27"/>
                  <figure entity="mayo27">
                     <figDesc>27th page A. D. Mayo's
The Nation's Sacrifice. </figDesc>
                  </figure>
fully borne their insults, endured their quarrels, adjusted their
rival claims, used them all, or consented to be used by any of them as
the country demanded? I would derogate from no man's just claim of
services, but I fancy history will paint many of these statesmen in
their relation to the President as we see groups of men in the
photograph standing about the trunk of the great California tree. He
surpassed them all in that massive manhood which is a perfect tower of
strength in days like these.</p>
               <p>And though the people may claim that they have done this
great thing under God Almighty, yet had God denied them such a father
on earth as Abraham Lincoln, I fear they would have gone on their way
many years yet in the wilderness before they saw the promised
land. For he it was, and none other that united and kept together the
parties of which the people were composed: Republican, Democrat,
Radical, Conservative; each by turn his denouncer, but every one at
last his follower; he has so impressed them that they all kneel and
clasp one another's hands about his bier to-day.  And the time is yet
to come when the children of the rebellious South will bless him who
subdued them without ignominy; who blasted all their wild and wicked
hopes, yet thereby raised them to the possibility of a new
civilization.</p>
               <p>Do you talk of such a man as simply "amiable,"
"goodhearted," "honest?" He was gifted with the rarest kind of
greatness known in this world. He was a great, religious,
philanthropic, reasonable soul, silently attracting all men to a vast
good. His powers were not showy, because so massive, so like nature
itself. His mind was like the nation he ruled--collossal, ever
emerging into new and higher developments of life, inexhaustible in
its latent capacity, crude and homely in its motions only when it was
reaching out to a higher truth than has yet been organized among
men. His presidency forms an era in the history of the world. Under
him first has there been a prospect of a great people united to
perpetuate the liberty and welfare of all men. He can wait for that
nation, in some hour of its future glory, to understand fully what he
was, and how he toiled, and how weary he became and how he died that
it might live.</p>
               <p>And of all the rulers of mankind, from the earliest to the
latest times, who has lived a purer, more blameless life than he? He
is only called a tyrant by the assassins who, failing to shoot the
republic to death, wreaked their vengence on his wearied
<pb n="28"/>
                  <figure entity="mayo28">
                     <figDesc>28th page A. D. Mayo's
The Nation's Sacrifice. </figDesc>
                  </figure>
brain. But who can lay his hand on his heart and accuse him of wilful
wrong? I have heard him ridiculed in certain quarters for lack of good
manners. Edward Everett said he was the peer of the noblest
representatives of the oldest courts of Europe.</p>
               <p>He has been called to order for his humor and love of
homely story telling. It was almost his only amusement; and if any
prince, king, emperor, or president has had a more innocent way of
amusing himself than Mr. Lincoln's "little stories " I have not read
of it. The recreations of the great men of the earth have too often
been the curse of their subjects. Can any man or woman in America say
that Abraham Lincoln has indulged himself to their harm? As well might
you criticise the cloudy sky for the levity of its heat lightning, as
such a lofty, grave, deep, faithful soul for that playful humor that
made him beloved by every child that could reach up and catch his hand
as he walked the streets, and saved his powers from premature
collapse.</p>
               <p>And the grandest thing of all is he has led us up to the
point where we can live without him. Why, in this hour of universal
mourning, when the tears of millions flow, is the heart of the nation
assured and hopeful? Why does commerce hold her sensitive scales
to-day with steady hand? Why do we all rejoice amid our woe? The
Republic has lost the friend who has taught it how to bear his
loss. We shall go right on. Great duties and dangers are yet ahead;
but we have learned how to meet them, and we fear no ruin. He has
united the loyal North. Let that North not give way now to the voice
of wrath and pagan vengeance, but live and act in his lofty spirit,
and all men in this broad land shall finally gather about his feet in
unity.</p>
               <p>Far in the East lies the grave of George Washington, which
no sound of war has disturbed. That turf is hallowed ground. To all
those thousands who have fought along the Potomac, the Rappahannock
and the James, his has been the one remaining honored name--Father of
his Country.</p>
               <p>In the far West, to-day we build the tomb of Abraham
Lincoln. We bury him now as Washington was buried, with thousands of
enemies. But time will abolish them all, and year by year the prairies
will be thronged by pilgrims to his resting place, till all know him
as the Father of the American People, and the American people are
one.</p>
            </div2>
         </div1>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI.2>