<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader><fileDesc>
         <titleStmt n="Character and Services of Abraham Lincoln">
            <title>Character and
Services of Abraham Lincoln  </title>
            <author>McCauley,
Rev. Jas. A.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Compiled and edited by</resp>
               <name>Beck Center</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent/>
         <publicationStmt><publisher>Lewis H. Beck Center</publisher><pubPlace>Emory University</pubPlace><address>
               <addrLine>Atlanta,
Georgia</addrLine>
            </address><availability>
               <p>1996 Emory
University. Permission is granted to download, transmit, or otherwise
reproduce, distribute or display the contributions to the work claimed
by Emory University for non-profit educational purposes, provided
this header is included in its entirety.  For inquiries about
commercial uses, contact the Director, 
Pitts Theology Library, Emory
University, Atlanta, Georgia 30322</p>
            </availability><date>1999</date></publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Lincoln
Sermons Project</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>McCauley,
Rev. Jas. A. Character and Services of Abraham Lincoln: A Sermon
Preached in the Eutaw Methodist Episcopal Church, on the Day of
National Humiliation and Mourning, Appointed by the President of the
United States, Thursday, June 1, 1865.  Baltimore: John D. Toy,
Printer. 1865.  </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc><encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This text derives from the Special Collections 
of Pitts Theology Library, Emory University, and is produced in 
collaboration with the Lewis H. Beck Center a, the Emory 
Preservation Office, and Pitts Theology Library.</p>
            <p>TRANSCRIBER: Lewis H. Beck Center and Emory University 
Preservation Office.</p>
            <p>PRODUCER:  BookLab, Inc., 1606 Headway Circle, 
Suite 100, Austin, TX 78754</p>
            <p>CAPTURE DEVICE: XEROX DocuImage 620S flatbed scanner</p>
            <p>CAPTURE DETAILS: Scanner software: XEROX ScanTool 
version 4.2.3; no gamma correction; images are all bitonal.</p>
            <p>CHANGE HISTORY: Using the Adobe Photoshop Batch Processor, 
we interpolated  the original TIFF files to 8-bit grays, 
and altered the resolution to 144 dpi, producing screen 
images twice the original size.  We then saved them in 
JPEG format.  We produced GIF thumbnails from the JPEG files.</p>
            <p>RESOLUTION: 600 ppi</p>
            <p>COMPRESSION: Resolution 144 per inch with Constrain 
Properties to 72 per inch.</p>
            <p>SOURCE: Original documents.</p>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc><revisionDesc><change><name>Stewart Varner</name> transformed this document from p4 to p5 on <date when="2010-03-22">March 22, 2010</date></change><change xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><date>1999</date><label>Staff</label><name>Scott Ellis</name>SGML tags inserted in compliance
with TEI guidelines using TEILITE</change></revisionDesc></teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div1 xml:id="mccauley.001" n="Character and Services of Abraham Lincoln" type="text">
            <head> 
               <bibl> 
                  <title>Character and
Services of Abraham Lincoln</title> 
                  <date>Thursday, June 1,
1865</date> 
                  <pubPlace>Eutaw Methodist Episcopal Church</pubPlace>
                  <author>McCauley, Rev. Jas. A.</author> 
                  
                     <pubPlace>Baltimore</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>John D. Toy,
Printer</publisher>
                     <date>1865</date>
                   
               <idno type="ark">http://pid.emory.edu/ark:/25593/15qn5</idno></bibl> 
            </head>
            <p>
               <figure><graphic url=""/>
                  <figDesc>1st Rev. Jas. A. McCauley's
Character and Services of Abraham Lincoln.</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <p>A SERMON</p>
            <p>PREACHED IN THE</p>
            <p>EUTAW METHODIST EPISCOPAL CHURCH,</p>
            <p>ON THE DAY OF</p>
            <p>NATIONAL HUMILIATION AND MOURNING,</p>
            <p>APPOINTED BY THE</p>
            <p>President of the United States,</p>
            <p>Thursday, June 1, 1865,</p>
            <p>BY REV. JAS. A. McCAULEY.</p>
            <p>BALTIMORE:</p>
            <p>JOHN D. TOY, PRINTER.</p>
            <p>1865.</p>
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>
               <figure><graphic url=""/>
                  <figDesc>2nd
Rev. Jas. A. McCauley's Character and Services of Abraham
Lincoln.</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>
               <figure><graphic url=""/>
                  <figDesc>3rd
Rev. Jas. A. McCauley's Character and Services of Abraham
Lincoln.</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <p>BALTIMORE, <hi rend="italic">June 2d</hi>, 1865.</p>
            <p>REV. J. A. McCAULEY,</p>
            <p>DEAR SIR:
	<lb/>Representing the wish of many members of the Congregation
who had the pleasure of listening to the admirable discourse,
delivered by you on the late day of National Humiliation and Prayer,
to have it for perusal and reflection; and also their anxiety that it
may have a publicity more commensurate with its merit and the
importance of the subject it so forcibly discusses, the undersigned
respectfully request a copy for publication.</p>
            <p>Truly and affectionately yours,</p>
            <p>SAMUEL HELSBY,
HENRY D. SHRIVER, <lb/>SUMMERFIELD BALDWIN,      WESLEY STEVENSON,<lb/>
JOHN W. KREBS,            A. WESTERMAN, <lb/>WM. J. REIMAN,
DAVID BALL, <lb/>GEORGE W. MAGERS,         JOSEPH BARLOW.</p>
            <p>BALTIMORE, <hi rend="italic">June 3d</hi>, 1865.</p>
            <p>GENTLEMEN:
	<lb/>I covet to be known, in every way, as honoring the man to
whom the Nation owes so unspeakable a debt; and could I feel that my
Discourse was a worthy treatment of its theme, your proposal to
prolong and widen its impression would be to me a real
satisfaction. Defective as it is, I place it in your hands, as thus,
besides complying with your wish, my witness, though unworthy, may
have a more enduring form than spoken words.</p>
            <p>Yours, very truly,
                                            <lb/>J.A. McCAULEY.</p>
            <p>TO S. HELSBY,
   <lb/>S. BALDWIN,
   <lb/>J. W. KREBS, and others.</p>
            <pb n="4"/>
<!-- blank page -->
<!--            <p>
               <figure entity="mccauley4">
                  <figDesc>4th
Rev. Jas. A. McCauley's Character and Services of Abraham
Lincoln.</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p> -->
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>
               <figure><graphic url=""/>
                  <figDesc>5th
Rev. Jas. A. McCauley's Character and Services of Abraham
Lincoln.</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <div2 xml:id="mccauley.002" n="SERMON" type="sermon">
               <head>SERMON.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <p>CONSIDER HOW GREAT THIS MAN WAS.--Hebrews vii
4.</p>
               </epigraph>
               <p>I SELECT these words with no design to use them in their
original reference. I take them merely as a motto for what I wish to
say concerning the man in memory of whom this service is appointed.</p>
               <p>It is well the nation has been summoned to cease from its
activities, and spend a day in contemplation of the scenes through
which it has been passing. So stirring and so stunning have been the
events crowding on us recently, sweeping us so rapidly through all the
possibilities of emotion--casting us down, by one rude fall, from the
raptures of rejoicing to a sorrow too deep for utterance or
tears--that we have been disqualified to estimate their real
magnitude. People stirred as we have been: dizzy, one day, with joy,
and dumb, the next, with grief; in the very whirl and din of events,
destined to fill the brightest and darkest pages history will write,
have lacked the composure needful to their just appreciation. Timely,
then, this day of pause and contemplation truly is, saddened, though
it be, by memories of a sorrow we can never cease to feel.</p>
               <p>Several days of our recent history will be noted in the
calendar of coming years. One day bears the double stigma of treason's
first and latest blow--the assault of Sumter, and the murder of the
President. On that day, too, the nation lifted up the symbol of its
majesty on the scene of its first humiliation. In fame, and infamy,
the fourteenth of April will be immortal. Remembered, too, while
freedom has a friend, will be the day of Richmond's fall, and the days
of the great surrenders. A day of sadder memory
<pb n="6"/>
                  <figure><graphic url=""/>
                     <figDesc>6th
Rev. Jas. A. McCauley's Character and Services of Abraham
Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
will the present be. But one day like it has this nation known. When
death removed the man, who made our fathers free, the spectacle was
seen of a nation bathed in tears. But the scene to-day is more
affecting. That was the sorrow of an infant nation; this, of one
immensely grown. That was sorrow for a man who died; this, for one
most foully slain. The man who piloted the nation through gloom, and
stress, and storm, just as the gloom was breaking, and the storm began
to lay, while at the helm, was stricken down. Never was there such a
blow. As the wires Hashed the heavy tidings from sea to sea, the
nation put on sackcloth, and wept as never nation wept before. That
scene will go down in history without an equal in the annals of the
race--a nation, elate with joy for rebellion overcome and liberty
preserved, tearfully bewailing its illustrious Chief untimely
slain. And though time has somewhat eased the agony that wrung all
hearts, and, in a measure, dried the tears that could not be
restrained, when the great bereavement fell upon us, it is not a form
of sorrow in which the nation now unites. The people of this land, in
solemn service, are to-day recording their tearful tribute to the
honored dead, and humbling themselves before Him, by whose righteous
sufferance their great distress has come.</p>
               <p>We are calmer now than when, in the freshness of our grief,
we shared in a service similar to this. And as our words could then
but be the sobbings of our sorrow, it is fit they now should voice our
more considered estimate of the man whose death we grieve. Of the deed
itself, it will not be for this generation to think or speak, without
emotion. But of its victim--his noble nature, and illustrious
deeds--we are enough recovered now to calmly think and speak. To this
my thoughts incline; and so I now invite you to review his character
and services, as seen in connection with the struggle through which he
led the nation to victory and peace. </p>
               <p>The order I propose regards his adaptation for the task
assigned him to perform; the singleness of mind and steadiness of zeal
with which he bent himself to its accomplish-
<pb n="7"/>
                  <figure><graphic url=""/>
                     <figDesc>7th
Rev. Jas. A. McCauley's Character and Services of Abraham
Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
ment; and the result which crowned his honest and persistent toil. In
fitness, performance, and success, it is acknowledged now, and the
years will growingly reveal that he was truly great.</p>
               <p>I. It is a truth not always seen at first, but afterwards
perceived too clearly to be doubted, that the men, to whom it falls to
take the lead in the great movements and struggles of our race, have
previously been schooled to fitness for their task. In the light of
Scripture and of History, it can be clearly read, that God prepares,
by special training, the instruments to execute His special
purposes. Slowly, perhaps through generations, He gets the world ready
for what He purposes to do; and when, at last, the time is full, there
never fails to step forth one qualified to take the lead, and carry
His purpose on to consummation.</p>
               <p>Israel's leader was an instance. Four hundred years--from
the day of Abram's call, till the cry of an oppressed people rose to
heaven--God was educating a people for severance and isolation, that
they, in turn, might educate the world for His ultimate designs of
mercy to the race. At length they are ready to go forth on their
Providential mission, and one to lead them is at hand. Peculiar was
the training, which formed that Hebrew boy for leadership and
rule. From the bosom of the Nile, he was transferred to the palace of
the Pharaohs. Until his fortieth year the schools of Egypt opened to
him the treasures of their lore; and gave him thus, as far as learning
could, fitness for his destined mission. But other fitness he would
need: heroic firmness, which foes and dangers could not turn; a sturdy
strength, which toils could not break down. And as courts were not the
place to foster these, God sent him to complete his training in a
sterner school. Forty years a herdsman, following flocks among the
deep ravines and frowning sides of Midian mountains, he was nurtured
to a vigor, which bore unhurt the cares and burdens of the Exodus; and
when, forty years thereafter, he sank to rest on Nebo, "his eye was
not dim, nor his natural force abated." In that school,
<pb n="8"/>
                  <figure><graphic url=""/>
                     <figDesc>8th
Rev. Jas. A. McCauley's Character and Services of Abraham
Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
too--aloof from men, in the loneliness of these grand solitudes
communing with himself and God--he grew to such a consecration that,
only once in forty years, a thought of self dishonored God. By
training so peculiar and protracted did God prepare, for the enslaved
seed of Israel, a Leader into liberty. And so in all his great
designs. John, to herald Christ, and Paul, to preach among the
Gentiles, were the fittest men of all that lived, because of what
their lives had been. And so in all the social struggles by which our
race has won its way to any higher ground: the men, who bore the
banners, got their place, and did their work, because of special
fitness.</p>
               <p>Abraham Lincoln was raised up of God to be the instrument
of a great Providential purpose: to conserve the liberties bequeathed
us by our fathers, and to make the bond among us free. On the sky of
our long night, God has been writing this fact for the world's
recognition; and, now that day has dawned, it shines as clear as
shines the sun. Recall the facts. The struggle was peculiar. It lacks
but little of a hundred years since the Colonies declared their
purpose to be a nation; and by their prowess, under God, they made
their purpose good. Not only, however, to <hi rend="italic">be</hi>, but
to <hi rend="italic">continue</hi>, nations must prove their
worthiness. And history shows that nations have a double peril to
their perpetuity--from without, and from within. Fifty years ago this
nation humbled, on land and sea, its mightiest foreign foe, and taught
the rest respect. The world won to fairness, there was no danger now
but from within. It was not long till mutterings of this began to jar
the land. Interest of sections clashing, it feigned to be; but its
real root and character were not long concealed. This nation was the
birth of one idea--Liberty. But another, essentially incongruous, wove
itself into the nation's life--Slavery. In their irreconcileable
antagonism, it was early seen our greatest peril lay. Mollified by
compromise, for thirty years slavery was content with menacing and
noise; but these grew angrier with the years, breaking forth at last
in the traitorous resolve that, if not allowed to overleap its bounds,
and have the
<pb n="9"/>
                  <figure><graphic url=""/>
                     <figDesc>9th
Rev. Jas. A. McCauley's Character and Services of Abraham
Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
soil of freedom for its own, it would take the nation's life. Favoring
its design was the theory it held, that the States were not component
parts of one organic whole, but separate sovereignties, entitled at
their option to withdraw. Following this, wherever it could, it
decreed dismemberment, and drew the sword to cleave its way to
separate empire. Whatever any think, this they may be sure the pen of
history will write was the real nature of the contest into which the
nation was compelled. Placable no more, Slavery decreed that Liberty
should perish, sooner than its purposes be foiled. Whatever in the
land had affinity for this, gathered to its standard--with sword and
bullet, those it could control; with smiles and succor, foes of
freedom everywhere. Fighting these, in front and rear, while on the
issue hung the fate of Liberty, was the real nature of that contest
from which the nation is emerging now--emerging, God be praised, with
victory on its banners.</p>
               <p>I speak of this that we may see how manifestly he, who was
the nation's leader in this great battle for its life, reveals a
fitness, which compels belief that his selection was of God. In all
his previous history we now can see the Providential training of a
champion for the Nation's cause in the day of its great peril. Sprung
from the people, love of freedom fired and filled him. To this his
being pulsed; to this his life was consecrate. His patriotism was a
vestal fire: it went not out nor waned. Again and again was his deep
conviction uttered, that freedom is the right of all. He was the
impersonation of that one idea, of which this Republic was the birth
and the embodiment. Coming up from humblest occupations, to posts of
honor in the nation, till the highest was attained, the unequalled
excellence of the institutions, framed and left us by the fathers, was
graven deep upon his heart by experience of their kindly working. And
in that love for these, which began with his life, and grew with his
years, and was fostered by his fortune, consists the ground-work of
his fitness, when these were put in peril, to marshal the Nation's
energies for their preservation. In saying this I do not mean that,
when hostile hands were lifted
<pb n="10"/>
                  <figure><graphic url=""/>
                     <figDesc>10th
Rev. Jas. A. McCauley's Character and Services of Abraham
Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
to cleave down the nation's liberties, no one else of all its sons
abhorred the traitorous deed as much as he; but only that devotion to
the cause of freedom, and abhorrence of the system in whose interest
the treason was conceived, were a needful part of fitness for the work
assigned him to perform. And these in part single him out as the
chosen of God to direct the nation's energies in the struggle for its
life.</p>
               <p>But other qualities were his, rarely fitting him for that
great work. Minds of loftier mould could likely have been found; finer
culture surely could. But it is doubtful if the nation had a single
other mind, better qualified than his, to grapple with the great
necessities of the Presidential office during his term. The world, I
think, consents that he was a man remarkable for quick and clear
perception; for cautious, acute, almost unerring, judgment; for a will
in which pliancy and strength were combined, in a singular
degree. And, to the occupant of his position, these were qualities of
imperative necessity. The easy round of peaceful times was not the
path he must pursue. To deal with trials wholly new was the task that
faced him at the first, and pressed him to the last. No sooner was he
chosen, than rebellion braced its arm to strike. The tones of his
inaugural had scarcely died upon the nation's ear, when worse than
lightning fires lit up the land, and thunders of war made the ear of
the world tingle. Yet, unappalled by these, with faith in the right,
and faith in the Lord, he grasped the reins for that perilous career
on which he had been driven; and, to the admiration of the world, he
held them, till the assassin's bullet struck them loose, just as was
wheeling the nation, through the gates of victory, into the morning
light of peace. On such a course--so full of perils so untried, and
daily new, frowning here, and yawning there--only the keenest eye, the
coolest brain, the steadiest hand, could save the nation from
disaster. Happy for the nation, God had given it a guide possessing
these abilities in wonderful degree. With intuitive celerity, he saw
the dangers as they rose, and saw the wisest thing to do; and, with
steady purpose, rested not till it was done.</p>
               <pb n="11"/>
               <p>
                  <figure><graphic url=""/>
                     <figDesc>11th
Rev. Jas. A. McCauley's Character and Services of Abraham
Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <p>Even his peculiarities were no trivial part of his peculiar
fitness for the place. Quaint, uncourtly, even droll, many, who wished
him well, thought his ways and talk sometimes undignified; while foes
were never weary, with tongue and pen, blazoning these as proofs of
incapacity. But, when people came to see that these were but the
healthful play of a genial and transparent nature, that through them
gleamed the genuine ore of invincible good sense, they wrote them down
for what they were--efficient helps to his great work. The dash of
humor was a medicine to him; and it poured a light sometimes into the
very centre of perplexities, which no logic could unravel. His manner,
always kind, drew the people to him with stronger hooks than
steel. The humblest got as near, and were as welcome to his presence,
as the mightiest that came.</p>
               <p>But time would fail to mention all that marked him as the
man of Providence. Patience that toiled untiringly; that bore,
unfainting, loads of care and work, which hardly one of any million
could have borne; honesty transparent as the light; unseduced by any
bait, unswerved by any pressure, hastening on, with single purpose, to
its goal, the nation's good; kindliness and clemency almost
superhuman, which hatred and abuse seemed but to kindle to an ardor
more divine, breaking out at last in those grand words, which will
ring down the centuries--"malice toward none, charity for all;" even
meditating kindest things for bitterest foes, when murder struck him
down--all these were his, and, with the rest, compose a wondrous
fitness for the work allotted him to do. A man of the people--one with
them in training, habitudes and spirit; of keen perception, practical
sense, and wisely-yielding will; of patience, conscientiousness, and
clemency, seldom united in mortal before--he centered in himself a
combination of qualities, which can leave no room for doubt that God
prepared him for the nation's need.</p>
               <p>II. From his fitness, I pass to speak of his performance:
the singleness of zeal with which he bent himself to meet the nation's
need.</p>
               <pb n="12"/>
               <p>
                  <figure><graphic url=""/>
                     <figDesc>12th
Rev. Jas. A. McCauley's Character and Services of Abraham
Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <p>He took the Presidential seat with one idea--to save the
Union of the States. That was the single star that fixed his eye. For
that he steered. Never from that could he be bent. His personal wish
for any result beside sank and was lost in the magnitude of this. All
measures were good that furthered this; all that hindered it were bad;
and those were best that helped it most. He was forced into a struggle
in which he felt that he must have the nation's energies on his side,
or fail. Hence one axiom controlled his policy: as people think, they
will do; as opinion rules, power goes. With an end in view that
consecrated all means, the conservation of national liberty, his sole
concern, regarding policy, was to have it be a reflex of the
predominant opinion of the nation, that so it might command the
preponderant power of the nation. Narrowly he watched the schooling of
events. As these came dimly whirling from the mists--from smoke of
battles and the darkness of defeat--no keener eye was turned to see
them taking shape; no readier mind to accept their lesson. That his
policy, from first to last, was undergoing change was not, as
sneeringly was said, because he was volatile, without a settled
purpose, a reed in the wind, a feather on the wave. It was because
there was in him, that practical wisdom which, with a goal in view,
watches the tide, and takes the flood, and goes to fortune. As the
currents of opinion swept wildly by, he did not try to battle them,
but bent his sail to catch their force, that so the precious ark,
instead of staggering in the storm, or going down beneath the wave,
might be carried, if with creaking timbers, yet unwrecked, to where
the haven lay in peaceful calm. Had he been a wilful man, set on
following certain lines, despite the pressure of events, Columbia
would to day be weeping, not for him, but for freedom, slain.</p>
               <p>Open thus to Providential teaching, he came, as soon as it
was safe, to that measure, with which his name will go down to
immortality--Emancipation. Long before the war, his individual views
were on the side of universal liberty. No public man had done more
efficient battle for it, with tongue and pen, than he. But when he
found himself the
<pb n="13"/>
                  <figure><graphic url=""/>
                     <figDesc>13th
Rev. Jas. A. McCauley's Character and Services of Abraham
Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
head of the imperiled nation, and needing to unite the nation's
strength to wage the battle for its life, he would not travel in the
line of his desires, faster than the nation signified its wish. None
can doubt that he was right in judging the nation unprepared for this
measure, when the war began. Adopted then, he had been deserted by the
border States entire, and by many in the North, and so the Union had
been lost. But opinion drifted to it rapidly as martial necessity. And
candid men will not deny that, had he delayed much longer than he did
to smite the shackles from the bound, the masses, unwilling longer to
connive at what they now believed the sole occasion of the great
rebellion against their liberties, would have left him unsupported;
and so, for this, the Union had been lost. This determined its
adoption. Solemnly he had said, if freeing a slave would peril the
Union, he would forbear; or, he would shatter the system, if so he
could the better compass its safety. Events were solving which to
do. Two years of indecisive war had passed. The armies of the West had
scarce been able to keep back the tide of invasion; and, in the East,
matters had gone even worse. The army of the Potomac had closed a
disastrous campaign. The Peninsula gory with the blood of thousands
shed in vain; the grand army driven from the Rapidan, broken and
dismayed, to the very gates of the Capital; the foe aggressive; the
Potomac crossed; fear of rapine, sword and flame; all were summoning
the nation to a solemn inquisition. Standing on his tower of anxious
observation, Mr. Lincoln seemed to hear it borne from every quarter,
that now it was the will of most that freedom be proclaimed. Voicings
of disaster, of the press, and of the ballot, seemed unitedly to say,
Re-inscribe the nation's banner. He ventured to obey; and, while the
guns of Antietam held the nation silent, he penned the notice of his
great resolve. The earliest light of '63 revealed upon the banner's
folds, beneath the old device, another word--Emancipation. The world
read and shouted its approval. And though some among ourselves
trembled lest that word should prove
<pb n="14"/>
                  <figure><graphic url=""/>
                     <figDesc>14th
Rev. Jas. A. McCauley's Character and Services of Abraham
Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
the signal of our doom, a little while revealed that he had rightly
read the nation's will.</p>
               <p>Thenceforth two stars flamed in his sky: Union--liberty
conserved for those already free; and Emancipation--liberty decreed
for the millions hitherto enslaved. These he steadily pursued. Through
storm and calm, through victory and reverse, toward these he sought to
lead the nation on. Questioned from whatever source, he let fall no
word ignoring these. Whether writing to any it might concern, or
speaking to representatives of the tottering rebellion, seeking
armistice and compromise, while assuring of concession on every minor
point, he clung to these: unconditional acknowledgment of the national
supremacy, and acquiescence in the fiat enfranchising the slave. And
though for this he fell, it was not till he had seen these stars fixed
in the clearing azure of the nation's sky, beyond the peril of
extinction or eclipse.</p>
               <p>III. A closing word I wish to say concerning his
achievement--the success which crowned his patient waiting, and
assiduous toil. To measure this, in all it means, the time has not yet
come. The great facts appear, indeed, before our eyes so real, so
cheeringly in contrast with all that recently has been, as to compel
their recognition. Recently the land was lurid with the flames of war;
the air was heavy with its woes. Now the noise of guns is hushed. The
dust is lifting from the field. Columbia smiles from sea to
sea. Grandly loom the great results: the Republic is safe; treason is
dead, or dares no longer strike; one flag floats, and not a second
will. These results, for which the nation has been toiling, as nation
never toiled before, are facts accomplished now. And much of what they
mean we already comprehend. We know that the questions, so troublous
in the past, will no more disturb the nation's peace. State supremacy,
that restless spirit which walked the land so long, and which no skill
of Statesmen could compose, has been laid to sleep to wake no
more. General Lee is rumored to have said, "the right of a State to
secede was an open
<pb n="15"/>
                  <figure><graphic url=""/>
                     <figDesc>15th
Rev. Jas. A. McCauley's Character and Services of Abraham
Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
question till my failure settled it."  It is settled now. No more will
rivalries of rule disturb the nation's peace. No more the stars will
leave the sun. In the Union every State will stay, each pursuing its
allotted course, and dutifully doing its appointed work.</p>
               <p>But order not alone, universal liberty has been
achieved. The nation's stain has been expunged. The one incongruous
element has been taken from its life. To-day it stands before the
world, and henceforth will, the real embodiment of that great truth
which its founders so nobly proclaimed, the right of all to "life,
liberty and the pursuit of happiness." And thus is sealed the other
source of dissension and disturbance. At the ballot, where people
voice their will, in the halls where laws are made, and on the benches
of decision, Slavery will no more inflame feeling, darken counsel,
pervert judgment, or inspire sedition. Quietus-may it be eternal!--has
come to this potency of ill.</p>
               <p>All of this is clear to us. But the measure of blessing
treasured in these results, for revelation and enjoyment in the future
we are pressing, is hidden from our eyes. Elevation of the masses;
development of material resource; scope for energy, growth of every
kind, the coming generations will increasingly attain, which, could
they be pictured now, would be pronounced the pencillings of poetry,
or the visions of romance.</p>
               <p>But whatever they may prove, our martyred President will be
associated with them. Through all the ages yet to come, the
generations of the American people will growingly revere and cherish
him as the man, who, under God, preserved their imperiled
institutions, and made them instrumental of the richer benefactions
they increasingly dispense. Nor they alone. Throughout the world
friends of liberty will keep fresh garlands on his brow, and consign
the keeping of his fame to their best traditions. The appreciation of
his character and deeds, as uttered in the tributes which have come
across the sea, seems as warm and loving, if not so universal, in
other lands, as in the land for which he lived and died. Like
Washington, he is not ours exclusively: the world
<pb n="16"/>
                  <figure><graphic url=""/>
                     <figDesc>16th
Rev. Jas. A. McCauley's Character and Services of Abraham
Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
claims him. A French historian of fame concludes an able and
appreciative estimate of the man and his services, in words that echo
the heart of freedom every where: "And now let him rest by the side of
Washington, the second founder of the Republic. European democracy is
present, in spirit, at his funeral, as it voted in its heart for his
re-election, and applauds the victory in the midst of which he passes
away. It will wish, with one accord, to associate itself with the
monument that America will raise to him upon the capital of prostrate
Slavery."</p>
               <p>And now for the loss of such a benefactor the nation
mourns, and humbles itself before Him whose sufferance has allowed
this heavy blow to fall. Dark, indeed, is this event; but the wrath of
men shell praise Him. The fame of Mr. Lincoln will not be hurt--it
likely will be helped--by the tragic close of his career. All the more
lovingly will he be thought of, and all the more undyingly his
services be cherished, for the cruel manner of his "taking off."
Washington rounded up a glorious life with a peaceful death. The eyes
of a prepared and expectant nation were turned upon the couch, where
ministries of love were tenderly solicitious of all that could make
his exit easy. But our preserver fell in the midst of unaccomplished
work; fell when, with fonder and more confiding expectancy, than ever
before, the torn and troubled nation looked to him to heal its feud
and stay its sorrow; fell unwarned, and in a place that deepens the
sorrow of his fall; fell by a blow that lacks no accessory to make it
the darkest, foulest, most atrocious, ever dealt against a human
life. We do not claim that he was perfect, for he was a man. But we
claim that he so stood in his Providential lot, and did his work so
well, that the ages will enthrone him by the side of those who have
lived and labored most to benefit their kind.</p>
            </div2>
         </div1>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>