<TEI.2>
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt n="A Great Man Fallen!">
            <title>  A Great Man
Fallen!  </title>
            <author>Paddock, Wilbur F.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Compiled and edited by</resp>
               <name>Beck
Center</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent/>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Lewis H. Beck Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Emory University</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Atlanta,
Georgia</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>1996 Emory
University. Permission is granted to download, transmit, or otherwise
reproduce, distribute or display the contributions to the work claimed
by Emory University for non-profit educational purposes, provided
this header is included in its entirety.  For inquiries about
commercial uses, contact the Director, 
Pitts Theology Library, Emory
University, Atlanta, Georgia 30322</p>
            </availability>
            <date>1999</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Lincoln
Sermons Project</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Paddock,
Wilbur F. A Great Man Fallen! A Discourse on the Death of Abraham
Lincoln.  Delivered in St. Andrew's Church, Philadelphia, Sunday
Morning, April 23, 1865.  Philadelphia: Sherman &#x0026; Co.,
Printers. 1865.  </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This text derives from the Special Collections 
of Pitts Theology Library, Emory University, and is produced in 
collaboration with the Lewis H. Beck Center a, the Emory 
Preservation Office, and Pitts Theology Library.</p>
            <p>TRANSCRIBER: Lewis H. Beck Center and Emory University 
Preservation Office.</p>
            <p>PRODUCER:  BookLab, Inc., 1606 Headway Circle, 
Suite 100, Austin, TX 78754</p>
            <p>CAPTURE DEVICE: XEROX DocuImage 620S flatbed scanner</p>
            <p>CAPTURE DETAILS: Scanner software: XEROX ScanTool 
version 4.2.3; no gamma correction; images are all bitonal.</p>
            <p>CHANGE HISTORY: Using the Adobe Photoshop Batch Processor, 
we interpolated  the original TIFF files to 8-bit grays, 
and altered the resolution to 144 dpi, producing screen 
images twice the original size.  We then saved them in 
JPEG format.  We produced GIF thumbnails from the JPEG files.</p>
            <p>RESOLUTION: 600 ppi</p>
            <p>COMPRESSION: Resolution 144 per inch with Constrain 
Properties to 72 per inch.</p>
            <p>SOURCE: Original documents.</p>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>1999</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Scott Ellis</name>
               <resp>Staff</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <item>SGML tags inserted in compliance
with TEI guidelines using TEILITE</item>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div1 id="paddock.001" n="A Great Man Fallen!" type="text">
            <head> 
               <bibl> 
                  <title>A Great Man
Fallen!</title> 
                  <date>Sunday Morning, April 23, 1865</date>
                  <pubPlace>St. Andrew's Church, Philadelphia</pubPlace>
                  <author>Paddock, Wilbur F.</author> 
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Philadelphia</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Sherman &#x0026; Co.,
Printers</publisher>
                     <date>1865</date>
                  </imprint> 
               </bibl> 
            </head>
            <p>
               <figure entity="paddock1">
                  <figDesc>1st page of Wilbur F. Paddock's
A Great Man Fallen!</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <p>A GREAT MAN FALLEN!</p>
            <p>A DISCOURSE</p>
            <p>ON THE</p>
            <p>DEATH OF ABRAHAM LINCOLN.</p>
            <p>DELIVERED IN</p>
            <p>St. Andrew's Church, Philadelphia,</p>
            <p>SUNDAY MORNING, APRIL 23, 1865.</p>
            <p>BY THE</p>
            <p>REV. WILBUR F. PADDOCK.</p>
            <p>PHILADELPHIA</p>
            <p>SHERMAN &#x0026; CO., PRINTERS.</p>
            <p>1865.</p>
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>
               <figure entity="paddock2">
                  <figDesc>2nd page of
Wilbur F. Paddock's A Great Man Fallen!</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <p>This Discourse is published at the request of Governor Pickering,
Senator Williams, and others of the Funeral Escort of President
Lincoln, who were present at the time of its delivery.</p>
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>
               <figure entity="paddock3">
                  <figDesc>3rd page of
Wilbur F. Paddock's A Great Man Fallen!</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <div2 id="paddock.002" n="DISCOURSE" type="sermon">
               <head>DISCOURSE.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <p> 2 SAMUEL 3:34, 38.</p>
                  <p>"THY HANDS WERE NOT BOUND,
NOR THY FEET PUT INTO FETTERS: AS A MAN FALLETH  BEFORE WICKED MEN, SO
FELLEST THOU. AND ALL THE PEOPLE WEPT AGAIN OVER HIM. AND THE KING
SAID UNTO HIS SERVANTS, KNOW YE NOT THAT THERE IS A PRINCE AND A GREAT
MAN FALLEN?"</p>
               </epigraph>
               <p>A GREAT leader and a brave man had fallen in Israel. Not in
battle, not by disease, not by the hands of the ministers of justice
in satisfaction to violated law, but by the hand of an assassin,--a
deed treacherously, cowardly, infamously and unsuspectedly
committed. In the gate at Hebron, the place of judgment and the place
of concourse, in defiance of the laws of God and man, Joab, openly
before the people, imbrues his hands in the blood of Abner, whom he
from jealousy feared, and towards whom he entertained the bitterest
feelings of revenge. "And David said to Joab and to all the people
that were with him, Rend your clothes, and gird you with sackcloth,
and mourn before Abner. And King David himself followed the bier. And
they buried Abner in Hebron; and the king lifted up his voice and wept
at the grave
<pb n="4"/>
                  <figure entity="paddock4">
                     <figDesc>4th page of Wilbur
F. Paddock's A Great Man Fallen!</figDesc>
                  </figure>
of Abner; and all the people wept. And the king lamented over Abner
and said, Died Abner as the fool dieth? Thy hands were not bound, nor
thy feet put into fetters. As a man falleth before wicked men, so
fellest thou. And all the people wept again over him. And the king
said unto his servants, Know ye not that there is a prince and a great
man fallen this day in Israel? And I am this day weak, though anointed
king; and these men, the sons of Zeruiah, be too hard for me. The Lord
shall reward the doer of evil according to his wickedness."</p>
               <p>How striking in many respects, the parallel between this
deed of blood and that committed but little more than a week ago in
our national capitol. A prince and a great man then fell by the hand
of an assassin; unsuspectedly, cowardly, cruelly murdered in the place
of concourse before the eyes of thousands, in defiance of the laws of
God and man. The deed itself spoke in thunder tones to the hearts of
the people. It needed not that Executive authority should call upon
the nation to gird itself in sackcloth and mourn before its fallen
friend, benefactor and ruler. Scarce had the terrible tidings flown
upon the lightning's wing through the loyal States, when, from
millions of stricken hearts there went up to Heaven a bitter cry of
anguish,--the pitiful moan of a crushed and bereaved people. The whole
land, just before revelling in excess of joy over unparalleled
military success, glowing with bright
<pb n="5"/>
                  <figure entity="paddock5">
                     <figDesc>5th page of Wilbur
F. Paddock's A Great Man Fallen!</figDesc>
                  </figure>
hopes and brilliant revelations of restored peace and prosperity, was
suddenly plunged into the very depths of woe. The sombre hue of death
everywhere visible, and the varied language of mourning, told how
universal and how great was the grief of the people. The angels of
sorrow stretched a pall of darkness and gloom over the whole land. In
every house there was, as it were, one dead; and that one--a
father.</p>
               <p>Twice, my friends, since this awful crime was committed,
have we assembled in this church. Upon Easter Day we sought to catch
the spirit of the service and ascend gladly in our hearts to the risen
and glorified Saviour. We sought to meditate upon the precious hopes
given us and the triumph achieved for us in His resurrection. But how
sad and fruitless all our efforts. A great woe pressed heavily upon
our hearts. Easter joys were turned into mourning, songs of
thankfulness into notes of sadness and bereavement. Our thoughts and
feelings would not but flow mournfully through the dark valley of
affliction into which we had been called as a nation to enter. We
could not, from very weeping, sing the songs of Zion.</p>
               <p>Wednesday's solemn service brought with it the same deep
impressions of the great and terrible loss we had sustained. We
gathered in spirit around the cold and lifeless form of our martyr
President, and paid, with distressed and weeping hearts, like offices
with those which were being at the same hour per-
<pb n="6"/>
                  <figure entity="paddock6">
                     <figDesc>6th page of Wilbur
F. Paddock's A Great Man Fallen!</figDesc>
                  </figure>
formed over his remains in Washington. We then realized as never
before that our truthful, loving, and noble-hearted friend and
benefactor had gone. No words could add solemnity or effect to those
funeral services under the powerful impression of this conviction.</p>
               <p>To-day, we are again assembled, and the same subject is
occupying our minds and moving the deepest emotions of our
hearts. There is no possibility of escaping it. Nor, dear friends,
would we if we could, until it shall produce the result God designed
it to accomplish in the gracious orderings of this most mysterious
providence. A blow so heavy, so sudden, so momentous in its
consequences, is not easily to be recovered from, or soon to be
forgotten. To-day, the great and noble dead is in our midst; and every
Church assemblage and every heart in this vast city feel the influence
of that presence. Meet was it, that the noblest, the greatest, and the
best of all the martyrs, who have been sacrificed upon the altar of
liberty since the birth of this nation, should upon this, the last
Sabbath before his sepulture, lie in state in the hall where liberty
was cradled, and in which were first authoritatively uttered those
great principles of human freedom, equality and constitutional law, in
the defence of which he died.<ref target="paddock.002.n01">*</ref> His lifeless and mutilated</p>
               <note id="paddock.002.n01" n="*" place="foot" anchored="yes">
                  <p>The remains of President Lincoln were placed in
Independence Hall, Saturday evening, April 22, and remained there
exposed to view until the following Monday morning. The head of the
deceased was towards the pedestal upon which rests the old State House
bell, which first pealed liberty throughout the land. The four walls
of the hall were tapestried with serge. The pictures which the heavy
serge festoons were allowed to reveal were six in number, and not
inappropriate silent watchers of the dead. Upon the coffin was placed
a beautiful cross, composed of perfectly white flowers of the choicest
kinds. A card attached was inscribed as follows:</p>
                  <p>"A tribute to our great and good President, fallen a martyr
in the cause of human freedom.</p>
                  <lg type="stanza">
                     <l>"In my hand no price I bring,</l>
                     <l>Simply to Thy cross I cling."</l>
                  </lg>
                  <p><hi rend="italic">Extract from Daily Paper.</hi></p>
               </note>
               <pb n="7"/>
               <p>
                  <figure entity="paddock7">
                     <figDesc>7th page of
Wilbur F. Paddock's A Great Man Fallen!</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <p>body calls upon us for a more extended notice of his character and
services than in this church has heretofore been given; and in so
doing, I shall not, I am assured, do violence to the proprieties of
time and place, or go counter to your just expectations and the
demands of the present occasion.</p>
               <p>I purpose, this morning, to show, first of all, the true
greatness of him whom the nation now mourns and seeks to honor;
second, to discover, if possible, the culprit by whose hand he fell;
and third, to indicate the manner in which his death may best be
avenged, and our great and irreparable loss be made a blessing to
ourselves and to our country. We must speak briefly upon each of these
points, and cannot, therefore, do more than present a faint outline of
the virtues and excellences of the illustrious dead, trusting that
the</p>
               <pb n="8"/>
               <p>
                  <figure entity="paddock8">
                     <figDesc>8th page of
Wilbur F. Paddock's A Great Man Fallen!</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <p>perfectness and moral grandeur of his character, may at least, not
suffer in your estimation by this necessarily imperfect
presentation.</p>
               <p>I. Consider then, how great Abraham Lincoln was, first, <hi rend="italic">in his devotion to truth</hi>. It is said of him as of the
immortal Washington, that he never told a lie. From the age of
twenty-five to the time of his death, he was more or less in political
life, and under its corrupting influences; and yet so sacredly did he
hold to the inviolability of oaths, to the sanctity of plighted word,
and to the great value and necessity of strict veracity in statement
and conduct, that his bitterest enemies have not been able to convict
him of a single falsehood, or prove upon him a single charge of fraud,
of intrigue or of deceit. He had an instinctive love of truth,--truth
in word, in principle, in belief, and in practice,--that caused him,
no matter what the consequences might be to himself, to do and say,
when duty demanded, what he thought and felt and believed. He was
incapable of acting a part, and careful that he might not be deceived
by others. No labor was too great, no pressure of business so severe,
as to prevent him from learning, if possible, the truth of every case
presented to him.</p>
               <p>He was honest with himself, and honest in his dealings with
others. It shone forth from earliest years. When a mere child, he
labored for two days to pay for
<pb n="9"/>
                  <figure entity="paddock9">
                     <figDesc>9th page of Wilbur
F. Paddock's A Great Man Fallen!</figDesc>
                  </figure>
a borrowed book, which he promptly confessed had been by his own
carelessness destroyed. Veracity and strict integrity marked all his
boyhood plays, bargains and engagements.</p>
               <p>In after life, this fidelity to truth in word, in principle
and in conduct, was marvellously manifested. History furnishes no
parallel of devotion so constant and unswerving,--under a combination
of circumstances so powerfully arrayed in opposition,--as
distinguished him during his entire Presidential career. In the midst
of plots and counterplots; amid the fluctuations of opinion and the
surging waves of intense feeling over different lines of policy; at
one time basely attacked by bitter enemies; at another, made the
subject of satire, ridicule, or unjust criticism; at another, still,
brought under the blandishments and seductive influences of greedy
politicians, unwise friends, or base pretenders--now contending with
factious elements at home, and now with intriguing or hostile cabinets
abroad--firmly relying upon the invincibility of his principles, the
correctness of his opinions, the rightfulness of his position, and the
integrity of his purpose, like a rock he stood courageously and
heroically beating back every wave, resisting every encroachment,
withstanding every seductive influence; unmoved alike by blame or
praise, bribes or threats, reproach, contempt, cajolery, or base
<pb n="10"/>
                  <figure entity="paddock10">
                     <figDesc>10th page of Wilbur
F. Paddock's A Great Man Fallen!</figDesc>
                  </figure>
insinuations,--true to himself, true to his principles, true to his
country, and true to his God. Oh, how noble such an exhibition of
character! How rarely is it seen in the history of public men.</p>
               <p>But again, the greatness of Abraham Lincoln was manifested
<hi rend="italic">in his devotion to the rights of humanity, and his
sympathy with his race</hi>. We see him at the very beginning of his
legal career, in the face of bitter prejudice and an intense feeling
of revenge on the part of the community, defending the life of the son
of a poor widow, charged with the crime of murder. Volunteering his
services without a thought of reward, he rested not day nor night
until the tangled and deceptive web of circumstance was completely
unravelled, the malicious falsehoods of witnesses disproved, the
innocence of the prisoner established, and light and life and joy
could again visit the home of the widow and the fatherless. And then,
not selfishly elated by his success, indeed scarcely conscious, so
great was the simplicity and humility of his heart, of the proud
distinction his talents had won for him in triumphing over prejudice,
hostility and wrong, regardless of needed rest or of the praise that
awaited his presence among his associates, in the greatness of his
disinterested devotion to the suffering, the neglected and the
defamed, he remembers only their needs, and lets the sun of that
eventful day go down upon him administering to their wants. And this
was the spirit he ever
<pb n="11"/>
                  <figure entity="paddock11">
                     <figDesc>11th page of Wilbur
F. Paddock's A Great Man Fallen!</figDesc>
                  </figure>
manifested. No thought of self, no concern for his own fame, no
feeling of personal pride, no expressions of triumph in the hour of
success, ever disturbed his heart, or passed his lips so far as we are
able to learn, throughout the whole period of his marvellous
history. Whether receiving the plaudits of a country court for a
successful defence, or the homage and praise of millions in this and
other lands, for the liberation of a long-oppressed race and the
preservation of the nation's life, he was the same modest,
self-forgetting, unelated man.</p>
               <p>This remarkable freedom from every form of pretension, from
self-commendation, and from all feelings of exultation over the defeat
of others or his own success, arose not only from the native
simplicity and generosity and divinely implanted humility of his
heart, and the singular mastery he exercised over the varied impulses
and passions of his nature, but, also, was largely the result of his
intense devotion to the right, and whole-souled sympathy for the
distressed, the needy and the wronged; causing him entirely to lose
sight of selfish considerations, and in all his legal and political
successes to be absorbed in the contemplation of truth vindicated, the
right maintained, justice honored, the bounds of liberty enlarged, and
the oppressed and afflicted blessed. Oh how grandly his whole heart
went forth in sympathy for all his race, and how earnestly,
faithfullly and untiringly, did he labor in
<pb n="12"/>
                  <figure entity="paddock12">
                     <figDesc>12th page of Wilbur
F. Paddock's A Great Man Fallen!</figDesc>
                  </figure>
its behalf. It was not the white man, or the red man, or the black
man, that he saw. It was humanity, suffering and needy, and
down-trodden. It was not numbers, rank, wealth or position, that
chiefly secured his attention, or obtained his most ready aid. The
wife of the poor soldier starving in the infamous prisons of the
South, or the widowed mother of a son who had fallen in battle,
received from him equal attention with the noblest, the richest and
the most exalted that passed the threshold of the Executive
mansion. We see him at one time, with his own hands binding up the
wounds of some suffering hero in the hospital; at another, riding ten
miles to carry a reprieve to a poor soldier boy, who has been
sentenced to death for sleeping upon his post; at another still,
patiently listening to the story, and granting the request of a
weeping servant girl, whose brother for desertion has been sent to the
Dry Tortugas for punishment; and, we say, is this the Chief Magistrate
of this great nation? Can he, who is engaged in such lowly offices,
really be the one to whom is intrusted the fate of millions, who bears
the weight of empire upon his shoulders, who daily decides great
questions of state, and by his wise and far-seeing policy, and
masterly direction of affairs, is largely shaping the future of other
nations as well as our own?</p>
               <p>Yes, even so. With Abraham Lincoln nothing was small or
unimportant which his sense of justice and
<pb n="13"/>
                  <figure entity="paddock13">
                     <figDesc>13th page of Wilbur
F. Paddock's A Great Man Fallen!</figDesc>
                  </figure>
kind heart told him ought to be done; and nothing for the amelioration
and elevation of his race was too great or too difficult for him to
undertake to do that demanded of him the effort. In speaking to a
friend of his Proclamation of Emancipation he said, "I did not think
the people had been educated up to it, yet I thought it right to issue
it, and I trusted in God and did it." How heroically grand this
sentiment! What expresses more perfectly the whole theory and practice
of his life! What sentence more worthy to be written in gold, and
claimed by every true man as the history of every truly great act?
"<hi rend="italic">I thought it right; I trusted in God; I did it</hi>."
Few, comparatively, approved of his course at that time; but he
hesitated not. Misrepresentations, censure and abuse were of little
consequence to him, so long as he knew his motives were pure, the end
he had in view right, and his course in accordance with the great
principles of justice and humanity. He proclaimed liberty to the
slave, and trusted in God that the victory which he sought to win over
the prejudices of the people and the past policy of the nation might
be crowned ultimately with success, both in the complete overthrow of
the influence of slavery in the North, and in the practical liberation
of an entire race from its thraldom in the South. The wisdom of his
course has been clearly demonstrated by the progress of events. Thank
God that he lived to see his views and his efforts sustained
<pb n="14"/>
                  <figure entity="paddock14">
                     <figDesc>14th page of Wilbur
F. Paddock's A Great Man Fallen!</figDesc>
                  </figure>
by the great body of the people of this land; and to behold the dawn
of a new era of privilege and blessing to the oppressed race, which,
in the midst of peril and difficulty, he stretched forth his brave
hand to save.</p>
               <p>Never had humanity a more faithful, devoted and
self-sacrificing friend. The principles of human liberty he
enunciated, and the blows he dealt to tyranny, oppression and wrong,
are felt the world over. The simple, unpretending man, whose body now
lies in yonder State House, has made the monarchs of Europe tremble
upon their thrones, and sent joy and the assurance of ultimate freedom
to every bondman who has been able to spell out his name and heard of
his glorious deeds; and they will weep, too, as we to-day weep, over
the cruel act that stilled the throbbings of his noble heart, and
closed in violence and blood his earthly career.</p>
               <p>Abraham Lincoln was great yet again, in his devotion to his
country. No testimony of mine, I am sure, is needed to strengthen your
convictions of the truth of this statement. His whole history, before
as well as after his elevation to the chief office of authority in
this nation, is in every part of it proof conclusive of his entire
single-hearted devotion to the land of his birth. An intense,
all-comprehensive patriotism, as has been said, was the constant
stimulus of all his public exertions. It grew into the very
constitution
<pb n="15"/>
                  <figure entity="paddock15">
                     <figDesc>15th page of Wilbur
F. Paddock's A Great Man Fallen!</figDesc>
                  </figure>
of his soul, and operated like a natural function, continuously,
spontaneously, and almost as it were, unconsciously. It pervaded and
vivified all that he said and formed the prime incentive of all that
he did. If he had ambition, it was to serve his country, and in that
sphere where he might do it most effectually. In no way did he ever
fail his country in the time of need. A public trust was to him a
sacred thing. Sublimer moral courage, more resolute devotion to duty,
cannot be found in the history of man than he has displayed for the
salvation of the American Union. It was the sublime performance of
sublime duties that made him so trusted, and which has given him a
fame as solid as justice, and as genuine as truth.</p>
               <p>And yet, once more. Chief above all things else, Abraham
Lincoln was to the Christian heart manifestly great <hi rend="italic">in
his devotion to his God</hi>. Whatever other elements may enter into
the composition of a great character, this undoubtedly is the noblest
and the best. And this especially distinguished him whom the nation
now mourns. Religion shed its pure and hallowed influence over his
life. It preserved him from those vices which too often disgrace men
in place and power. It made him a pattern of goodness even to those
who made greater professions. It opened fountains of comfort,
encouragement and support to his soul, and gave him that grand and
<pb n="16"/>
                  <figure entity="paddock16">
                     <figDesc>16th page of Wilbur
F. Paddock's A Great Man Fallen!</figDesc>
                  </figure>
abiding trust in the final overthrow of the rebellion, which, amid all
the vicissitudes and varied fortune which attended our arms never
wavered, and enabled him to guide, with a firm and steady hand, the
destinies of this great people. When he left his home in Springfield
to assume, for the first time, his great and responsible duties, he
declared that he humbly leaned upon Divine guidance and mercy. This
was the keynote of all his after declarations. Faith in God was his
pillar of cloud by day and pillar of fire by night. It supplied him
with comfort and peace in the midst of family bereavement. It guided
him safely through the wilderness of perplexing doubts and
discouragements that he was called upon to enter, in leading this
people up to a higher standard of duty, and to the possession of
greater privileges and blessings. It inspired him with calm and
cheering hope in the darkest days of this rebellion, when other hearts
were inclined to despondency and gloom. "Gentlemen," said he to a
company of clergymen who were paying their respects to him, "my hope
of success in this great and terrible struggle rests on that immutable
foundation, the justice and goodness of God. And when events are very
threatening, and prospects very dark, I still hope that some way which
man cannot see, all will be well in the end; because our cause is
just, and God is on our side." And so again, when the rebel army
invaded this State, and all confidence seemed for a time gone in our
<pb n="17"/>
                  <figure entity="paddock17">
                     <figDesc>17th page of Wilbur
F. Paddock's A Great Man Fallen!</figDesc>
                  </figure>
ability to beat back the foe, we learn the manner in which he met the
trial, and how his fears were overcome. "I rolled on God," he said,
"the burden of my country, and I rose from my knees lightened of my
load, feeling a peace that passeth understanding--feeling that I could
leave myself, my country and my all, in the hands of God." Oh, what a
noble character was his. How we love to study it. How we long more and
more and more, to imitate it. Great as we have seen in his devotion to
his God, to his country, to humanity and to truth, Abraham Lincoln was
a prince in a line of royalty that contains the best blood that God
ever permitted to flow through the veins of fallen man. The words of
Cardinal Wolsey to one whom England has likened in some respects unto
himself, seem ever to have sounded in his ears, as though uttered by a
voice from heaven, to indicate and prepare him for his fate.</p>
               <lg type="stanza">
                  <l>"Be just and fear
not;</l>
                  <l>Let all the ends thou aim'st at be thy country's,</l>
                  <l>Thy God's, and truth's! Then if thou fallest, O Cromwell!</l>
                  <l>Thou fallest a blessed martyr!"</l>
               </lg>
               <p>Thou <hi rend="italic">hast</hi> fallen, just and fearless
one! greater in thy devotion to truth, to country and to God, than
Wolsey ever could have believed of man, or Cromwell ever was capable
of being! And thou art a martyr blessed! Blessed with the honors of
Heaven, the smile of God, the gratitude of the rescued and the
<pb n="18"/>
                  <figure entity="paddock18">
                     <figDesc>18th page of Wilbur
F. Paddock's A Great Man Fallen!</figDesc>
                  </figure>
saved, and the love of the good and true, the loyal and the brave, in
whatever clime thy name and thy history is known. We thank our God
to-day for what thou hast been to us.</p>
               <p>II. But who was his murderer? Whose the hand that dared to
still the beatings of that noble heart, destroy the great champion of
human freedom and the preserver of our national life, make desolate
the home of pure affection and filial devotion, and plunge a whole
nation into mourning? Not that poor wretch who, now horror-stricken at
the deed he has done, and the terrible penalty attached to it, seeks
to escape the ministers of justice. He, indeed, was the tool, the
agent in the execution of this diabolical act, and ought when found to
be punished according to the atrocity of his crime. But he was not the
inspirer, he was not the soul of this murder. There were others as
much more guilty than he, as he was more guilty than the pistol which
he held in his hand. Both were merely tools. Who set them to
accomplish this awful deed? Who used them? Perhaps you may say, the
chief of the Southern traitors, and those who with him devised this
infernal plot. But can <hi rend="italic">they</hi> truly be said to be
the murderers of our noble-hearted President? Have we found the real
culprit yet? No, my friends, though all we have mentioned may be
guilty, and I believe they are of <hi rend="italic">this</hi> crime, as
well as the hundred
<pb n="19"/>
                  <figure entity="paddock19">
                     <figDesc>19th page of Wilbur
F. Paddock's A Great Man Fallen!</figDesc>
                  </figure>
others with which they are charged, yet the originator and the
executer of this fearful murder is to be found, not in one traitor or
in a band of them, but in that great Evil against which Abraham
Lincoln battled all his life, and was sacrificed in attempting to
destroy. It is the accursed Spirit of Slavery; the sum of all
villanies; the mother of treason, arson, perjury and crimes of every
color and name; the fruitful source of most of our woes as a nation
and the destroyer of thousands of immortal souls. This it is that
struck down our lamented President. This it is that has added another
to the long line of martyrs that have fallen to appease the insatiable
thirst for blood which it has incited and inspired. It were not
possible for the soil of America to produce a wretch so cowardly, so
detestable, so devilish, as the reputed assassin of our late Chief
Magistrate, unless possessed by this demon of wrong. It has given
birth to the rebellion which has made our land wet with blood and
strewn with the bodies of the slain. It has starved sixty thousand of
our noble soldiers in the prisons of the South. It has carried sorrow
into every heart, and darkened every home in our land. It has crushed
out the very manhood of those whom God made in His own image, and
Christ died to redeem. It has debauched the conscience of the South,
so that the broad distinctions between right and wrong, virtue and
crime, loyalty and treason, are not clearly seen but
<pb n="20"/>
                  <figure entity="paddock20">
                     <figDesc>20th page of Wilbur
F. Paddock's A Great Man Fallen!</figDesc>
                  </figure>
by few, the large proportion of the people upholding and defending
upon the authority of Holy Writ, that which the plain letter of the
law of God and man clearly declares to be a sin and a crime. It has
corrupted public morals, tastes, sentiments and opinions in the North,
greatly blinding it to the guilt of treason and the crime of
rebellion: degrading many of its merchants into mere sycophants and
slaves in their greediness to appropriate its gains and share in its
favors: setting up as models of excellence and as the true aristocracy
of the nation, those who now do not refrain from every crime to effect
their unholy ends: pouring contempt upon the humbler virtues when not
redeemed by graces of manner, or the stamp of noble birth: perverting
the purposes and aims of life, and dishonoring labor. This is what
slavery has done and is doing to destroy this land. Thank God that its
power is not now as great as in days gone by. Thank God that he whom
the nation now mourns, was permitted before his death, to grapple with
this great evil as man never did before, and to crush out its life in
many portions of our land. Thank God that the loyal and true men in
our National and State halls of legislation, have decreed its total
destruction, and soon, if we mistake not, so far as its outward
presence is concerned, it will be seen no more on this continent. But
it has a Spirit which will not so easily die. And it is this Spirit,
as we have said, which drank the life-blood of our Presi-
<pb n="21"/>
                  <figure entity="paddock21">
                     <figDesc>21st page of Wilbur
F. Paddock's A Great Man Fallen!</figDesc>
                  </figure>
dent. Here we find the real author and perpetrator of this horrid
crime. This is the criminal which we arraign in the sight of high
Heaven, and charge with this foul murder, and with the agony of heart
that now is felt throughout our beloved land.</p>
               <p>III. How, then, may this cruel murder best be avenged, and
our great and irreparable loss be made a blessing to ourselves and our
country?</p>
               <p>Dear friends, not by indiscriminate denunciation of all now
in rebellion against this Government. Not by giving vent to feelings
of hatred and revenge against even its leaders, red as are their hands
with this the best blood of our land. No. There is a better way of
avenging it. It is by destroying entirely and forever the Spirit of
Slavery and all its most infamous progeny. Let the <hi rend="italic">law</hi> deal with the mere tools and agents of this awful
crime according to the severity which justice demands,--no less and no
more. But let <hi rend="italic">us</hi>, as citizens and Christians,
deal with that which has inspired them. This Spirit of Slavery as we
see it in the North, let it be crushed out, root and branch. Let us
hate treason and rebellion with a perfect hatred, because they are
sins against God and crimes against the State. Let us make such
distinctions between the guilty and the innocent as truth and justice
demand. Let us require that the guilty and unrepentant be punished;
<pb n="22"/>
                  <figure entity="paddock22">
                     <figDesc>22nd page of Wilbur
F. Paddock's A Great Man Fallen!</figDesc>
                  </figure>
but let us pardon and forgive those who have been misled and are
penitent. Let us frown down the mean and sordid spirit that would
barter away the true dignity of manhood for gold, whether it be
exhibited in trafficking with Southern products, Northern manufacture,
or the nation's life and credit. Let the model of excellence we adopt
and imitate, be, not what slavery, but freedom produces, --freedom of
body and mind and spirit--freedom, human and divine--such a
magnificent exhibition of character as God gave us in Abraham
Lincoln. Let us see for what end we live, and what God has placed us
here to do.</p>
               <p>Oh, what a momentous time is the present to the young men
of our country! What opportunity for noble effort, for a high
development of character, for exerting great influence, and fighting
glorious battles for truth, for humanity, for country and for God. Are
they doing it? Are they meeting the great questions of the day with
the seriousness and consideration which their importance demands? Are
they placing themselves positively and clearly upon the side of human
liberty and equality, truth and justice, law and loyalty, virtue and
religion? Are they rising to the height of the demands of the years
that are coming to a nation which God has preserved for a great work,
and in which they are to act a most important part? Are they preparing
themselves for it by a full dedication to their Lord and Saviour as
well as their country?</p>
               <pb n="23"/>
               <p>
                  <figure entity="paddock23">
                     <figDesc>23rd page of
Wilbur F. Paddock's A Great Man Fallen!</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <p>Would God I could answer these questions in the
affirmative, even as regards the young men of my own beloved
flock. There are some who realize these times as they ought. Some who
knowing their duty solemnly meet and perform it. Others are only
partially awake to their responsibilities and unfitted to do the work
assigned them. They love their country, but they do not love their
God. And yet it is only Christian men that God would have direct the
glorious future of this people. They only are equal to the work,
because it is a work that they only can do. We have not been baptized
in blood for nothing, or to be what we once were. God, I believe, has
saved us, that we may extend far and wide His Gospel, while advocating
at the same time, by theory and practice the cause of universal
liberty and equality. Our mission as a people is the moral, social,
political and religious elevation of mankind.</p>
               <p>Let us, then, appreciate our work and its
responsibilities. Let us begin with our own personal infirmities and
sins, and seek to have them removed,--with individual aims, purposes,
and positions, and seek to have them right. Let us take hold of every
foolish prejudice and every false notion, and by the power of God,
destroy their influence upon ourselves, and as far as we can, upon
others. If we cowardly shrink from our duty, and say as did David,
"These sons of Zeruiah be too hard for me," like him we may be
<pb n="24"/>
                  <figure entity="paddock24">
                     <figDesc>24th page of Wilbur
F. Paddock's A Great Man Fallen!</figDesc>
                  </figure>
called hereafter to lament our weakness, and suffer punishment again
for our sins.</p>
               <p>This day, when the body of our noble and sainted President
is in our midst, and our hearts are touched by feelings of grateful
love, let us over his lifeless and disfigured corse, pledge ourselves
to truth, to humanity, to our country and to our God. And that we may
do it aright, let us confess and forsake our sins, and trust and love
and worship the Saviour, who hath bought us with His blood, and would
present us to His Father without spot, clothed with His own most
precious robe, and sealed with the signet of His covenanted and
unchangeable love.</p>
            </div2>
         </div1>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI.2>