<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader><fileDesc>
         <titleStmt n="Moses and Joshua">
            <title>  Moses and
Joshua</title>
            <author>Rankin, Rev. J. E.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Compiled and edited by</resp>
               <name>Beck
Center</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent/>
         <publicationStmt><publisher>Lewis H. Beck Center</publisher><pubPlace>Emory University</pubPlace><address>
               <addrLine>Atlanta,
Georgia</addrLine>
            </address><availability>
               <p>1996 Emory
University. Permission is granted to download, transmit, or otherwise
reproduce, distribute or display the contributions to the work claimed
by Emory University for non-profit educational purposes, provided
this header is included in its entirety.  For inquiries about
commercial uses, contact the Director, 
Pitts Theology Library, Emory
University, Atlanta, Georgia 30322</p>
            </availability><date>1999</date></publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Lincoln
Sermons Project</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Rankin,
Rev. J. E. Moses and Joshua. A Discourse on the Death of Abraham
Lincoln, Preached in the Winthrop Church, Charlestown, Wednesday Noon,
April 19, 1865.  Boston: Press of Dakin and Metcalf, No. 37
Cornhill.</bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc><encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This text derives from the Special Collections 
of Pitts Theology Library, Emory University, and is produced in 
collaboration with the Lewis H. Beck Center a, the Emory 
Preservation Office, and Pitts Theology Library.</p>
            <p>TRANSCRIBER: Lewis H. Beck Center and Emory University 
Preservation Office.</p>
            <p>PRODUCER:  BookLab, Inc., 1606 Headway Circle, 
Suite 100, Austin, TX 78754</p>
            <p>CAPTURE DEVICE: XEROX DocuImage 620S flatbed scanner</p>
            <p>CAPTURE DETAILS: Scanner software: XEROX ScanTool 
version 4.2.3; no gamma correction; images are all bitonal.</p>
            <p>CHANGE HISTORY: Using the Adobe Photoshop Batch Processor, 
we interpolated  the original TIFF files to 8-bit grays, 
and altered the resolution to 144 dpi, producing screen 
images twice the original size.  We then saved them in 
JPEG format.  We produced GIF thumbnails from the JPEG files.</p>
            <p>RESOLUTION: 600 ppi</p>
            <p>COMPRESSION: Resolution 144 per inch with Constrain 
Properties to 72 per inch.</p>
            <p>SOURCE: Original documents.</p>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc><revisionDesc><change><name>Stewart Varner</name> transformed this document from p4 to p5 on <date when="2010-03-22">March 22, 2010</date></change><change xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><date>1999</date><label>Staff</label><name>Scott Ellis</name>SGML tags inserted in compliance
with TEI guidelines using TEILITE</change></revisionDesc></teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div1 xml:id="rankin.001" n="Moses and Joshua" type="text">
            <head> 
               <bibl>
                  <title>Moses and Joshua</title> 
                  <date>Wednesday Noon, April 19, 1865</date>
                  <pubPlace>Winthrop Church, Charlestown</pubPlace> 
                  <author>Rankin,
Rev. J. E.</author> 
                  
                     <pubPlace>Boston</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Press of Dakin and Metcalf, No. 37 Cornhill</publisher>
                     <date>1865</date>
                   
               <idno type="ark">http://pid.emory.edu/ark:/25593/15qsq</idno></bibl> 
            </head>
            <p>
               <figure><graphic url=""/>
                  <figDesc>1st page of Rev. J. E. Rankin's
Moses and Joshua.</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <p>MOSES AND JOSHUA.</p>
            <p>A</p>
            <p>DISCOURSE</p>
            <p>ON THE DEATH OF</p>
            <p>ABRAHAM LINCOLN</p>
            <p>PREACHED IN THE</p>
            <p>WINTHROP CHURCH, CHARLESTOWN,</p>
            <p>Wednesday Noon, April 19, 1865.</p>
            <p>BY</p>
            <p>REV. J.E. RANKIN,</p>
            <p>PASTOR</p>
            <p>BOSTON:</p>
            <p>PRESS OF DAKIN AND METCALF,</p>
            <p>NO. 37
CORNHILL.</p>
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>
               <figure><graphic url=""/>
                  <figDesc>2nd page of
Rev. J. E. Rankin's Moses and Joshua.</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>
               <figure><graphic url=""/>
                  <figDesc>3rd page of
Rev. J. E. Rankin's Moses and Joshua.</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <p>REV. J.E. RANKIN:</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italic">Dear Sir</hi>,--Having
listened with great interest to your sermon, preached on Wednesday,
April 19, 1865, in the Winthrop Church, on the occasion of the death
of President Lincoln, we respectfully request, in behalf of ourselves
and many others, who were present, a copy of the same for
publication.</p>
            <p>Respectfully and truly yours, <lb/>H. S. DOANE,<lb/>
A. WHITNEY, <lb/>WM. CARLETON, <lb/>GEO. HYDE, <lb/>JAMES ADAMS,<lb/>
ARTHUR W. TUFTS, <lb/>CALEB EMERY, <lb/>NATHAN A. TUFTS.</p>
            <p>CHARLESTOWN, April 20, 1865.</p>
            <p>CHARLESTOWN,
April 20, 1865.</p>
            <p>DEAR FRIENDS,--</p>
            <p>Your request has taken me entirely by surprise; and I fear
that the hastily-prepared manuscript which I place at your disposal
will only disappoint you when printed.</p>
            <p>Wishing it were worthier of the occasion, your kindness,
and my own feelings,</p>
            <p>I am yours truly, <lb/>J.E. RANKIN.  <lb/>DEACON HEMAN S. DOANE, and
others.</p>
            <pb n="4"/>
<!-- blank page -->
<!--            <p>
               <figure entity="rankin4">
                  <figDesc>4th page of
Rev. J. E. Rankin's Moses and Joshua.</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p> -->
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>
               <figure><graphic url=""/>
                  <figDesc>5th page of
Rev. J. E. Rankin's Moses and Joshua.</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <div2 xml:id="rankin.002" n="DISCOURSE" type="sermon">
               <head>DISCOURSE.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Joshua I</hi>. 1, 2: "NOW AFTER THE DEATH
OF MOSES, THE SERVANT OF THE LORD, IT CAME  TO PASS THAT THE LORD
SPAKE UNTO JOSHUA, THE SON OF NUN, MOSES' MINISTER SAYING, MOSES MY
SERVANT IS DEAD; NOW, THEREFORE, ARISE, GO OVER THIS JORDAN, THOU AND
ALL THIS PEOPLE, UNTO THE LAND WHICH I DO GIVE TO THEM."</p>
               </epigraph>
               <p>THE Bible contains the history of the human race in
epitome; is the mirror in which every age and every generation may see
reflected its own features and complexion. The prophecies of the Bible
have a germinant fulfilment; have a manifold application. Its
historical portions furnish illustrations and analogies for almost
every type of character and event.</p>
               <p>Nothing can be more beautiful or appropriate than many of
the parallels which the American people have traced between their own
recent history and that of the children of Israel in their exodus from
the house of bondage; and, doubtless, the parallels are far more
striking in the history of that oppressed race, whose deliverance has
been a literal one, than in our own. And no parallel of this kind
could be more appropriate or touching than that suggested by the
melancholy passage in our national experience which is now
transpiring.</p>
               <p>From poverty, obscurity, and untold social disadvantages,
God raised up Abraham Lincoln to enact a part, second to none in
importance, in the history of the world, whose consequences are to
affect the condition and happiness of
<pb n="6"/>
                  <figure><graphic url=""/>
                     <figDesc>6th page of
Rev. J. E. Rankin's Moses and Joshua.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
unnumbered millions. While living, and enacting his part with
characteristic simplicity and fidelity, none of his contemporaries
could appreciate it. Like the unfinished work of the artist, which
needs only the slightest touch upon eye or mouth to round and complete
the likeness, so the work of this patient and unpretending ruler
needed but the touch of death to render it immortal. There are
documents written by the hand that now lies nerveless in the nation's
capital; there are words prompted by that great heart, whose kind
beatings have been so rudely hushed forever, uttered by those lips,
upon which the people nevermore will hang in expectancy or delight,
which can never die.</p>
               <p>The Emancipation Proclamation will always be classed with
the Declaration of Independence, as its suitable complement and
fulfilment. Take the state papers of this Illinois lawyer, all of
whose common-school education did not exceed a single year, and how
clear, how direct, how sagacious, how cogent, they are!--how
exhaustive of the subject in hand, how overwhelming to antagonists,
how opportunely put forth, how satisfactory to the people! How
thoroughly this man understood and was master of the situation!
Watching every pulse of the nation, watching every providence of
God,--now radical, now conservative, now moving with the grand
progress of the people, now waiting for the people to move,--during
four years of civil war he has kept united upon his policy the sound
judgment, the keen moral sense, of the most intelligent, the most
thinking, people upon the face of the earth! Nay, more! Every time the
tide of feeling has in any measure ebbed away from his administration,
it has only been to come back from the great bosom of the nation with
increased fulness and volume! And when he so suddenly and so sadly
fell, this tide of affection and enthusiastic trust had reached its
highest point. 
<pb n="7"/>
                  <figure><graphic url=""/>
                     <figDesc>7th page of
Rev. J. E. Rankin's Moses and Joshua.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
In the admiring view of the whole nation, he stood upon that Pisgah to
which his own fidelity to God and to the principles of truth and
justice had elevated him. He stood there, and looking northward, all
was industry, thrift, and success. The axe of the woodman still rang
from the forests of Maine; the white wings of commerce still sought
the harbors of New England; the din of business still rose from the
mighty centres of manufacture and of trade; the husbandman followed
his shining plough afield, and scattered his seed with the certainty
of reaping an undisturbed and abundant harvest. He looked toward the
prairies of his own beloved Western home, the scene of his early
struggles and achievements. He saw the great artery of the nation's
system pouring its unshackled currents into the waiting Gulf. The
broad prairies were putting on their spring attire; the children, as
they played about the distant cabins of the settler, mingled his name
with that of their fathers', who were fighting under the country's
flag; and off to the Pacific coast, the virgin soil of mountain and of
valley was forever free. If there was sorrow all over these portions
of the land, it was not the sorrow of those who mourn without
hope. The people felt that every soldier's life had given years of
immortality to the republic; that what had been "sown in weakness" on
so many hard-fought fields would be "raised in power;" and every flag
was flung to the breeze, and every vale was made vocal with cheer and
cannon and bell; and even the soldier's widow mingled the colors of
the republic with her weeds, and his children knew no music like the
fife and drum. And when our Moses turned his gaze southward, he saw
Ethiopia--a nation born in a day--stretching out her liberated hands
to God, and invoking his richest benedictions to descend upon her
deliverer. He saw Treason vacating her capital and strongholds,
<pb n="8"/>
                  <figure><graphic url=""/>
                     <figDesc>8th page of
Rev. J. E. Rankin's Moses and Joshua.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
in the vain attempt to flee inland to the mountains, ensnared on every
hand, and, finally, surrendering her sword, and sending her disarmed
minions to proclaim at their own homes their final discouragement and
discomfiture. This was the vision that blessed the gaze of Abraham
Lincoln; and all this success and prosperity and freedom was
henceforth and forever to be associated with his own name. Ah, when he
passed through the streets of Richmond an unarmed conqueror, was not
his cup of happiness filled to the brim? Was it not enough to satisfy
the purest and highest earthly ambition of the soul? And upon this
summit he died,--died with this vision still lingering in his memory,
with these acclamations of gratitude and trust still ringing in his
ears!</p>
               <p>"Thus always to tyrants!" muttered the lips of the cowardly
assassin, as the fatal bullet sped to its mark. And the nation, as she
drapes her proud mansions and her humble dwellings, her places of
business, her sanctuaries, and public offices in mourning,--as her
banner droops, as the brazen lips of bells and the sullen mouths of
cannon syllable her grief,--the nation, as clothed in widow's weeds
she stands at this hour by the open grave of the man twice-honored
with the highest position in her gift, takes up the word, "Thus always
to patriot martyrs! So will we ever mourn the ruler thus true to his
country and his country's God!"</p>
               <p>Never had a President such a hold upon the affections of
the people! Every loyal man, woman, and child in the nation has felt,
since his death occurred, as though the form of a cherished one lay
unburied within their own dwellings, as though it were wrong to think
or speak of anything else. The instincts of the people are true. Here
was a man that did not surround himself with stately formalities; that
did not disguise his sentiments by putting them into courtly
<pb n="9"/>
                  <figure><graphic url=""/>
                     <figDesc>9th page of
Rev. J. E. Rankin's Moses and Joshua.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
phrases; that heard their petitions with a paternal ear; that drew
their heart up to his own, that he might feel its beat. We have had
many a Chief Executive whose memory the people will honor; but here
was one who, though compelled by his imperative duty to call hundreds
of thousands of our brothers and sons into the field from which they
never returned to gladden our homes,--here was a President whose
memory the people love, and will love forever! Place his dust wherever
you may, they will make their hearts his shrine. Pile up proud
monuments to his memory, put his figure into bronze or marble, there
shall be a memorial more enduring than these. They will always
remember the pensive and sympathizing look of that deep-set eye, the
holiest angles of that homely face.</p>
               <p>Abraham Lincoln is dead! but his work lives, his memory
lives. It is a rich inheritance for the American people to have the
memory of one public man in modern times who has achieved such
greatness as his, without a stain upon his personal character. There
are men who have risen faster than he,--men of eminent intellectual
ability, who have had their eye upon the presidential chair, who have
schemed and intrigued and contrived until they have succeeded in
sitting there; and others who have failed, and died disappointed. But
Abraham Lincoln attained the position which he occupied while living,
and which he will occupy in history, by the strictest integrity, by
old-fashioned, downright honesty. "Honest old Abe," inelegant as is
the phrase, was no unmeaning sobriquet. It was written all over
him,--in gait and feature and dress. He had a sincere purpose to serve
the people, and not himself or his party, and so the people trusted in
him, filled his armies, and bought his bonds. I believe, also, that he
had a sincere purpose to serve his God, and so God accepted him as his
<pb n="10"/>
                  <figure><graphic url=""/>
                     <figDesc>10th page of
Rev. J. E. Rankin's Moses and Joshua.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
servant, even as he did Moses; honored him as his servant; permitted
him to do--nay, raised him up to do--a work almost as marked, in its
political aspects, as was that of Moses himself. It is his sovereign
prerogative and method to adapt the man to the work which he would
have accomplished; and having accomplished the work, and all the work,
which he had for Abraham Lincoln to do, he has taken him to
himself.</p>
               <p>Abraham Lincoln fell a victim to his own lenient and
unsuspecting nature. He knew there were as black-hearted traitors in
Washington as anywhere in the South; and yet--because he loved that
peculiarity of our institutions which surrounds the Chief Magistrate
with no military escort, with nothing which privileges him above, or
distinguishes him from, an ordinary citizen--he who will hereafter be
regarded the most eminent ruler of modern times, the representative
man of this epoch, came and went as though the thrust of a dagger or
the ball of a revolver might not at any moment terminate his life, and
leave the nation in mourning.</p>
               <p>Every Christian man must deeply regret that the Chief
Executive of the nation was assassinated in a theatre. Theatre-going
is too likely to train up just such desperate men as become assassins,
and the frequenters of such amusements are never too select. Indeed,
his probable assassin had been educated in this school of morals. But
there is reason to believe he was there, because he would not
disappoint the people, though one of them who was enjoying the
benefits of his benignant administration was even then plotting to
take his life. I do not regard his presence there as any evidence of a
taste for such places or such pleasures; but surely, his example had
been better, his life had been safer, elsewhere. And this is all that
need be said.</p>
               <pb n="11"/>
               <p>
                  <figure><graphic url=""/>
                     <figDesc>11th page of
Rev. J. E. Rankin's Moses and Joshua.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <p>Our Chief Executive fell by the hand of an assassin. Thus
to terminate the life of the humblest and meanest citizen in the land
is a most wicked and cowardly act, and is deserving of the most
ignominious fate. But what shall we say of the creature who can
deliberately plan and deliberately arrange and execute the murder of a
nation's great and beloved ruler; who can shoot an unsuspecting, an
unarmed, victim, whose greatest weakness has been his tenderness and
clemency toward his own and his country's foes? It may well be said</p>
               <lg type="stanza">
                  <l>"Besides, this Duncan </l>
                  <l>Hath borne his faculties so meek, hath been</l>
                  <l>So clear in his
great office, that his virtues</l>
                  <l>Will plead like angels,
trumpet-tongued, against</l>
                  <l>The deep damnation of his taking
off."</l>
               </lg>
               <p>The life of a ruler was intended by God to be regarded as
far more sacred than that of an ordinary man. Government is his
ordinance, and the ruler his representative. And though our Chief
Executive is chosen by the people, and but temporarily bears the
responsibilities of state, yet no ruler could have an anointing, a
consecration, higher and holier than his. And if the free millions of
a great people twice bestow their highest trust upon a man, his life
is doubly sacred. When, therefore the assassin singled out the man
thus again selected by a singularly united nation, thus again selected
by God himself, and brutally murdered him, he committed an act so
cruel and inhuman and unholy, so dastardly, that, had he ten thousand
lives, he could not expiate or atone for it. And yet, perhaps, the
great lesson which the people were to learn, were to be educated by
poignant grief properly to appreciate, was this: that to destroy the
life of a nation is an infinitely greater crime than to destroy the
life of a nation's ruler. The ruler dies, but the nation lives. And,
to my own mind, it af-
<pb n="12"/>
                  <figure><graphic url=""/>
                     <figDesc>12th page of
Rev. J. E. Rankin's Moses and Joshua.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
fords the highest possible proof of the sufficiency of our political
system for the most sudden and disastrous emergency, as well as of the
moral strength and intelligence of this great people and the favor of
Jehovah himself, that the nation, thus suddenly and disastrously
afflicted, does not, for a single moment, waver or hesitate as to the
future, but with new calmness and trust and determination, addresses
herself to the great work which God's providence has thrust upon
her. Yes, the nation lives. But treason is only another name for an
attempt to take the nation's life. The same spirit that prompted the
starving of our prisoners at Donaldsonville and Belle Isle plotted
against the life of the President when first on his way to the
nation's capital, and consummated his death on Friday evening
last. Every cannon and gun discharged during the last four years has
been aimed by those in rebellion not against men; is of no such
private interpretation; has been aimed at the life of the nation. And
the time has come when, putting aside all the mawkish sentimentalism
which has been so prevalent, the people should rise up and insist, not
upon vengeance, but upon the vindication of their government. I say it
deliberately: treason of such long standing, so intelligent, so
persistent, so destructive, so infernal, as that of the leading
spirits in the South ought not to be forgiven by this people. God does
not intend it shall be forgiven. And yet who will say that this was
not the tendency of public sentiment before the death of the late
President? And who will say that this sad event was not needed to
furnish us with a new standard for taking the dimensions of this
crime? Is it not time that we cease shooting deserters and let
assassins go unpunished, if the men who have deluged this land with
blood are to escape merely because they have usurped the titles and
worn the insignia of authority? 
<pb n="13"/>
                  <figure><graphic url=""/>
                     <figDesc>13th page of
Rev. J. E. Rankin's Moses and Joshua.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
Those who have been guilty of treason, those who have deliberately
foresworn their allegiance to the government of their fathers, who
have waged four years of relentless warfare against their country,
have not only forfeited all rights as citizens, but have so vitiated
and corrupted themselves that they never hereafter can be trusted as
fellow-citizens. They have forever unfitted themselves for
citizenship. The men who have been cognizant of, and have never
attempted to discountenance, the cruelties inflicted upon our captured
soldiers, can the people receive them back again?</p>
               <p>In Abraham Lincoln, God gave us just the man to take us
safely through the past stages of the rebellion; just the man to
determine the true policy of the nation, to inaugurate it and render
it secure. But the nation had now reached the Jordan, beyond which
were sterner duties than any in the past God saw that to compromise
with the surviving leaders of this conspiracy against the existence of
the nation, to give back Arlington Heights--that beautiful spot where
one looks across the valley of the Potomac to the dome of the
capitol--to its former proprietor, and to permit him to enjoy again
the rights of citizenship, was simply to furnish occasion and
encouragement for other treasons in the future. Rebellion had been
subdued; but treason had not been touched. Its brands were only
scattered again over the land, waiting for another favorable
opportunity to kindle into flames. Rather, to have been one of the
original conspirators, to have been among the leaders in these designs
which have so afflicted the nation, to have attained this bad eminence
in grime, seemed sufficient to insure pardon and release. Such might
not have been the policy of the government; but, surely, there was
great reason to apprehend it. We can never be secure against future
treachery among our public men, whose ambition has been disappointed
and
<pb n="14"/>
                  <figure><graphic url=""/>
                     <figDesc>14th page of
Rev. J. E. Rankin's Moses and Joshua.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
whose arrogance affronted, until the neck of this treason bears the
mark of the halter and dangles beneath the gibbet! Had this been the
fate of John C. Calhoun, Jefferson Davis would have taken warning. But
treason was permitted to make its nest in the very Cabinet, to utter
its words of defiance upon the floor of the Senate, and then to depart
unquestioned, unchallenged.</p>
               <p>In Andrew Johnson, God has given us a man who, if we may
confide in his repeated utterances, knows how to define and to punish
this crime against the life of a nation; a suitable workman to stitch
the shroud of this rebellion. The leaders in this conspiracy lost all
prospect of a nationality on April 9th, when their hitherto invincible
Lee surrendered to General Grant his surrounded and dispirited
army. Now--in the assassination of Abraham Lincoln--they have lost all
prospect of recovering their estates and their citizenship, and if
adjudged guilty of the crime of treason, no executive clemency will
interpose for their pardon. The law must take its course; the people
will demand this. And this is as it should be. The desperate men
concerned knew what they risked when they engaged in this contest. If
they had succeeded, they would have been regarded as heroes fighting
for their homes. They have failed. Let them take the fate of
felons.</p>
               <p>There is an incalculable moral influence proceeding, and to
proceed from this contest. We are a spectacle to the nations of the
earth, and God has a government to vindicate as well as man. It is not
the misfortune of failure which sufficiently punishes such
unprincipled spirits as have undertaken to destroy the sacred work of
our fathers. The world needs the exhibition of a justice more severe
and exact. When rebellion failed in heaven, there were everlasting
chains of darkness for those engaged in it:</p>
               <pb n="15"/>
               <p>
                  <figure><graphic url=""/>
                     <figDesc>15th page of
Rev. J. E. Rankin's Moses and Joshua.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <lg type="stanza">
                  <l>"Hurled headlong flaming from th' ethereal sky</l>
                  <l>With hideous ruin and combustion."</l>
               </lg>
               <p>And I believe that God has ordained that what the world calls
"poetical justice"--justice in some measure adequate to the crime
committed--shall yet be meted out to the men most guilty in conspiring
against the life of this nation; whose bloody hands would</p>
               <lg type="stanza">
                  <l>"The multitudinous seas incarnadine,</l>
                  <l>Making the green one red."</l>
               </lg>
               <p>Some individuals find it difficult to distinguish between
vindictiveness and a sense of justice. They are afraid to urge the
application of the divine law against murder, lest they may be
regarded vindictive. But God intended human government to be a terror
to those that do evil. The pardoning power is a dangerous one to the
innocent. Can our executive officers expect to escape assassination,
when they stay the processes by which the assassination of the
humblest citizen is prevented or avenged? Let us beware of those views
of government, whether human or divine, in which there is no justice,
in which there are no penalties, in which there is no terror to
evil-doers. And while we are cautious not to transcend the limits and
methods of the law, let us not enervate and emasculate our national
authority by mingling in our moral decisions too great tenderness
toward the transgressor.</p>
               <p>The mournful solemnities of this occasion,--the fourth
anniversary of the first shedding of blood in Baltimore, and the
ninetieth anniversary of the battle of Lexington,--upon which a whole
land, as one family, mingle their tears in sorrow, only illustrate the
spirit with which we have to deal. Had treason at the capital been
more severely punished, had a price been put upon its head, had it
always had the manacles and halter which it has deserved, perhaps the
<pb n="16"/>
                  <figure><graphic url=""/>
                     <figDesc>16th page of
Rev. J. E. Rankin's Moses and Joshua.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
nation had never experienced this heavy loss. But such conjectures are
unprofitable now. We bury our true-hearted President to-day, tenderly
and reverently as we would bury a father. We wonder at God's goodness
in raising up such a man, and enabling him to accomplish so much in a
single term of office. We accept the proof that we are yet under the
guidance of the Lord of hosts, which this gift at such a time
affords. We turn from the sun just set amid so much glory in the
west--to another man from the people--to our rising sun in the east,
trusting that what Abraham Lincoln, of Illinois, has not lived to
accomplish God will enable Andrew Johnson, of Tennessee, to do. We are
disappointed, but we are not discouraged. We have passed the Red Sea
and the wilderness, and have had unmistakable pledges that we shall
occupy that land of Union, Liberty, and Peace which flows with milk
and honey. The curtain has risen for the last scene. Let us quit
ourselves like men. Let us go over this Jordan and take possession of
what is before us! God changes the men, but keeps his purpose, to give
it to us and to our children forever! And let us respond to the appeal
of our new President for sympathy and support as the Israelites did to
Joshua: "According, as we hearkened unto Moses in all things, so will
we hearken unto thee, only the Lord thy God be with thee as he was
with Moses."</p>
            </div2>
         </div1>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>