<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader><fileDesc>
         <titleStmt n="Sermon on the Death of Abraham Lincoln.">
            <title>  Sermon on the
Death of Abraham Lincoln.  </title>
            <author>Rice, N. L., D.D.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Compiled and edited by</resp>
               <name>Beck
Center</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent/>
         <publicationStmt><publisher>Lewis H. Beck Center</publisher><pubPlace>Emory University</pubPlace><address>
               <addrLine>Atlanta,
Georgia</addrLine>
            </address><availability>
               <p>1996 Emory
University. Permission is granted to download, transmit, or otherwise
reproduce, distribute or display the contributions to the work claimed
by Emory University for non-profit educational purposes, provided
this header is included in its entirety.  For inquiries about
commercial uses, contact the Director, 
Pitts Theology Library, Emory
University, Atlanta, Georgia 30322</p>
            </availability><date>1999</date></publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Lincoln
Sermons Project</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Rice, N. L.,
D.D. 
Sermon on the Death of Abraham Lincoln, Late President of the United States.
Preached on the Occasion of the National Funeral.
 New York. Wm. C. Bryant &amp; Co.,
Printers. 1865. </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc><encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This text derives from the Special Collections 
of Pitts Theology Library, Emory University, and is produced in 
collaboration with the Lewis H. Beck Center a, the Emory 
Preservation Office, and Pitts Theology Library.</p>
            <p>TRANSCRIBER: Lewis H. Beck Center and Emory University 
Preservation Office.</p>
            <p>PRODUCER:  BookLab, Inc., 1606 Headway Circle, 
Suite 100, Austin, TX 78754</p>
            <p>CAPTURE DEVICE: XEROX DocuImage 620S flatbed scanner</p>
            <p>CAPTURE DETAILS: Scanner software: XEROX ScanTool 
version 4.2.3; no gamma correction; images are all bitonal.</p>
            <p>CHANGE HISTORY: Using the Adobe Photoshop Batch Processor, 
we interpolated  the original TIFF files to 8-bit grays, 
and altered the resolution to 144 dpi, producing screen 
images twice the original size.  We then saved them in 
JPEG format.  We produced GIF thumbnails from the JPEG files.</p>
            <p>RESOLUTION: 600 ppi</p>
            <p>COMPRESSION: Resolution 144 per inch with Constrain 
Properties to 72 per inch.</p>
            <p>SOURCE: Original documents.</p>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc><revisionDesc><change><name>Stewart Varner</name> transformed this document from p4 to p5 on <date when="2010-03-22">March 22, 2010</date></change><change xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><date>1999</date><label>Staff</label><name>Scott Ellis</name>SGML tags inserted in compliance
with TEI guidelines using TEILITE</change></revisionDesc></teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div1 xml:id="rice.001" n="Sermon on the Death of Abraham Lincoln, Late President of the United States. Preached on the Occasion of the National Funeral" type="text">
            <head> 
               <bibl> 
                  <title>Sermon on the
Death of Abraham Lincoln, Late President of the United States.
Preached on the Occasion of the National Funeral</title>
                  <date>Wednesday, April 19, 1865</date> 
                  <pubPlace>Presbyterian Church
in Fifth Avenue, cor. 19th St., N. Y.</pubPlace> 
                  <author>N. L. Rice,
D.D.</author> 
                  
                     <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Wm. C. Bryant &amp; Co., Printers</publisher>
                     <date>1865</date>
                   
               <idno type="ark">http://pid.emory.edu/ark:/25593/15qw4</idno></bibl> 
            </head>
            <pb facs="rice1.jpg"/>
            <p>SERMON</p>
            <p>On the Death</p>
            <p>OF</p>
            <p>ABRAHAM LINCOLN,</p>
            <p>LATE PRESIDENT OF THE UNITED
STATES.</p>
            <p>PREACHED ON THE OCCASION OF THE NATIONAL FUNERAL,</p>
            <p>Wednesday, April 19, 1865,</p>
            <p>BY</p>
            <p>N. L. RICE, D.D.,</p>
            <p>Pastor of the Presbyterian Church in Fifth Avenue, cor. 19th, St.,
N. Y.</p>
            <p>New York</p>
            <p>WM. C. BRYANT &amp; CO., PRINTERS, 41 NASSAU STREET,
COR. OF  LIBERTY.</p>
            <p>1865.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="rice2.jpg"/>
            <p>Note-This Sermon, kindly furnished by Rev. Dr. Rice, at their
request, is published by several gentlemen of his congregation.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="rice3.jpg"/>
            <div2 xml:id="rice.002" n="SERMON" type="sermon">
               <head>SERMON.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <p>Psalm XLVI.: 10.-"Be still, and know that I
am God!"</p>
               </epigraph>
               <p>It is only in the light of Divine revelation that we can interpret
the movements of Divine Providence. The Word of God reveals the
purposes for which this world was created, and for the accomplishment
of which it is governed. But even with all the light which shines upon
us from Heaven, we can comprehend the ways of God only in part. When
we have learned all that comes within the grasp of our limited
intellects, we must yet adopt the language of Job - "Lo, these are
parts of his ways; but how little a portion is heard of Him! but the
thunder of His power "who can understand?" Not less appropriate is the
language of the Psalmist-" Clouds and darkness are round about him:
righteousness and judgment are the habitation of his throne."</p>
               <p>The difficulty which presses the mind is far greater, when
Providential events of a peculiarly startling and alarming character
are the subject of contemplation. In such circumstances, the feelings
of the heart become too strong for the intellect. It is easy, in the
indulgence of the feelings that burst forth in view of an event so
sudden and so appalling, as that which has called us together, to give
utterances, and
<pb n="4" facs="rice4.jpg"/>
thus impart intensity to them. Yet we may not disregard the admonition
of God's Word-" In the day of adversity "consider." Be still, and know
that I am God."</p>
               <p>Let us, then, try to interpret the awful Providence which has
summoned this whole nation to mourning so far as to make a wise
improvement of it, and to secure the blessing which our Heavenly
Father is willing to connect with afflictive dispensations. Let us
then--</p>
               <p>I.--Be still, and know that the hand of God is in it, and that He
is speaking to us. If it be true, that the life of a sparrow is the
object of God's care; if it be true, that the very hairs of our heads
are all numbered by Him, much more must it be true, that there was a
Providence over the man whose life was so intimately connected with
all the interests of a great nation. True, he fell by the hand of the
assassin; but it is also true, that "The wrath of man shall praise
"Him; the remainder of wrath He will restrain." The murderous purpose
could be executed only by Divine permission; and such permission
contemplates some great and wise end. Moreover, there are
peculiarities connected with this murder, which give it special and
awful significancy.</p>
               <p>In the first place, the assassination of a civil ruler, in high
position, is a thing almost unheard of in modern times, and especially
in a Christian nation. Now and then attempts of the kind have been
made, but they have almost always been providentially defeated. That
in this enlightened and Christian nation such a thing would be
attempted, and if attempted, would prove successful, had not entered
into our minds.</p>
               <p>The assassination of <hi rend="italic">such</hi> a man as President
Lincoln, is yet more marvellous and more alarming. The great majority
of civil rulers, who have been assassinated, have driven
<pb n="5" facs="rice5.jpg"/>
men to desperation by their tyranny and cruelty; but how different the
character of the man who has fallen in our midst!</p>
               <p>Mr. Lincoln was a man of remarkably amiable disposition, and of
kindly feelings. This no one acquainted with his character, as I have
been for some years, will question. He was a man of unblemished moral
character. His principles have been proof against all temptations to
corruption. He passed through a severe ordeal, in the midst of the
most intense political excitement, when every act is scrutinized and
every defect magnified. Yet he came out of that ordeal with a
character unstained, challenging the respect, if not the admiration,
of even political opponents. And now that be has left us forever, I am
sure there will be but one testimony respecting his moral
character.</p>
               <p>Mr. Lincoln was constitutionally calm-not carried away by the
excitement by which he was surrounded. He possessed, in a remarkable
degree, not only self-control, but sound common sense, which is often
worth, far more than brilliant talents and great learning. He was not
a man who ran to extremes in the opinions he formed. In the midst of
unparalleled excitement, and pressed by powerful influences, he firmly
maintained moderate and conservative views.</p>
               <p>On the agitating question of Slavery, he held and openly avowed the
old doctrine of our fathers. Regarding the system, as it existed in
our country, as a great evil and wrong, he saw plainly the great
calamities which must inevitably result to the slaves themselves by an
immediate and universal emancipation; and he saw the great
disadvantages under which they must ever labor whilst living amongst
the whites. He, therefore, favored gradual emancipation and
colonization. Only the stern necessities of war constrained
<pb n="6" facs="rice6.jpg"/>
him to resort to more summary measures. He would, if he could, have
accomplished what some of us have long labored to accomplish for the
country and the poor slaves.</p>
               <p>On the important question of the relations of Church and State he
exhibited much clearer views than many who should have understood the
subject better than he. During the whole period of his Presidency, he
sat under the ministry of a pastor, of views so conservative, and who
confined himself so strictly to the simple preaching of the Cross, as
to expose himself to frequent charges of disloyalty by heated
partizans. And when a minister of the Gospel, in a Western city, was
deprived of his church, and put under sentence of banishment by a
Provost Marshal-his church being placed under the control of three
individuals, charged by the Marshal to employ a minister of more <hi rend="italic">loyal</hi> views; Mr. Lincoln, after a careful inquiry
into the case, and on ascertaining that the banished man was
chargeable with the violation of no law, civil or military, promptly
restored him to all his rights-stating, in his quaint manner, a most
important principle: " The State must not undertake to run the "
churches."</p>
               <p>Mr. Lincoln was a true patriot. Mistakes he doubtless committed. It
would have been almost miraculous, if he had not. With little previous
experience, he was called to the discharge of the arduous duties of
the highest office in the nation, in the most trying circumstances
conceivable. The ship of State seemed just ready to founder; and a war
of fearful proportions met him at the very threshold. Few men have
been called to face difficulties so appalling. Very few could have
been as calm and undaunted. Instead of judging him harshly for
mistakes committed, we may well wonder that he did not commit more and
greater. The fact, that at the end of four years, he commanded the
confi-
<pb n="7" facs="rice7.jpg"/>
dence of the nation to so great extent, that they could find no other
man to whom they were so willing to entrust the management of their
affairs, whilst the great conflict was yet raging, is a high testimony
to his patriotism. However widely men may differ (as the best men will
differ), respecting the leading measures of his administration, few, I
am persuaded, will doubt that his single aim was to promote the true
interests of the country.</p>
               <p>I must not omit to record my admiration of his generous treatment
of those who had taken up arms against the Government. He manifested
no revengeful spirit, but seemed anxious to restore to the country a
true and lasting Union.</p>
               <p>That an attempt should have been made to assassinate such a man,
presents a fearful view of human depravity. That the diabolical
attempt was allowed to be successful, presents a profound mystery in
Divine Providence, " Be "still, and know that I am God."</p>
               <p/>
               <p>II.  Be still, and know that He is God, and therefore will be
obeyed and honored. He will be "exalted in the earth."</p>
               <p>Both in his word and by his providence God speaks to men in two
ways, and addresses to them two classes of motives. In his word we
read, on the one hand, invitations, promises, even entreaties; on the
other, we find solemn warnings and threats of vengeance upon the
rebellious and obdurate. In his providence we have, on the one hand,
goodness, pouring into our laps his rich and varied gifts, thus
appealing to gratitude, and leading to repentance; and, on the other,
we have severity, appealing powerfully to fear, and warning us to flee
from the wrath to come. "Behold," saith Paul, "the goodness and
severity of God." 
<pb n="8" facs="rice8.jpg"/>
"I will sing," says the Psalmist, " of mercy and of judgment."</p>
               <p>The judgments of God are of two kinds, designed to accomplish two
very different ends. There are <hi rend="italic">destructive</hi>
judgments-designed to remove the incorrigibly wicked out of the way,
and to hold them up a beacon to others. Thus, Korah, Dathan and Abiram
were swallowed up by the miraculous opening of the earth under their
feet. Thus the ten tribes of Israel, having apostatized from God, were
as a people swept from the earth. Thus Babylon was swept as with the
besom of destruction. Thus, every nation that will not honor God,
shall perish.</p>
               <p>There are <hi rend="italic">corrective</hi> or <hi rend="italic">reformatory</hi> judgments, designed to bring individuals
or nations to repentance and reformation.  "Whom the Lord loveth he
chasteneth." Thus, speaking of the sufferings of the children of
Israel for their apostacy, God said, "I will go and return to my
place, till "they acknowledge their offence, and seek my face: in
"their affliction they will seek me early." The seventy years of
captivity in Babylon came as a Divine judgment upon the Jewish Church
and nation; but it was reformatory, not destructive. It was the
purpose of God, after they had been brought to confess and forsake
their wickedness, to restore them, a purified people, that they might
again be "the light of the world."</p>
               <p>And we are permitted to rejoice, not only that mercy mingles with
such judgments, but that it abounds over them. Two facts are of
special interest to us. The first is, that God never sends His
judgments upon a people for sins <hi rend="italic">after</hi> they have
confessed and abandoned them. The second is, that they are removed, so
soon as reformation is effected. By the prophet Jeremiah he speaks
thus: "At "'what instant I shall speak concerning a nation, and con-
<pb n="9" facs="rice9.jpg"/>
"cerning a kingdom, to pluck up and to pull down, and to "destroy it,
if that nation against whom I have pronounced "turn from their sin, I
will repent of the evil that I thought "to do unto them." And of the
Jewish nation it is written: "When they in their trouble did turn unto
the Lord " God of Israel, and sought him, he was found of them."
Beautifully is this truth set forth in the parable of the Prodigal. He
came to himself and said, " I will arise and go " to my father." His
father saw him a great way off, and ran and fell upon his neck, and
kissed him. So readily does God meet the first movement in individuals
and nations toward himself. And so, as the Apostle James has it, Mercy
rejoiceth against judgment."</p>
               <p>But in whatever way God speaks to men, whether to individuals or to
nations, whether by mercies or by judgments, His aim is to bring them
to acknowledge His authority, to embrace the Gospel of Christ, to obey
His laws, to exalt him in the earth.</p>
               <p/>
               <p>III.-Be still, and know that He is God-the only guide, supporter
and protector of individuals, families, churches, and nations. He will
have men not only acknowledge their obligation to obey Him, but their
entire dependence upon Him. Whilst his Gospel is received, and his law
obeyed, His blessing must be sought, and His goodness gratefully
acknowledged. To bring individuals and nations to feel and acknowledge
their dependence, is one aim of his dealings with them. "When He slew
them," says the Psalmist, "then sought they Him; and they returned and
"inquired early after God; and they remembered that God "was their
rock, and the high God their Redeemer." The King of Babylon disdained,
though often warned, to acknowledge his dependence on God, and,
walking in his
<pb n="10" facs="rice10.jpg"/>
palace, viewing the wealth, the power and the splendor with which, as
the greatest monarch on earth, he was surrounded, he soliloquised
thus: " Is not this great Babylon, that I have built for the house of
the kingdom, by the might of my power, and for the honor of my
majesty?" In an instant, "while the word was in the king's mouth,
there fell a voice from Heaven, saying, 0, King Nebuchadnezzar, to
thee it is spoken: the kingdom is departed from thee." His reason
fled; he became a miserable idiot or a raving maniac, and was driven
to dwell with the beasts of the field. He was effectually humbled,
when his understanding returned to him, and he proclaimed to the
world: "Now, I, Nebuchadnezzar, praise, and extol, and honor the King
of Heaven, all whose works are truth, and his ways judgment; and those
that walk in pride he is able to abase."</p>
               <p>This same lesson will God, sooner or later, teach every man and
every nation; and the sooner an afflicted people learn it, the sooner
will they, like the King of Babylon, bless God for the removal of His
judgments, and for the restoration of His favor. On this day of
mourning, God is teaching us this lesson. He has removed from us the
man in whom so much confidence was reposed, and is impressing on us
our dependence on Him alone.</p>
               <p/>
               <p>IV.-Be still, and know that He is God; and, therefore, His ways are
not to be fully comprehended, nor yet called in question. God is an
infinite Spirit; and it is inconceivable that the purposes of the
infinite Mind should be comprehended by finite minds. From the
necessities of the case, therefore, we must be compassed about on
every side with providential mysteries. But God will teach us to trust
him as implicitly, when " His judgments are a great deep," as when
all, is clear as light. "For," saith he, "My
<pb n="11" facs="rice11.jpg"/>
thoughts are not your thoughts, neither are your ways my ways, saith
the Lord. For as the heavens are higher than the earth, so are my ways
higher than your ways, and my thoughts than your thoughts." The
inspired Paul was filled with awe, as he contemplated God's dealings
with his chosen people, as he foresaw their approaching dispersion
among all nations, and their wanderings in spiritual darkness through
many centuries; and he exclaimed: " 0, the depth of the riches both of
the knowledge and wisdom of God! how unsearchable are His ways, and
His judgments past finding out!"</p>
               <p>We never honor God more than when we follow him with implicit
confidence, when we cannot see our way, and believe him just, and
good, and wise, when his dealings with us are enveloped in painful
mystery. "Behold," says Job, " He taketh away, who can hinder Him? Who
will "say unto Him, what doest thou?," "I was dumb," says "the
Psalmist, " I opened not my mouth because thou "didst it."</p>
               <p>Such are the great principles in the light of which we must seek to
interpret the providences of God towards ourselves, and towards this
nation. What improvement do these principles enable us to make of the
awful dispensation we are this day contemplating?</p>
               <p/>
               <p>1. Deep and tender sympathy with the smitten family; grief on
account of a calamity which is both national and individual;
indignation against the perpetrators of the horrid act; these are
feelings which arise spontaneously in the heart, and grow in intensity
as we think over all the aggravating circumstances. Nor are such
feelings, within proper bounds, to be condemned. When Abner fell by
the murderous hand of Joab, David said to the people, " Rend
<pb n="12" facs="rice12.jpg"/>
"your clothes, and gird you, with sackcloth, and mourn "before Abner;"
and David himself followed the bier to the grave, weeping. And he said
to his servants, " Know "ye not that there is a prince and a great man
fallen this "day in Israel?" And when Josiah, the pious king of Judah,
fell in battle, " Jeremiah lamented for Josiah, and "all the singing
men and singing women spake of Josiah "in their lamentations to this
day, and made them an "ordinance in Israel."</p>
               <p>Similar feelings swell the bosoms of the people of this nation
to-day. We feel that the nation has suffered an affliction, the extent
of which we cannot yet foresee. We feel more than this-that each
individual is afflicted; for we are in feeling and interest fully
identified with our beloved country. In its bereavement we are
bereaved, in its sorrows we sorrow. Never before has this country
known such a day of sorrow as this. The symbols of grief meet our eye
in every direction, and are visible over the whole land. All
distinctions are, for the time, forgotten in the common sorrow and
alarm.</p>
               <p/>
               <p>2. Yet let us not forget, in the gush of natural feeling, that the
awful voice of God is to be heard in this event, and that he aims to
impress great truths of his word deeply and indelibly upon our
minds. The prayer of Job is peculiarly appropriate now: "Do not
condemn me; show me wherefore thou contendest with me."</p>
               <p>We know that all sin is offensive and dishonoring to God, and is,
therefore, calculated to bring his displeasure upon men ; but to
determine for what particular sins a nation is visited with judgments,
is not easy, nor is it wise to attempt it. One thing on this point we
do know:</p>
               <p/>
               <p>That this, calamity has not come upon the nation for sins
<pb n="13" facs="rice13.jpg"/>
                  <hi rend="italic">confessed and forsaken</hi>. We have already shown
that God never visits a people with judgments for sins, after those
sins have been abandoned.</p>
               <p>The last four trying years have wrought great changes, and we hope
the severe discipline has not been wholly lost upon us. Slavery, the
bone of contention, the gigantic evil which has been the occasion of
the war, has been swept away. Even before the struggle began, the
nation, by a decisive vote, had gone the full extent of its
constitutional power in determining that it should be confined within
its then present limits. And since then the nation has fully sustained
its President in striking a death blow at it. Nor have the people been
indifferent to the wants and sufferings of the thousands so suddenly
emancipated. That the South has brought upon itself fearful sufferings
by attempting to break up our noble Union for the purpose of
perpetuating and extending a terrible evil, of which they were bound
to have sought the entire removal, is clear enough. But in seeking to
understand the meaning of God's dealings with <hi rend="italic">the
nation,</hi>, especially the present sore visitation, we must look, I
cannot but think, at the sins not yet abandoned, and at lessons not
yet well learned.</p>
               <p>In all war, especially civil war, there is great sin committed and
there is always danger of incuring the displeasure of God. I do not
doubt that such has been the case in our terrible conflict. And yet
there are some things in connection with this war, which distinguish
it happily from many others. I refer to the great pains taken and
labor bestowed, both for the physical comfort and the spiritual
interests of the soldiers. The Sanitary and the Christian Commissions
go far to relieve some of the darker features of war; and the many
conversions reported in the army have caused joy amongst the angels of
God.</p>
               <pb n="14" facs="rice14.jpg"/>
               <p>Yet, when we have said all that truth will permit us to say of a
favorable character, the painful and alarming truth remains, that God
still has a controversy with the nation. Nor can we wonder at this, if
we venture to take even a partial view of the moral condition of the
country. There are sins yet to be repented of--lessons yet to learn,
that God may be exalted in the land. May he enable us to discover
those sins, and abandon them, and to learn those lessons of wisdom.</p>
               <p>It required a training of forty years in the wilderness to prepare
the Jews to become a free and prosperous nation. During that period of
training, stroke after stroke fell upon them, until all, save two of
those over twenty years of age when they left Egypt, had died. And
over and over again had they, in the course of their history, to be
taught the same lessons. Few families enjoy unmixed prosperity for any
great length of time; and nations, even more than families, require
chastisements, lest pride and wickedness destroy them.</p>
               <p>The foundations of this nation were laid in sufferings. Our fathers
were called to learn wisdom in the severe school of affliction. But we
became a great, wealthy, corrupt nation forgetful of the author of our
greatness; and now that voice of warning has come to us-"Be still, and
know that I am God."</p>
               <p>Great sorrow has come upon us during the last four weary years; may
we not hope that we have not suffered in vain? God could have made the
first battle decisive, or brought the war to a termination in a
month. He did not do so; not because he delights in the sufferings of
men, but because we had not learned those lessons so essential to the
future progress of the nation.</p>
               <p>The war is now, we trust, substantially over; the authority
<pb n="15" facs="rice15.jpg"/>
of the Government is supreme over nearly all our territory. But in the
midst of our rejoicings at the prospect of the unity and peace of the
nation, a fearful stroke, as from heaven, fills our minds with grief
and alarm. By that stroke the man is taken from us, who had so
completely possessed himself of the confidence and love of the
people. He is removed just when he was most needed-when all his
experience, and skill, and influence were required to adjust those
delicate and difficult questions that must now arise.</p>
               <p>Why is this?" Be still, and know that I am God." Are we not, in a
peculiar sense, in this crisis of our affairs, thrown upon God for
guidance and help? And can we not trust him? He has brought us through
the darkness and alarm of the past, when men's hearts were failing
them for fear and for looking after those things which seemed
concerning, when anarchy stared us in the face; when we feared, that
Republican government was a failure-that there was not yet sound
morals enough to sustain it. I confess I have, within these four
years, thought, with more pain than pleasure, of a lecture I once
published on the mission of the United States. With intense interest,
I have watched for the signs of moral and religious improvement in the
church and the country. I hope a brighter day is dawning; yet, I fear,
as well as hope.</p>
               <p>May not this severe stroke have in it something of hope? May it
not, by the very perils in which it involves us, lead us to look up
for aid? May it not make a deep and salutary impression upon the whole
people? If it should, then, indeed, the future will be brighter.</p>
               <p>Let us adopt the language of this 46th Psalm and say- "God is our
refuge and strength, a very present help in "trouble. Therefore will
we not fear, though the earth be "removed,  and though the mountains
be carried into the
<pb n="16" facs="rice16.jpg"/>
"midst of the sea; though the waters thereof roar and be "troubled;
though the mountains shake with the swelling "thereof."</p>
               <p>The path of duty and of safety is plain. Let the people gather
around the man who now fills the place so sadly vacated, as I rejoice
to see a general disposition to do, and sustain him by their prayers,
as well as by other means. If ever a man needed the prayers of a
people, he needs them now. Called so unexpectedly, and with so little
preparation, to discharge the functions of such an office, in such a
crisis, so surrounded with difficulties and perils, what other than
Divine guidance and support can enable him to go forward with safety
to himself, and to the vast interests in trusted to him? Our own
dearest interests, and the interests of unborn generations, are
involved in the questions now to be settled, in the work now to be
done. If we shall heed the voice that now speaks to us so solemnly,
and turn to God in obedience and in supplication, we shall pass safely
through this crisis; the nation, made wiser and purer by means of its
trials, will again go forth on its great mission, shedding its clear
light upon the nations of the earth. And then we shall give to God all
the glory, and He will be exalted in the earth.</p>
               <p>Finally, let us not forget that religion is, in its very nature, an
individual matter. God is speaking, not to masses of people, but to
each individual He is warning all to become reconciled to Him, and
calling His children nearer to Him. How uncertain a thing is life, and
how comparatively worthless wealth, office, honor, and all that this
world can offer us! In the twinkling of an eye, we may be called to
part with it all. " One thing is needful." Let us seek it earnestly,
and without delay.</p>
            </div2>
         </div1>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>