<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader><fileDesc>
         <titleStmt n="The Assassinated President">
            <title>The Assassinated President</title>
            <author>Seiss, Joseph A.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Compiled and edited by</resp>
               <name>Beck
Center</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent/>
         <publicationStmt><publisher>Lewis H. Beck Center</publisher><pubPlace>Emory University</pubPlace><address>
               <addrLine>Atlanta,
Georgia</addrLine>
            </address><availability>
               <p>1996 Emory
University. Permission is  granted to download, transmit, or otherwise
reproduce,  distribute or display the contributions to the work
claimed by Emory University for non-profit educational  purposes,
provided this header is included in its entirety.   For inquiries
about commercial uses, contact the Director,  Pitts Theology Library,
Emory University, Atlanta, Georgia 30322</p>
            </availability><date>1999</date></publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Lincoln
Sermons Project</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Seiss, Joseph
A. The Assassinated President, or the Day of National Mourning for
Abraham Lincoln, at St. John's (Lutheran) Church, Philadelphia, June
1st, 1865. For Sale at No. 42 North Ninth Street,
Philadelphia. 1865.</bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc><encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This text derives from the Special Collections  of
Pitts Theology Library, Emory University, and is produced in
collaboration with the Lewis H. Beck Center a, the Emory  Preservation
Office, and Pitts Theology Library.</p>
            <p>TRANSCRIBER: Lewis H. Beck Center and Emory University 
Preservation Office.</p>
            <p>PRODUCER:  BookLab, Inc., 1606 Headway Circle, 
Suite 100, Austin, TX 78754</p>
            <p>CAPTURE DEVICE: XEROX DocuImage 620S flatbed scanner</p>
            <p>CAPTURE DETAILS: Scanner software: XEROX ScanTool 
version 4.2.3; no gamma correction; images are all bitonal.</p>
            <p>CHANGE HISTORY: Using the Adobe Photoshop Batch Processor, 
we interpolated  the original TIFF files to 8-bit grays, 
and altered the resolution to 144 dpi, producing screen 
images twice the original size.  We then saved them in 
JPEG format.  We produced GIF thumbnails from the JPEG files.</p>
            <p>RESOLUTION: 600 ppi</p>
            <p>COMPRESSION: Resolution 144 per inch with Constrain 
Properties to 72 per inch.</p>
            <p>SOURCE: Original documents.</p>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc><revisionDesc><change><name>Stewart Varner</name> transformed this document from p4 to p5 on <date when="2010-03-22">March 22, 2010</date></change><change xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><date>1999</date><label>Staff</label><name>Scott
Ellis</name>SGML tags inserted in
compliance with TEI guidelines using TEILITE</change></revisionDesc></teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div1 xml:id="seiss.001" n="The Assassinated President" type="text">
            <head>
               <bibl> 
                  <title>The Assassinated President</title> 
                  <date>June 1st,
1865</date> 
                  <pubPlace>St. John's (Lutheran) Church,
Philadelphia</pubPlace> 
                  <author>Seiss, Joseph A.</author> 
                  
                     <pubPlace>Philadelphia</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>[N/A]</publisher>
                     <date>1865</date>
                   
               <idno type="ark">http://pid.emory.edu/ark:/25593/15r1s</idno></bibl> 
            </head>
            <pb facs="seiss1.jpg"/>
            <p>The Assassinated President,</p>
            <p>OR THE</p>
            <p>DAY OF NATIONAL</p>
            <p>FOR</p>
            <p>ABRAHAM LINCOLN,</p>
            <p>AT</p>
            <p>ST. JOHN'S (LUTHERAN) CHURCH, PHILADELPHIA,</p>
            <p>JUNE <hi rend="italic">1ST</hi>, 1865.</p>
            <p>THE PASTOR</p>
            <p>JOSEPH A. SEISS, D.D.</p>
            <p>OFFICIATING.</p>
            <p>FOR SALE AT</p>
            <p>No. 42 NORTH NINTH STREET,</p>
            <p>PHILADELPHIA.</p>
            <p>1865.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="seiss2.jpg"/>
***NOTE: at this corresponding spot in the file lincoln/branches/xml-p4/seiss.xml, instead of "seiss2," you'll see "seiss1." I assumed that this was an error in the other document and went with seiss2 here, because the previous one is also seiss1 and the subsequent one is seiss3. Could you double check?
            <lg type="stanza">
               <l>"The tyrannous and bloody act is done;</l>
               <l>The most arch
deed of piteous massacre,</l>
               <l>That ever yet this land was guilty
of."</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="3" facs="seiss3.jpg"/>
            <div2 xml:id="seiss.002" n="I. THE DEVOTIONAL EXERCISES." type="service">
               <head>I. THE DEVOTIONAL EXERCISES.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <p>INTROIT.-"Let the words of my mouth, and the meditation
of my heart, be acceptable in thy sight, 0 Lord, my Strength and my
Redeemer."</p>
                  <p>Reading of the Ten Commandments, Ex. 20: 1-17.</p>
               </epigraph>
               <p>THE CONFESSION OF SINS.</p>
               <p>ALMIGHTY and most holy Lord and God, who dost command us to humble
ourselves under thy mighty hand, that thou mayest exalt us in due
time; in humility of spirit we confess before thee, in this our
bereavement and affliction, how deeply, as a nation, we have deserved
thy wrath. We acknowledge thy righteousness in the sorrowful
visitation which has come upon us, and bow to thy holy will in
submission and self-abasement. Manifold are our transgressions, and
the more sinful because of the many and great mercies which thou hast
bestowed upon us. We have sinned, in pride and living to ourselves, in
covetousness and worldliness of mind, in self-sufficiency and too much
trusting in man instead of thee. 
<pb n="4" facs="seiss4.jpg"/>
Profaneness of speech, violation and disregard of thy holy day,
neglect of thy worship, unbelief and contempt of thy word,
unfaithfulness to public trusts, dishonesties in worldly business, and
above all, receiving in vain thy wonderful grace in the Gospel of our
Lord Jesus Christ, all cry out for thy indignation and wrath. It is
because thy compassions have not failed, that we have not been
consumed. We adore the riches of thy forbearance and long-suffering;
and beseech thee, 0 Lord, to turn the hearts of this people to
repentance and supplication, that still thou mayest have compassion
upon us; not weighing our merits, but pardoning our offences. For thy
Son, our Lord Jesus Christ's sake, forgive us all that is past, and
grant that ever hereafter we may all serve and please thee in newness
of life, to the honor and glory of thy name, through him who liveth
and reigneth with thee and the Holy Ghost, ever one God, world without
end. Amen.</p>
               <p>HYMN.</p>
               <lg type="stanza">
                  <l>"Great Maker of unnumbered worlds,</l>
                  <l>And whom unnumbered
worlds adore,</l>
                  <l>Whose goodness all thy creatures share,</l>
                  <l>While nature trembles at thy power," &amp;c.</l>
               </lg>
               <p>SCRIPTURE LESSONS.-Isaiah 59, and Luke 6: 20-38.</p>
               <pb n="5" facs="seiss5.jpg"/>
               <p>THE GENERAL PRAYER.</p>
               <p>Almighty and most merciful God, we lift our hearts to thee, the
hearer of prayer, from whom alone cometh our help. We adore thee as
the great Parent of the Universe, from whom all things proceed, and on
whom all creatures depend. Thou art worthy of all honor, gratitude,
affection, and obedience. Thou art the blessed and only Potentate, the
King of kings and Lord of lords. Thou alone hast immortality. With
thee are the issues of life and of death. Thou doest after the
counsels of thine own will among the angels in heaven and in the
affairs of men. We, thine unworthy servants, desire to recognize thy
hand in all things, and to be duly grateful to thee for thy many and
great mercies. We bless thee for our creation, preservation, and all
the comforts and privileges of this life. As citizens of a country
which thou hast highly favored, as well as sorely chastised, we adore
thee for what thou hast done for us, and humbly submit ourselves to
thy holy governance. We adore thee for all the way which thou hast led
us, in darkness and in light, in defeats and in victories, in days of
discouragements and days of rejoicing, and for. all the lessons which
thou art in all addressing to us. We bless thee for the steadfast
devotion and obedience of the people to the Govern-
<pb n="6" facs="seiss6.jpg"/>
ment, under their many burdens during these years of trial. We thank
thee that when dangerous conspiracies arose, thou didst bring them to
nought. We thank thee that no invasions of loyal territory have been
permitted to prosper; and that, in so large a part of the land, there
have been preserved to us tranquillity and prosperity, abundance of
the fruits of the ground, and the undisturbed enjoyment of the means
of grace. We thank thee for the devotion and bravery and patience and
faithfulness of the national forces, on land and water, through whose
skill and courage thou hast wrought such great things for us;
beseeching thee to return them to their homes in safety, to give them
all happiness in their families, to fill their hearts with love to
thee, and to bring them finally to the blessedness of thy kingdom. And
we pray thee so to impress the hearts of all the nation with a just
sense of thy providence, goodness, and mercy in the years just passed,
and in our present deliverance and prospects, that all may most
thankfully acknowledge their debt of love and praise, and serve thee
henceforth in humble obedience to thy word.</p>
               <p>And as thou hast seen fit, O thou mighty Ruler of the
world, in thine all-wise administrations, to permit us to be deprived
of the presence and further counsels of our late Chief Magistrate, and
hast so deeply grieved the hearts of the people, turning
<pb n="7" facs="seiss7.jpg"/>
our songs into mourning and our joy into sorrow; we beseech thee to
have mercy upon us in this our calamity, and to overrule it to the
furtherance of our humility and peace, and to thine everlasting
glory. Give unto us the gracious aid of thy Holy Spirit, that we may
rightly learn thy will, and profit by all thy dealings with us. Enable
us to have a right estimate of the good example and timely services
vouchsafed to us in the life of him whom thou hast taken, and to be
governed aright in all our feelings and meditations concerning the
same. We thank thee for the great grace and faithfulness thou gavest
him in his high office, and for the success with which thou hast
favored his administrations to the preservation of our national unity
and the enlargement of human freedom, and beseech thee to help us to
appreciate the high trusts which thou hast by him re-given to our
keeping. Have compassion upon his sorrowing family and relatives, whom
thou hast called to endure this sore bereavement. Cause their hearts
to be lifted toward thy grace for support and consolation. Mingle the
ministrations of thy love with the bitterness of their cup. Grant
them, in this cloud of darkness, to see and rejoice in the light of
life; and lead them by thy heavenly grace to life everlasting.</p>
               <p>And for him who, by this mysterious providence, is now
called to assume the highest office in the na-
<pb n="8" facs="seiss8.jpg"/>
tion, we entreat thy protection, support, and guidance. Teach him
where to look for all he needs under the heavy duties which have come
upon him, and give him grace so to administer the Government after the
good example which has been set before him, that by wisdom and
moderation, by firmness and clemency, in the due vindication of
justice and remembrance of mercy, the laws may be truly honored, the
wounds of the nation healed, and peace and unity restored to the land
for all generations.</p>
               <p>We implore thy blessing upon our entire country, and upon
all its inhabitants. Have compassion, 0 Lord, upon those regions which
war has desolated, and in which the weapons of rebellion were
lifted. Restore to them thy gracious favor. May the waste places be
made to bloom again. Give to the erring and the vanquished the spirit
of loyal submission to the rightful authority of the nation. Heal the
wounds that have been made in their homes and neighborhoods, in their
peace and prosperity. Take away from them and from us all bitterness,
wrath, and anger, and make us all kind one toward another. Make us
again one people, not only by union under the same laws, but in
affectionate participation in the same national privileges; serving
together in the one faith of thy holy word, working together for the
advancement of the one glorious kingdom of righteousness and peace,
and inheritors together of eternal life,
<pb n="9" facs="seiss9.jpg"/>
through the one sacrifice and mediation of our Lord and Saviour Jesus
Christ.</p>
               <p>Let it please thee, also, to help and bless all sorts and
conditions of men, making thy ways known unto them, and saving them
from their sins. Endow all rulers and magistrates with thy grace, and
fill them with the spirit of wisdom and justice. Show thy goodness to
the sorrowing and afflicted, and give deliverance to the enslaved and
oppressed. Remember thy Church in tender mercy, and refresh and
prosper it with the continual dew of thy heavenly blessing. Send down
upon all ministers of the Gospel, and upon all thy people, the needful
Spirit of thy grace. Cause the number of thy saints to be multiplied
in all the earth; and let thy blessed kingdom speedily come, and thy
holy will be done on earth as it is in heaven.</p>
               <p>Hear us, most gracious Lord and God, and despise not these our
unworthy services, neither deny us our requests, which we present
before thy Divine Majesty in the name of Jesus Christ, our Mediator
and Redeemer, to whom, with thee, and the Holy Ghost, be all honor and
glory, world without end.</p>
               <p>AMEN.</p>
               <pb n="10" facs="seiss10.jpg"/>
               <p>SECOND
HYMN.</p>
               <lg type="stanza">
                  <l>"God moves in a mysterious
way,</l>
                  <l>His wonders to perform;</l>
                  <l>He plants his footsteps in the
sea,</l>
                  <l>And rides upon the storm," &amp;c.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb n="11" facs="seiss11.jpg"/>
            </div2>
            <div2 xml:id="seiss.003" n="II. THE DISCOURSE." type="sermon">
               <head>II. THE DISCOURSE.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <p>TEXT.-" And Moses was an hundred and twenty years
old when he died: his eye was not dim, nor his natural force
abated. And the children of Israel wept for Moses in the plains of
Moab thirty days." <hi rend="italic">Deut. 33: 7, 8.</hi>
                  </p>
               </epigraph>
               <p>MANY-SIDED, and full of light, are even the simplest records of the
word of God. This little historic fragment is rich in fruitful themes
for solemn meditation. Even in the line of thinking to which the
appointment of this day specially calls us, there are sundry very
noteworthy suggestions.</p>
               <p>We here find that the most eminent servants of God, as well
as other people, are subject to the dominion of death.</p>
               <p>We here find that men high in office and favor, are
sometimes suddenly taken away in the fulness of their strength, in the
midst of their labors and usefulness, just when their presence seems
most indispensable, and on the very eve of the consummation of their
most earnest endeavors.</p>
               <p>We here find that from remote antiquity, from
<pb n="12" facs="seiss12.jpg"/>
some motive of religion, or praiseworthy impulse of justice,
gratitude, or admiration, it has been the custom of good people to
take special notice of the deaths of distinguished public servants, to
express by unwonted tokens the sense of loss sustained by their
removal, and to give befitting indications of appreciation of their
qualities and worth on the part of their survivors.</p>
               <p>But I do not propose to dwell on these topics. I mention
them, as I use the text itself, not for discussion, but chiefly as a
preface and starting-point for other observations. The mention of
Moses, the close of his career, and the mourning of the people for
him, calls up the character and mission of Moses. These, connected
with the purposes for which we are this day in the sanctuary,
naturally suggest the comparison of this illustrious personage with
him over the recent, sudden, and melancholy termination of whose life
the nation mourns, and the civilized world is moved.</p>
               <p>Who Moses was needs scarcely to be stated. His history is
written in the best known and most sacred books of nearly all nations,
and is familiar to the children of almost every home. His origin among
a people who labored in the brickyards and served the Egyptians, his
inheritance of hardships deserved neither by him nor his parents, and
his providential preservation in early infancy, are things which we
<pb n="13" facs="seiss13.jpg"/>
learned in the first lessons of our childhood. You remember how he was
committed to his mother to be nursed and reared for Pharaoh's
daughter, whose maids had found him in the river. You know from whose
lips he was taught in the traditions and religion of his people, and
whence he drank in those sentiments of justice, faith in God, sympathy
with the oppressed, and love of freedom and equal rights, which
manifested themselves so strikingly in his early manhood, and became
the guiding-star of his life and greatness. You do not need to be told
what office it was that he was called to fill, and how he was
gradually schooled for it by his training in Egyptian learning, by his
military experiences in an expedition against the depredatory tribes
of Ethiopia, in his voluntary exile from the place of his birth, in
his servitude and quiet meditations as keeper of Jethro's flocks, and
in his sharp and prolonged contest with the Magicians of Pharaoh's
court. Nor will it ever be forgotten how he humbled the pride of them
that withstood him, and gathered to himself the confidence of the
people, and submitted himself to the promptings of his conscience, and
enraged Egypt's haughty aristocrats with his proposals and demands in
behalf of the oppressed, and in the face of Egypt's armies led out the
enslaved from the house of bondage, and saw the hosts of Israel's
oppressors overwhelmed under
<pb n="14" facs="seiss14.jpg"/>
the waving of his staff, and silenced the murmurs of the rebellious in
his own camp, and rewrote and reasserted the great laws of right,
loyalty, and justice, and forced his way through lands which he had
been forbidden to pass, and was tried by the treacherous schemes of
Balak and Baalam, and vanquished the tribes who took up arms against
his people, and conducted Israel through the wilderness to the very
borders of the land of rest, and then suddenly ended his career, as he
had been forewarned, amid the tears and lamentations of those whom he
had delivered and led.</p>
               <p>And how closely all this resembles the story of his life,
for whom the national mourning has been appointed, scarcely requires
to be pointed out. If Moses was of humble parentage, so was he. His
father was a poor Kentuckian, who could neither read nor write; and
his mother was a lowly woman, whose highest literary attainment was
ability to read her Bible. If Moses derived from his mother those
sentiments and feelings which formed the basis of his exalted
character and success, the same may be said of the late
President. Though uneducated, his mother was a talented woman, of
sound practical wisdom, earnest piety, and great devotion to her son
and to her influence and teachings, many of the traits which
distinguished his life are traced by his biographers. A child of
poverty and hardships, he
<pb n="15" facs="seiss15.jpg"/>
was early expatriated from the place of his birth, transferred to the
wilderness, subsisted on scanty fare, and made to serve
strangers. Though not "learned in all the wisdom of the Egyptians,"
and obliged to borrow the books from which he obtained the first
rudiments of his literary knowledge, he was thoroughly educated in the
school of humble life, and familiarized with all its necessities and
trials, which, in his case, as in that of Moses, was the most valuable
part of his education. He, too, was a captain and soldier in a
campaign against tribes of marauding savages. He, too, found it a
great turning point in his life, when, in answer to the generous
impulses of his heart, he volunteered to stand between an innocent
sufferer and his accusers, and rescued him from a death which he had
not merited. And if the controlling sympathies of Moses ran with the
injured, the wronged, and the enslaved, such was exactly the temper of
Abraham Lincoln, who, also, at an early period, gave decisive evidence
of his utter contempt for the preferments and luxuries of enslaving
power. He, too, was born to figure in a great crisis in the affairs of
his country, and remarkably called to execute a mission as pregnant
with results as it was feeble in friends, resources, and promises of
success. Even the complaint which the Jewish leader uttered with
reference to the apparent inadequacy of the instrument to the end to
be ac-
<pb n="16" facs="seiss16.jpg"/>
complished, had its correspondence in him for whom we this day
mourn. "Who am I," said he, "that I should go unto Pharoah, and that I
should bring forth the children of Israel out of Egypt"-" 0 my Lord, I
am not eloquent." (Ex. 3: 11; 4: 10.)</p>
               <p>And that great debate, of
which all the people of Illinois were the witnesses, and in which all
sections of the country were unwontedly interested; in which he was
resisted by perhaps the most formidable champion of the political
arena then living; in which all the powers of extraordinary genius,
adroitness, and forensic skill were brought to bear against him; and
which first fully laid open the question of freedom and slavery which
the God of battles has since decided in his favor;--what was it but a
re-enactment upon another theatre, and in another form, of that
contest between the shepherd of Midian and the Magicians of Egypt?
Indeed, contemplated from almost any point, the considerate mind will
be at no loss to trace resemblances between his character and career
and that of the matchless man whom the Scriptures set before us as the
great hero of Israel's deliverance.</p>
               <p>Nor were the times and
circumstances in which the two were called to operate, very
dissimilar. By some strange forgetfulness of acknowledged rights and
covenants, there had been a power put forth in Egypt, by which the
multiplied posterity of Jacob
<pb n="17" facs="seiss17.jpg"/>
were divested of their freedom, and subjected to rigorous taskmasters,
"who made their lives bitter with hard bondage, in mortar and in
brick, and in all manner of service in the field." (Ex. 1: 8-14.)</p>
               <p>And the children of Israel sighed by reason of the bondage,
and they cried, and their cry came up unto God. And God heard their
groaning. And God looked upon the children of Israel, and God had
respect unto them." (Ex. 2: 23-25.) In other words, the time had come,
in the decrees of Heaven, when the heavy yoke was to be broken, the
pride of the oppressor humbled, and these suffering tribes set
free.</p>
               <p>So, on this continent, a new power in the world had risen
up, in the Constitution of which, owing to whatever causes, or
modified by whatever apologies, contrary to the convictions and
desires of its framers, elements of oppression and undoubted wrong had
been embodied and legalized, by which millions of human beings,
brought hither in their misfortunes, were doomed to abject and
unqualified servitude; a servitude which, however mild, gentle, and
benficent in some cases and relations, or excusable on the part of
those who had no share in producing it, did embrace, in its very
nature, a violation of the common rights of man, and was everywhere
attended more or less with hardships and horrors, for which the
inexorable requirements of justice demanded that a day of retributive
revolution should come. To such 
<pb n="18" facs="seiss18.jpg"/>
a pass had things been carried, that, in some sections of the land,
there was not a day in which human souls were not bought and
transported as common chattels, and families severed without
compunctions, and nameless crimes perpetrated without the possibility
of redress; whilst the whole population of all the States was put
under requirements to aid in holding tight the bonds of the
unoffending, and in remanding to their toils and miseries such as had
sufficient human feeling left to seek for freedom by their
flight. What the founders of our institutions regarded and lamented as
a wrong to the bondman and an evil to the state, had come to be
accepted and defended as the sublimest beneficence, the foundation of
liberties, and the proper basis of republican government; nay, as the
very ordination of Almighty Goodness, to touch or question which was
considered treason to the country and sin against God. The enlargement
and consolidation of enslaving power had come to be the engrossing
object of national legislation, and the making firm of slave bonds the
great test of patriotism. The press, the rostrum, and the pulpit, were
being largely subsidized to the same interest; and the free speech of
men who failed in the pronunciation of its Shiboleth, in nearly every
section of the country, was put under ban, and held obnoxious to all
the penalties of this world and of that which is to come. Long had,
the nation sub-
<pb n="19" facs="seiss19.jpg"/>
mitted and yielded to the ever-multiplying demands of the "peculiar
institution," until the God of justice said, "<hi rend="italic">It is
too much</hi>," and gave commission to this angels to strike it down,
yea, and to sweep it from the earth.</p>
               <p>While Egypt was busy riveting the fetters tighter and
tighter upon Israel, little did she dream that, within her own
borders, there was a young mind maturing, who, with no ally but God,
and no supports but the righteousness of his cause, was presently to
scatter all her infamous legislation to the winds. Little did she
think, that, from among the poor and despised whom her tyranny was
oppressing, there was one gradually being prepared, upon whose plain
unvarnished words should follow consternating judgments, before which
the pride of her dominion was to be laid level with the dust. And
little did she imagine how, from the wilds of Midian, there
was. presently to come a sun-browned shepherd, by whose calm
administrations all her great houses were to be filled with mourning,
stript of their illgot treasures, and deprived forever of the
unrequited services of those on the sins against whose manhood her
haughty ones had fattened and exulted. But, when God wanted a Moses,
there was a Moses ready, hidden away far back in the desert of Horeb,
and who, in due time, received his commission from among the trees of
the wilderness.</p>
               <pb n="20" facs="seiss20.jpg"/>
               <p>The same has been repeated, in our day, in our country. The
picture rises to your view without my aid to call it up.</p>
               <p>*		*		*		*		*		*		*		*</p>
               <p>One of the most controlling features in the character of Moses,
which shines out in his whole career, undimmed by a single stain of
inconsistency, was his self-sacrificing devotion to his convictions of
justice and right, based upon his religious faith. His inspired
eulogist has said of him, and meant in this to sum up the great
actuating principle of his life, that he "chose rather to suffer
affliction with the people of God than to enjoy the pleasures of sin
for a season, esteeming the reproach of Christ greater riches than the
treasures in Egypt; for he had respect unto the recompense of the
reward." (Heb. 10: 24-28.)</p>
               <p>The same is, in a large measure, true of our late Chief
Magistrate. Though not, so far as I am informed, a professed
Christian, at least not in all particulars, he was a man of decided
religious turn of mind, who lived and acted in the light and influence
of a practical faith. It was from his religious persuasions that all
his ideas were shapen, and according to which he honestly sought to
settle his judgment and direct his course, whether in matters of
private life or of public policy. All his opinions thus came to
partake of the nature of religious principles,
<pb n="21" facs="seiss21.jpg"/>
which no personal hazards or counter motives could induce him for one
moment to forsake, and for which he was willing to assume any amount
of responsibility, and to submit to any degree of self-sacrifice. He
died a martyr's death, but only because he was pervaded from the
beginning with the elements of a martyr's spirit. He had learned, from
the holiest authority, that God "hath made of one blood all nations of
men," and that the immutable rule of right, as between man and man, is
to do unto others as we would that they should do unto us. And his
entire career, in all his public acts at least, was simply the earnest
and honest application of these principles. Hence his uniform and
generous sympathy with the oppressed and the suffering. Hence his
early protest, upon the records of his State, in which he declared it
to be his solemn belief, "that the institution of slavery is founded
on both injustice and bad policy." Hence his advocacy, in Congress, of
the right of petition for its removal, his votes to exclude it from
the Territories where it had not yet been planted, his efforts to have
it abolished in the District of Columbia, his indignation at the
repeal of the Missouri Compromise, his ever-deepening abhorrence of
the whole system, and his consent to undertake the leadership of an
effort to withstand its insatiable encroachments, and to carry his
principles into a national administration which had nei-
<pb n="22" facs="seiss22.jpg"/>
ther precedents nor records to guide it, and which the great mass of
those in power stood pledged to resist.</p>
               <p>Nor did he count anything too dear to be laid upon the
altar of that cause, which he believed to be the cause of humanity and
of God. Nobler words, and revealing the whole structure of his moral
thinking, perhaps were never uttered by man, than those in which he
said to the people of Illinois:</p>
               <p>"The thirteen colonies, by their representatives in old
Independence Hall, said to the world of men, 'We hold these truths to
be self-evident, that all men are born equal; that they are endowed by
their Creator with certain inalienable rights; that among these are
life, liberty, and the pursuit of happiness! This was their lofty and
wise and noble understanding of the justice of the Creator to His
creatures,--to the whole great family of man. In their belief, nothing
stamped with the Divine image and likeness was sent into the world to
be trodden on, and degraded and imbruted by its fellows. They grasped
not only the race of men then living, but they reached forward and
seized upon the furthest posterity. They created a beacon to guide
their children, and their children's children, and the countless
myriads who should inhabit the earth in other ages. Wise statesmen as
they were, they knew the
<pb n="23" facs="seiss23.jpg"/>
tendency of prosperity to breed tyrants; and so they established these
great self-evident truths, that when, in the distant future, some man,
some faction, some interest, should set up the doctrine that none but
rich men, or none but white men, or none but Anglo-Saxon white men,
were entitled to life, liberty, and the pursuit of happiness, their
posterity might look up again to the Declaration of Independence, and
take courage to renew the battle which their fathers began, so that
truth and justice and mercy, and all the humane and Christian
virtue's, might not be extinguished from the land; so that no man
would hereafter dare to limit and circumscribe the great principles on
which the temple of liberty was being built. And if you have been
taught doctrines conflicting with the great landmarks of the
Declaration of Independence, if you have been inclined to believe that
all men are not created equal in those inalienable rights enumerated,
let me entreat you to come back, to return to the fountain whose
waters spring close by the blood of the Revolution. Think nothing of
me; take no thought for the political fate of any man whomsoever, but
come back to the truths that are in our chart of liberty. You may do
anything with me you choose, if you will but heed these sacred
principles. You may not only defeat me for the Senate, but you may
take me and put me to death, but do
<pb n="24" facs="seiss24.jpg"/>
not destroy that immortal emblem of humanity,--the Declaration of
American Independence."</p>
               <p>And with what patient steadiness and self-possession did he
pursue his great mission!</p>
               <p>Moses was the very model of steadfast fortitude and
perseverance. Defiantly resisted, repeatedly unsuccessful, and again
and again foiled and mocked, he continued the conflict, by argument,
by expostulation, by miracle, and maintained his ground with a
firmness of endurance which outwearied even Pharaoh's hardness. And
when his own people lost heart and confidence, and found fault with
him, and basely conspired against him, and God himself, by reason of
their unbelief, added to his charge and difficulties, by deferring the
fulfilment of the promise, he never once thought of giving up, but
kept to his work, reasoned, waited, and devoutly persevered, till,
from Nebo's top, he beheld the expected land lying invitingly at his
feet.</p>
               <p>How like Moses, in these respects, was our late President?
Who ever encountered more or greater perplexities, difficulties,
provocations, and discouragements than those which beset his way? And
yet, with what earnest but passionless calmness did he grapple with
them! Look at him; unexpectedly called from an humble sphere in which
he had been content to remain, and suddenly made the head of a party
for the first time, and, as it were, by accident,
<pb n="25" facs="seiss25.jpg"/>
coming into power, and as yet wholly without settled habits of
traditions of official life, charged with the administration and
maintenance of a government which one powerful state after another had
renounced and repudiated, required to locate among a people who were
almost all opposed to him, the subject of misrepresentation and
unqualified abuse, waylaid for his life at almost every turn, mocked
at for official awkwardness, maligned and resisted for his opinions
and steadfast policy, tried by years of apparent failure before that
policy obtained a single success, embarrassed by the zeal and
boastfulness of his friends and subordinates no less than by his
inexperience, and that of the country, in such a state of affairs,
pressed on every side by some who could see no force in his
obligations as a constitutional ruler, and cried down on the other by
men whose sympathies with treason would allow of no measures large
enough for the revolutionary emergency which had arisen, often
forsaken by his friends, and deceived and censured and conspired
against by those whom he had honored with his confidence; he patiently
endured all, and stood calmly to the helm amid the shoals and
tempests, never once giving way to anger, to resentment, to
despondency under discouragements, or to intemperate exultation over
the most rapid and brilliant successes, when at last they came. In all
his extraordinary trials, and notwithstanding
<pb n="26" facs="seiss26.jpg"/>
his great solemn earnestness, his good nature, his generosity, his
kind feeling, and his wonderful meekness, never once departed from
him. Uncouth and inexperienced as he was at the beginning, he knew his
place, and understood his own mind, and added with every year to his
force of character, his self-possession, his executive capacity, and
his magnanimous devotion, until there shone forth from under that
ungainly figure a grasp of principle, a directness of judgment, a
dignity of manner, a solemnity of purpose, a goodness of heart, and a
comprehensive simplicity and justness of policy, which arrested the
attention and commanded the admiration of foreign courts, and which
place his name on the roll of earth's best men and greatest rulers.</p>
               <p>Some said that he was a tyrant. And if inflexible patriotic
devotion, and the bold maintenance of the majesty of law over
self-will, unruly sectionalism, and daring revolution, if untiring
study and courageous promptness in bringing every power and resource
of the Government into exercise for the overthrow of armed
conspirators and the preservation of his country from ignoble
dismemberment, if unquailing confrontation of a subtle and mighty
attempt to destroy the most beneficent rule on the face of the earth,
if daring to use power to save a great and useful nation at a moment
when the last flames of its life seemed to flicker for extinction, if
these, and
<pb n="27" facs="seiss27.jpg"/>
such like instances of patriotic and Christian effort, constitute
tyranny, then Abraham Lincoln was a tyrant.</p>
               <p>But we have not so learned to count usurpation and tyranny.
There is another spirit and style of action, of which there has much
been seen and felt in recent years, to which these terms much more
appropriately apply. It is the spirit which says of the black man, "If
he complains of his wrongs, <hi rend="italic">lash him</hi>," and of the
white man, "If he stands in your way, KILL HIM." It is the spirit
which comes to the Senate chamber with loaded canes, and answers
patriotic logic with physical blows upon its author's head, to leave
him dying in his seat. It is the spirit which enters defenceless towns
in the guise of peaceful travellers, in order to rob, burn, and
murder, out of mere brutish vengeance. It is the spirit which gathers
infected clothing from the pest-houses, and sends them as honest
Merchandise to be distributed in unsuspecting communities, for the
purpose of breeding death and desolation. It is the spirit which, with
oaths in heaven registered to serve and defend, plots plunder,
dismemberment, and revolution; which schemes in secret, and sends
forth its emissaries in darkness, to burn unoffending cities unwarned,
and to erase them, if it can, from the earth; which undertakes, in the
name of freedom and religion, to subvert the very foundations of
both, and to rear in
<pb n="28" facs="seiss28.jpg"/>
their places an illegitimate thing, conceived in self-will,
established by rebellion, and subsisted upon the forced toil of
millions consigned to brutal degradation and eternal servitude. It is
the spirit which incarcerates unfortunate prisoners of honorable
warfare in pestilential holds, stifles them with thirst, starvation,
diseased meats, if not slow poisons, and plants tons of gunpowder
under them that, in case of inability to retain them, they might be
blown to atoms at the mere touch of a match. It is the spirit which
gets into the house of a sick public servant with a lie, and stabs him
in his bed, and deals out slaughter to his unarmed and terrified
attendants; and which nothing daunted, holds the charged pistol to the
head of the nation's legitimate chieftain, and blows out his brains in
the presence of his family and friends, because it cannot overawe his
noble purpose, nor drive him from his fixed fidelity to his country,
his conscience, and his God.</p>
               <p>Men and brethren, I way be mistaken; but if I have at all
learned to estimate the character of human actions; if I have any true
insight into the nature of human rights; if I have any just perception
of what enters into the composition of the praiseworthy or the base,
there is in things like these, the very quintessence of tyranny, and
all its worst and most intolerable infamies. And I pity the man who
cannot justify, or at least excuse, any stretching of
<pb n="29" facs="seiss29.jpg"/>
official power, however questionable in other circumstances, that may
be requisite to save a free people, and a government based on equal
rights, from falling into the hands of such wrongful domination. Rise
from the little muddy circles of party politics and prejudices, and
look at it in the broad sunlight of eternal morality, and see whether
such "chivalry," fairly interpreted by its own acts, does not
unmistakably belong to the sphere of the ugly, the brutal, and the
devilish.</p>
               <p>It is not for me to say where the responsibility lies; nor
would I direct criminating words where they do not apply. But these
things are the true fruits of secession, which show what it
practically is, and index what I take as a full vindication of almost
any measures calculated to weaken and to vanquish the unholy thing. If
some were, by rigid construction, extra-constitutional, they were not
the offspring of resentment and vengeance, nor of self-will, and vain
ambition, and love of power, which are the characteristics of
tyranny. If some were unprecedented in the nation's history, so was
the occasion which demanded them, and the treason which made them
necessary. And if, peradventure, certain provisions of the
Constitution, repugnant to its framers, and applying only to sections
which had, by deeds of resistance and assault, forfeited their claims
to its protection, were ignored, what good man would put his
<pb n="30" facs="seiss30.jpg"/>
country's existence in jeopardy, and imperil the cause of freedom in
all the earth, by endeavoring to uphold what could but weaken himself,
and strengthen those who were at the time trampling the whole
instrument under their feet, and glorying before the world in their
purpose to destroy it?</p>
               <p>Silence as the antidote for traitorous proceedings, and the
Constitution to fetter the hands of conscientious loyalty in grappling
with them, is a political creed which argues ill for the patriotism of
its confessors; but it embodies the exact logic of those who look upon
Abraham Lincoln as a tyrant.  Another man, an officer of the
government, and sworn to defend it, may use his place to manipulate
for that government's destruction; he may go and levy war, and raise
armies, and make generals, and commission agents, public and secret,
to strike the death-blow to its heart; and the Constitution, which
ranks such proceedings with earth's foulest crimes, is never
named. But when a God-fearing executive plants himself in the way of
the destroyer, and exerts his proper power to save the most precious
of political creations, and gives promise of success in restoring his
country's unity, with its freedom enlarged, its impurities purged, and
its greatness augmented, he is denounced as a tyrant, and murdered for
his devotion. Shame to such shallowness, and woe to the guilt of such
hypocrisy!</p>
               <pb n="31" facs="seiss31.jpg"/>
               <p>And whilst upon this point, let me quote a sentence or two
even from that organ of out country's enemies, the London
Times. "Abraham Lincoln," says that paper, in a recent issue, "was as
little of a tyrant as any man who ever lived. He could have been a
tyrant had he pleased, but he never uttered so much as an ill-natured
speech. The war was attended with all war's horrors, but there was no
cruelty at Washington. If the people of the seceding States were
rebels, never was rebellion, except on the field of battle, more
gently handled. In all America there was not one man who less deserved
to be the victim of this revolution than he who has just fallen. He
did nothing to aggravate the quarrel short of conceding the
independence of the South, he did everything to prevent or abbreviate
it. He recognized it as his one great duty to preserve the Union, and
whatever opinions may be entertained about the war and its policy,
nobody can say that such a principle was otherwise than becoming in
the President of the Republic." (April 29th.)</p>
               <p>It would seem, however, to be one of the common laws in
human affairs, that the most virtuous and useful men are the most
hated and abused in their lifetime. This was remarkably illustrated in
the history of Moses. How was he sneered at when first he appeared at
Pharaoh's court! How did all Egypt despise him for his miracles! How
did his own peo-
<pb n="32" facs="seiss32.jpg"/>
ple complain of him in their timidity, when they saw the Egyptians
coming upon them at Baal-Zephon! How did they murmur against him at
the waters of Marah, and accuse him in the wilderness of Sin, and cry
out in condemnation of him at Rephidim! How vexatiously did they
depart from him while engaged with God on their behalf, and rail at
him, and take up stones to destroy him in the plains of Paran! How was
he wronged by the conspiracy of Korah and Dathan, and tried by the
treacheries of Balak and his apostate prophet, and mistreated at every
step of his self-denying career! And so it was with all the
prophets. Some of them were stoned, sawn asunder, tempted, slain with
the sword, "being destitute, afflicted." Even the blessed Saviour of
the world was crucified; his apostles were martyred; and his great
confessors, in every age, have been hunted down with wrath and
bloodthirstiness. Even among the heathen, we find such men as
Aristides banished, Socrates poisoned, Demosthenes exiled, Cicero
expelled and assassinated. And now, in this boasted home of
civilization, in these days claimed as the culminating period of
triumph for human rights, we have to add to the list, the kind,
generous, passionless, self-sacrificing, honest-hearted Abraham
Lincoln, who in the midst of his wonderful achievements for his
imperilled country, and his great magnanimity towards its foes and
his, was sought out, and mur-
<pb n="33" facs="seiss33.jpg"/>
dered, for no other reason than that he was good and true and
great.</p>
               <p>He was but a man. God forbid that he should for one moment
have a higher place in our affections or esteem than that which may
lawfully be assigned to a man. I believe that there is real danger in
these days, and one which is pointed out as the peculiar snare of the
last times, of falling into a spirit of hero-worship, and an
apotheotizing of human leaders, which is among the subtlest, easiest,
and deadliest of idolatries. It was the great crime of some of the
most enlightened nations of antiquity, and it will be the essence of
the great apostacy under the Antichrist. We need, therefore, to be
carefully on our guard in that direction. But, let us not fail to do
justice to the virtues of the dead, or refuse to keep in kind
remembrance those whom God has honored as great servants of their
kind.</p>
               <p>It was a sublime work which Moses did for his people and
for the world. He relaid the foundations of Israel's great nationality
by new illustrations of God's covenant concerning them. He was the
great reasserter of human rights over against the tyrannies of Egypt,
and the great representative of Law at a time when the world had
become oblivious to its high and immutable obligations. He was the
great mediator between Jacob's seed and their oppressors, and the
friend who kept Israel from compromising their
<pb n="34" facs="seiss34.jpg"/>
proper destiny. He was the great instrument in the Divine hand through
whom deliverance was administered to an enslaved race. He was the
great collector of the simple traditions of his people, and the
reproducer of them for the enlightenment of mankind.  And, taken all
in all, he was one of those sublime mountains of human greatness from
which new eras date, and the most important affairs of time take
complexion and shape.</p>
               <p>We are not yet in a position so well to understand the
relations and importance of Lincoln's life and deeds. It remains for
future ages to trace the bearings of his work upon the fortunes of
humanity. But we know enough to warrant the remark, that generations
to come will recur with grateful interest and holy reverence to the
story of that rugged pioneer, coming suddenly from the wilderness to
steer the greatest of the nations through the greatest of its perils,
and to set an example of wise and prudent administration, worthy of
the study and imitation of all the reigning powers on earth. Though
never once setting up to be great, and seemingly unconscious that he
was anything more than a man of the common average, history will not
fail to write him down a great man and a model servant of his
kind. Though occupying now no very exalted place in some men's
estimation, his administration will mark a new era in the history of
this continent, and
<pb n="35" facs="seiss35.jpg"/>
the time will come when his name shall be cherished by freedom's
children as warmly as that of Washington himself.</p>
               <p>Had he left no other legacy by which to be favorably
remembered than the magnificent illustration he has given of the value
of talents which oft lie hidden in the humbler walks of life, and of
the genial excellence of institutions which throw open the paths of
honor and official greatness as  well to the low born and the poor as
to the educated and the rich, the world would still have reason to
bless God that he has lived. In this one respect alone there gathers
round his history an importance to which no one can afford to be
indifferent. The facts in his career open a fountain of ever fresh
inspiration to improvement, fidelity, courage, and triumph, which must
give strength to many a fainting heart, and fan the fires of generous
ambition in many a lowly spirit, and thrill and cheer to greatness and
to good many a one of whom the world otherwise would never have heard,
and teach the proud, the high-born, and the wealthy, that their
children are by nature no better and no greater than the children of
those who serve in their houses, hew their wood, and draw their
water. There is, after all, an equality among men, too prone to be
forgotten; and this fresh, instructive, and finished life, now added
to the treasures of mankind, reopens and recalls the fact, and
<pb n="36" facs="seiss36.jpg"/>
sets it up on high for the everlasting encouragement of the lowly, and
the thoughtful contemplation of all men.</p>
               <p>This, however, is but a fragment of the case. Think of the
terrific perils through which we have just passed; of the
thunder-clouds of destruction which, time and again, threatened to
overwhelm our homes and country in one common ruin; of the great
feebleness to which the cause of loyalty, freedom, and humanity, had
been reduced; and of the almost miraculous deliverance which has been
vouchsafed. Think of the gigantic proportions, far-reaching
influences, and subtle sophistries of that long organizing movement,
which must be henceforward known as treason and rebellion; of the
universal ignorance of the resources and real mightiness of those
despised States to which the preservation of the Union and the
maintenance of the General Government's sovereignty were left; of the
quietus which has been given to the exultations of the hirelings and
friends of despotic and aristocratic power at the prospect of
America's humiliation; and of the shame which has been made to
overtake the insulting babblings of foreigners touching the follies of
the North. Think how, in the midst of discouragements and disasters on
sea and land, the contest for the majesty of law, national unity, and
equal rights was maintained, until rebellion was defeated in its
<pb n="37" facs="seiss37.jpg"/>
disorganizing aims, disrobed of its pride and usurpations, and bereft
of its ill-directed power. Consider where this great nation of ours
this day stands in the estimation of the world, and how sublimely it
is rising up to the true greatness of its earliest manifestos, with
one of its greatest stains and most troublesome causes of difference
and dissension as good as purged away forever, and the great motto of
"LIBERTY AND UNION, ONE AND INSEPARABLE," nailed to its flag-staff,
and woven with its emblematic colors, to signal hope to the oppressed
of every land; and, when you have searched out the agency by which
such great things have been wrought, and found the earthly well-spring
of those successes which half the world believed to be impossible, all
will be seen connecting with a name till recently as humble as it will
henceforth be great, and radiating from the meek heart, the calm
judgment, the wise administration, and the patriotic fidelity of
ABRAHAM LINCOLN.</p>
               <p>And this is the man against whom it has been in the hearts
of some to plot schemes of assassination, and, with a malignant
effrontery for which the English language has no name, to carry into
execution, Alas! for which shall we lament the most,--the loss which
has been inflicted by the audacious murder, or the awful depravity and
bloodthirstiness which it shows to be lurking in the hearts of men who
would
<pb n="38" facs="seiss38.jpg"/>
fain have us believe them to be our country's truest friends? Both are
subjects for our profound grief; but for both we have this great
consolation left, that a just God is upon the throne of the universe,
and that He will bring every work into judgment, with every secret
thing, whether it be good or whether it be bad.</p>
               <p>I will not undertake to maintain that our late Chief
Magistrate made no mistakes, or that he never erred in his estimates
of men or adoption of measures; even Moses himself did ill-advised
things, and was censured of God for his conduct at the waters of
Meribah.</p>
               <p>Neither do I conceive of all the surroundings in which the
assassin found him, as good, pious, or becoming a Christian's
dying-place. He was but a man, lacking in experience in public
affairs, and of that meek and generous nature which was, perhaps, too
willing, in smaller matters, to acquiesce in the tastes and wishes of
people less conscientious than himself.</p>
               <p>But, in the great elements of his character, he was just,
devout, Christian, and of a moral make and stamen, to which few in
politics have ever attained. He believed in God, in Revelation, in
Christ, in prayer, in the necessity of virtue, in providence, and in
the habit of settled dependence upon the precepts and administrations
of Heaven; and his creed was per-
<pb n="39" facs="seiss39.jpg"/>
haps quite as real, as influential, as practical, as that of any who
venture to sit in judgment upon him, and certainly as much so as that
of thousands who give tithe of mint, anise, and cummin, but are not
quite so particular in the weightier matters of judgment, mercy, and
faith. God is his judge, and in His hands I am hopefully willing to
leave him. If he was not so eminent a saint, he was an honest friend
of his country, a sincere sympathizer with the suffering and the
lowly, and a great servant and benefactor of mankind. If he was shot
down in a theatre, he died a martyr to his country and to principles
which good men in every age will honor and approve.</p>
               <p>It is time, my friends, that I should dismiss you; but
indulge me with yet a remark or two, before I conclude. The public
mind is a good deal exercised about monuments and memorials to our
deceased chieftain. Now, the greatest honor that can be rendered to
his memory is for those who revere him to stand by the principles for
which he lived and fought and died,--to reproduce his good, honest
purposes and generous nature in themselves,--to steer by those
landmarks which guided him to greatness. Other monuments will
perish. The memorials constructed of nature's elements will pass away
with nature's wastes. At best, they are but mute things, the meaning
of which may be lost even while they yet
<pb n="40" facs="seiss40.jpg"/>
stand. But great principles and truths, practically wrought into
immortal minds, and lived into the histories of mankind, will endure
through all the ages, and keep telling their impressive story
forever.</p>
               <p>Moses is dead, and to this day no man has ever seen his
sepulchre; but his genius lives, fresh, vigorous and active, and will
continue to live on, increasing in dominion as the race expands and
men are found to accept his ideas. No monumental piles could so
perpetuate his honor.</p>
               <p>Nor can the fame of Lincoln wane, or his potent greatness
fail in its power on the earth, if men will keep to the channels of
thought and action again laid open in his life.</p>
               <p>And if there was that in him worthy of honorable
commemoration, the nearest to immortality that we can give it is, to
live it and act it ourselves, and to teach our children to do the
same. If his ideas and convictions were framed to the statements and
precepts of Revelation, and yielded fruits worthy of our honor, that
honor is best rendered by giving to that self-same Revelation full
sway in all our thoughts and reasonings. If he considered it bad
policy, and a crime which cannot escape Divine indignation, to
withhold from a fellow-being his native rights, and we think him
entitled to our praise for his consistent and conscientious adherence
to that belief, we shall praise him most effectually by making it the
basis of
<pb n="41" facs="seiss41.jpg"/>
our actions too. If he regarded all men as of one blood, and entitled
by their Maker to the same rights, and acted out to sublime
distinction the golden rule, to do to others as we would have them do
to us, and the credit of his course calls for significant celebration,
we cannot answer the call in better form than to take the same into
our souls as the inviolable law of our lives. If his great devotion to
his country's unity, and his patient self-sacrifice for its
preservation, demand some marked acknowledgment from his countrymen,
there is no way in which that acknowledgment can be more handsomely
made, than by the earnest and honest copying of his example. If he
held secession to be treason, and felt it as a solemn obligation upon
his conscience to make no compromises with it or with the doctrines of
its defenders, and men would honor his judgment and scruples in the
case, let them cling to these teachings as their political creed, and
see that they are enthroned among the inviolable stabilities of our
cherished institutions. And if he had no double conscience, one for
private life, and another for political conduct, but for all his
relations kept to the one great and ever-binding law of right and
conscience, and you think it meet to give honorable expression to your
appreciation of such simple integrity, the sublimest thing to be done
is, conscientiously and always to conform your course to the same
<pb n="42" facs="seiss42.jpg"/>
Divine standard, and live to truth and right and God, in business and
in politics, the same as in your charities and in your church.</p>
               <p>But whether any are moved or not by such reference to the
dead, let us not forget, that we all have obligations upon us, and
duties to discharge, and responsibilities to meet, in the directions
indicated, which take their rise from our very position in the
universe, and which it is our great business in this world to learn,
acknowledge, and obey.</p>
               <p>We may be humble, feeble, and unnoticed in the great crowd
of men; but we are each God's workmanship. He has put each of us here
for a purpose; and we each must some day answer to Him for the manner
in which we have fashioned our lives, and fulfilled our mission.</p>
               <p>We may not have nations to lead, or to organize to new
ideas, or to guide and keep in the hours of trial; but we each have
spheres of importance in which to operate, and little gardens which we
ourselves alone can cultivate, and webs of little deeds to weave, in
which our highest life is to be found.</p>
               <p>We may not, indeed, be Moseses or Lincolns, but, like both
of them, we can be ourselves; and by being honestly our true selves in
humble things, we know not to what high spheres we yet may be
raised. We have the highest authority for it, that faithful-
<pb n="43" facs="seiss43.jpg"/>
ness in that which is least, is faithfulness also in much. We know by
whom, and to whom, it was said, "Well done, good and faithful servant;
thou hast been faithful over a few things, I will make thee ruler over
many things." (Matt. 25: 23; Luke 16: 10.) And both the histories of
the men whose names I have associated in these remarks, preach and
illustrate the same hopefulness.</p>
               <lg type="stanza">
                  <l>"Lives of 'great men all remind us</l>
                  <l>We can make our lives
sublime,</l>
                  <l>And, departing, leave behind us</l>
                  <l>Footprints on
the sands of time--</l>
               </lg>
               <lg type="stanza">
                  <l>Footprints that perhaps another,</l>
                  <l>Sailing o'er life's
solemn main</l>
                  <l>A forlorn and shipwrecked brother,</l>
                  <l>Seeing,
shall take heart again.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg type="stanza">
                  <l>Let us then be up and doing,</l>
                  <l>With a heart for any
fate;</l>
                  <l>Still achieving, still pursuing,</l>
                  <l>Learn to labor
and to wait."</l>
               </lg>
               <pb n="44"/>
<!-- blank page -->
<!--               <p>
                  <figure entity="seiss44">
                     <figDesc>44th page of
Joseph A. Seiss' The Assassinated President.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </p> -->
               <pb n="45" facs="seiss45.jpg"/>
            </div2>
            <div2 xml:id="seiss.004" n="III. THE CLOSING SERVICES." type="service">
               <head>III. THE CLOSING SERVICES.</head>
               <p>THE FINAL PRAYER.</p>
               <p>ALMIGHTY GOD, the eternal Source of wisdom and purity, from
whom all good counsels, all holy desires and all just works do
proceed; sanctify our hearts by Thy holy Word. What we know not, teach
Thou us. Whatever is wrong in us, help us to overcome, and to put far
from us. Whatever in us is good, aid us in cherishing, and in carrying
forward to perfection. Enable us to go forth into the world with the
spirit of true religion in our hearts, and to spend all our days in
Thy fear and love. May Thy Gospel ever be precious to our souls. And
when Thou shalt see fit to remove us from this state of toil, trial,
and danger, may Thy grace avail for us, and the gates of eternal life
open to receive us, through Jesus Christ, our Lord, and our Hope.
AMEN.</p>
               <p>THE CONCLUDING HYMN.</p>
               <lg type="stanza">
                  <l>"Guide Me, 0 thou great Jehovah!</l>
                  <l>Pilgrim through this barren land;</l>
                  <l>I am weak, but thou art mighty,	</l>
                  <l>Hold me with Thy powerful hand," &amp;c..</l>
               </lg>
            </div2>
         </div1>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>