<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader><fileDesc>
         <titleStmt n="Victory and Mourning">
            <title>Victory and Mourning</title>
            <author>Steele, Rev. Richard H.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Compiled and edited by</resp>
               <name>Beck
Center</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent/>
         <publicationStmt><publisher>Lewis H. Beck Center</publisher><pubPlace>Emory University</pubPlace><address>
               <addrLine>Atlanta,
Georgia</addrLine>
            </address><availability>
               <p>1996 Emory
University. Permission is  granted to download, transmit, or otherwise
reproduce,  distribute or display the contributions to the work
claimed by Emory University for non-profit educational  purposes,
provided this header is included in its entirety.   For inquiries
about commercial uses, contact the Director,  Pitts Theology Library,
Emory University, Atlanta, Georgia 30322</p>
            </availability><date>1999</date></publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Lincoln
Sermons Project</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Steele,
Rev. Richard H. Victory and Mourning. A Sermon Occasioned by the Death
of Abraham Lincoln, Late President of the United States; Preached in
the First Reformed Dutch Church, New-Brunswick, N. J., June 1st,
1865. New-Brunswick, N. J.: Terhune &amp; Van Anglen's Press, Albany
St. 1865.</bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc><encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This text derives from the Special Collections  of
Pitts Theology Library, Emory University, and is produced in
collaboration with the Lewis H. Beck Center a, the Emory  Preservation
Office, and Pitts Theology Library.</p>
            <p>TRANSCRIBER: Lewis H. Beck Center and Emory University 
Preservation Office.</p>
            <p>PRODUCER:  BookLab, Inc., 1606 Headway Circle, 
Suite 100, Austin, TX 78754</p>
            <p>CAPTURE DEVICE: XEROX DocuImage 620S flatbed scanner</p>
            <p>CAPTURE DETAILS: Scanner software: XEROX ScanTool 
version 4.2.3; no gamma correction; images are all bitonal.</p>
            <p>CHANGE HISTORY: Using the Adobe Photoshop Batch Processor, 
we interpolated  the original TIFF files to 8-bit grays, 
and altered the resolution to 144 dpi, producing screen 
images twice the original size.  We then saved them in 
JPEG format.  We produced GIF thumbnails from the JPEG files.</p>
            <p>RESOLUTION: 600 ppi</p>
            <p>COMPRESSION: Resolution 144 per inch with Constrain 
Properties to 72 per inch.</p>
            <p>SOURCE: Original documents.</p>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc><revisionDesc><change><name>Stewart Varner</name> transformed this document from p4 to p5 on <date when="2010-03-22">March 22, 2010</date></change><change xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><date>1999</date><label>Staff</label><name>Scott
Ellis</name>SGML tags inserted in
compliance with TEI guidelines using TEILITE</change></revisionDesc></teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div1 xml:id="steele.001" n="Victory and Mourning" type="text">
            <head>
               <bibl> 
                  <title>Victory and Mourning</title> 
                  <date>June 1st, 1865</date>
                  <pubPlace>First Reformed Dutch Church, New-Brunswick, N. J.</pubPlace>
                  <author>Steele, Rev. Richard H.</author> 
                  
                     <pubPlace>New-Brunswick, N. J.</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Terhune &amp; Van
Anglen's Press</publisher>
                     <date>1865</date>
                   
               <idno type="ark">http://pid.emory.edu/ark:/25593/15r46</idno></bibl> 
            </head>
            <p>
               <figure><graphic url=""/>
                  <figDesc>1st page of Rev. Richard
H. Steele's Victory and Mourning.</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <p>Victory and Mourning.</p>
            <p>A</p>
            <p>SERMON</p>
            <p>OCCASIONED BY THE DEATH OF</p>
            <p>ABRAHAM LINCOLN,</p>
            <p>LATE PRESIDENT OF THE UNITED STATES;</p>
            <p>PREACHED IN THE</p>
            <p>FIRST REFORMED DUTCH CHURCH.</p>
            <p>NEW-BRUNSWICK, N.J.,</p>
            <p>JUNE 1st, 1865,</p>
            <p>By</p>
            <p>REV. RICHARD H. STEELE,</p>
            <p>PASTOR OF THE CHURCH.</p>
            <p>NEW-BRUNSWICK, N. J:</p>
            <p>TERHUNE &amp; VAN ANGLEN'S PRESS,
ALBANY ST.</p>
            <p>1865.</p>
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>
               <figure><graphic url=""/>
                  <figDesc>1st page of
Rev. Richard H. Steele's Victory and Mourning.</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>
               <figure><graphic url=""/>
                  <figDesc>3rd page of
Rev. Richard H. Steele's Victory and Mourning.</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <p>Correspondence.</p>
            <p>NEW-BRUNSWICK, JUNE 1ST, 1865.</p>
            <p>REV. RICHARD H. STEELE,</p>
            <p>DEAR SIR:-</p>
            <p>The
undersigned, members of the Congregation of the First  Dutch Church,
heard with profound satisfaction your discourse to-day. An utterance
so distinct and manly, and so admirably adapted to the times,
deserves, to be put into more enduring form, and to have a free
circulation. The congregation earnestly desire to have it
printed. Will you give it for the purpose?</p>
            <p>Very truly yours,</p>
            <p>JOHNSON LETSON,		DAVID COLE	       LEWIS
APPLEGATE, <lb/>HENRY VAN  LIEW,		K. T. B. SPADE,        JOHN
VAN DEVENTER, <lb/>JOHN R. VAN ARSDALE,             JOHN BRUNSON,
DAVID CODDINGTON, <lb/>H. V. D. SCHENCK,		JOHN JOHNSON,    HENRY
McDONALD, <lb/>R. A. VAN ARSDALE,                   G. S. VAN PELT,
ISAAC V. VAN DOREN, <lb/>WILLIAM VAN DEURSEN.</p>
            <p>NEW-BRUNSWICK, JUNE, 2D, 1865.</p>
            <p>TO JOHNSON LETSON,</p>
            <p>PROF. COLE, AND OTHERS:</p>
            <p>Gentlemen:-</p>
            <p>The
discourse commemorative of our lamented Chief Magistrate, of which you
make such kind mention, is at your disposal. I have no doubt that your
just admiration for the Illustrious Dead has led you to overestimate
the worth of the sermon, yet I yield to your wishes in the hope that
we may all receive profit from the contemplation of a character so
worthy of study and admiration as that of President Lincoln.</p>
            <p>With great respect, your friend and Pastor,</p>
            <p>RICHARD
H. STEELE.</p>
            <pb n="4"/>
<!-- blank page -->
<!--            <p>
               <figure entity="steele4">
                  <figDesc>4th page of
Rev. Richard H. Steele's Victory and Mourning.</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p> -->
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>
               <figure><graphic url=""/>
                  <figDesc>5th page of
Rev. Richard H. Steele's Victory and Mourning.</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <div2 xml:id="steele.002" n="SERMON" type="sermon">
               <head>SERMON.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <p>2ND SAMUEL, 19; 2.</p>
                  <p>AND THE VICTORY THAT DAY WAS
TURNED INTO MOURNING UNTO ALL THE PEOPLE.</p>
               </epigraph>
               <p>Never perhaps in the whole history of the world did two such
extremes of experience occur as that which our nation passed through
during the second week of April last. Joy in its wildest delight, and
sorrow in its deepest wail of anguish, in most rapid succession rolled
over the land. We shall none of us forget the effect produced
throughout the loyal North, when early on Monday morning of that
eventful week it was announced by swift telegraphic messages that the
Capital of the rebellion was not only in our possession, but that now
also the great army of the Confederacy under the leadership of its
ablest General, had surrendered to the greatest living commander of
the world, Lieutenant General Grant.</p>
               <p>We remember how the daily papers greeted us that morning with the
broad capitals--Union--Victory--Peace--The surrender of General Lee
and his whole army--The work of Palm Sunday. This was the climax of
glad tidings, and after the four long dark dreary years, years in
which the heart staggered under its great burden of wo, we do not
wonder, that the people almost ran wild with excitement. The
<pb n="6"/>
                  <figure><graphic url=""/>
                     <figDesc>6th page of Rev. Richard
H. Steele's Victory and Mourning.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
official congratulation from the Secretary of War to the commander of
our armies, "Thanks be to Almighty God for the great victory with
which he has this day crowned you and the gallant armies under your
command," was enough to awaken the most latent patriotism, and to make
each loyal heart beat with gratitude.</p>
               <p>It was not altogether unlooked for. And yet it was so sudden in its
announcement; so promising in its significance; and even the
circumstances connected with the capitulation, displaying in the
character of our Lieutenant General the diplomacy of the statesman, as
well as the prowess of the warrior, was so unexpected, that we
accepted the whole matter as a distinct, almost miraculous gift of
heaven. We could not help thinking what it all meant. It meant the end
of rebellion, the end of civil war, the end of deadly feuds, and the
reestablishment of Government and Law all over the land. No wonder
that the joy was so great that it overstepped the rules of sobriety,
and exhibited itself in forms such as never before had found
expression. Men wept for joy, and embraced each other in public
places, they sang doxologies of praise, and with uncovered heads
reverently acknowledged the hand of God. We felt that our noble
Government was stronger now than it had ever been before; that now
peace would surely spread its broad mantle over our war-trampled
territories; that the pestilence was stayed in its ravages; and the
thunder cloud of war was rolling away from our political skies as the
exhausted storm dies along the heavens. We felt that the weary nation
would now start again in its career of greatness, purified by
<pb n="7"/>
                  <figure><graphic url=""/>
                     <figDesc>7th page of Rev. Richard
H. Steele's Victory and Mourning.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
suffering, and make its way through the ages. All these emotions, and
even more, than the most exuberant fancy could kindle, sent their
surge of joy over the soul.</p>
               <p>The next Sabbath was the Easter Sunday, the joyful festival of the
church. And the event of national victory occurring just at this
juncture, it seemed as if the good God intended to link the salvation
of our land with that event which was the crowning triumph of the
Redeemer's life--his Ressurrection from the dead. We were preparing to
observe the day in this appropriate joyful manner, when in an hour all
our hopes were dashed to the earth, and a chill of horror froze our
very life-blood.</p>
               <p>During that very week occurred Good Friday, the day on which our
Lord was crucified, and ever kept in remembrance of that event in the
history of the Christian church. The succeeding morning brought to us
the intelligence of the most awful event that had ever occurred, save
one, in the history of the world. In the very midst of the wildest
joy, in the flash of a moment, the heavy tidings rolled over the land,
that Abraham Lincoln, our honored chief magistrate, the foremost man
of the age, had perished by the hand of the assassin. All at once,
"The victory that day was turned into mourning unto all the people."
The patriot just before so elated with hope that he would fain lift up
the voice, clap the hands, and sing songs of gladness in the streets,
was now prostrated in the dust, speaking in hushed voice and with
bated breath. During all day long we could not realize the greatness
of the calamity, in the greatness of our grief. We could only ask, can
it be that the Presi
<pb n="8"/>
                  <figure><graphic url=""/>
                     <figDesc>8th page of Rev. Richard
H. Steele's Victory and Mourning.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
dent of the United States, the honored representative of the dignity
and authority of our government; the chosen man of the people after
four years of severe trial; the man whose unfaltering integrity had
won the confidence of this nation more largely than any other man
since the days of Washington; the man whom God seems to have qualified
most eminently, by the natural formation of his character, the
sterling honesty of his heart, and his deep moral principles, for the
high office which he filled during these stormy years:-can it be that
he, the good Abraham Lincoln, just in the hour of national triumph has
fallen a victim of the dark assassin? We can only stand in profoundest
awe before the scene. Did ever two such extremes of experience meet?
Did human hearts ever touch two such opposite emotions? Verily, "The
victory that day was turned into mourning unto all the people."</p>
               <p>THE FUNERAL PROCESSION.</p>
               <p>What a change has Providence made in the order of our
proceedings. We were on the eve of arranging great civic processions,
and calling the people together to study the lessons of victory, and
learn the duties now devolving upon the American citizen in this new
crisis of our history. But God meant it not so. Instead of rejoicing
he called for mourning; instead of great celebrations he called for
funeral marches; and in the place of long processions moving through
our streets beneath gaily decorated banners and exulting with glad
voices, lo! yonder funeral train starting from the capital, bearing
with them, as in ancient days the children of Israel did the body of
<pb n="9"/>
                  <figure><graphic url=""/>
                     <figDesc>9th page of Rev. Richard
H. Steele's Victory and Mourning.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
Joseph, the remains of our Chief Magistrate through the cities and
villages of the land to his distant place of burial, among the people
who knew and loved him well, and a nation following the bier as
mourners.</p>
               <p>Never among the events of history has there been such a pageant
witnessed as that; and its chief interest arose from the fact that it
was the heart-felt expression of national grief. There have been great
funeral processions upon earth. When Samuel died, all Israel was
gathered together at his burial, and they made great lamentation over
the best of the Judges. When Jacob died, his sons reverently took up
the body out of the land in which they were strangers, and at his own
bidding bore it back to Canaan, and buried him with his fathers; and a
great company went up with them out of Egypt as mourners. Nations also
have mourned when statesmen, warriors, and emperors have passed away
from the scenes of their glory. How profound was the grief of the
British heart, and even of all Europe when the young Princess
Charlotte died, whose winning traits of character had twined around
her the love of the nation. When the ashes of Napoleon Bonaparte were
brought back to France in his coffin, the whole land rose up to
receive him at his coming, and the dead Emperor received more honor
than the living hero.</p>
               <p>But never was grief so profound and mourning so sincere, as that
which has followed the funeral march of Abraham Lincoln to his burial
place at Springfield. In yonder city I stood for two hours beholding
the funeral pageant following the train of the dead chieftain. And as
his remains were born past the throng,
<pb n="10"/>
                  <figure><graphic url=""/>
                     <figDesc>10th page of
Rev. Richard H. Steele's Victory and Mourning.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
with uncovered head, and reverent mien, and moistened eye, the whole
great crowd bowed down in grief. The heart of the nation was touched,
and every household felt the sad shock of personal bereavement. "Far
more," it has been said, "have gazed upon the face of the departed,
than have ever gazed upon the face of any other departed man. More
eyes have looked upon the procession for sixteen hundred miles or
more, by night and by day, by sunlight, dawn, twilight and torchlight,
than ever before watched the progress of a procession."</p>
               <p>THE
MEANING.</p>
               <p>We are here to inquire, why was all this mourning in the nation? Is
there an adequate cause for this swelling grief of the land? My answer
is-</p>
               <p>I. <hi rend="italic">The man himself, his position, and the
circumstances of his death, warrant this expression of national
mourning.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The man himself was simply Abraham Lincoln; in some respects no
more than a man, and standing in the same relation to God with you and
me. And yet in the native cast of his character, and in his training,
he was a man of commanding influence and mark, with endowments mental
and moral unusual for his position; and I believe that this has been
the increasing conviction of the people in the progress of events and
more especially during the closing months of his life. There was
something peculiar in the cast of his mind; and the elements that went
to make up his character were of such a remarkable type, that he won
largely the popular heart.  In forming an
<pb n="11"/>
                  <figure><graphic url=""/>
                     <figDesc>11th page of
Rev. Richard H. Steele's Victory and Mourning.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
estimate of the man there are some things that we are to take into the
account, which do not come into the calculation in weighing other
characters. We must take our estimate from the circumstances of his
early, training, from the times in which he lived, the various
disadvantages under which he established himself, and the native force
of his intellect and heart.</p>
               <p>He had by nature a kind, companionable, and jovial disposition,
free from every taint of vanity, adulation, or conceit of, his own
greatness; and on the first interview he would awaken in one's mind a
deep impression of solid worth, sound common sense, perfect simplicity
of character, and unaffected goodness of heart. He was loved by those
who knew him on account of his sterling and uncompromising integrity;
his industry and patience in discharging the minutest details of his
office; his freedom from all unkindness towards those who differed
from him in the policy of his administration; his remarkable skill in
healing divisions among his friends, and leading them to adopt the one
idea as the great end of the conflict--the preservation of the Union
in all its integrity; and for his calmness of temper, combined with
deep moral principle, and intense patriotism. He was a man of
unaffected modesty, never disclosing the slightest appearance of
elation or conceit at the honors which were heaped upon him, or that
it was necessary for him to be anything more than simple Abraham
Lincoln. He was in close sympathy with the people, and had an openness
of heart which won for him the deepest affections of those who were
around him; and going beyond that circle for the same reason, there
were thousands who knew the
<pb n="12"/>
                  <figure><graphic url=""/>
                     <figDesc>12th page of
Rev. Richard H. Steele's Victory and Mourning.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
man only by his life, who felt toward him all the warmth of personal
attachment.</p>
               <p>In the character of his mind, and modes of thought and expression,
he was entirely himself. While he was constitutionally slow in forming
his plans, and arriving at a decision; this did not denote any
weakness of character, or lack of moral courage. We know that he
surrounded himself with the most distinguished men of his party, with
senators and statesmen who had the advantage of him in their long
experience with the public affairs of the nation; yet none of them
could obtain such an influence over him as to set aside his own
carefully formed judgment. It was known the country over that he was
the President, and they were his cabinet ministers. He sought light
from every quarter, and obtained the advice of his counsellors; but
every leading act of his administration was an act of his own
mind. And when once formed no power could reverse his decision. He had
made up his judgment deliberately, and with a sagacity which took in
all its bearings, and after that he did not waver for a moment.</p>
               <p>One striking peculiarity of the man was the style of his
composition, and the character of his eloquence. This was his own as
decidedly as were his manners, and personal appearance. He read few
works, but we are informed that among his favorites, were Bunyan's
Pilgrim's Progress, and Spark's Life of Washington. And while the
style of his composition was formed after no model, and is not marked
out by the rules of the rhetorician, yet we cannot fail to trace in
those terse, shrewd sentences, a resemblance to the great Christian
dreamer.  There is
<pb n="13"/>
                  <figure><graphic url=""/>
                     <figDesc>13th page of
Rev. Richard H. Steele's Victory and Mourning.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
nothing elegant in them as a whole, yet now and then a thought would
break from his lips with all the sparkling freshness of Addison; and
although it sometimes lacked a precision such as we look for in close
analysis, and had even a grotesque twist in the language that would
awaken a smile, yet what it lost in comeliness, it more than gained in
point and vigor. His last inaugural address is a fair sample of his
style of thought and expression; and its solemn religious tone seems
to have been written under the shadow of approaching martyrdom.</p>
               <p>That he was a sincere Christian we have every reason to believe
from the frequent declarations of his lips, and the acts of his
life. With a mind always pervaded with deep reverence for God and
divine things, and chastened with many afflictions, he had the
consciousness of the forgiveness of sin through atoning merits, of
love to Jesus, and the character of an heir of his great salvation.</p>
               <p>The place which our lamented President is to fill in history is not
now ours to determine, though we have the privilege with others to
form a philosophical estimate. The circumstances of his elevation to
office will after a few years have elapsed be lost sight of, and
nothing will remain for the historian but to look at the man and his
acts in the light of events. Some future Bancroft or Hildreth, will in
that future day pen a record something like the following; This
remarkable man from an obscure family subsisting by manual toil,
laboring with his own hands for daily maintenance, having few
advantages of education, and of a fixed integrity of heart, combined
with rare native talents, is first heard of as a diligent and suc
<pb n="14"/>
                  <figure><graphic url=""/>
                     <figDesc>14th page of
Rev. Richard H. Steele's Victory and Mourning.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
cessful village lawyer; then takes his seat in the lower house of
Congress; is next seen canvassing his adopted State in rivalship with
the accomplished orator Stephen A. Douglas for the Senate of the
United States; then next raised by the popular voice to the Chief
Magistracy of the Republic; and four years after we find this same
man, at a time when the finances of the country are in the greatest
embarrassment, and when a desolating and cruel civil war is raging
with unabated violence and uncertain issue, retaining such an
ascendency over the American nation that he is re-chosen by
acclamation to the Presidency, and to a burden of responsibility which
the Father of his country never sustained. The writer will place in
contrast the condition of public affairs when he assumed the reins of
government, a nation torn and rent asunder, treason whispered in
almost every breath, and the noble republic a scene of wide desolation
and ruin; with the state of the country when he was taken up to his
reward, a nation restored and saved, the laws reasserting their
supremacy from the lakes to the gulf, the flag of the union waving
over the whole land, and our glorious nationality shining out again in
the return of blessed peace, and the revival of the ancient spirit of
loyalty. The historian will give him the honor of bestowing freedom
upon a nation of slaves, and by virtue of his own moral power combined
with the material forces at his command of quelling the gigantic
rebellion of the world; and the future sculptor will place high up on
the pedestal of fame the perhaps externally ungraceful, but truly
noble figure of Abraham Lincoln, as the great vindicator and conserver
of our popular form of free institutions.</p>
               <pb n="15"/>
               <p>
                  <figure><graphic url=""/>
                     <figDesc>15th page of
Rev. Richard H. Steele's Victory and Mourning.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <p>Passing from the man himself to the <hi rend="italic">position that
he occupied</hi>, and the <hi rend="italic">circumstances of his
death</hi>, we justify the mourning of the nation when we reflect that
he was our President. Contemplated in itself it was the death of one
of our fellow men; it was death by the hand of violence; a dark,
deadly blow upon an unarmed man. The act in itself stands unparalleled
in its cold, malicious, cowardly intent. But it was not the life of
that kind-hearted man that was intended. He was the Head of the
Government, the representative of the honor and dignity of the
American nation. It was not Abraham Lincoln, but the honored President
of the United States who fell in that murderous assault. It was a blow
struck by the rebellion at the very heart of the nation; a cowardly
effort of defeated and. disappointed men to destroy our institutions,
and tear down the pillars of our national edifice. I know indeed that
the act most signally failed--thanks to the overruling Providence of
God; but the spirit in which it was conceived and executed was the
very essence--the ripened fruit of this accursed rebellion.</p>
               <p>The miserable wretch whose grave no one wants to know, and his aids
and accomplices now on trial, did not stand alone. We are told by the
Government that the plan was known by the authorities in rebellion,
and approved by them. And I for my part believe that the Southern
Chivalry are capable of the deed. I believe that the men who could
leave our brave boys prisoners in their power to starve, and perish by
idiotcy induced by cruelties at which a savage would shudder, as at
Andersonville and Saulsbury, and Belle Island, and Libby Prison; I
believe
<pb n="16"/>
                  <figure><graphic url=""/>
                     <figDesc>16th page of
Rev. Richard H. Steele's Victory and Mourning.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
that the men who could approve the massacre at Fort Pillow in which
men in the service of their country, disarmed and unresisting
prisoners, were buried alive, and shot down like wild beasts; I
believe that the men who could dig up the bodies of our dead soldiers
slain in battle, as they did that of my personal friend and former
parishioner, Major Ballou on the disastrous field of Bull Run, and
carve their bones into spurs and ornaments, and send them home to
their children; I believe that the men who could plot the burning of
hotels and places of public amusement thronged with their unsuspecting
occupants and helpless children; I believe that the men who could
deliberately plan the introduction of pestilence into the City of
New-York, appropriating to the act as it stands in sworn evidence two
hundred thousand dollars; I believe that the men who could offer in
their public journals large rewards to be paid to those who would
bring to the authorities the heads of our officers, imitating the
worst forms of barbarism; I believe that the men who could receive the
tidings of our President's assassination with the shocking
announcement--"if the work. was to be done it had better be well done
and if the same were done to Andy Johnson, the beast, and to Secretary
Stanton, the job would be complete;" I believe that these men are
capable of instituting the diabolical plot of the assassin to attempt
the overthrow of a Government which they could not accomplish by the
system of honorable warfare.</p>
               <p>While we know that there are thousands at the South who look upon
this closing drama of rebellion
<pb n="17"/>
                  <figure><graphic url=""/>
                     <figDesc>17th page of
Rev. Richard H. Steele's Victory and Mourning.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
with the same horror that we do at, the North; yet the men who stand
connected with the deeds I have enumerated are today exulting in this
deed of blood. It was a plan of long standing, and now in the
extremity of desperation, treason has killed our President. The life
of Abraham Lincoln was taken, because he was entrusted with all the
executive and military power of the Government, and was administering
the laws to crush a most causeless and wicked rebellion. He died in
the discharge of, the noblest duty, in the very zenith of his fame,
honored by all the people and loved by God. He died in the arms of
victory, his work completely done; and his weary soul has entered into
rest. We may well justify a nation's tears. Though in the hour of
triumph, we may well grieve, under a deep impression of the greatness
of our loss. For surely "The victory that day was turned into mourning
unto all the people."</p>
               <p>II. <hi rend="italic">A principal part of the interest awakened
arises from the circumstances connected with the times, the principles
which have been brought to light by these circumstances, and God's
meaning in our great national conflict now, so happily terminated.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>VICTORY AND ITS LESSONS.</p>
               <p>As far as its military features are concerned we have come to the
close of the great rebellion; the greatest conflict through which any
nation has ever passed. The end is not entirely reached, and there are
difficult questions about reconstruction, which will need the wisest
statesmanship to carry us successfully through.  But I leave it to
others to discuss the various measures which seem the best adapted to
promote
<pb n="18"/>
                  <figure><graphic url=""/>
                     <figDesc>18th page of
Rev. Richard H. Steele's Victory and Mourning.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
the restoration of our beloved land,--and I find that many are lavish
in their recommendations to our Chief Magistrate as to what course he
bad better pursue. We are very willing to leave all these questions in
the hands of Andrew Johnson, a man who keeps his own counsels, who
makes up his mind carefully, who loves his country, who believes that
treason should be punished, and who has no indecision of character.</p>
               <p>During the progress of this war we have had prophecies almost
without number, and as is often the case in reference to human
calculations, most of them have failed. It is easier to study the
lessons which God is teaching by the progress of events, than to
forecast the probable future. And there are certain great facts which
have been brought to light by this contest and in its progress, and
which have culminated in the death of President Lincoln, which we do
well to understand.</p>
               <p>I. <hi rend="italic">God has been on our side.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is easy to see this now that the end is reached; though our
hearts sometimes trembled at the bloody way along which he was leading
us. No other nation has ever passed through what ours has and lived,
not even the Netherlands in that long contest with the combined powers
of Louis 14th of France, and Charles II of England. We have had
confidence in our cause, in Government, in Justice, in God: but how
near did we come to ruin. What terrible disasters have we experienced!
What wholesale jealousy among our officers, amounting almost to
treachery! What incompetent generals at the head of our armies! 
<pb n="19"/>
                  <figure><graphic url=""/>
                     <figDesc>19th page of
Rev. Richard H. Steele's Victory and Mourning.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
We were sorely tried and sometimes painfully discouraged. We cannot
forget the gloom which hung over the loyal North during the first
years of the struggle, the sadness that attended the repulse of our
armies as they were rolled back in their efforts to advance through
Virginia, at Bull Run, and Balls Bluff, and Chancellorsville, and
Fredericksburg, and on the Peninsula--the defiant spirit of the
rebellion which seemed to rise up hydra-headed in its aggressions. We
shall not forget how the leaders of the rebellion again and again
attempted to advance upon our Northern territory, and threatened to
carry devastation through our cities and towns, and over our land. It
would be foolish to deny to the Southern generals and armies a spirit,
a determination, and a courage worthy of a better cause.</p>
               <p>But in the midst of it all God has been with us, enabling us to
overcome. We have followed the march of General Grant, then almost
unknown, in his triumphant way through the West, at Fort Donelson, and
Corinth, and Vicksburgh; we saw our gallant officers of the Navy doing
their noble work, Dupont planting our flag on the soil of South
Carolina, and Farragut of peerless fame unlocking the gate of the
Mississippi at New Orleans, and Porter in his descending sail joining
the fleet from the gulf below; we saw the battle roll increased by the
brilliant victories of Antietam and Gettysburgh won from the Southern
hosts on our Northern soil in the darkest day of the rebellion; we
beheld with astonishment the noble Sherman sweeping down from
Chattanooga, fighting his way through passes and defiles which the
engineers of Napoleon's army on their way over the
<pb n="20"/>
                  <figure><graphic url=""/>
                     <figDesc>20th page of
Rev. Richard H. Steele's Victory and Mourning.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
Alps never encountered, opening through the gates of Atlanta the key
to the heart of the Confederacy, then marching through Georgia to
Savannah, and upward through the Carolinas, sweeping the chivalry of
Charleston, and Branchville, and Columbia from his path, and holding
at bay until another work should be done, the strong army of Johnston;
then finally, we have seen our Lieutenant General when the hour for
action came, hurling Lee from his intrenchments marching triumphantly
into the heart of the capital, and in the end surrounding the great
army of the rebellion in his iron grasp and grinding it to powder. It
is impossible not to discover in all this the hand of God leading us
to victory.</p>
               <p>It has been brought to light that in this struggle Providence has
been against this Southern rebellion; and Providence is
irresistible. The very weapons they had forged against us have been
turned against themselves. And the whole scene as it lies before us is
a picture of the wonderful Providence of God. How clearly is there
revealed in all this a mightier will than human!</p>
               <p>No one was more ready to recognize this than our lamented
President. The secret of his wonderful patience, and strength and
confidence of success, was his implicit trust in God. And among the
pleasing recollections of his life are his proclamations of
thanksgiving, calling upon the people to give thanks unto God who
alone maketh us to triumph.</p>
               <p>2.  <hi rend="italic">God means the end of Slavery.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If any man has lingering doubt on the subject, the recent Amnesty
Proclamation of President Johnson
<pb n="21"/>
                  <figure><graphic url=""/>
                     <figDesc>21st page of
Rev. Richard H. Steele's Victory and Mourning.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
must be the last argument, and it will bring conviction to even the
most reluctant understanding. Slavery is dead, and buried so deep that
it can never be raised again.  This is now an accepted fact, and one
of  the lessons of Divine Providence. God meant that it should be
destroyed, and there is written the result.</p>
               <p>It has been a remarkable school of discipline through which we have
passed in coming to this result, but there is the fact; and we must
accept it, or be blind to one of the plainest indications of the
hour. The time has passed for us to enter into discussion upon this
subject, its probable effect upon our country in the character of its
institutions. War, long, terrible, dire war, has brought this whole
matter to a conclusion. Battle is the argument that has settled it
once and forever. And for my part I am glad of it, and I trust that
you are. If this bone of contention is to be buried never to be dug up
again, from the bottom of my heart I will rejoice. The bullet of the
assassin, has made more converts on this point, and the events of the
war, than the arguments of philanthropists the world over. We now see
more fully than ever what its spirit is; what a gigantic wrong
national, social, and religious; and now that it is so near its end,
we ought to sing praises and thank God fervently.</p>
               <p>It would have been better for all classes if the evil of slavery
had been removed gradually and by the arts of peace. But if its end is
near at hand, violently if it must be so, let all the people say
Amen. To President Lincoln will belong the honor of giving to four
millions of slaves the station of freemen, and
<pb n="22"/>
                  <figure><graphic url=""/>
                     <figDesc>22nd page of
Rev. Richard H. Steele's Victory and Mourning.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
they are among the chief mourners to-day, all over the land. It has
long been the settled conviction of the great mass of people in this
country, that a system like this cannot stand. The framers of our
government never looked for its continuance. It was an evil that had
its limits, and was not to be perpetuated. They felt that in our land
of professed liberty, such an institution as that of Slavery was a
reproach to ourselves, and to the whole civilized world; and that it
ought to die. And now that the end is so near reached, every Christian
heart should rejoice.</p>
               <p>3. <hi rend="italic">God intends that there shall be only one
Government in the land.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That question is now fixed, and if we have ever had any misgivings
on the subject, we may as well amend our judgments, and come to the
conclusion which has now been written in characters of blood, that
this land is to be henceforth one and undivided.</p>
               <p>There has been a class of men from the beginning of our national
existence, who have been haunted with the idea, that any State might
withdraw from the Union, and enter upon its own independent
career. That spirit Daniel Webster combated in his argument with Hayne
in the Senate of the United States in one of the greatest forensic
efforts of the age. That same spirit Andrew Jackson grappled in his
famous proclamation against the nullifiers of the South, warning them
of what he would do if they dared so much as whisper treason, and they
knew the man too well to lift so much as their little finger against
the government. But all this did not destroy this spirit of
secession. It still lived, and it has been
<pb n="23"/>
                  <figure><graphic url=""/>
                     <figDesc>23rd page of
Rev. Richard H. Steele's Victory and Mourning.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
vexing this nation in every political contest for these thirty five
years. And now it is dead--twice dead and plucked up by the roots. It
has given us a hard struggle, millions on millions of property, and
more than half a million of precious lives, have been the price paid
for our noble government. It has had a hard death, and the whole
fabric of civilization has been shaken in its fall.</p>
               <p>Secession in this land has been more than a ghost, it is a
monster. The idea that any body of men can throw off their allegiance,
and set up a power of their own, is a monstrous doctrine, and fraught
with untold evil. But we have fought that radical error down. This is
its last struggle for the privilege of living. It never will have as
fair advantages again. It is a controversy that is decided. Battle is
the last dread argument, and it is conclusive. It is a fixed fact now
and forever that in this system of government the majority shall elect
the rulers, and the minority shall submit.</p>
               <p>The shocking murder of President Lincoln in the hour of
unsuspecting repose and in the moment of triumph, and the assassin's
assault upon Secretary Seward, in the helplessness of sickness, and in
the quiet of home; a scheme that was well arranged, and in open day,
vindicated among leading southern rebels, brings to light the demoniac
spirit of the horrid doctrine of secession. We see now that we have
been fighting with desperate men engaged in a desperate, cause; and
had it succeeded it would have been for all time the darkest page in
the world's history. But it has not lived. The surrender of great
armies has been its dying gasp; and the work by
<pb n="24"/>
                  <figure><graphic url=""/>
                     <figDesc>24th page of
Rev. Richard H. Steele's Victory and Mourning.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
President Lincoln under God, has been so complete, that we are left to
gaze in perfect wonder on the dissolving scene.</p>
               <p>4. <hi rend="italic">God means to show us that he alone gives the
victory.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is said that Napoleon Bonaparte once made the remark "The
Providence of God is always on the side of the heaviest battalions."
The expression is so contrary to his doctrine of fixed fate, and is so
entirely disproved by the great facts of history of which we know that
he was not ignorant, that we are disposed to doubt whether he ever
made the declaration. The truth is that God is always on the side of
right, and the cause which he espouses in the long race will win. He
who is on the right side with God, will surely succeed; the wrong
shall certainly be overthrown. True, there may be needed the
discipline of adversity to reveal the hidden power of Omnipotence. The
good cause may meet with stunning blows from the rapid and heavy
onsets of rebellion, and be hurled, back again and again in its
effort, to press forward; but it awakens to the greatness of the
conflict, and rallying to the fight it moves forward with the steady
front of truth, liberty, law and God; and it will come forth the
victor. Search the world's history over and you will find that the
great movements which have shaped the destinies of men have had their
inspiration from above. In every decisive conflict of the world they
win who are on the righteous side; and it matters not what skill of
generalship, what prowess of concentrated hosts, what desperate valor
is arrayed against the right.  The victory is the Lord's.</p>
               <pb n="25"/>
               <p>
                  <figure><graphic url=""/>
                     <figDesc>25th page of
Rev. Richard H. Steele's Victory and Mourning.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <p>More times than commanders of armies are willing to acknowledge has
it been shown, that the race is not to the swift, nor the battle to
the strong. The feeble David's have crushed the mighty Golioth's, and
in a way that puts to naught all the rules of scientific warfare. The
little Monitor sent the giant Merrimac staggering back to her birth,
and in the light of victory we cried "it is the Lord." When the
Kearsarge and the Alabama sailed out to fight that ocean duel, it was
known that save in a single feature, the Confederate was an overmatch
for the Federal. She was a new ship, of approved construction, built
by experienced craftsmen, of iron plate, and terrible engines of war,
and fought by good officers and desperate men. But she dealt her fire
wildly and rapidly; while the other with deliberate aim made, every
shot tell upon her quivering antagonist. An hour decides the contest,
and we have the explanation in the Providence of God; He gave the
victory.  On her deck over which floated yonder stars and stripes was
a patriot captain; and at her guns stood brave hearts fighting for
their country and homes. On the deck of the other stood a man whose
cause was unrighteous; and the crew were miserable hirelings who
fought only for pay and plunder.</p>
               <p>The whole scene of our civil contest has brought to light the fact,
that it is God alone who has crowned us with victory. The work is a
completed work; and he whom we lament to day acknowledged that while
he labored with a patient heart, the result was the Lord's. All honor
to our noble armies on their homeward march, and soon to mingle with
us in the
<pb n="26"/>
                  <figure><graphic url=""/>
                     <figDesc>26th page of
Rev. Richard H. Steele's Victory and Mourning.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
peaceful scenes of industrial life. But while they fought so valiantly
in the field, to them as to the Prophet of Israel, the mountain was
covered with horses and chariots of fire, and God was in the
fight. Their long marches and terrible hardships have been endured in
the sustaining thought of a good cause and an approving country. Their
tent fires gleamed with the radiance of home. The shock of arms was
the test of all that is sacred in the gift of God and in the happiness
of man. Every trumpet note was the clarion of liberty. And every
victory shall send its triumph along the path of ages. Surely to the
cause in which God is present, every man will be a hero, and the
result is plain.</p>
               <p>5. <hi rend="italic">God means the perpetuity of our free
institutions.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A sublimer spectacle has not been witnessed than the inauguration
of President Johnson, and the unanimity with which the people stand
around his administration. In the midst of the most appalling
circumstances, and at a most critical juncture, the Chief Magistrate
is smitten down by the hand of an assassin. At the same hour the
Secretary of State receives a murderous assault, though languishing on
a bed of sickness. It was speedily known that a conspiracy was in
progress to cut off all the heads of government. Lieutenant General
Grant was to have been one of the victims, and Secretary Stanton
another. No one could tell but that a bullet from some unseen hand
might pierce his heart.</p>
               <p>But the leaders of the nation during that awful night did not waver
for a moment in their allegiance to the government. In a short time
after the death
<pb n="27"/>
                  <figure><graphic url=""/>
                     <figDesc>27th page of
Rev. Richard H. Steele's Victory and Mourning.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
of the President, they assembled in the presence of Andrew Johnson,
and gave him the same loyal support which they had rendered to his
martyred predecessor. The dignity and glory of our institutions
exhibited in that simple act, is a picture such as the world cannot
parallel. And while we cannot but mourn the Providence which has
removed from us our honored Chief Magistrate, we will thank God that
in our present Executive, he has bestowed upon us a Ruler who, already
in the brief period of his office, has given us the promise of a
wisdom so sagacious, and of a policy so sound, that we will trust him
as the agent under a higher power, to complete the work of rebuilding
the glorious edifice of our free institutions.</p>
               <p>Let every Christian heart pray God that he will bless and prosper
Andrew Johnson, and give him wisdom to bring back this land to its
ancient renown. Let us all cherish for our country the best hopes and
anticipations. Let us free our minds of prejudice, passion, and the
spirit of vain-glorious trust. Let us have confidence in our
government, in the people, in justice, in God. Let us cherish no
dishonorable resentments, vengeance, or wrath. Let us cordially
support our rulers; and plant round the grave of our President the
olive grove, to testify that accept the closing lesson from his lips
and life--<hi rend="italic">Peace, peace to our country; Good will to
all mankind.</hi>
               </p>
            </div2>
         </div1>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>