<TEI.2>
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt n="A Sermon on the Assassination of Abraham Lincoln">
            <title>A Sermon on the Assassination of Abraham Lincoln</title>
            <author>Vincent, Rev. Marvin R.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Compiled and edited by</resp>
               <name>Beck
Center</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent/>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Lewis H. Beck Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Emory University</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Atlanta,
Georgia</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>1996 Emory
University. Permission is  granted to download, transmit, or otherwise
reproduce,  distribute or display the contributions to the work
claimed by Emory University for non-profit educational  purposes,
provided this header is included in its entirety.   For inquiries
about commercial uses, contact the Director,  Pitts Theology Library,
Emory University, Atlanta, Georgia 30322</p>
            </availability>
            <date>1999</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Lincoln
Sermons Project</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Vincent,
Rev. Marvin R. A Sermon on the Assassination of Abraham Lincoln,
Delivered in the First Presbyterian Church, Troy, on Sunday Morning
April 23, 1865. Troy, N. Y.: A. W. Scribner, Book and Job Printer,
Cannon Place. 1865.</bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This text derives from the Special Collections  of
Pitts Theology Library, Emory University, and is produced in
collaboration with the Lewis H. Beck Center a, the Emory  Preservation
Office, and Pitts Theology Library.</p>
            <p>TRANSCRIBER: Lewis H. Beck Center and Emory University 
Preservation Office.</p>
            <p>PRODUCER:  BookLab, Inc., 1606 Headway Circle, 
Suite 100, Austin, TX 78754</p>
            <p>CAPTURE DEVICE: XEROX DocuImage 620S flatbed scanner</p>
            <p>CAPTURE DETAILS: Scanner software: XEROX ScanTool 
version 4.2.3; no gamma correction; images are all bitonal.</p>
            <p>CHANGE HISTORY: Using the Adobe Photoshop Batch Processor, 
we interpolated  the original TIFF files to 8-bit grays, 
and altered the resolution to 144 dpi, producing screen 
images twice the original size.  We then saved them in 
JPEG format.  We produced GIF thumbnails from the JPEG files.</p>
            <p>RESOLUTION: 600 ppi</p>
            <p>COMPRESSION: Resolution 144 per inch with Constrain 
Properties to 72 per inch.</p>
            <p>SOURCE: Original documents.</p>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>1999</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Scott
Ellis</name>
               <resp>Staff</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <item>SGML tags inserted in
compliance with TEI guidelines using TEILITE</item>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div1 id="vincent.001" n="A Sermon on the Assassination of Abraham Lincoln" type="text">
            <head>
               <bibl> 
                  <title>A Sermon on the Assassination of Abraham Lincoln</title>
                  <date>Sunday Morning April 23, 1865</date> 
                  <pubPlace>First
Presbyterian Church, Troy</pubPlace> 
                  <author>Vincent, Rev. Marvin
R.</author> 
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Troy, N. Y.</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>A. W. Scribner, Book and Job Printer</publisher>
                     <date>1865</date>
                  </imprint> 
               </bibl> 
            </head>
            <p>
               <figure entity="vincent1">
                  <figDesc>1st page of Rev. Marvin
R. Vincent's A Sermon on the Assassination of Abraham
Lincoln.</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <p>A SERMON</p>
            <p>ON THE,</p>
            <p>Assassination of Abraham Lincoln,</p>
            <p>DELIVERED IN THE</p>
            <p>FIRST PRESBYTERIAN CHURCH, TROY,</p>
            <p>ON SUNDAY MORNING, APRIL 23, 1865,</p>
            <p>BY THE PASTOR,</p>
            <p>REV. MARVIN R. VINCENT.</p>
            <p>TROY, N. Y.:</p>
            <p>A. W. SCRIBNER, BOOK AND JOB PRINTER, CANNON
PLACE.</p>
            <p>1865.</p>
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>
               <figure entity="vincent2">
                  <figDesc>2nd page of
Rev. Marvin R. Vincent's A Sermon on the Assassination of Abraham
Lincoln.</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>
               <figure entity="vincent3">
                  <figDesc>3rd page of
Rev. Marvin R. Vincent's A Sermon on the Assassination of Abraham
Lincoln.</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <p>TROY, April 24, 1865.</p>
            <p>Rev. M. R. VINCENT:</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italic">Dear Sir.</hi>--The
undersigned having listened, with great pleasure, to your  discourse
on the 23d instant on the death of our beloved President, and heartily
approving its sentiments, respectfully request a copy of it for
publication.</p>
            <p>Very Respectfully, &#x0026;c.,</p>
            <p>J. F. WINSLOW,			JOHN E. WOOL,<lb/>
A. L. HOLLEY,			GILES B. KELLOGG, <lb/>DAVID
COWEE,		J. A. MILLARD,<lb/>
H. J. KING,			BENJ. H. HALL,<lb/>
J. W. FREEMAN,		IRVING BROWNE,<lb/>
F. S. THAYER,			A. H. GRAVES,<lb/>
G. B. SAXTON,			S. B. SAXTON,<lb/>
G. V. S. QUACKENBUSH,	J. SHERRY,<lb/>
N. DAVENPORT,		A. B. MORGAN,<lb/>
M. I. TOWNSEND,		GEORGE H. CRAMER, <lb/>JESSE
A. HEYDRICK.</p>
            <p>TROY, April 25, 1865.</p>
            <p>Maj.-Gen. JOHN E. WOOL,
Messrs. WINSLOW,</p>
            <p>HOLLEY,
COWEE, KELLOGG, and others.</p>
            <p>GENTLEMEN:</p>
            <p>In accordance with your request I transmit
to you the manuscript of my discourse of the 23d inst.</p>
            <p>Very Respectfully Yours,</p>
            <p>MARVIN
R. VINCENT.</p>
            <pb n="4"/>
<!-- blank page -->
<!--            <p>
               <figure entity="vincent4">
                  <figDesc>4th page of
Rev. Marvin R. Vincent's A Sermon on the Assassination of Abraham
Lincoln.</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p> -->
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>
               <figure entity="vincent5">
                  <figDesc>5th page of
Rev. Marvin R. Vincent's A Sermon on the Assassination of Abraham
Lincoln.</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <div2 id="vincent.002" n="SERMON." type="sermon">
               <head>SERMON.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <p>2 SAMUEL, III. 38: "Know ye not that there is a
prince and a great man fallen this day in Israel?"</p>
               </epigraph>
               <p>The events of history are often like figures in relief. We see but
one side of them, that which the artist chooses to represent. But this
is not an <hi rend="italic">universal</hi> truth. Some events have a
dramatic interest inherent in them. They are independent of the
artist. Though, like the sculptor who would hew Mount Athos into the
figure of a recumbent giant, the historian may mould and drape and
soften the lines, yet as the mountain, spite of the sculptor's work,
would have been a mountain still; so such events stand out from their
age, bearing their own character and speaking for themselves under all
the misrepresentations of history. They convey their own great
lesson. They resolutely strip from themselves all palliations.</p>
               <p>Concurrent events, moreover, have often much to do with the
sharpness with which these historic eras or incidents are cut. Often
the accumulated
<pb n="6"/>
                  <figure entity="vincent6">
                     <figDesc>6th page of Rev. Marvin
R. Vincent's A Sermon on the Assassination of Abraham
Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
sentiment and action of a whole, cycle concentrate and find expression
in a single event which henceforth becomes typical of the cycle. Often
the condensed power of a century is behind a word or a blow. Often
too, contemporary events are so disposed as to heighten to the utmost
the effect of a single deed, and to form a background against which
its lines come out with preternatural sharpness.</p>
               <p>If these characteristics ever united in any event, they do so in
that which brings us here to-day. Death is not a new event. Death in
high places is not a strange thing, even to us who twice before this
have been called to mourn over the nation's chief magistrate. Even
death under such circumstances is not unheard of nor uncommon. Not to
us alone attaches the stigma of a murdered ruler. But this event is
nevertheless instinct with a horror and with a significance
independent of our nearness to it, and our practical connection with
it. It concentrates in itself the elements of one fearful phase of our
national life. It is its natural offshoot, its pet child, its crowning
development of horror, its grand expression before the civilized
world. And, at the same time, concurrent circumstances are such
<pb n="7"/>
                  <figure entity="vincent7">
                     <figDesc>7th page of Rev. Marvin
R. Vincent's A Sermon on the Assassination of Abraham
Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
as to define its lines more sharply. In many instances, as I have
already said, even the assassination of a man in power does not
impress us like this event. In so many instances the man owes his
consequence only to his position. So much coloring is given to the
deed by his tyranny or inefficiency. So many conflicting interests
whose claims history gives us no means of estimating, have been
eddying round him, and the moral basis of the age has been so rotten
and wavering, the moral sentiment of the age so perverted, that <hi rend="italic">that</hi> event seems but in harmony with surrounding
events. But here it is otherwise. The nation since its rise, and more
rapidly within the last four years, has been developing a process of
grouping. On one side of the line have been ranging themselves order,
the government of reason and not of passion, fair and open discussion,
patriotism, loyalty, devotion to the morals rather than to the
politics of government. As an exponent of these principles, a man
occupied the seat of power who could not, if he would, have been a
tyrant, and who would not if he could; a man whose virtues commended
themselves to the people, whose policy commanded their confidence and
their endorsement. Break-
<pb n="8"/>
                  <figure entity="vincent8">
                     <figDesc>8th page of Rev. Marvin
R. Vincent's A Sermon on the Assassination of Abraham
Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
ing sharply off from such sentiments appeared another group,
representing treason, disloyalty, impatience of control, passion,
disregard of the principle of majority rule, oppression of the weak,
deeper degradation of the degraded, its principles represented by
factious demagogues who would rather "rule in hell than serve in
Heaven." No distinction was ever clearer. Ever diverging more and
more, these two developments have gone on since the foundation of the
Republic, until at last the distinction has culminated. The one side
has exhausted its venom in this crowning atrocity, and placed it in
such startling relief against the virtues of the victim and the great
order-loving, liberty-loving, rebellion hating, humanity-cherishing
sentiment of the Nation, as henceforth to stamp the act and that of
which it was the product with a character which no future historian
will dare to palliate, and to insure to them a detestation the
bitterness of which shall, be intensified with every succeeding
generation. God has forestalled the judgment of history, and on this
act, at least., its decision shall be unanimous.</p>
               <p>There then stands the fact in its terrific proportions. <hi rend="italic">Abraham Lincoln, President of the United</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="9"/>
               <p>
                  <figure entity="vincent9">
                     <figDesc>9th page of
Rev. Marvin R. Vincent's A Sermon on the Assassination of Abraham
Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">States, has been foully murdered by an
assassin</hi>. Truly the murderer must have well studied the effect of
contrasts. Had the deed been done when, as it is said, it was first
contemplated, it might have harmonized somewhat better with the
confusion which swayed the popular mind, with the anxiety respecting
the still unfinished conflict, and the still menacing rebellion. But
this had passed. Victory had perched upon the banners of our brave
generals. The routed army of the Confederacy had laid down its
arms. The pseudo President had abandoned his capital and fled, none
knew whither. The land was gay with waving banners and vocal with the
thunder of cannon and the pealing of bells; and the President, a man
of the people, was rejoicing with the people. For the moment</p>
               <lg type="stanza">
                  <l>"Grim visaged war had smoothed his wrinkled front."</l>
               </lg>
               <p>For a moment the nation that had sailed so long under the gloomy,
bristling head-lands of war, had caught a glimpse of a calm, open bay,
with the sun of peace shining down on its green encircling hills. And
for an hour the man whose shoulders had borne, for over four years,
the heaviest burden ever placed upon any ruler,
<pb n="10"/>
                  <figure entity="vincent10">
                     <figDesc>10th page of
Rev. Marvin R. Vincent's A Sermon on the Assassination of Abraham
Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
the man whose unceasing vigilance had been in demand to guide the
vessel of State through such tortuous channels and around such reefs
as never threatened nation before, for an hour he had laid aside the
cares of State: for an hour he had said "Good bye to pain and care:"
for an hour he had forgotten the nation's burden and given himself up
to the current of the nation's joy. And in that hour of grateful
relaxation the blow fell. The assassin, inspired with hellish daring,
threw his life upon the issue, and to-day the nation mourns his
success.</p>
               <p>I will not dwell upon the horrible fact. It is my duty to-day to
gather up its lessons as far as may be; and I go back now to my
introductory thought that some of the deeds of history are the
concentrated expression of a long train of previous events, giving in
their expression a typical character to the whole. It were easy enough
to cite illustrations, did time permit; yet it is unnecessary with
such an illustration before our eyes. To repeat once more what I have
already said from this place, I go back of the deed and its
perpetrator. I remind you only of the words of the assassin as he
leaped to the floor--"<hi rend="italic">Sic semper tyrannis. Virginia is
avenged</hi>"--as
<pb n="11"/>
                  <figure entity="vincent11">
                     <figDesc>11th page of
Rev. Marvin R. Vincent's A Sermon on the Assassination of Abraham
Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
showing, that the fatal blow was struck in the spirit of hatred to
constituted authority, in the spirit of devotion to that pestilent
heresy of State Sovereignty, in the interest of rebellion. The
rebellion was the direct outgrowth of slavery, and the assassination
of the President is the grand consummate expression of the <hi rend="italic">spirit of slavery</hi>. This is not the first time it has
struck from behind. It is full of the instinct of its own meanness. It
knows it is a vile thing, a suspected thing, a dangerous, false and
cruel thing, and it would fain call itself by other names, and make
its way under a mask. But thank God its name is written, and to-day it
stands baptized in the name of the devil and all his angels as the
spirit of <hi rend="italic">assassination and murder</hi>.</p>
               <p>For, look you calmly at this thing. I ask the most strenuous
advocate of slavery, if there be one left, whether, in reason, we
could expect any other development? Go back to the fundamental
principle of this institution which enables a man to own another, and
tell me if that is a safe right to entrust to any man. Tell me if the
testimony of history is not uniform on this point? Tell me if the
principle which permits one man to regard another as a chattel is not
destructive in
<pb n="12"/>
                  <figure entity="vincent12">
                     <figDesc>12th page of
Rev. Marvin R. Vincent's A Sermon on the Assassination of Abraham
Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
the end of respect for all human right, even the inalienable right of
life? You may put restrictions upon a master, forbidding him to kill
his slave but the spirit which thinks nothing of whipping a man or
degrading a woman, will only be restrained by policy or penalty or
want of opportunity from going further. The moment you admit in <hi rend="italic">any case</hi> the absolute right of one man over another's
person or property or family, that moment you remove the question from
its only substantial basis, and put it upon varying circumstances,
such as distinctions of social position or color. Be what you are
to-day, mentally and morally, only black, and the planter will sell
you, or whip you, or degrade you as readily as he would the African
fresh from the Guinea coast. The man who is taught that he is at
liberty to disregard <hi rend="italic">any</hi> right of another, is in
a fair way to disregard <hi rend="italic">all</hi>. It is dangerous to
set such a principle in motion. You cannot stop it where or when you
will. It laughs at statutes. It is like the demons in the old story,
which were called to draw water by one who knew the spell to set them
at work, but had forgotton how to lay them again; and which drew and
drew until they flooded his dwelling. You can confine the
<pb n="13"/>
                  <figure entity="vincent13">
                     <figDesc>13th page of
Rev. Marvin R. Vincent's A Sermon on the Assassination of Abraham
Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
application of this principle to no one class. Begin with distinction
of color, and gradually it will have come to overleap all distinction
of color, as it has done already; for you know that men and women have
been sold in the slave marts with skins as white as yours. Assume that
a slave woman is rightfully the toy and property of her master, and
you lessen the respect for female virtue everywhere, and stop not
short of that state of society which this is no place to lay bare, but
which has been for years existing at the South, and than which Hell
itself can present nothing more revolting. Begin with right over a
slave's person, and insensibly the master spirit will assert itself
over other persons; and if it dare not strike, will affect contempt of
wise and virtuous men, and come with its slave-driving councils. Begin
with killing a negro in the heat of passion, or by the administration
of a few dozen lashes too many, and under a system which finds it most
politic to wink at such deeds, and the transition is easy to holding
the life of a white man in light esteem. The hot blood, the childish
view of honor which sends the hand of the Southern desperado to his
knife-hilt or pistol
<pb n="14"/>
                  <figure entity="vincent14">
                     <figDesc>14th page of
Rev. Marvin R. Vincent's A Sermon on the Assassination of Abraham
Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
handle on the first fancied provocation, and which has made the South
the favorite arena of the duelling code, are but other cases in point
showing how disregard of one class of rights has begotten disregard of
all. The spirit which shot the President in his chair is the same
spirit which has been inflicting mutilation and death upon men and
women who dared open their mouths to condemn the benignant institution
of slavery, and sometimes on mere suspicion of their sentiments. It is
the same spirit that struck down Charles Sumner in his place in the
United States Senate for daring to hold the mirror up to slavery, and
to call things by their right names, and which gave public ovations to
the miscreant who did the deed. And if you want a catalogue without
end, turn over the history of this war, leaf by leaf, and see whether
the spirit of slavery can be expected to respect <hi rend="italic">any</hi> right. Rights! even the grave has had no
rights. We have lived to see enacted on this land which we have
claimed for Christian civilization, the feats that were deemed heroic,
centuries ago by barbarians who could quench their rage only in
draughts from the skulls of their slain foes. We have driven the
Indian from his native forest, and wept sentimentally over the
<pb n="15"/>
                  <figure entity="vincent15">
                     <figDesc>15th page of
Rev. Marvin R. Vincent's A Sermon on the Assassination of Abraham
Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
horrors of the scalping knife, only to see the mutilation of the dead
incorporated into the civilized warfare of the chivalrous South, and
to have our murdered sons and brothers dug from their graves, and
their bones hacked into pieces to furnish amulets for dainty Southern
dames. We have lived not only to read of the Inquisition as history,
but to see it revived with refinements of cruelty in Southern
prisons. We have seen even the hard mercies of civilized warfare
ignored, and the Policy deliberately inaugurated of maiming and
disabling hundreds and thousands of Northern men. Have you seen the
photographer's work? Have you marked the idiotic stare, the ghastly
features, the protruding bones, the swollen joints? Have you studied
the horrors of fever in the stockades of Andersonville? Do you think
it a small cause that will send men deliberately across the dead-line
to be shot rather than pine longer amid such misery? Did you see the
bread which George Stuart brought here a year ago, the staple of our
imprisoned soldiers' fare? Do you know that Libby Prison was
undermined when the authorities of Richmond anticipated the approach
of our troops, and that the hellish machinery was all in readiness to
blow the prison
<pb n="16"/>
                  <figure entity="vincent16">
                     <figDesc>16th page of
Rev. Marvin R. Vincent's A Sermon on the Assassination of Abraham
Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
into the air with its whole living tenantry? Do you remember that this
very act of murder over which we grieve was in contemplation four
years ago, and that only a superintending Providence saved Abraham
Lincoln to the United States, and Baltimore from adding another crime
to the murder of Massachusetts troops? And are you to think this last
event strange? Is an assassination out of keeping with the antecedents
of slave-barbarism? No, no! Slavery has done this deed, and upon it I
call down the curse of Heaven. I invoke it in the name of a
down-trodden race; I invoke it in the name of the hearts it has torn,
the domestic ties it has severed, the virtue it has corrupted, the
ignorance it has fostered; in the name of man robbed of the image of
his Maker, and of woman shorn of her dearest and most sacred rights;
in the name of slave mothers sitting like Niobes all over the wasted
heritage of the South; in the name of the blighted hopes and desolate
hearths of the North; in the name of the emaciated skeletons in our
hospitals, and the maimed forms that crawl along our streets; in the
name of the mutilated and pillaged dead; in the name of that bereaved
widow and her fatherless children, and of the bereaved nation
<pb n="17"/>
                  <figure entity="vincent17">
                     <figDesc>17th page of
Rev. Marvin R. Vincent's A Sermon on the Assassination of Abraham
Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
lying to-day in sackcloth and ashes; I call down upon it the blight of
heaven; I brand it as the <hi rend="italic">representative trampler upon
human rights</hi>. Oh! that when its vile head shall have been
crushed, as crushed it will be ere long, its vestiges might be
obliterated forever. But this cannot be. They will remain to bear
testimony against the Southern lords who have fostered and fought for
it, and against the Northern men who, in admiration of its patriarchal
beauties, have lavished upon it their sympathy, and truckled to its
imperious demands. The reminders are written all over the land. The
white tablets gleaming from a thousand hill-side churchyards shall
tell the story. The rough boards that mark the thousands of graves by
the Rappahannock and Potomac and Chickahominy shall moulder, but the
grass shall grow more greenly there, and flowers bloom more
luxuriantly; and even in their summer loveliness, the voice of
brothers' blood shall cry from the ground. The plow shall turn up mute
witnesses, and the fields, with their multitudinous relics of battle,
be vocal with slavery's reproach.</p>
               <p>And the West shall remember it. It shall keep 
<pb n="18"/>
                  <figure entity="vincent18">
                     <figDesc>18th page of
Rev. Marvin R. Vincent's A Sermon on the Assassination of Abraham
Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
the lesson to whet its good sword, and to fire its heart, if ever
traitors attempt a like experiment; for there, in one of its quiet
cemeteries, shall rise the monument of slave-treason's last and
greatest victim. To the home of his early struggles and successes, to
the home from which he went with prayer and faith to assume his high
destiny, to it shall be the honored task of cherishing his loved
remains, and his obelisk shall stand when our beloved land shall have
emerged purified and triumphant from this bloody ordeal, with its
marble finger ever pointing to heaven in protest against the barbarism
which tore him from the hearts of a loving people.</p>
               <p>But I turn now from the authorship of this calamity to the
illustrious dead himself.</p>
               <p>Our late beloved President, while in no sense a sectional
President, represented nevertheless a peculiar phase of our national
life--its youngest, its most progressive side. The West was his
birth-place; the West, that grand theatre where the pent up energy and
glowing aspiration of all other portions of the land find ample room
for development. While the West furnishes types of the best growths of
other soils, it superadds to them a character peculiarly its own. It
exhibits
<pb n="19"/>
                  <figure entity="vincent19">
                     <figDesc>19th page of
Rev. Marvin R. Vincent's A Sermon on the Assassination of Abraham
Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
the shrewdness of New England without its rigidity; the geniality of
the South without its passion. It combines the impulsiveness of the
Carolinas, and the caution of Maine and Connecticut. In its more
thinly settled districts men are obliged to fill larger spaces. The
circumstances are more favorable for the development of strong
individualities. A man cannot merge himself in a multitude or retire
into a convenient obscurity. He must fill a place, do a work, assert
himself, bring out the best that is in him, or suffer the consequent
odium. The early life of the President was well adapted to call out
the practical shrewdness, the strong common sense, and the knowledge
of men which characterized him. In such societies men's culture,
except in its practical adaptations, would have been wasted. Men's
knowledge was estimated according to its visible practical
contributions to the common weal. The emergencies of that pioneer life
called for tact, readiness, practical ability. In the development of
these the future President was not wanting in mental stimulus and
training. The very meagreness of the sources of knowledge sharpened
his appetite for it, and perhaps contributed to that characteristic
thoroughness which placed
<pb n="20"/>
                  <figure entity="vincent20">
                     <figDesc>20th page of
Rev. Marvin R. Vincent's A Sermon on the Assassination of Abraham
Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
what knowledge he bad so thoroughly at his command. The conscientious
carefulness so early exhibited marked him throughout his official
life; so that whatever men may think of his expressed sentiments on
any subject, his discussions always show an opinion laboriously and
conscientiously formed. The freedom and geniality of western life, its
rough but genuine familiarity, tended to deepen a naturally sunny and
affectionate disposition. No less were the circumstances under which
he appeared in political life adapted to sharpen his intellect and fit
him for the wider arena upon which he was destined to enter. That
close contact of political leaders with the people, requiring that the
representatives of opposite parties should discuss the great questions
of the day in their presence, was unfavorable to superficial knowledge
or evasive logic. No point must be shirked, however difficult. In the
sword play of debate before the people, exposed to a running fire of
question and comment, with the keenest interest and the most intense
feeling excited, he who evaded, if not exposed by his adversary, was
discovered by the people, and compelled to meet the issue or blush for
his ignorance or cowardice. From such a
<pb n="21"/>
                  <figure entity="vincent21">
                     <figDesc>21st page of
Rev. Marvin R. Vincent's A Sermon on the Assassination of Abraham
Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
school he came to the executive chair. You know well how exciting and
alarming was the crisis at which he assumed it. His own election had
been connived at by the opposite party to gain a pretext for the
execution of their long cherished scheme of secession. South Carolina
had begun the pestilent work and had turned her guns upon a government
fortress. The executive, too timid, too imbecile, or too much in
sympathy with the treason, to act, refused to lift a finger to
strangle the infant rebellion. States were falling into line under the
new Confederacy. Its agents had pilfered the public treasury and
scattered the public munitions. The border States hung wavering in the
balance, an object of apprehension and desire to either party. The
slavery question was presenting itself under the most complicated
aspect the acknowledged source of the difficulty, yet incapable of
being assailed for the time. Foreign nations were prepared to extend
their sympathy only on the ground of a crusade against slavery, and we
were compelled by fidelity to the Constitution, to deal only with the
overt act of treason, at the risk of forfeiting sympathy and insuring
foreign intervention. The conspirators were jubilant over their
<pb n="22"/>
                  <figure entity="vincent22">
                     <figDesc>22nd page of
Rev. Marvin R. Vincent's A Sermon on the Assassination of Abraham
Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
first success, and boasting that their flag would soon wave over the
capitol. On this scene of turmoil and danger Abraham Lincoln entered
at his inauguration. Well might he look forward with
apprehension. Well might he say on leaving his Western home: "A duty
devolves upon me which is perhaps greater than that which has devolved
upon any other man since the days of Washington." But once committed
to his duty he was not the man to shrink. He had been used to meeting
emergencies. He had been trained in the school of difficulty; and
gathering up his manhood with a calm dignity and a child-like trust in
God, he went forth to give his labor and his life for his country. It
is, of course, foreign to my purpose to follow him through that
administration so fruitful in events, in which the nation has made
history faster than in all the rest of her life together. I desire
only to bring out a few of those traits which most clearly illustrate
the man, and with which the nation has been made familiar in his late
position. His qualities of heart were such as commended him to all
men. He was in the real sense of that term a hearty man. The
expression of this characteristic was with him something more than
that assumed
<pb n="23"/>
                  <figure entity="vincent23">
                     <figDesc>23rd page of
Rev. Marvin R. Vincent's A Sermon on the Assassination of Abraham
Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
cordiality and familiarity which is counted one of the politician's
necessary weapons. It went beyond mere hand-shakings and expressions
of good fellowship. He was naturally disposed to think well of his
race. His prepossessions were generally in favor of a man. He would
rather love than hate him; and hence his feeling was literally <hi rend="italic">cordial</hi>--the spontaneous outgoing of a frank and
manly nature. In the theatre of his earlier victories, he was a man
whose intellectual power his adversaries feared; but <hi rend="italic">he</hi> would rather disarm an opponent with a good
natured jest than with a sarcasm or denunciation. With such a nature,
backed by a keen appreciation of the ludicrous, a ready memory, a
quick perception, a wide experience, his power of anecdote and
repartee has become proverbial. This feature of his character, which
has provoked the sneers of the starched magnates of Europe, has ever
appeared to my mind as a special gift for a special emergency. As
already remarked, such a burden rested upon him as seldom or never
fell to any ruler's lot. Added to the intricacy and number of the
State questions constantly before him, his natural kindness of heart
rendered him accessible to numberless petty, personal applications
which
<pb n="24"/>
                  <figure entity="vincent24">
                     <figDesc>24th page of
Rev. Marvin R. Vincent's A Sermon on the Assassination of Abraham
Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
he would have been fully justified in committing to subordinates; and
that never-failing fund of cheerfulness, that exhaustless humor which
the most complicated problem would so often "remind of a story," that
elasticity which suffered him to bate not one jot of heart or hope in
those times when the strongest held their breath, were God's own gifts
to the care-worn man, blessed springs of refreshing and strength
gushing up all along the dusty road of official duty. His errors, some
of them, lay in the direction of his kindness. His deep
conscientiousness, his keen sense of justice, his unwillingness to
wrong anything human, and perhaps his too great faith in the natural
goodness of mankind, led him at times to be lenient and forgiving,
when many thought that severity would have been but justice. His
personal kindness had extended to his own assassin. His mind, at the
time of his death, was full of schemes for the forgiveness and
restoration of the traitors who had struck at the nation's heart; and
if it be that the South is avenged in his death, she will find it to
be a vengeance that will recoil upon her own head; for in him she has
lost her best friend, and however little <hi rend="italic">we</hi> could
afford to spare him, <hi rend="italic">she</hi> could afford it still
less.</p>
               <pb n="25"/>
               <p>
                  <figure entity="vincent25">
                     <figDesc>25th page of
Rev. Marvin R. Vincent's A Sermon on the Assassination of Abraham
Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <p>The lightness and jocularity of which I have spoken, were but a
veil for sterner traits. They were but as the waving verdure, flecked
with passing shadows, and toyed with by every wind, yet growing upon
the everlasting hills whose heart is rock, and whose foundations are
in the depths of the earth. His uprightness has passed into a
proverb. His jest and story covered a strength of purpose, a rigid
determination, an adherence to principle which no crooked policy could
undermine, and which no bribe was great enough to tempt. In the real
old Roman sense of the term he was an <hi rend="italic">honest</hi>
man--an embodiment of manly worth and honor. Where men or measures
stood in the way of principle they must go down. When even plausible
views of moral right on certain great questions were urged upon him by
reformers, he could even consent for the time to be deemed false to
the great objects of philanthropy, rather than swerve from his
conscientiously chosen policy. He did not consult personal
popularity. He regarded himself as the people's servant; and to do
their work in the best way, and in accordance with his sworn
obligation to the Constitution, was his sole care. And the
<pb n="26"/>
                  <figure entity="vincent26">
                     <figDesc>26th page of
Rev. Marvin R. Vincent's A Sermon on the Assassination of Abraham
Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
secret of this lay in his <hi rend="italic">religiousness</hi>. From the
time of his assumption of his office to his death, his words on all
public occasions breathe a spirit of trust in the God of nations. As
nearly as I can ascertain, moreover, circumstances go to indicate that
after his assumption of office, he became the subject of deeper
religious experience. This sentiment is the key-note of the few words
spoken by him on leaving his home for Washington. "Washington would
never have succeeded except for the aid of Divine Providence, upon
which he at all times relied. I feel that I cannot succeed without the
same Divine aid which sustained him, and on the same Almighty being I
place my reliance for support." Of him it might be justly said, as of
William of Orange, to whose character his own presents some points of
similarity: "From his trust in God, he ever derived support and
consolation in the darkest, hours. Implicitly relying upon Almighty
wisdom and goodness, he looked danger in the face with a constant
smile, and endured incessant labors and trials with a serenity which
seemed more than human;" and, in the beautiful words of him who
pronounced his funeral eulogy, "While we admired and loved him on many
accounts, more suitable than any
<pb n="27"/>
                  <figure entity="vincent27">
                     <figDesc>27th page of
Rev. Marvin R. Vincent's A Sermon on the Assassination of Abraham
Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
or all of these, more holy and influential, more beautiful and strong
and sustaining, was his habitual confidence in God, and in the final
triumph of truth and righteousness through him and for His sake. This
was his noblest virtue and grandest principle, the secret alike of his
strength, his patriotism and his success. And this, it seems to me,
after being near him steadily, and with him often for more than four
years, is the principle by which, more than by any other, he being
dead yet speaketh."</p>
               <p>Oh! were it my lot to speak this day to men in high places, I would
commend to him who comes to Abraham Lincoln's place, this trait above
any in Abraham Lincoln's character. I would implore him by the great
interests of humanity now committed to him, in view of the fact that
the questions which sway the nation to-day have risen far above the
realm of politics, into that of morals and religion; in view of the
insignificance of all human power and wisdom, in an arena where God is
so manifestly exercising control, and shaping the age's destiny, to
look to this first of all. I would implore him to let the wave of
prayer that sweeps toward him from every hearthstone in the land, bear
him to the secret place of the
<pb n="28"/>
                  <figure entity="vincent28">
                     <figDesc>28th page of
Rev. Marvin R. Vincent's A Sermon on the Assassination of Abraham
Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
Most High, there to seek the leadings of that higher will, there to
have his thought drawn into sympathy with the Divine purposes, there
to be clad in the mantle of Lincoln's unswerving faith, and thence to
come forth and place himself at the nation's head, girt with a
sublimer strength, a purer patriotism, and a holier wisdom.</p>
               <p>The elements of the President's intellectual character were not
complex. It has been taken for granted that he did not exhibit the
characteristics of a great statesman. But without presuming to deny
this, I would not be too certain that he was wanting in the capacities
for the highest statesmanship. His discernment was quick; his power of
generalizing not inferior; his grasp of a subject firm; his knowledge
of political machinery extensive, though gathered from experience more
than from study. His policy, as exhibited in his administration, was
cautious and far-reaching. To his sterling, integrity and frankness he
added the wiliness of a Talleyrand. Under other influences, and in a
foreign court, he might have developed into a diplomat of the first
order. After all that has been said of his statesmanship, it cannot be
denied that he piloted the nation through one of the most difficult of
all
<pb n="29"/>
                  <figure entity="vincent29">
                     <figDesc>29th page of
Rev. Marvin R. Vincent's A Sermon on the Assassination of Abraham
Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
possible junctures with consummate skill and tact, and, the result
will probably show, with as few mistakes as any man would have been
likely to make under similar circumstances. His ignorance or rejection
of mere technicalities may, in some instances, have blinded
superficial observers to the statesmanlike qualities of his mind. He
was one of those to whom it was given to show the courts of Europe
that the difference between the administrators of the old and new
world is in the <hi rend="italic">polish</hi> rather than in the temper
of the blade. He laid no claim to the rhetorician's laurels, yet his
public documents were strongly, clearly and vigorously written. His
state papers were eminently popular documents. The discussions of
political issues introduced into them were set forth ofttimes with
familiar illustrations, which, while they might provoke a smile from
the sticklers for official stateliness, imparted to them a wonderful
freshness, and tended to root their principles deep in the popular
mind. No President has ever surpassed him, if any has equaled him, in
clearly defining his policy to the masses. His strong, practical
common sense was the basis of his intellectual character. In his
political discussions he had a rare faculty of detecting and
<pb n="30"/>
                  <figure entity="vincent30">
                     <figDesc>30th page of
Rev. Marvin R. Vincent's A Sermon on the Assassination of Abraham
Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
exposing sophistry. He seized intuitively upon the vital point of
every question, clearly stated the real issue, ranged all subordinate
facts round this, and summarily discarded everything which had no
relation to it. This faculty proved especially valuable in the class
of questions with which his administration so largely dealt. His
strong sense saved the Constitution from its greatest danger, the
danger of tying its own hands; and this was what enabled him to cut
the Gordian knot where some men would have found themselves
embarrassed by a mere technicality or formula.</p>
               <p>A recent article from the London <title>Spectator</title> so
forcibly illustrates these views that I may be pardoned for quoting an
extract:</p>
               <p>"But without the advantages of Washington's education or training,
Mr Lincoln was called from a humble station at the opening, of a
mighty civil war to form a government out of a party in which the
habits and traditions of official life did not exist. Finding himself
the object of Southern abuse so fierce and so foul that in any man
less passionless it would long ago have stirred up an implacable
animosity; mocked at for his official awkwardness and denounced for
his stead
<pb n="31"/>
                  <figure entity="vincent31">
                     <figDesc>31st page of
Rev. Marvin R. Vincent's A Sermon on the Assassination of Abraham
Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
fast policy by all the Democratic section of the loyal States; tried
by years of failure before that policy achieved a single great
success; further tried by a series of successes so rapid and brilliant
that they would have puffed up a smaller mind and overset its balance;
embarrassed by the boastfulness of his people and of his subordinates
no less than by his own inexperience in his relations with foreign
States; beset by fanatics of principle on one side, who would pay no
attention to his obligations as a constitutional ruler, and by
fanatics of caste on the other, who were not only deaf to the claims
of justice but would hear of no policy large enough for a
revolutionary emergency, Mr. Lincoln has persevered through all
without ever giving way to anger, or despondency, or exultation, or
popular arrogance, or sectarian fanaticism, or caste prejudice,
visibly growing in force of character, in self-possession, and in
magnanimity, till, in his last short Message to Congress on the 4th of
March, we can detect no longer the rude and illiterate mould of a
village lawyer's thought, but find it replaced by a grasp of
principle, a dignity of manner, and a solemnity of purpose which would
have been unworthy neither of Hampden nor of Cromwell, while his
<pb n="32"/>
                  <figure entity="vincent32">
                     <figDesc>32nd page of
Rev. Marvin R. Vincent's A Sermon on the Assassination of Abraham
Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
gentleness and generosity of feeling towards his foes are almost
greater than we should expect from either of them."</p>
               <p>At once the representative fact of his administration, and that
which distinguished it above any other in our history, is its
relations to the great question of human bondage. In this respect his
administration forms an era in the history of the race. The status of
the question at the time of his inauguration, and for a long time
after, was peculiar and difficult. The moral and political aspects of
the contest were brought into apparent antagonism; and the foreign
emissaries of secession had no dearer object than to prove this
antagonism real, and thus alienate from us the sympathy of
Europe. Europe, knowing slavery to lie at the root of our trouble,
expected us to strike at once at slavery. <hi rend="italic">We</hi>,
knowing the fact equally well, could, at the time, strike only at
treason. We could deal only with the immediate development, not with
the ultimate cause. The provisions of the Constitution, the divided
sentiment of the North, the hesitating attitude of the border States,
the general ignorance of the extent and maturity of the conspiracy,
made it a matter of the utmost difficulty and delicacy. The Pre
<pb n="33"/>
                  <figure entity="vincent33">
                     <figDesc>33rd page of
Rev. Marvin R. Vincent's A Sermon on the Assassination of Abraham
Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
sident clearly appreciated the source of the difficulty, and, as the
result showed, had its removal as deeply at heart as any man. Hence,
at Philadelphia, prior to his inauguration, he remarked: "I have often
inquired of myself what great principle or idea it was that kept this
confederacy so long together. It was something in the Declaration of
Independence, giving liberty not only to the people of this country,
but hope to the world for all coming time. It was that which gave
promise that in due time the weights should be lifted from the
shoulders of all men, and that all should have an equal chance. If
this country cannot be saved without giving up that principle, I was
about to say <hi rend="italic">I would rather be assassinated upon the
spot than surrender it</hi>." I need not follow the great question
through the history of its solution. The world will bear testimony to
the cautious, far-seeing wisdom with which he dealt with it. History
will do justice to the man who could make impulse, however high and
generous, stand back for duty. It will bear witness to the faith which
could wait as well as labor; which was content to let the result come
out in the slow grinding of the mills of God, without putting forth
<pb n="34"/>
                  <figure entity="vincent34">
                     <figDesc>34th page of
Rev. Marvin R. Vincent's A Sermon on the Assassination of Abraham
Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
his hand to quicken the machinery. It will record how sacredly he
respected the Constitutional rights of the South; how timely were his
warnings; how liberal his solicitations, until at last, when he saw
that God's purpose was ripe, when, having kept adroitly in the rear of
events, yet having so employed them as to make the full power of the
popular wave bear him to his goal, he rose in his might, and with a
word that echoed through the world, the fetters fell forever from the
slave. How a great moral act like this looms up amid the political
developments of the age, and those things which more directly touch us
as individuals--questions of financial policy, learned diplomatic
correspondence, generals, victories, deeds of individual heroism,
party triumphs. For when state volumes shall be mouldering in
libraries, and the soldiers' children's children playing with his
rusty sword and asking its story, when the names of old political
parties shall be obsolete, and the issues which created them
forgotten, this fact shall be fresh in the nation's memory. Abraham
Lincoln signed the death warrant of American slavery. Thank God, "the
past at least is secure." What he has done in this matter will not be
undone. The moral
<pb n="35"/>
                  <figure entity="vincent35">
                     <figDesc>35th page of
Rev. Marvin R. Vincent's A Sermon on the Assassination of Abraham
Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
sentiment of the nation, educated by the stern discipline of war and
sorrow, has followed up the blow and clinched the nail, and to-day one
mighty will pulsates from East to West, that this curse shall be no
more. Shut close thine accursed door, oh! slave mart. Stand in the
midst of the Southern cities, a monument of a past barbarism, a
haunted place past which the belated wayfarer shall hasten, and whose
story of horror shall be told with bated breath. Where the
auctioneer's hammer sealed the doom of humanity and virtue, let the
rank grass grow, and scorpions lurk, and silence brood, and over its
door let it be written-"<hi rend="italic">Aceldama</hi>." Lie still, oh!
slave ship, in thy port, thou whose every plank and timber is seasoned
with bitter tears; lie still and rot in the blistering sun; let the
foul slime and ooze gather about thy keel, and the crawling things of
the deep, foul shapes that fishers' line never brought to light, lurk
in thy shadow; and let the breeze refuse to fill thine idle sails, and
no traitorous wind ever send thee lessening down the west on thy
mission of woe. Pile the fetters into the furnace, and let the molten
flood pour forth into moulds of plow and pruning-hook wherewith the
ransomed man shall bring beauty
<pb n="36"/>
                  <figure entity="vincent36">
                     <figDesc>36th page of
Rev. Marvin R. Vincent's A Sermon on the Assassination of Abraham
Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
out of the wilderness, and train the clustering vines of the South
over his cabin, his home, his castle, on whose threshold he shall have
a man's right to stand and keep the destroyer from his flock. This
land at least cannot, dare not renew the curse. It dare not cancel the
charter to which Abraham Lincoln set his hand. His great shade would
rise from the grave in its fiery indignation. No, the hand cannot be
found that shall rivet the chains again, and this deed of his shall
stand in time to come, a monument more enduring than brass, whose
inscription angels shall pause to read on their messages of peace.</p>
               <p>But he could not be spared to us longer. His work here was
done. Heaven had new and higher purposes concerning him which it does
not reveal to us; and now that he has been so mysteriously and
suddenly snatched from us, it becomes us to ask with all due
reverence, "What does it mean?"</p>
               <p>He must be presumptuous indeed who shall assume to interpret such a
providence, and to say for what end this blow hath fallen. We can do
little more than sit reverently at God's closed gates, and wait until
He shall tell us more. Yet there are some thoughts so naturally
suggested to us that we should not be justified in wholly passing them
by.</p>
               <pb n="37"/>
               <p>
                  <figure entity="vincent37">
                     <figDesc>37th page of
Rev. Marvin R. Vincent's A Sermon on the Assassination of Abraham
Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <p>The juncture at which the event occurred is significant. The
President was fully committed to a vigorous prosecution of the war,
and to the submission of the rebels as the first condition of
peace. He was re-elected on this basis over a man who, in all human
probability, would have stopped the war where it was, patched up an
unrighteous peace, and left the whole fundamental question open for
our children to settle. Lincoln lived to see his policy carried
out--the military power of the rebellion broken; and almost at the
very hour of this consummation his life was cut short. I accept this
as an indication that his work as an instrument of Providence ended
here, and that the work of reconstruction belonged to other and
doubtless fitter instruments. I will not positively assert that his
policy toward traitors was so much too lenient that God replaced him
by a man who, we have good reason to think, will not err in this
direction. Yet I say that this may be so, and that it looks like
it. Mr. Lincoln was a man whose policy was formed in the light of
events, and in this instance it had not had time to develop itself
fully; but I have no hesitation in saying that in so far as it had
developed itself, it was setting, in my opinion, much too strongly
<pb n="38"/>
                  <figure entity="vincent38">
                     <figDesc>38th page of
Rev. Marvin R. Vincent's A Sermon on the Assassination of Abraham
Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
in the direction of lenity and conciliation. We may talk as we will
about the great right of freedom of speech, but if this right be
admitted to be unlimited at all times, I cannot see but that a popular
government like this deliberately exposes itself to the most
mischievous of all results--a perverted public opinion. I see nothing
in the letter or spirit of the Constitution which should prevent such
men as Vallandigham and the Woods, and others who might be named,
whose treason was open and blatant, and who, from their public
position and influence, were enabled to divide the North, and give aid
and comfort to our enemies--nothing which should prevent their mouths
being stopped, and they themselves being put beyond the possibility of
doing further mischief. And as for the leading traitors of the
South--the men who struck their blow deliberately and with malice
aforethought, who, for years before the overt act, were digging their
mines and laying their train, I call upon the Christian justice and
common sense of this nation to show cause why they should not suffer
the extreme penalty of the law? Do we not yet realize the full
significance of their crime? Have we been so free from the damning
crime of
<pb n="39"/>
                  <figure entity="vincent39">
                     <figDesc>39th page of
Rev. Marvin R. Vincent's A Sermon on the Assassination of Abraham
Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
treason, that we do not yet recognize it, even when it comes to us
without pretence of disguise? Do we realize the murder and outrage and
desolation that have followed in its track? and are we to stand here
to-day and clasp their bloodstained hands in ours, and welcome back to
fellowship those who only want the opportunity to renew their devilish
work? For one, I say <hi rend="italic">no</hi>! In simple justice no! We
have been all along discussing this question on the basis of the right
or wrong of retaliation, forgetting that that question does not enter
into the consideration at all. The question is simply whether we will
put in force the laws against treason which we have made for our own
protection. We forget that, in the words of our present Executive,
lenity to the few may be injustice to the many. By an indiscriminate
lenity we shall only be setting so many vipers loose to sting and to
poison. It was the spirit of the <hi rend="italic">conquered</hi> South
that smote down the President. The hatred of free institutions, and
the spirit of revenge and malice have not died out with the military
power of the rebellion. They are as strong to-day in the crushed and
humbled South as on the morning when its bastard Palmetto first waved
over Sumter. The snake is
<pb n="40"/>
                  <figure entity="vincent40">
                     <figDesc>40th page of
Rev. Marvin R. Vincent's A Sermon on the Assassination of Abraham
Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
scotched, but not killed. We owe something to justice as well as to
mercy. Something to self-protection as well as to forgiveness; and in
the name of this bleeding country, in the name of our maimed and
starved soldiers, in the name of our blighted hearts and homes, I call
upon government to put in force against these leading traitors the
penalty of' the law. And I would their gibbet were so high that every
man North and South might see it from his housetop, and learn as he
looks that treason is not safe for the perpetrator: high enough for
the despots of Europe, and its statesmen who have longed for the fall
of the Republic, to learn that the Republic has yet strength enough
and self-respect enough to punish terribly those who strike at her
vitals. Citizens of this community, gathered here to-day, let this be
our last experience in the toleration of treason. It has been allowed
too much liberty heretofore. It is time its mouth was stopped. If we
cannot stop it at the South, we can at least stop it here. Nothing
less than this is our duty; and let us go forth from this place
resolved to foster a public sentiment that shall from this time forth
sternly silence the press or the man, no matter what his position,
that dares to lift up a voice in favor of extenuation of treason.</p>
               <pb n="41"/>
               <p>
                  <figure entity="vincent41">
                     <figDesc>41st page of
Rev. Marvin R. Vincent's A Sermon on the Assassination of Abraham
Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <p>As another lesson, we are taught to respect our own government
more; to cherish it more fondly than ever. What has it done for us in
the present crisis? There are nations where such an event would have
blocked the wheels of legislation, and thrown all things into direst
confusion. To-day government moves on without a break or jar. Ere the
nation's ruler is scarce cold in death, his successor steps quietly
into his vacant place, without a movement or a remonstrance from the
great nation. And the nation itself but falls back a pace to let the
retiring leader's bier pass out, to look for one moment on his beloved
face, to exchange a word on his many virtues, and then closes up fast
and firm round his successor, with a sterner determination to push its
great work to its completion.</p>
               <p>Again we are reminded "Little children keep yourselves from idols."
As much as any other people we are hero-worshipers. With all our
vaunted independence, popular leaders sway us mightily. All through
this conflict God's voice has been saying to us, as one after another
of our trusted champions bit the dust., "Put not your trust in
princes," I tremble when I hear men 
<pb n="42"/>
                  <figure entity="vincent42">
                     <figDesc>42nd page of
Rev. Marvin R. Vincent's A Sermon on the Assassination of Abraham
Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
say, "Grant is left. Sherman is left. Sheridan and Thomas are left."
God wants this nation to trust in Him, and in Him only. He comes to us
to-day in our heart-sickness, and asks us if we think any man or body
of men is indispensable, and dictates to us our lesson again, <hi rend="italic">The Lord reigneth! Let the earth rejoice</hi>." And when
our leaders fall, he bids us not to be looking back to the ranks,
anxiously and tearfully asking: "What shall we do now?" but forward to
where his pillar of fire moves steadily on through the night in solemn
and mysterious majesty, and saying to our fainting hearts, "<hi rend="italic">God is left</hi>! and in the name of the Lord will we set
up our banners."</p>
               <p>And this event draws us more closely together. Around the coffin of
our beloved dead we clasp hands, and feel shoulder touch shoulder, and
even amid the bitterness of this bereavement it is a blessed thing to
know that we are more nearly one than ever. If the South had striven
to select the act which of all others should concentrate the sentiment
of the North against her, which should commit the whole people
irrevocably to the completion of the work they have taken in hand,
they could not have made a happier choice. If anything were needed to
teach a certain class
<pb n="43"/>
                  <figure entity="vincent43">
                     <figDesc>43rd page of
Rev. Marvin R. Vincent's A Sermon on the Assassination of Abraham
Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
of Northern men the true nature and tendencies of the cause they have
been secretly favoring, this deed has supplied the want. Henceforth,
brothers, we go forth more unitedly to our work. Henceforth the lines
are more sharply drawn. Henceforth we know but two classes--loyal men
and traitors. Northern men with Southern principles, I tell you your
skirts are not clear of the President's blood. You have fostered the
spirit which struck the blow. You have apologized for it. You have
fretted and been angry at those who would insist that slavery was at
the root of that carelessness of human right and human life, that mad
ambition, that aristocratic folly which precipitated the country into
war. And now the result has justified them. This last deed has crowned
the catalogue which has been running up so rapidly for four years
past; and I do most of you the credit to believe that from this, its
last work, you shrink aghast. I do you the justice to believe that
your hearts equally with mine condemn this deed. I could not believe
otherwise and believe you men. And now, by the open grave of the
nation's President, amid the tears of the people, by every
consideration of national honor and self-respect, I entreat you to
<pb n="44"/>
                  <figure entity="vincent44">
                     <figDesc>44th page of
Rev. Marvin R. Vincent's A Sermon on the Assassination of Abraham
Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
look upon the legitimate fruit of Southern principles, and from this
time forth, in the name of God and humanity, come out from among them
and be separate, and touch not the unclean thing.</p>
               <p>And still we linger by the open grave. One look more ere the clods
fall and the tomb enfolds him in its cold embrace. Is it not some
ghastly nightmare--some dreadful dream from which we shall awake by
and by to find the nation still undisgraced by murder, and him still
at the helm? Alas, alas! the cold reality will not depart at our
bidding. Abraham Lincoln is dead. Gone from a nation's burdens and a
nation's love. Stricken down in the fore front of the battle; his
great work done, yet with his armor on, in the high noon of a noble,
successful, God-fearing manhood. And by that sterling worth, that
simple piety, that kindness and tenderness, that never faltering faith
in God and humanity, he, being dead, yet speaketh. Aye, speaketh. I
hear his voice come down to us from the tranquil heights of his
eternal rest, bidding us be true to ourselves, true to our national
idea, true to freedom, true to God, daring to be just though the
Heavens fall. I hear him saying to the nation: "Away with
<pb n="45"/>
                  <figure entity="vincent45">
                     <figDesc>45th page of
Rev. Marvin R. Vincent's A Sermon on the Assassination of Abraham
Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
these idle tears, these vain regrets; ye have no time now for
lamentation;</p>
               <lg type="stanza">
                  <l>'The day of the Lord is at hand, at hand,</l>
                  <l>Its storms
roll up the sky.'</l>
               </lg>
               <p>and the meekest of saints may find stern work to do. Up and be
doing!"</p>
               <p>We hear thee beloved leader, and here, beside thy tomb, we put off
our sackcloth and ashes and take our armor to ourselves again. We turn
our faces to the future, and from under the shadow of this
dispensation we go forth with girded loins and trimmed lamps and in
God's strength to work out our destiny. We leave thee with God on thy
mount of vision, and press on at the beck of our new leader to that
promised land which thou sawest from afar, but wert not permitted to
enter; press on, bearing the inspiration of thy courage into battles
yet to come. And thou shalt be gloriously avenged one day. Thou shalt
be avenged when our Union, the object of thy dearest desire, shall
stand cemented anew, "now and forever, one and inseparable." Thou
shalt be avenged in every look which down-trodden humanity shall send
across the sea to our land, then, as never before, the home of the
oppressed. Thou shalt be
<pb n="46"/>
                  <figure entity="vincent46">
                     <figDesc>46th page of
Rev. Marvin R. Vincent's A Sermon on the Assassination of Abraham
Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
avenged when one heart and one mind shall animate the people; when
Americans shall know no North, no South, and one starry flag, the dear
old banner which was the joy of thine eyes, cover with its ample folds
the children of those who now thirst for each others blood. Thou shalt
be avenged when the echo of war shall have died out from our
hillsides, and the war desolated land be blossoming like a paradise
beneath the willing hand of free industry. Thou shalt be avenged when,
beneath the Palmetto's shade, Africa's sons shall teach their children
to lisp thy name, and bedew thine immortal charter with their grateful
tears. Oh! even amid the grand realities which ere this have dawned
upon thy vision, thou shalt not surely be so far removed from sympathy
with the land thou lovedst and diedst for, that thou wilt not follow
her career with thy spirit gaze, and smile with heavenly joy, when
thou shalt see peace within her walls and prosperity within her
palaces. And so, till our work be done, and we follow thee into the
silence, we bid thee farewell. Sleep! beloved ruler! Rest! great,
tender, careworn heart! Sleep sweetly in the bosom of the West, while
the gratitude of the downtrodden and the love of the nation gather
like clustering
<pb n="47"/>
                  <figure entity="vincent47">
                     <figDesc>47th page of
Rev. Marvin R. Vincent's A Sermon on the Assassination of Abraham
Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
vines round thy tomb, and thy monument points through the years to
Heaven, telling the oppressed of a liberator and the tyrant of an
avenger.</p>
               <lg type="stanza">
                  <l>"Uplifted high in heart and hope are we,</l>
                  <l>Until we
doubt not that, for one so true</l>
                  <l>There must be other, nobler
work to do,</l>
                  <l>And victor he must ever be. </l>
                  <l>For tho' the
giant ages heave the hill,</l>
                  <l>And break the shore, and evermore</l>
                  <l>Make and break and work their will;</l>
                  <l>Tho' worlds on
worlds in myriad myriads roll </l>
                  <l>Round us, each with different
powers,</l>
                  <l>And other forms of life than ours, </l>
                  <l>What know
we greater than the soul?</l>
                  <l>On God and godlike men we build our
trust.</l>
                  <l>Hush! The dead-march wails in the people's ears: </l>
                  <l>The dark crowd moves, and there are sobs and tears;</l>
                  <l>The
black earth yawns; the mortal disappears; </l>
                  <l>Ashes to ashes, dust
to dust: </l>
                  <l>He is gone who seemed so great, </l>
                  <l>Gone, but
nothing can bereave him </l>
                  <l>Of the force he made his own </l>
                  <l>Being here, and we believe him </l>
                  <l>Something far advanced in
state</l>
                  <l>And that he wears a truer crown</l>
                  <l>Than any wreath
that man can weave him.</l>
                  <l>But speak no more of his renown, </l>
                  <l>Lay your earthly fancies down </l>
                  <l>And in the vast cathedral
leave him;</l>
                  <l>God accept him--Christ receive him."</l>
               </lg>
            </div2>
         </div1>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI.2>