<TEI.2>
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt n="National Disappointment.  A Discourse Occasioned by the Assassination of President Lincoln.">
            <title>  National
Disappointment.  A Discourse Occasioned by the Assassination of
President Lincoln.  </title>
            <author>Bingham, Joel F.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Compiled and edited by</resp>
               <name>Beck
Center</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent/>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Lewis H. Beck Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Emory University</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Atlanta,
Georgia</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>1996 Emory
University. Permission is granted to download, transmit, or otherwise
reproduce, distribute or display the contributions to the work claimed
by Emory University for non-profit educational purposes, provided
this header is included in its entirety.  For inquiries about
commercial uses, contact the Director, 
Pitts Theology Library, Emory
University, Atlanta, Georgia 30322</p>
            </availability>
            <date>1999</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Lincoln
Sermons Project</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Bingham, Joel
F. National Disappointment.  A Discourse Occasioned by the
Assassination of President Lincoln.  Delivered in Westminster Church,
Buffalo, Sunday Evening, May 7th, 1865.  Buffalo: Breed, Butler and
Company, 1865.  </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This text derives from the Special Collections 
of Pitts Theology Library, Emory University, and is produced in 
collaboration with the Lewis H. Beck Center a, the Emory 
Preservation Office, and Pitts Theology Library.</p>
            <p>TRANSCRIBER: Lewis H. Beck Center and Emory University 
Preservation Office.</p>
            <p>PRODUCER:  BookLab, Inc., 1606 Headway Circle, 
Suite 100, Austin, TX 78754</p>
            <p>CAPTURE DEVICE: XEROX DocuImage 620S flatbed scanner</p>
            <p>CAPTURE DETAILS: Scanner software: XEROX ScanTool 
version 4.2.3; no gamma correction; images are all bitonal.</p>
            <p>CHANGE HISTORY: Using the Adobe Photoshop Batch Processor, 
we interpolated  the original TIFF files to 8-bit grays, 
and altered the resolution to 144 dpi, producing screen 
images twice the original size.  We then saved them in 
JPEG format.  We produced GIF thumbnails from the JPEG files.</p>
            <p>RESOLUTION: 600 ppi</p>
            <p>COMPRESSION: Resolution 144 per inch with Constrain 
Properties to 72 per inch.</p>
            <p>SOURCE: Original documents.</p>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>1999</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Scott Ellis</name>
               <resp>Staff</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <item>SGML tags inserted in compliance
with TEI guidelines using TEILITE</item>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div1 id="bingham.001" n="National Disappointment.  A Discourse Occasioned by the Assassination of President Lincoln." type="text">
            <head pn="1"> 
               <bibl> 
                  <title> National Disappointment.  A Discourse Occasioned
by the Assassination of President Lincoln.</title> 
                  <date>Sunday, May 7th, 1865</date>
                  <pubPlace>Westminster Church, Buffalo, NY</pubPlace> 
                  <author>Bingham,
Joel F.</author> 
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Buffalo, NY</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Breed, Butler and Company</publisher>
                     <date>1865</date>
                  </imprint> 
               </bibl> 
            </head>
            <p pn="1">
               <figure entity="bingham1">
                  <figDesc>1st page of Joel Bingham's
National Disappointment.  A Discourse Occasioned by the Assassination
of President Lincoln.</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <p pn="1">National Disappointment</p>
            <p pn="1">A</p>
            <p pn="1">DISCOURSE</p>
            <p pn="1">OCCASIONED BY THE </p>
            <p pn="1">ASSASSINATION OF PRESIDENT LINCOLN</p>
            <p pn="1">DELIVERED IN WESTMINSTER CHURCH, BUFFALO,</p>
            <p pn="1">SUNDAY EVENING, MAY 7TH, 1865</p>
            <p pn="1">BY JOEL F BINGHAM</p>
            <p pn="1">PASTOR OF THE CONGREGATION</p>
            <p pn="1">BUFFALO: <lb/>BREED, BUTLER AND COMPANY. 
<lb/>
1865</p>
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p pn="2">
               <figure entity="bingham2">
                  <figDesc>2nd page of
Joel Bingham's National Disappointment.  A Discourse Occasioned by the
Assassination of President Lincoln.</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <p pn="2">FRANKLIN PRINTING HOUSE</p>
            <p pn="2">THOMAS, TYPOGRAPHER</p>
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p pn="3">
               <figure entity="bingham3">
                  <figDesc>3rd page of
Joel Bingham's National Disappointment.  A Discourse Occasioned by the
Assassination of President Lincoln.</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <div2 id="bingham.002" n="DISCOURSE" type="sermon">
               <head pn="3">DISCOURSE.</head>
               <epigraph pn="3">
                  <p pn="3">I WILL BRING THE BLIND BY A WAY THAT THEY KNEW NOT.-ISAIAH
XLII, 16.</p>
               </epigraph>
               <p pn="3">No other fact has been more conspicuous upon the face of society
among us, during the progress of the war that is now closing, than the
constantly spreading and deepening sentiment of our national
dependence on the allotments of the Divine Hand. We have learned, with
all our fellow-countrymen, during the last four years, as we never
before understood it, the uncertainty of human calculations, and the
double blindness of human self-sufficiency, conceit and
independence. Inexorable and repeated disappointments have taught us
the most careful estimates and the most sanguine expectations, now
immeasurable cut short, and then immeasurably outrun, have taught us,
<pb n="4"/>
                  <figure entity="bingham4">
                     <figDesc>4th page of Joel
Bingham's National Disappointment.  A Discourse Occasioned by the
Assassination of President Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
thoroughly at last, that God, above all earthly forces, still directs
the destinies of this world, and, by an inscrutable and irresistible
Providence, WILL BRING BLIND MEN INTO HIS PURPOSES, (<hi rend="italic">nationally as well as individually</hi>,) BY A WAY THEY
KNEW NOT.</p>
               <p pn="4">At the outset of the rebellion, we were both unwilling and unable
to believe that a civil war among us would ever actually come, till
the sudden bombardment and fall of Sumter thrilled, like lightning,
through the national heart, in the terrible conviction 'that civil war
was already begun. So, the blind eyes of the people were then opened,
so far as to see that the incredible crisis was upon us, and their
heart was so far fired, as to rouse them to gird themselves for the
dreadful strife. But the magnitude of the treason which was on foot,
and the time and force which would be required to crush it was not
then perceived, and only dawned on our dull vision in the mortifying
and overwhelming defeat of the national arms at Bull Run. Thus, again,
we were strained to the sending of those huge armies into the field
which have swept with desolation from
<pb n="5"/>
                  <figure entity="bingham5">
                     <figDesc>5th page of Joel
Bingham's National Disappointment.  A Discourse Occasioned by the
Assassination of President Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
the Potomac to the Gulf, and have destroyed at once the status of
Rebellion and the status of Slavery. Slavery, however, even then, we
meant not to disturb, and commander after commander was removed in
disgrace for smiting it, even as a military blow upon the strength of
the public enemy. But the tedious and unsuccessful campaigns in
Virginia, the dreadful disasters on the Peninsula, before
Fredericksburg, in the Valley of the Shenandoah, and especially the
alarming irruptions of the rebel armies into Pennsylvania and
Maryland, threatening the destruction of Washington, and even of our
great northern cities-- it was this terrible path of God which brought
us, in the peril of our existence, to lift our hand with the might of
despair, and sweep utterly from our soil that accursed system of wrong
under which rebellion was born, and by which it was mightily fostered,
even in its grapple upon the throat of our liberties. By such bitter
disappointments and terrors, were the President and the nation nerved
up to utter, (with doubt and hesitation,) the immortal proclamation of
January 1, 1863, by which the heathenish shackles were
<pb n="6"/>
                  <figure entity="bingham6">
                     <figDesc>6th page of Joel
Bingham's National Disappointment.  A Discourse Occasioned by the
Assassination of President Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
knocked at a blow from four millions of wretched fellow-beings, at
whose outrageous wrongs humanity had wept for ages, though powerless
to break the tremendous strength, or alleviate the horrors of their
iron bondage. See then, fellow citizens, in these bitter surprises,
how gloriously God has led us, in our blindness, by a way of His own
that we knew not.</p>
               <p pn="6">But these things are now securely past. We have been coming, in
these preparatory remarks, to speak of our recent tremendous surprise
and grief. For surely we expected no such thing. We have been equally
confounded with amazement, and crushed with sorrow. We did not dream
that the path along which God was leading us, already actually
emerging, as it seemed, forever, from the darkness and peril under
which we had wept for four long years-we did not dream that this path
of Providence, already so cheering, and brightening every day with the
realization of our best hopes, was to turn again into the gloom of
that bitter sorrow which overspreads the land. That the great and good
man whom we all delighted to
<pb n="7"/>
                  <figure entity="bingham7">
                     <figDesc>7th page of Joel
Bingham's National Disappointment.  A Discourse Occasioned by the
Assassination of President Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
honor--that the twice chosen President of the now regenerated
nation--the President, beyond all question, who was beloved with a
tenderer affection, and a more nearly unanimous sentiment among the
people, than any other who has occupied that seat of power and of
popular criticism, save, perhaps, the first, the unopposed, the
uncompared, the solitary Washington, who is now henceforth to divide
his glory with this second object of a nation's eternal veneration--a
man, too, not only of rare and tried wisdom, of an integrity as high
as heaven above every bribe, and of a patriotism burning like the
flame of life itself, but a man so gentle, so conciliatory and
forgiving, so unwilling to inflict pain even upon the guilty--a man of
such transparent honesty, of such child-like simplicity--the very
embodiment of every kind and sweet and almost womanly virtue of our
nature--that this man, the embodiment, also, of the supreme authority
of the nation, God's anointed over us--truly, but a few days ago,
nothing short of an accredited prophecy from the skies could have made
us believe that this incomparable President, this intensely beloved
man,
<pb n="8"/>
                  <figure entity="bingham8">
                     <figDesc>8th page of Joel
Bingham's National Disappointment.  A Discourse Occasioned by the
Assassination of President Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
this representative of our national power and our national life-that
he would fall a murdered victim to the bloody work of a political
assasin. When the terrible news first sounded in our ears we could not
believe the tidings. We can now scarcely credit the testimony of our
senses. But for three live-long weeks we have been dwelling in the
midst of weeds. Every home in the land has been draped in
mourning. The temples of public authority, law and justice, and the
sanctuaries of religion of every name, from Maine to Louisiana, stand
robed in black. We have all witnessed and mingled in the funeral
cortege, magnificent in signs of woe. Many of us have gazed with our
eyes upon the blackened ruin, fast crumbling back into unrecognizable
dust--all of the nation's Deliverer and Slavery's Destroyer which the
murderer's work has left to a mourning people.</p>
               <p pn="8">Now we have to ask <hi rend="italic">what that new light is which God
has just made to dawn on our slow vision by this new and terrible turn
in the path of his Providence</hi>. The occasion of such mighty
mourning--a nation bowed, and each man for himself bowed in the agony
of
<pb n="9"/>
                  <figure entity="bingham9">
                     <figDesc>9th page of Joel
Bingham's National Disappointment.  A Discourse Occasioned by the
Assassination of President Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
a personal bereavement--what has this revealed to us which, in our
blindness, we were before overlooking? What now are the new, or at
least newly reiterated and reemphasized facts which these blackened
heavens are thundering in the ears of the nation?</p>
               <p pn="9">Why, in the first place, what all good men have been slow to read,
and unwilling to read, but are now compelled to read in letters of
blood and fire in the heavens--<hi rend="italic">that the animus of this
rebellion--the spirit which gave it life, and which has been its
living principle ever since</hi>--IS ABSOLUTELY HELLISH TO THE LAST
DEGREE. For it were useless to attempt to shield the cause of
rebellion, from responsibility for, and complicity with, this last
supreme culmination of its guilt and murder. It were useless to talk
of this deed, which has shocked and disgusted the world, as merely the
individual guilt of a maddened villain. Supposing, for a moment, that,
in point of fact, it had been so, (which is now officially proven to
have been far otherwise,) yet then, even, what must have been the
seed, the atmosphere, the culture which could germinate and ripen this
accursed fruit! 
<pb n="10"/>
                  <figure entity="bingham10">
                     <figDesc>10th page of Joel
Bingham's National Disappointment.  A Discourse Occasioned by the
Assassination of President Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
No good cause, no laudable spirit, no worthy end could inspire a man
to such devilish deeds. The cause, its spirit, its end are
unmistakably set forth, before heaven and earth, in the fiendish
champion and his fiendish work.</p>
               <p pn="10">But the almost incredible truth has been made as clear as
noonday-the unwelcome evidence has rolled up in masses of terrible
light over innumerable enterprises and deeds of darkness, till one
must be more sightless than the blind who does not see, to-day, that
the nameless act of April 14th was but striking a higher and more
conspicuous note in the same dreadful harmony of hell, which has been
playing, half-muffled and in the distance, for the last four years,
the name of which is "Revenge and Ruin." The accomplishment of this
very deed was but narrowly escaped, at Baltimore, four years ago. That
attempt was, indisputably, in the hands of the leaders of revolt. It
was intended to forestall the inevitable struggle, and render an
appeal to arms impossible. Six months ago, when re-election was
certain, it was coolly advertised for, in the newspapers, at a
magnificent reward. 
<pb n="11"/>
                  <figure entity="bingham11">
                     <figDesc>11th page of Joel
Bingham's National Disappointment.  A Discourse Occasioned by the
Assassination of President Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
Commencing at Selma, Georgia, (a copy of which I have seen,) the offer
was copied from paper to paper, till it had spread throughout the
South; and at least one prominent Southern journal, mentioning the
project with applause, took occasion to urge upon the attention of the
leaders, at Richmond, that a few millions appropriated in this way
would be certain to secure the fact, and would achieve more for the
cause, than hundreds of millions spent in the regular prosecution of
civilized warfare. This course, however attractive, the leaders dare
not <hi rend="italic">openly</hi> take. It was too perilous, thus to
outrage the conscience of all civilized mankind. Yet it has now
transpired that they were <hi rend="italic">privy</hi> to a most
formidable conspiracy, to prevent, in this same diabolical way, the
second inauguration on the 4th of March last, which, no thanks to
them, miscarried.</p>
               <p pn="11">Look, now, for a moment, at the Southern methods of prosecuting
their public and civilized warfare, so-called, which the late climax
of crime has powerfully illuminated. In Virginia, arsenic was thrown
into the wells, where national armies were likely to pass; and the
inhabitants of the country, whom these
<pb n="12"/>
                  <figure entity="bingham12">
                     <figDesc>12th page of Joel
Bingham's National Disappointment.  A Discourse Occasioned by the
Assassination of President Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
armies had spared in life and property, were employed to bring into
the national camps and sell to these soldiers poisoned pies and
fruit. Sheridan himself, early in the summer of 1864, barely escaped
with his life from a fatal dose received in a similar way.</p>
               <p pn="12">Throughout the territory in rebellion, and during the whole
contest, numberless murderous gangs have swept to and fro, hunting out
and chasing down, like wild beasts, every man, however unarmed,
unoffending and quiet, against whom the faintest suspicion whispered
that he still loved, and, in the bottom of his heart, still clung to,
the flag and the government of his fathers. Once caught, these
"faithful among the faithless found," whose only offence was loyalty,
were treated with every refinement of cruelty and murder. They were
butchered in the midst of their families. They were hung upon trees in
front of their own door. They were starved to death in the
forests. They were waylaid and shot from the wayside. Their houses
were set on fire over their heads, and their wives and infant children
driven naked into the night and the storm and the wilderness.</p>
               <pb n="13"/>
               <p pn="13">
                  <figure entity="bingham13">
                     <figDesc>13th page of
Joel Bingham's National Disappointment.  A Discourse Occasioned by the
Assassination of President Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <p pn="13">Our children will be compelled to read with a shudder of the wholesale
massacres of hundreds and thousands of national troops after
surrender; of wounded national soldiers, on the field of battle and in
the power of the enemy, purposely left to welter and languish, for
days, without attendance, or so much as the service of a drop of water
for their terrible thirst; of unnecessary and cruel amputations, by
rebel surgeons, with the double purpose, openly avowed, to punish and
disable; of hospitals purposely set on fire, with sick and wounded
national soldiers left, by scores, to roast and consume in the burning
building; in short, of the fortunes of battle, so terrible at the
best, savagely aggravated, in a thousand horrible ways, by the inhuman
and unheard of barbarities which this rebellion has developed.</p>
               <p pn="13">Our children and the world will read, too, with indescribable
detestation, how great and peaceful cities, far remote from the armies
in conflict, were secretly set on fire, by the skulking incendiaries
of the rebellion; of the attempted destruction of moving railroad
trains, filled with unarmed men, women and children, by similar
emissaries from the same quarter; and of the
<pb n="14"/>
                  <figure entity="bingham14">
                     <figDesc>14th page of Joel
Bingham's National Disappointment.  A Discourse Occasioned by the
Assassination of President Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
cruelest ocean piracies on record, perpetrated in ships of foreign
make and outfit, under this monstrous assumption of illegitimate
authority.</p>
               <p pn="14">But the blackest page, as it seems to me, which the whole history
of the past can show will be that on which shall stand the yet
unwritten, yet ungathered and unknown summary of <hi rend="italic">the
horrors of the rebel prisons</hi>, which confined and slowly destroyed
the soldiers captured from the national armies-- pits of torture,
where a deliberate, systematic, long protracted process of freezing,
infection and starvation was coolly and unrelentingly carried forward
upon tens of thousands of men taken in open battle, and carried
forward in connection with circumstances of brutality whose horror is
beyond expression, and which the ear of decency refuses to hear. Our
posterity will turn pale as they read that record. Mankind will
execrate the story with everlasting curses, and confess that this
alone were enough to consign the exploded slave-holders' rebellion to
the blackest abyss of human infamy.</p>
               <p pn="14">Now it should seem strange, if it were not found, (though the
evidence which has transpired all points in the opposite direction,)
nev-
<pb n="15"/>
                  <figure entity="bingham15">
                     <figDesc>15th page of Joel
Bingham's National Disappointment.  A Discourse Occasioned by the
Assassination of President Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
ertheless, it were strange, that some of the cooler heads among the
insurgent authorities should not have foreseen the reactionary effect
which a knowledge of these barbarities must of necessity work to the
prejudice of their cause, and, however careless as to the atrocities
in themselves, should not have felt compelled to put a stop to this
disgraceful and self-damaging course. But the important fact is that
these atrocities have not been stopped, in any direction, from the
beginning until now. 0n the contrary, history will be compelled to
declare, that this rebellion, from the first, has clothed itself with
every possible atrocity as with a garment. There is nothing whatever
that its partisans have scrupled to do. Unexampled perjuries, deceit
and theft, the most dreadful and extensive persecution of neighbors
and fellow citizens, piracies of the most outrageous character,
wholesale poisoning, mining of prisoners' quarters, ready for the
match, in case they were likely to be retaken, massacres, tortures,
starvation of tens of thousands of prisoners of war, the destruction
of railway trains, the conflagration of great cities full of peaceful
<pb n="16"/>
                  <figure entity="bingham16">
                     <figDesc>16th page of Joel
Bingham's National Disappointment.  A Discourse Occasioned by the
Assassination of President Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
inhabitants by the nightly torch of the incendiary, and finally, oh
heavens! the concerted butchery of the President of the United States,
by a too long tolerated play-actor!</p>
               <p pn="16">The evidence which is daily transpiring points, as we have said,
with increasing certainty to the conclusion, (hard as it is to credit
both the stupidity of the mistake and the brutality of the guilt,)
that the head and representative and for a time essentially the
dictator over the whole insurrectionary movement--the eternally
infamous Davis--that he and his coadjutors could, in a great degree,
at least, have checked and prevented this career of inhuman
proceedings, but did not; because their better judgment was clouded by
crime, and even their desire for the surest success, overpowered by a
terrible thirst for revenge--a result which might naturally enough be
expected from that spirit of hate and destruction to which they
surrendered their souls, when they entered the conspiracy to break up
and destroy this gentlest of governments and happiest of nations on
earth. This view, it must be confessed,
<pb n="17"/>
                  <figure entity="bingham17">
                     <figDesc>17th page of Joel
Bingham's National Disappointment.  A Discourse Occasioned by the
Assassination of President Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
is corroborated, also, by the reflection that the incredible
starvation horrors at the Libby Prison in Richmond, especially, to say
nothing of the corresponding horrors at Belle Isle, at Salisbury,
N. C., at Danville, Va, at Andersonville and elsewhere, must have been
dependent on the will of the President, as commander-in-chief of the
rebel forces. He must have known perfectly the facts. Whether the
cruelties were first begun by his order, or not, he could, it seems
certain, have spoken a word, or given a stroke of his pen, which would
have sent relief and life to these dying men. But this he did not
do. That word he did not speak. Their cruel and unnecessary deaths,
therefore, it is scarcely possible to deny, cry out of the ground by
thousands, and call him their relentless murderer.</p>
               <p pn="17">But there is another possible explanation of the strength and
steadiness of that unbroken current of brutalities and fiendish
deeds. We are able to suppose, that, the rebellion once under way, the
leaders were practically unable altogether to control its lawless
spirit, and restrain its hideous excesses. It is not im-
<pb n="18"/>
                  <figure entity="bingham18">
                     <figDesc>18th page of Joel
Bingham's National Disappointment.  A Discourse Occasioned by the
Assassination of President Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
probable, perhaps--though we must confess that there is not a morsel
of evidence to sustain the supposition--yet it is conceivable, at
least, that the rebelling leaders, from motives of far-sighted policy,
however malignant their passions might be, never advised to these
cruelties and brutalities, but counseled to the opposite course, and
resisted, even, the actual perpetration. We say it is conceivable that
it may have been so; and if this be the true alternative; if the
spirit of rebellion has developed a fury and madness which its leaders
could not restrain; if it has seized the bits in its teeth, and run
unmanageable into outrageous inhumanities from which its instigators
may well endeavor to extricate themselves with repudiation and shame
and alarm; if it be so; if this, rather than the other, be the true
explanation of these atrocities; yet in what respect is the situation
alleviated, whether as to the more than murderous guilt of the
instigating leaders, or as to the terrible character of the now
developed and maddened spirit of misrule and destruction? Oh, how
irreparable and eternal, is the mischief, and how unpardonable is the
thousandfold murder-
<pb n="19"/>
                  <figure entity="bingham19">
                     <figDesc>19th page of Joel
Bingham's National Disappointment.  A Discourse Occasioned by the
Assassination of President Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
ous guilt of those desperate men who have persistently roused, and
lashed into an ungovernable fury, this demoniac temper which in the
fruitless support of an abominable cause has deluged a happy continent
with human blood, and gloated over thousands of the most blissful
homes on earth covered with blight, desolation and woe! Oh, there are
crimes <hi rend="italic">so big</hi> and <hi rend="italic">so
dreadful</hi>, as almost to paralyze our sense of right and wrong, and
we stand in a kind of uncertainty and bewilderment before their
tremendous guilt! Fellow citizens, it is madness to talk of pardon and
amnesty for such men. In a civil sense they have committed the
unpardonable sin, for which there can be no forgiveness. The history
of the world has invariably shown that a weak pity for the guilty is
cruelty to the innocent. The only possible stability for our
Government, and safety for our children, depends on the irrevocable
doom of these men, who stand before heaven and earth the murderers at
once of ourselves and our liberties.</p>
               <p pn="19">But this disposal of the leaders in treason, painful and difficult
as it may be, is not the most painful, nor the most difficult aspect
of our
<pb n="20"/>
                  <figure entity="bingham20">
                     <figDesc>20th page of Joel
Bingham's National Disappointment.  A Discourse Occasioned by the
Assassination of President Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure> 
situation. It is comparatively easy, (though I confess to much
misgiving, lest the government and the nation shall prove morbidly and
dangerously merciful in this quarter, even,) yet it is comparatively
easy to deal with a few conspicuous traitors; but we shall be terribly
deceived if we imagine that this will either remove or paralyze the
dreadful and now maddened spirit of rebellion, revenge, and ruin. We
hear dangerous syrens in one quarter and another singing delusive
strains of pity and pardon. "The spirit of vengeance" against us, we
hear it said in some high conservative quarters, " the spirit of
vengeance is now quelled. The war is over. The day has gone by for
anger, severity and alarm." No assertion could be more untrue. None
could be more perilous for us to accept in such a time as this. We do
not speak of the almost indifferent masses. They did not excite the
war. But there are hearts, by hundreds, and I know not but by
thousands, in which the spirit of vengeance is not quelled, and never
will be, while they breathe in earthly air. Consider, we pray you, how
astonishingly, beyond all we were able to believe possible, the spirit
of treason and blood grew
<pb n="21"/>
                  <figure entity="bingham21">
                     <figDesc>21st page of Joel
Bingham's National Disappointment.  A Discourse Occasioned by the
Assassination of President Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
strong and spread, by the fostering care of its early fomenters, even
under the peaceful skies of our former visible unity and
fraternity. How rank and widely extended, then, must have become its
growth, under the congenial tempests and malignity of these four years
of visible separation and exasperating war? Its purposes are now
defeated, but its disposition is unchanged, except as it is now the
more frenzied by chagrin and despair. It is but a specimen of this
sublimated venom which, be it remembered, since the hopeless collapse
of their cause, and when the door of peace was already opening, has
filled our land with blacker mourning, than the united slaughters of
the whole war. From this horrible specimen Providence is calling us to
learn of the spirit which is yet to be dealt with.</p>
               <p pn="21">How long this state of things is to continue--how long this temper
of murderous treason is to remain, suppressed, indeed, but not
dead--how long it is to exist, scattered and concealed, but alive and
rankling in embittered and desperate bosoms, or perhaps fostered and
deliberative in the darkness of secret organizations-this is the first
and foremost of the
<pb n="22"/>
                  <figure entity="bingham22">
                     <figDesc>22nd page of Joel
Bingham's National Disappointment.  A Discourse Occasioned by the
Assassination of President Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
great questions on which our national destiny is now hinged; and the
tremendous interests which it involves are equalled only by the
tremendous uncertainty that hangs over it, and utterly baffles every
attempt to predict, or calculate its future developments. To await
these developments would be to await perdition. The contingency to be
instantly met, with all its uncertainties, is already upon us. Its
uncertainties constitute a great part of its peril, as well as its
demand for immediate, effectual and decisive remedies.</p>
               <p pn="22">In times like these it must be wise, then, for us and our rulers to
recall, and to be willing to take for the guidance of our conduct,
principles of safety which have been so often demonstrated, at the
cost of seas of human blood on other continents and in former
generations. We cannot afford, in days like these, to throw history
and experience aside, in order to make trial of humanitarian theories
and crude speculations. The exigency calls for well-aimed and rapid
strokes, such as the experience of the world has proved to be
efficacious and sure.</p>
               <p pn="22">Among the principles which have been
<pb n="23"/>
                  <figure entity="bingham23">
                     <figDesc>23rd page of Joel
Bingham's National Disappointment.  A Discourse Occasioned by the
Assassination of President Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
settled by the bloody experiments of all the ages, and stand written
in blood-red letters along all the pages of the past, one of the first
is, that treason, the <hi rend="italic">crimen majestatis</hi>, is not
only in its own character the supremest pitch of human guilt, but also
always contains, potentially, in its black bosom, all possible crimes;
and, by the common consent of the civilized world, whoever enters into
a treasonable conspiracy, openly takes his life in his hand, and
voluntarily sets up in the sight of all mankind, as the stake of his
success in quenching the life of his government, his own death,
poverty and infamy. Another of the principles which belong to this
same category is, that the stability of human government indispensably
requires a conviction pervading the minds of all its subjects, of the
certainty that law will be executed, penal justice inflicted, legal
equity maintained, in spite of opposition and combinations, no matter
how formidable, and at the cost, even, if necessary, of the happiness,
the reputation, the property, the life of individuals, no matter how
numerous, no matter of what station. It is also one of the stern facts
which have been estab-
<pb n="24"/>
                  <figure entity="bingham24">
                     <figDesc>24th page of Joel
Bingham's National Disappointment.  A Discourse Occasioned by the
Assassination of President Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
lished by experience, that the spirit of murder cannot be cured by
caresses. It has most commonly been the gentlest of governments, and
the most generous of rulers, that have fallen by treason and
murder. Republics, in comparison with monarchies, have ever been
notoriously insecure, and, for the most part, have been finally
destroyed by traitors from within. So, as a rule, has it been of
gentle, unsuspicious, large-hearted rulers in dangerous times. It was
not Herod, dripping with the blood of the innocents, but Julius
Caesar, the most generous of men, who fell at the foot of Pompey's
statue, by the daggers of <hi rend="italic">pardoned</hi>
conspirators. It was not the infamous Catharine de Medicis, of France,
the patroness of profligates and assassins, the instigator of the
massacre of St. Bartholomew, but it was the lovely, peerless Henry
IV., the mildest, wisest, most paternal prince France ever saw, who
fell by Ravaillac's knife, in the streets of Paris, and covered France
with unexampled mourning. It was not Philip II. of Spain, the meanest,
cruelest, darkest spirit that ever occupied a throne, but it was
William of Orange, the brave, devoted, glorious deliverer of Holland,
<pb n="25"/>
                  <figure entity="bingham25">
                     <figDesc>25th page of Joel
Bingham's National Disappointment.  A Discourse Occasioned by the
Assassination of President Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
the idol of his people, who was shot, at the door of his dining-room
at Delft, by a hired assassin of Philip. It was not the arch-traitor
Davis, hated and cursed as he was by his outlawed coadjutors, and yet
likely to get away with his life, but it was the gentle, forbearing,
forgiving, the incomparably loved and honored President Lincoln, who
received the assassin's ball, and whose untimely and cruel death has
filled every loyal heart in the land with unutterable sorrow.</p>
               <p pn="25">These principles, which ought to be worth to us, whatever our lives
and fortunes and liberties are worth, are familiar and easily
apprehended; and the inferences which of necessity follow are certain
and terrible. These principles, we say, and the stern and terrible
inferences which they carry, have just been written, anew, over the
heads of this nation, as it were, in letters of fire and blood on a
midnight sky. Nevertheless we have not recalled these things with a
view to dictate, nor with the desire that you, or that our fellow
citizens at large, should dictate in their hearts, even, much less
should clamorously prescribe to our rulers and tribunals
<pb n="26"/>
                  <figure entity="bingham26">
                     <figDesc>26th page of Joel
Bingham's National Disappointment.  A Discourse Occasioned by the
Assassination of President Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
what kind, or what measure, of punishment shall be meted out to the
various participants and abettors of this fearful but now smitten and
dying rebellion--who shall die, who shall be exiled, who disfranchised
and left at home, who, from various reasons of public expediency,
pardoned and restored. No good, as it appears to us, is to be hoped
for, but great damage is to be apprehended, from such discussion. In
the case of an ordinary, everyday crime, it is by common consent
admitted to be unwise and improper to discuss the measure of
punishment, before the constituted authorities have sifted both facts
and expediences, and passed the lawful decision. Much more must it be
so in a case like the present, of such transcendent magnitude, and of
such an unexampled character. Opinions will be sure to differ in
respect to details; partisanship is easiest kindled and passions blaze
most furiously over such personal material, and dissension cannot fail
to retard and render more uncertain that stroke of justice which all
desire to see fall, in some form, upon the guilty; while, too, the
most essential thing, and perhaps the only thing
<pb n="27"/>
                  <figure entity="bingham27">
                     <figDesc>27th page of Joel
Bingham's National Disappointment.  A Discourse Occasioned by the
Assassination of President Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
really vital to the republic is, that the stroke of retribution should
be at once sure and speedy.</p>
               <p pn="27">But, unquestionably, as the whole class of facts to which we have
just alluded, and above all the terrible fact which has brought us to
this discussion to-night, distinctly indicate, <hi rend="italic">the
danger which chiefly threatens us lies not in the direction of
severity, but in that of leniency</hi>--we are in no danger whatever
of being too severe, but we are in great danger of an easy
indifference. Severity was never a popular virtue, because its face
looks unlovely, at first sight, and, especially, to a crowd, and also
because its exercise requires of most men an effort and a
self-sacrifice which the majorities, unless stimulated by some great
excitement, like that with which God is now stimulating us, are seldom
or never ready to undertake. Unquestionably, a few weeks ago, when the
last great support of the rebellion gave way to our arms, and the
speedy end of all armed resistance to the government flashed upon our
view, then, our very success was operating to overset our safety. The
joy of final victory, the inexpressible sense of relief
<pb n="28"/>
                  <figure entity="bingham28">
                     <figDesc>28th page of Joel
Bingham's National Disappointment.  A Discourse Occasioned by the
Assassination of President Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
in every mind, and the exuberance of our rose-colored hopes,
unfortunately, but not unnaturally, went at once to melt down the
sternness of the popular heart, and efface the just sense of wrong and
danger which were still indispensable to key the national nerve up to
the thorough work of annihilating the last fragment of treason.</p>
               <p pn="28">But if, after the new and terrible light which this fearful
Providence has thrown upon the spirit and purposes of treason among
us--if, after this wholesome alarm, which has touched the minds of
millions who would not otherwise have seen, or believed, the great and
insiduous perils by which we are still encompassed--if, after all, we
now fail to put the stern and necessary and finishing hand to the
tottering and skulking remnants of this rebellion, smiting with every
most effective blow, till the last fibre of its existence is
annihilated, beyond resuscitation and beyond resurrection -then what
will be the judgment of history upon us, and who will pity our
miseries, or, should we be utterly devoured by endless treason, who
would drop a tear on
<pb n="29"/>
                  <figure entity="bingham29">
                     <figDesc>29th page of Joel
Bingham's National Disappointment.  A Discourse Occasioned by the
Assassination of President Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
the page that should record our national extinction?</p>
               <p pn="29">But, thanks to the kind efficiency of God's bitter strokes, this
will not be. Our last lesson has been enough. The American people is
ready, now, to sustain, with unflinching determination, the execution
of law and justice and expediency, both upon the shattered carcass,
and upon every existing limb, of this hideous treason; and no matter
how terrible and how extensive the application of punishment may be,
they are ready to make the welkin ring with their contented and hearty
Amen!</p>
               <p pn="29">The American Government has passed, and emerged in safety, from the
crucial test of its lawful authority and its power to maintain it. It
is settled, whether the United States be a nation, living an
indivisible unity of life, or whether it be a loose and lifeless
conglomeration of thirty-six supreme sovereignties. That troublesome
folly is no longer debatable, whether the will of a State, or of any
coalition of States, can effectually defy the authority of the
American people, as embodied in the General Government. These heresies
<pb n="30"/>
                  <figure entity="bingham30">
                     <figDesc>30th page of Joel
Bingham's National Disappointment.  A Discourse Occasioned by the
Assassination of President Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
have found their end. They have been ground to powder in the shocks of
battle, and trampled into the dust of the Southern plantations under
the terrible marches of the national armies.</p>
               <p pn="30">Above all, that cause of causes--that force behind all other
forces-that germinating power and foster-father of the States' rights
heresy -that heaven -assaulting system of sin--legalized slavery--has
been throttled in the exigencies of war, and its very carcass, in the
smoke of battle, has disappeared. This was a way of deliverance, and
advancement, which we knew not, and four years ago were too blind to
see, but by which God (glory to His name) has astonishingly brought
us.</p>
               <p pn="30">The immediate instrument by whom we have been thus led-blindly
indeed and through terrible alarms, yet safely and gloriously led-has
been, I need not say, the departed, lamented, venerated President,
whose precious dust, the nation, sobbing in the agony of bereavement,
have just followed with benedictions to the place which shall give it
an honored rest, till the morning of the resurrection He has not only
deserved to
<pb n="31"/>
                  <figure entity="bingham31">
                     <figDesc>31st page of Joel
Bingham's National Disappointment.  A Discourse Occasioned by the
Assassination of President Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
be, but he has been, the most fortunate of men. Well might the most
illustrious of emperors envy his fame. His history is sublime. His
glory is peerless.</p>
               <p pn="31">There is but one measure of greatness and glory which the American
people will ever tolerate to be used, in attempting to estimate the
grandeur of his excellence, and the brightness of his name. Upon a
monumental column, at the northeast corner of Trafalgar Square, in
London, stands, in marble, the immortal Nelson, evermore attracting
the gaze of the multitudes which are surging along at his feet, and
reminding them of patriotism, valor and glory. The opposite, northwest
corner has a similar pedestal column, but its empty top has been for
fifty years awaiting the coming hero who should be found worthy to
stand in marble beside the glorious Admiral, and divide with him the
silent instruction of the surging, admiring throng. Mount Vernon, in
the south of our land, planted on the bosom of slavery and chivalry,
has hitherto held the form of the one great glory of our nation,
whither pilgrims trod to admire the character of Washington, and
receive new
<pb n="32"/>
                  <figure entity="bingham32">
                     <figDesc>32nd page of Joel
Bingham's National Disappointment.  A Discourse Occasioned by the
Assassination of President Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
inspirations of liberty and patriotism, at his tomb. The prairie of
the north, in an atmosphere of purer freedom and sterner toil, has
been standing, an empty pedestal, in the sight of heaven, though we
knew it not, awaiting through these sixty-five years, the tomb of the
coming hero who should be worthy to divide with the Father of his
country the applause and the inspiration of posterity. The path of
patriot pilgrims will henceforth branch alike northward and southward
to the resting place equally of the Founder of American Liberty, and
of the Destroyer of American Treason and Traitorous Slavery. The two
niches of glory are now full. Let us accustom our eyes to the
glittering letters of immortality, and our ears to the golden sound
which our children's children will chant, together, to the latest
generation--WASHINGTON AND LINCOLN!  WASHINGTON AND LINCOLN!!</p>
               <p pn="32">The few great names grow greater and more glorious, as years go
by. They require the perspective of ages, to allow us to make a true
measurement of their vastness; and it is only the calm atmosphere of
written history, and the increasing light of developing truth,
<pb n="33"/>
                  <figure entity="bingham33">
                     <figDesc>33rd page of Joel
Bingham's National Disappointment.  A Discourse Occasioned by the
Assassination of President Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
which is able to bring out, and will continue more and more to bring
out, in the apprehension of mankind, their real splendor. So it has
been with WASHINGTON, the first of our golden names, so it will be
with LINCOLN, our second.</p>
               <p pn="33">There are reasons which will render this law of human glory more
sure in the second case, than it has been in the first. WASHINGTON was
a military chief-a position which always affords the best opportunity
for building up a rapid fame of the most showy and captivating
kind. He was gilded, at once, with the whole military glory of his
country's successful arms. The just departed LINCOLN, though
officially and truly commander-in-chief of the armies and navies of
the nation, controlling with marvelous firmness, sagacity and
singleness of purpose, the whole complicated machinery of this
tremendous war, and having finally organized and achieved for the
nation a general and conclusive victory, (so far as any human chief
can, reverently, be said to have organized a victory, in affairs so
immense and complicated beyond any sure calculations of man,) yet wore
no other uniform but the dress of an
<pb n="34"/>
                  <figure entity="bingham34">
                     <figDesc>34th page of Joel
Bingham's National Disappointment.  A Discourse Occasioned by the
Assassination of President Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
American citizen, he rode at the head of no armies, he remained in the
shade of his official closet, he was absorbed in thought and prayer,
he was toiling in silence at the heavy cares of civil policy, and he
was listening to the plea of the distressed. The immediate applause of
successful arms he gladly left for his faithful and illustrious
lieutenants in the field, who richly deserve their fame; while,
nevertheless, many a specific and unexpected blow which fell with
crushing weight upon the bleeding head of the rebellion was contrived
and matured in his own original and sagacious brain.</p>
               <p pn="34">Then again, WASHINGTON was not called to encounter a breath of
political prejudice, in his opening career, but rode at once to his
illustrious station, on a whirlwind of popular choice, esteem and
expectation. The just departed LINCOLN fell upon far different times,
and encountered a far different beginning. He was sharply opposed. He
was extensively and outrageously defamed. Even by his friends, he was
then but partially known, and relied on with many painful misgivings
and fears, which gave way but slowly at first, though they disap-
<pb n="35"/>
                  <figure entity="bingham35">
                     <figDesc>35th page of Joel
Bingham's National Disappointment.  A Discourse Occasioned by the
Assassination of President Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
peared more and more rapidly, as the splendor of his integrity and the
richness of his affections and the clearness of his insight and the
invincibility of his purpose and his flaming patriotism, began to form
that wonderful halo of glory which shone so brightly, at last, around
his venerated head.</p>
               <p pn="35">Another thing--which fixes a stronger impression upon
contemporaries than on posterity, and the essential splendor of which
steadily vanishes as ages go by--<hi rend="italic">the family</hi> of
WASHINGTON was old, dignified and wealthy; and these factitious
advantages, never to be despised in gilding a contemporary renown,
possessed, unquestionably, a greater influence upon the men of his
times, than they would exert among us to-day. The just departed
LINCOLN has gathered no temporary dignity from this quarter, and
while, therefore, the brightness of his name will never fade in the
least by the depreciation of such honor, on the contrary, even the
romantic enchantment that gathers about the name of Cincinnatus, taken
from the plough-field to the command and the salvation of the Roman
state, will weave its peculiar and increasing witchery
<pb n="36"/>
                  <figure entity="bingham36">
                     <figDesc>36th page of Joel
Bingham's National Disappointment.  A Discourse Occasioned by the
Assassination of President Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
of glory, around the strange, homely origin of "the people's
President."</p>
               <p pn="36">Finally, WASHINGTON <hi rend="italic">lived</hi> for his country, and
died as a great and good man would wish to die, who had no more
sacrifices to make for his fellow men. The life of the just departed
LINCOLN, after having wrought out the painful salvation of the
Republic, has been. offered, a bloody sacrifice, upon the altar of
human freedom and the happiness of his fellow countrymen. He has taken
the last degree of glory, and set above his undying name the martyr's
crown. The best who shall arise among us, in the future, may imitate,
but none can surpass him. Further than his, human effort and human
glory cannot go.</p>
               <lg type="stanza">
                  <l>"Shroud the banner! rear the cross!</l>
                  <l>Consecrate a nation's loss!</l>
                  <l>Lay the gentle son of Toil!</l>
                  <l>Proudly in his native soil;</l>
                  <l>Crowned with honor to his rest,</l>
                  <l>Bear the Prophet of the West!"</l>
               </lg>
            </div2>
         </div1>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI.2>