<TEI.2>
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt n="An Address in Commemoration of the Re-Establishment of the National Flag at Fort Sumter.">
            <title>  An Address in
Commemoration of the Re-Establishment of the National Flag at Fort
Sumter.  </title>
            <author>Boardman, Reverend George Dana</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Compiled and edited by</resp>
               <name>Beck
Center</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent/>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Lewis H. Beck Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Emory University</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Atlanta,
Georgia</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>1996 Emory
University. Permission is granted to download, transmit, or otherwise
reproduce, distribute or display the contributions to the work claimed
by Emory University for non-profit educational purposes, provided
this header is included in its entirety.  For inquiries about
commercial uses, contact the Director, 
Pitts Theology Library, Emory
University, Atlanta, Georgia 30322</p>
            </availability>
            <date>1999</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Lincoln
Sermons Project</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Boardman,
Reverend George Dana. An Address in Commemoration of the
Re-Establishment of the National Flag at Fort Sumter, April 14, 1865.
Delivered in the Meeting-House of the First Baptist Church of
Philadelphia, on the Same Day.  Philadelphia: Sherman &#x0026; Co.,
Printers.  1865.   </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This text derives from the Special Collections 
of Pitts Theology Library, Emory University, and is produced in 
collaboration with the Lewis H. Beck Center a, the Emory 
Preservation Office, and Pitts Theology Library.</p>
            <p>TRANSCRIBER: Lewis H. Beck Center and Emory University Preservation Office.</p>
            <p>PRODUCER:  BookLab, Inc., 1606 Headway Circle, Suite 100, Austin, TX 78754</p>
            <p>CAPTURE DEVICE: XEROX DocuImage 620S flatbed scanner</p>
            <p>CAPTURE DETAILS: Scanner software: XEROX ScanTool version 4.2.3; no gamma correction; images are all bitonal.</p>
            <p>CHANGE HISTORY: Using the Adobe Photoshop Batch Processor, we interpolated  the original TIFF files to 8-bit grays, and altered the resolution to 144 dpi, producing screen images twice the original size.  We then saved them in JPEG format.  We produced GIF thumbnails from the JPEG files.</p>
            <p>RESOLUTION: 600 ppi</p>
            <p>COMPRESSION: Resolution 144 per inch with Constrain Properties to 72 per inch.</p>
            <p>SOURCE: Original documents.</p>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>1999</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Scott Ellis</name>
               <resp>Staff</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <item>SGML tags inserted in compliance
with TEI guidelines using TEILITE</item>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div1 id="boardman.001" n="An Address in Commemoration of the Re-Establishment of the National Flag at Fort Sumter." type="text">
            <head> 
               <bibl> 
                  <title> An Address in
Commemoration of the Re-Establishment of the National Flag at Fort
Sumter.</title> 
                  <date>April 14, 1865</date> 
                  <pubPlace>First Baptist
Church of Philadelphia</pubPlace> 
                  <author>Boardman, Reverend George
Dana</author> 
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Philadelphia</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Sherman &#x0026; Co.</publisher>
                     <date>1865</date>
                  </imprint>
               </bibl> 
            </head>
            <p>
               <figure entity="boardman1">
                  <figDesc>1st page of Reverend George
Dana Boardman's An Address in Commemoration of the Re-Establishment of
the National Flag at Fort Sumter.</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <p>AN ADDRESS</p>
            <p>IN COMMEMORATION</p>
            <p>OF THE</p>
            <p>RE-ESTABLISHMENT OF THE NATIONAL FLAG</p>
            <p>AT FORT SUMTER,</p>
            <p>April 14, 1865.</p>
            <p>DELIVEBED IN THE MEETING-HOUSE</p>
            <p>OF THE</p>
            <p>FIRST BAPTIST CHURCH OF PHILADELPHIA,</p>
            <p>On the Same Day,</p>
            <p>BY THE</p>
            <p>REVEREND GEORGE DANA BOARDMAN,</p>
            <p>PASTOR.</p>
            <p>PHILADELPHIA:</p>
            <p>SHERMAN &#x0026; CO., PRINTERS</p>
            <p>1865.</p>
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>
               <figure entity="boardman2">
                  <figDesc>2nd page of
Reverend George Dana Boardman's An Address in Commemoration of the
Re-Establishment of the National Flag at Fort
Sumter.</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>
               <figure entity="boardman3">
                  <figDesc>3rd page of
Reverend George Dana Boardman's An Address in Commemoration of the
Re-Establishment of the National Flag at Fort
Sumter.</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <p>PHILADELPHIA, April 21st, 1865</p>
            <p>THE REV. GEORGE DANA BOARDMAN. 
	<lb/>REVEREND AND DEAR SIR: Many of the undersigned were
present at the First Baptist Church on Friday, the 14th instant,
during the impressive services there held in commemoration of the
re-establishment of the National Flag at Fort Sumter. Some of us were
also present the following Sabbath, and on Wednesday, the 19th
instant, when our joy had so suddenly been changed into mourning and
our rejoicing into deep grief.</p>
            <p>The occasion of the delivery of your noble, patriotic, and
eloquent Address being the fourth anniversary of the day when the
gallant Major Anderson and his brave compatriots were compelled to
evacuate the Fort, and being also the day and hour when, by direction
of the President of the United States, the same officer was ordered to
raise the same flag over Sumter's ruined battlements,-once more in our
possession,-rendered your remarks peculiarly fitting and
appropriate.</p>
            <p>Your words of cheer and hope, of joy and gratulation,
stirred every heart, and they deserve to be handed down to posterity,
so that future generations may know how Christians in this city felt
at such a crisis in the history of our country. We believe that at a
time when, even amid the sound of cannon and the smoke of our
battle-fields, we can behold the dawning of Peace, such sentiments as
fell from your lips should be disseminated far and wide.</p>
            <p>The reference to our beloved President was as touching and
truthful as it was eloquent, and the tribute to his eminent worth, to
his nobleness of heart and integrity of purpose, is all the dearer to
us now since the dastard hand of a traitor has deprived us, in our
time of greatest need, of his wise counsels and safe guidance.</p>
            <p>The addresses delivered by you last Sabbath and on the day
of his funeral, when the whole country was weeping and mourning as for
the death of a dearly loved parent, well deserve to be pondered over
by us in our homes,-by the quiet of our firesides.</p>
            <p>Our noble President no longer lives on earth, but he will
live forever in the hearts of the people; and in all future history
ABRAHAM LINCOLN will be known and revered as the Martyr President of
the American Republic.</p>
            <p>We therefore request a copy of your several Addresses for
publication; and, while sorrowing at the great loss we have sustained
as a Nation, we can heartily unite with you in rendering thanks to
Almighty God for the gift of so pure a patriot and for the victories
which have been achieved by the armies of the Union.</p>
            <p>We remain, with sentiments of high regard,
	<lb/>Your brethren and fellow-citizens,
<lb/>
THOMAS WATTSON,		WASHINGTON BUTCHER,<lb/>
WM. S. HANSELL		BENJAMIN BULLOCK, <lb/>JAMES
POLLOCK,		JOHN C. DAVIS, <lb/>HORATIO GATES
JONES,	CHARLES H. AUNER, <lb/>ARCH. A. MCINTYRE		STEPHEN
A. CALDWELL <lb/>JOSEPH W. BULLOCK		EDWIN HALL, <lb/>JOSEPH
F. PAGE		ALEXANDER T. LANE, <lb/>H. C. HOWELL,		ISAAC
H. O'HARRA, <lb/>S.F. HANSELL,		HENRY CLAY BUTCHER</p>
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>
               <figure entity="boardman4">
                  <figDesc>4th page of
Reverend George Dana Boardman's An Address in Commemoration of the
Re-Establishment of the National Flag at Fort
Sumter.</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <p>No. 1712 VINE
STREET, April, 25, 1865.</p>
            <p>TO THOMAS WATTSON, ESQ., WILLIAM S
HANSELL, ESQ.,
	<lb/>HON. JAMES POLLOCK, HORATIO GATES JONES, ESQ., AND
OTHERS.</p>
            <p>GENTLEMEN: Your courteous note of the 21st instant, requesting for
publication the addresses delivered in the meeting-house of the First
Baptist Church on the 14th, 16th, and 19th days of April, has been
received.</p>
            <p>Aware that the interest which attaches to these addresses
springs altogether from the grandeur of the events which occasioned
them, I accede to your generous request, feeling assured that their
imperfections will be hidden in the intensity of the gloom which
oppresses us all.</p>
            <p>I am, gentlemen, with profound respect, </p>
            <p>Your brother and townsman,</p>
            <p>GEORGE DANA BOARDMAN.</p>
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>
               <figure entity="boardman5">
                  <figDesc>5th page of
Reverend George Dana Boardman's An Address in Commemoration of the
Re-Establishment of the National Flag at Fort
Sumter.</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <div2 id="boardman.002" n="ADDRESS" type="sermon">
               <head>ADDRESS.</head>
               <p>On the night of December twenty-sixth, eighteen hundred and
sixty, a sudden stir began in the historic fort of Moultrie. Men
hurried to and fro, in silent haste, gathering together the rations,
accoutrements, ammunition, and other movable property of the fort; gun
after gun was silently spiked, and every gun-carriage burned. Last of
all, the flagstaff was cut down; for the gallant Anderson had resolved
that the staff which had once borne the Star-spangled Banner should
never bear the accursed weight of a traitor's ensign. And then the
entire garrison, numbering scarcely sixty men, crept into the boats,
and, with muffled oars, under the lustrous gaze of the full moon, sped
straight under the bows of the South Carolina guard-ship Nina, across
the sleeping waters to the securer ramparts of Sumter. The Charleston
Courier of the next day makes the following announcement: "Major
Robert Anderson, U. S. A., has achieved the unenviable distinction of
opening civil war between American citizens, by an act of gross breach
of faith. He has, under counsels of a panic, deserted his post at Fort
Moultrie, and, under false pretexts, has transferred his garrison and
military stores and supplies
<pb n="6"/>
                  <figure entity="boardman6">
                     <figDesc>6th page of Reverend
George Dana Boardman's An Address in Commemoration of the
Re-Establishment of the National Flag at Fort
Sumter.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
to Fort Sumter." <hi rend="italic">Breach of faith</hi>? In what school
of infamy had South Carolina chivalry been trained, that she could
brand the defense of the United States flag by a United States
officer, as a " gross breach of faith?" The day after the evacuation,
a little before morn, Major Anderson summoned his little force around
the flagstaff of Fort Sumter, for the purpose of raising the banner
which he had brought from Moultrie. The chaplain offered a most
fervent prayer that the God of our fathers would enable that little
garrison to maintain the honor of that flag undimmed through the fiery
ordeals which awaited, and the entire garrison responded with a deep
Amen. At twelve o'clock precisely, Major Anderson, dropping on his
knees, and holding the lines in his hands, reverently drew the
national ensign to the top of the staff, and then the entire garrison
burst forth into exultant hurras, again, again and again
repeated. That thrilling scene lives in song as well as in
history. Listen to an old man's ballad for December twenty-six,
nineteen hundred and ten:</p>
               <p>
                  <q direct="unspecified">Come, children, leave your playing this dark and stormy night;
Shut fast the rattling window-blinds, and make the fire burn bright;
And hear an old man's story, while loud the fierce winds blow, Of
gallant Major Anderson and fifty years ago.</q>
               </p>
               <p>After a recital of the evacuation, the scarred veteran
continues:</p>
               <p>
                  <q direct="unspecified">I never can forget, my boys how the next day, at noon, The drums
beat and the bands played a stirring, martial tune, And silently we
gathered round the flagstaff strong and high, Forever pointing upward
to God's temple in the sky.</q>
               </p>
               <pb n="7"/>
               <p>
                  <figure entity="boardman7">
                     <figDesc>7th page of
Reverend George Dana Boardman's An Address in Commemoration of the
Re-Establishment of the National Flag at Fort
Sumter.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q direct="unspecified">Our noble Major Anderson was good as he was brave, And he knew
without God's blessing no banner long could wave; So he knelt with
head uncovered, while the chaplain made a prayer, And as the last amen
was said, the flag rose high in air.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q direct="unspecified">Then our loud huzzas rung out, far and widely o'er the sea!  We
shouted for the Stars and Stripes, the standard of the free!  Every
eye was fixed upon it; every heart beat warm and fast, As with eager
lips we promised to defend it to the last!</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q direct="unspecified">'Twas a sight to be remembered, boys, the chaplain with his
book, Our leader humbly kneeling, with his calm, undaunted look; And
the officers and men, crushing tears they would not shed, And the blue
sea all around us, and the blue sky overhead!</q>
               </p>
               <p>Three and a half months now crept away; months of gloom and
terrible apprehension. I need not go into particulars; it is enough to
remind you that meantime Florida, Mississippi, Alabama, Georgia,
Louisiana, Texas, and North Carolina followed the example of South
Carolina, and deluded themselves with the idea that, because they had
passed ordinances of secession, they had voted themselves out of the
Union. The halls of Congress echoed with the infamous valedictories of
senators and representatives, never, I trust in God, to enter those
halls again, save as prisoners, to be impeached of high treason before
the nation's judgment bench. One bright scene alone relieved the
darkness of this horrible panorama; it was when the Old Public
Functionary, nervously swinging between the God of his fathers and the
Baal of slaveholding treason, on the fourth of March yielded the chair
of Washington to God's anointed champion of American freemen, Abraham
Lincoln, of Illinois, crowned by the Grace of God and the National Will
<pb n="8"/>
                  <figure entity="boardman8">
                     <figDesc>8th page of Reverend
George Dana Boardman's An Address in Commemoration of the
Re-Establishment of the National Flag at Fort
Sumter.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
the Moses of the New World. But I must press on with the narrative.</p>
               <p>During these three months and a half, Fort Sumter was
closely besieged. The South Carolina insurgents had strengthened the
armament of Fort Moultrie and Castle Pinckney, and erected many new
batteries, so as to place Sumter under the fire of nearly
three-fourths of a circle, mounting one hundred and forty guns in all,
many of them of very heavy calibre, while the besieging host numbered
seven thousand. They had also cut off all supplies, so that the
garrison was almost reduced to the point of starvation. On the eighth
of April they learned that Government was about to relieve the
garrison by sending supplies and reinforcements. You will be
interested, doubtless, if I recall to you some of the correspondence
which then took place. It is historic.</p>
               <p>MONTGOMERY, ALA., April 10, 1861.  <lb/>"TO GENERAL
P. G. T. BEAUREGARD,
				<lb/>Charleston, S.C.</p>
               <p>"If you have no doubt of the authorized character of the
agent who communicated to you the intention of the Washington
Government to supply Fort Sumter by force, you will at once demand its
evacuation; and, if this is refused, proceed in such a manner as you
may determine, to reduce it.</p>
               <p>" L. P. WALKER, <lb/>"Secretary of War."</p>
               <p>CHARLESTON, S.C.,
April 10, 1861.</p>
               <p>"TO HON. L.P. WALKER, <lb/>"Secretary of
War.</p>
               <p>"The demand will be made to-morrow at twelve o'clock.<lb/>
" P. G. T. BEAUREGARD."</p>
               <pb n="9"/>
               <p>
                  <figure entity="boardman9">
                     <figDesc>9th page of
Reverend George Dana Boardman's An Address in Commemoration of the
Re-Establishment of the National Flag at Fort
Sumter.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <p>"HEADQUARTERS PROVISIONAL ARMY C.S.A.,
						<lb/>CHARLESTON, S.C.,
April 11, 1861, 2 P.M.</p>
               <p>"To MAJOR ROBERT ANDERBON, <lb/>"Commanding at Fort Sumter,
Charleston Harbor, S.C.</p>
               <p>"SIR: The Government of the Confederate States have
hitherto forborne from any hostile demonstration against Fort Sumter,
in the hope that the Government of the United States, with a view to
the amicable adjustment of all questions between the two Governments,
and to avert the calamities of war, would voluntarily evacuate it
. . .  . . . But the Confederate States can no longer delay assuming
actual possession of a fortification commanding the entrance to one of
our harbors, and necessary to its defense and security.</p>
               <p>"I am, therefore, ordered by the Government of the
Confederate States to demand the evacuation of Fort Sumter. All proper
facilities will be afforded for the removal of yourself and command,
together with arms and all private property, to any post in the
United	States which you may select...My aids, Colonel Chesnut and
Captain Lee, will, for a reasonable time, await your answer.</p>
               <p>"I am, sir, very respectfully, your obedient servant,
		<lb/>"P. G. T. BEAUREGARD, <lb/>"Brigadier-General,
Commanding."</p>
               <p>"HEADQUARTERS, FORT SUMTER, S.C., <lb/>Apri1 11, 1861.</p>
               <p>"To
BRIGADIER GENERAL P. G. T. BEAUREGARD.</p>
               <p>"GENERAL: I have the honor to acknowledge the receipt of
your communication demanding the evacuation of this fort, and to say,
in reply thereto, that it is a demand with which I regret that my
sense of honor and of my obligations to my Government prevent my
compliance. Thanking you for the fair, manly, and courteous terms
proposed, I am, General,</p>
               <p>"Very respectfully, your obedient
servant,
	<lb/>"ROBERT ANDERSON, <lb/>Major U. S. Army, Commanding."</p>
               <p>HEADQUARTERS PROVISIONAL ARMY
C.S.A., <lb/>"CHARLESTON, April 11, 1861, 11 P. M.</p>
               <p>"To MAJOR
ROBERT ANDERSON, <lb/>"Commanding at Fort Sumter, Charleston, S. C.</p>
               <p>"MAJOR: In consequence of the verbal observations made by
you to my aids, Messrs. Chesnut and Lee, in relation to the condition
of
<pb n="10"/>
                  <figure entity="boardman10">
                     <figDesc>10th page of Reverend
George Dana Boardman's An Address in Commemoration of the
Re-Establishment of the National Flag at Fort
Sumter.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
your supplies, and that you would, in a few days, be starved out if
our guns did not batter you to pieces, or words to that effect; and
desiring no useless effusion of blood, I have the honor to say that,
if you will state the time at which you will evacuate Fort Sumter, and
agree that, in the meantime, you will not use your guns against us
unless ours shall be employed against Fort Sumter, we will abstain
from opening fire upon you. Colonel Chesnut and Captain Lee are
authorized by me to enter into such an agreement with you. I am,
Major,</p>
               <p>"Very respectfully, your obedient servant,<lb/>
"P. G. T. BEAUREGARD."</p>
               <p>"HEADQUARTERS, FORT SUMTER, S.C., <lb/>2.30 A.M., April 12,
1861.</p>
               <p>TO BRIGADIER-GENRAL P.G.T. BEAUREGARD.</p>
               <p>"GENERAL: I have the honor to acknowledge the receipt of
your second communication of the 11th inst., by Colonel Chesnut, and
to state, in reply, that, cordially uniting with you in the desire to
avoid the useless effusion of blood, I will, if provided with the
proper and necessary means of transportation, evacuate Fort Sumter by
noon on the 15th inst., should I not receive, prior to that time,
controlling instructions from my Government, or additional supplies;
and that I will not, in the mean time, open my fire upon your forces,
unless compelled to do so by some hostile act against this fort, or
against the flag of my Government by the forces under your command, or
by some portion of them, or by the perpetration of some act showing a
hostile intention on your part against this fort, or the flag it
bears. I have the honor to be, General,</p>
               <p>"Your obedient servant,
					 <lb/>"ROBERT ANDERSON,
 <lb/>"Major U. S. Army, Commanding."</p>
               <p>You see from this correspondence just how matters
stood. Major Anderson frankly states to the insurgents that, in
consequence of the extreme scarcity of provisions in the fort, he
would be compelled in all events to evacuate by noon of April 15th,
unless supplies for the garrison should meantime arrive. Now observe
the mad, atrocious haste
<pb n="11"/>
                  <figure entity="boardman11">
                     <figDesc>11th page of Reverend
George Dana Boardman's An Address in Commemoration of the
Re-Establishment of the National Flag at Fort
Sumter.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
with which civil war was inaugurated. Unwilling to wait till the 15th
inst., only three days, and so avert, as the rebel authorities would
have us believe, " the useless effusion of blood," and fearing, it may
be, that supplies would in the interim arrive, fifty minutes after
Major Anderson's manly note was penned, the following paper, signed by
Colonel Chesnut and Captain Lee, was put in his hands:</p>
               <p>FORT SUMTER, S.C., April 12, 1861, 3.20 A.M</p>
               <p>"SIR: By authority of Brigadier-General Beauregard,
commanding the provisional forces of the Confederate States, we have
the honor to notify you that he will open the fire of his batteries on
Fort Sumter in one hour from this time."</p>
               <p>In an hour the bombardment commenced. O, my countrymen!
what a scene then opened! I do not wonder that they did not wait till
the sun rose, dreading to have that burning eye of God witness the
inauguration of the dreadful fratricidal massacre. Fiercely thundered
for thirty-four hours the balls of one hundred and forty guns against
the walls of the doomed fortress, and fiercely replied from rampart
and casemate the guns of the little patriot band. It was a most
gallant defence. Human powers could do no more. But it was all in
vain. And from the steamship Baltic, off Sandy Hook, April 18,1861,
the heroic Anderson sent the following stirring despatch to
Mr. Cameron, then Secretary of War:</p>
               <p>"SIR: Having defended Fort Sumter for thirty-four hours,
until the quarters were entirely burned, the main gates destroyed by
fire, the gorge wall seriously injured, the magazine surrounded by
flames, and its doors closed from the effects of the heat, four
barrels and
<pb n="12"/>
                  <figure entity="boardman12">
                     <figDesc>12th page of Reverend
George Dana Boardman's An Address in Commemoration of the
Re-Establishment of the National Flag at Fort
Sumter.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
three cartridges of powder only being available, and no provisions but
pork remaining, I accepted terms of evacuation offered by General
Beauregard, being the same offered by him on the 11th inst., prior to
the commencement of hostilities, and marched out of the fort Sunday
afternoon the 14th inst., with colors flying and drums beating,
bringing away company and private property, and saluting my flag with
fifty guns.</p>
               <p>"ROBERT ANDEBSON,
							<lb/>"Major
First Artillery."</p>
               <p>Since then four years, I could almost say four centuries,
have rolled away. O God! what years of national humiliation and agony
have they been! Verily, Thou hast given us the bread of affliction to
eat and the cup of tears to drink. Thou hast led us by way of the
wilderness and the desert, through rivers of blood, and hast laid us
down in the hospital, the dungeon, and the unslabbed grave. But all
glory be to Thee! God of our fathers! Thou hast never deserted us. If,
for a small moment Thou didst seem to hide Thy face from us, it was
only that with greater mercies Thou mightest gather us together
again. Thou hast gone forth with our hosts in the day of battle. Thy
pillar of cloud has led us by day, and Thy pillar of fire by
night. And when, at times, the national heart has grown faint, and we
have felt that all was lost, Thou hast renewed before our eyes the
vision of the Hebrew Seer, and permitted us to behold on every side,
swarming over every hilltop and through every valley, Thy chariots and
steeds of fire bounding to our deliverance. And now Thou hast brought
us to see the day for which heroes have fought and sighed and prayed
and died. Thou hast girded on Thy sword, O Most Mighty! and led us
forth conquering and to conquer, till now we see this Confederacy,
born of the pit, cloven in
<pb n="13"/>
                  <figure entity="boardman4">
                     <figDesc>4th page of Reverend
George Dana Boardman's An Address in Commemoration of the
Re-Establishment of the National Flag at Fort
Sumter.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
twain, and these in twain again; its black chattel cornerstone
disallowed and rejected of its own builders; its forts wrested from
them; its capital abandoned; its legions, now routed and dying like
chaff before the Northern hurricane, now overtaken and flanked and
confronted, and caught between the upper and nether millstones, and
forced to yield up their arms, their general-in-chief a disarmed
prisoner; the arch-conspirator and ringleader himself a panting
fugitive, his brow marked of God and the nation with the red brand of
Cain.</p>
               <lg type="stanza">
                  <l>"Sing, then, unto the Lord a new song,</l>
                  <l>For He hath
done marvellous things;</l>
                  <l>His right hand and His holy arm </l>
                  <l>Hath gotten
Him the victory!</l>
                  <l>Who is like unto Thee, O Lord, among the gods?</l>
                  <l>Who is like unto Thee, glorious in holiness,</l>
                  <l>Fearful in praises,
doing wonders</l>
                  <l>Thy right hand, O Lord, is become glorious in power!</l>
                  <l>Thy right hand, O Jehovah, has dashed in pieces the enemy! </l>
                  <l>Thou
hast sent out Thine arrows, and scattered them!</l>
                  <l>Thou hast shot out
Thy lightnings, and discomfited them!</l>
                  <l>So let all Thine enemies
perish, O Jehovah!"</l>
               </lg>
               <p>To-day we have met to celebrate this great victory. "But
why," you ask me, "do you select this particular day, rather than
that, for instance, which commemorates the fall of Richmond, or the
surrender of Lee?" For this simple reason: The National Flag is the
symbol of the <hi rend="italic">National Authority</hi>. It so
thoroughly represents and even incarnates to the popular heart the
Government of which it is the symbol, that wherever the flag is, there
the Government itself
<pb n="14"/>
                  <figure entity="boardman14">
                     <figDesc>14th page of Reverend
George Dana Boardman's An Address in Commemoration of the
Re-Establishment of the National Flag at Fort
Sumter.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
is, robed in full sovereignty. It was on the 14th of April, 1861, that
the National Authority was first symbolically overthrown by the
compulsory lowering of the national flag at Fort Sumter. It is on the
14th of April, 1865, that the National Authority is symbolically
restored by the raising of the national flag on the spot where it was
first struck down, in sight, too, of the birth-place of the grand
conspiracy and of the dishonored grave of its chief sponsor. There is
profound poetry in this order of the chief magistrate of the
republic. There is a touch of nature in it which makes him and the
whole nation kin. He knew the power of emblems and symbolic acts over
the human soul. He felt, as you and I cannot help feeling, that there
is a classic decorousness, an inherent propriety, an aesthetic grace,
a religious beauty, in thus symbolically announcing to the world the
reinstatement of the national majesty on the very spot where the
national majesty was first dethroned. Nor, so far as I myself am
concerned, can I deem it a misfortune that this symbolic restoration
of the national authority takes place on the day so tenderly enshrined
in the mournful homage of many of my Christian brethren. For if ever
that holy law which all mankind had insulted and trampled on, was
magnified again and made honorable,--if ever the majesty of Jehovah's
justice and authority was vindicated amidst triumphs the most
transcendent, it was when the Son of the Highest, mercifully gathering
into His own Divine person the penalties of the race, and bowing His
head beneath the thunderbolts of Jehovah's wrath, yielded up the ghost
on the Judean cross. Meet it is that the day which celebrates the
<pb n="15"/>
                  <figure entity="boardman15">
                     <figDesc>15th page of Reverend
George Dana Boardman's An Address in Commemoration of the
Re-Establishment of the National Flag at Fort
Sumter.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
vindication of Jehovah's ordinance of earthly government, is the same
which celebrates the triumph of His celestial sovereignty.</p>
               <p/>
               <p>What now are some of the lessons which the scene
transpiring to-day at Fort Sumter teaches the ages?</p>
               <p>The first
is this: The American Republic is not a league, but a nation; not a
confederacy, but a people; not a congeries of States, but a Union;
being in fact the United States, which is but another name for the
American State. This question has long been a matter for grave
meditation among political thinkers. But now it has been decided in
the crimson court of war. That decision is this: The American Union is
a vital, organic nationality, pervaded by a common life, which binds
together in indissoluble union each and every member, thus making the
whole absolutely ONE. The Union is no mere series of States, joined to
each other by no organic bond, simply touching each other like the
grains of silex in a sand-box. Neither is the Union some vast polyp,
as many seem to imagine, capable of division and subdivision, and
still thriving on, each fragment becoming the centre of a new
life. But the American Union is a vital, throbbing, indivisible
organism; so that secession is something more than subtraction, or
even amputation: it is vivisection, suicide, murder, a death as real
as that proposed in King Solomon's order for bisecting the child
brought before him for adjudication.</p>
               <pb n="16"/>
               <p>
                  <figure entity="boardman16">
                     <figDesc>16th page
of Reverend George Dana Boardman's An Address in Commemoration of the
Re-Establishment of the National Flag at Fort
Sumter.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <p>Another lesson which the scene now transpiring at Fort
Sumter teaches, is one which is addressed to foreign
nations. Democracy has been on trial, and we see the result. When we
take into consideration the awful magnitude of the rebellion, gaining
more and more of stupendousness as time revealed more and more of its
colossal proportions; when we recall the long continuance of this
painful, desolating war, the hopes long deferred, and the terrible
defeats which ever and anon have befallen our arms; when we take into
consideration the oppressive burdens of taxation, and the enormous
rise of prices; when we remember the forebodings of oft-repeated and
merciless conscriptions; when we reflect that every widow who has lost
a husband, and every parent a child, and every family a member, has
been tempted to call in question the justice of the administration and
the righteousness of the war; when we remember how sensitive the
Americans, sons of revolutionary fathers, are to the slightest
encroachments on their personal rights as citizens, and then recall
the sonorous and everlasting oratory about constitutional rule, and
arbitrary arrests, and military despotism, and star-chamber courts,
and the ambitious schemes of the chief magistrate; when we remember
how every city and hamlet of the North has been infected with
discontented men, secretly sympathizing with the insurrection, and
doing their utmost to discourage the people and paralyze the
Government; when we remember that thousands and tens of thousands of
men have been secretly banded together as Knights of the Golden
Circle, or as Sons of Liberty, for the atrocious purpose of making
organized resistance to the powers that be; when we re-
<pb n="17"/>
                  <figure entity="boardman17">
                     <figDesc>17th page of Reverend
George Dana Boardman's An Address in Commemoration of the
Re-Establishment of the National Flag at Fort
Sumter.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
member how wide and profound at times, especially in the earlier part
of the war, has been the disaffection with the administration in the
loyal ranks themselves; when we remember how the people, sickening
with these woful scenes of carnage and desolation, have sighed for the
tranquillity and ease and beatitudes of peace; in fine, when we take
into consideration the countless and tremendous obstacles which have
stood in the pathway of our rulers in their effort to restore
everywhere the national supremacy; and, then, when we remember that,
in spite of all these tremendous obstacles, the large majority of the
people have ever been saying, even in the darkest hours: " Let this
war go on! This rebellion shall go down! We have put our hands to the
work, and, God helping us, we will not falter till we have beaten,
crushed, trampled it down, and ground it beneath our heels, till not a
microscopic splinter be left to pollute the soil over which has once
floated the Star-spangled Banner;"--when we remember all these things,
and then recall the scene now transpiring at Fort Sumter, I seem to
hear a voice of awful majesty, which shall surge like a billow of
thunder against the reef of the coming ages, exclaiming: "Democracy,
under God, is not a failure!" Never in human history has the question
concerning a republican form of government been put with such
distinctness and grandeur of consequence. Never in human history has
the question been answered with an emphasis so imperial. Henceforth,
let no defender of monarchical forms of government dare say that
Democracy is unable to rule itself! That flag, whose reinstatement we
celebrate to-day, announces to the waiting ears of earth's nations,
that the
<pb n="18"/>
                  <figure entity="boardman18">
                     <figDesc>18th page of Reverend
George Dana Boardman's An Address in Commemoration of the
Re-Establishment of the National Flag at Fort
Sumter.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
government the most capable of maintaining itself under circumstances
the most adverse, is a government administered, not by rulers born to
the throne in the line of hereditary succession, but by rulers crowned
with the free ballots of a free people. And, standing here, I echo
back with joyous pride the diapason of the cannonade which rent the
sky over Fort Sumter at noon to-day: <hi rend="italic">Long Live the
Republic!</hi> LONG LIVE THE REPUBLIC!</p>
               <p>Thoughts crowd upon me; but I must not detain you with
them. The occasion is too simple for argument, too self-suggesting and
exultant for explanation. Yet I cannot forbear alluding to a point
which the swift rush of events is forcing on our attention. "What
shall be done," you ask me, "with the insurgents in this hour of our
triumph?" A grave, perplexing, baffling question this. I implore you,
fellow citizens, to answer it calmly, with generous regard for those
who may differ from you. Learn caution, considerateness, generosity,
from our noble, thoughtful, sagacious, far-sighted, inflexibly just,
magnanimous Chief Magistrate. He who, with the blessing of the God of
hosts, has safely brought us through the wilderness to the Jordan,
will, with the same blessing, provide some means by which we shall
cross the Jordan itself, into the promised land. Unquestionably, if
ever the halter was a fit instrument for ridding the earth of
monsters, it is in the case of these murderous, fiendish traitors, who
inaugurated and guided this colossal and gory treason. But let us be
careful how we permit these miscreants to become martyrs. The veriest
caitiff that ever cowered beneath the majesty of the law may gather
around him the semblance of heroism, if you
<pb n="19"/>
                  <figure entity="boardman19">
                     <figDesc>19th page of Reverend
George Dana Boardman's An Address in Commemoration of the
Re-Establishment of the National Flag at Fort
Sumter.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
grant him the stateliness of a national gallows. On the other hand, I
cannot say to these wretched ringleaders: "I forgive you, though you
have drenched a continent in blood, desolated our hearth-stones,
massacred our brothers, husbands, fathers, sons, on the gory
battle-field, murderously imprisoned in skeleton pens, and starved and
tortured into idiotcy and a nameless grave thousands of America's
noblest heroes." I cannot say to such men as Davis, and Benjamin, and
Toombs, and Breckinridge, and Cobb,--men who traitorously plotted
treason while clad in the robes of the American Senate and Hall of
Deputies, and murderously lighted the torch that should lay in ashes
our republican nationality: "Come back into our national embrace, and
we will treat you as though you had always been an Ellsworth, a Lyon,
a Baker, a Winthrop, a Birney!" But this is what I would say, could I
catch the ear of President Lincoln: "Seize some island of the sea! Buy
some province of Europe, Asia, or Africa! Prepare some Botany Bay!
Banish these felons thither! Establish a rigorous passport system, and
make it as impossible for them to enter this purified Republic as it
was for Themistocles to return to Athens, or as it is for a Bourbon to
re-enter the empire of Napoleon! Let us do with them as the Lord God
did with the first murderer, and send them forth to be fugitives and
vagabonds in the earth, setting a mark on their brows, lest any
finding them should slay them. And then with Cain shall they exclaim:
'My punishment is greater than I can bear!'"</p>
               <p>But while I would thus sternly dispose of the leaders and
arch-conspirators, I would speak words of forgiveness and
<pb n="20"/>
                  <figure entity="boardman20">
                     <figDesc>2-th page of Reverend
George Dana Boardman's An Address in Commemoration of the
Re-Establishment of the National Flag at Fort
Sumter.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
good cheer to the multitudes they have duped. I would learn a lesson
from the cross, the lifting up of whose sacrificial Victim so many in
Christendom this day mournfully celebrate. While, like the crucified
One, I would show no mercy to the apostate angels who tempted to sin,
yet, like the crucified One, I would enfold in my forgiving embrace
the multitudes tempted by them to rush on the thick bosses of
Jehovah's buckler of Civil Government, knowing not what they did. To
them I would say: "Come back, come back into this disenthralled,
regenerated, transfigured Republic, beneath the glorious mantle of
that edict of Universal Emancipation, issued by the Chief Magistrate
in January, 1863, and ratified by the people, November 8,1864." Fellow
citizens! be patient, and after a few more blows from our peace-maker,
Grant, they will do it; and then, with a depth of meaning which the
defender of the Constitution did not conceive when he uttered the
glowing words beneath the dome of the Capitol, thirty-five years ago,
shall an emancipated and exultant Republic announce to the ages as its
everlasting motto: LIBERTY AND UNION, <hi rend="italic">now and,
forever, one and inseparable!</hi> Yes, glorious Flag! borne in
triumph by heroic legions from the Chesapeake to the Mississippi; from
Richmond to Mobile; thou art at last purified of thy stains, and
to-day thou proudly floatest over "the land of the free," as thou
always hast over " the home of the brave."</p>
               <p>In conclusion, I congratulate you, my countrymen, of the
bright portents which are gilding the horizon. Watch man! what of the
night? Watchman! what of the night? 
<pb n="21"/>
                  <figure entity="boardman21">
                     <figDesc>21st page of Reverend
George Dana Boardman's An Address in Commemoration of the
Re-Establishment of the National Flag at Fort
Sumter.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
The watchman saith: <hi rend="italic">The morning cometh!</hi> Peace is
near at hand. I already feel my cheek fanned with the beating of her
halcyon wings. All glory be to Thee, Thou Prince of Peace! Thou hast
not died in vain. A millennium awaits the groaning, travailing
creation, more resplendent than that which dazzled the eye of
England's poet-laureate when, in mystic trance, he</p>
               <lg type="stanza">
                  <l>---Dipt into the future, far as human eye could
see,</l>
                  <l>Saw the Vision of the world, and all the wonder that would
be;</l>
                  <l>Saw the heavens fill with commerce, argosies of magic
sails,</l>
                  <l>Pilots of the purple twilight, dropping down with costly
bales;</l>
                  <l>Heard the heavens fill with shouting, and there rain'd a
ghastly dew</l>
                  <l>From the nations' airy navies grappling in the
central blue;</l>
                  <l>Far along the world-wide whisper of the
south-wind rushing warm,</l>
                  <l>With the standards of the peoples
plunging thro' the thunder-storm;</l>
                  <l>Till the war-drum throbb'd no
longer, and the battle-flags were furl'd </l>
                  <l>In the Parliament of
man, the Federation of the world.</l>
               </lg>
               <p>Then shall dawn that blessed era, foretold by seers of
every time, and sighed for by holy men of every clime, when all men's
good shall</p>
               <lg type="stanza">
                  <l>Be each man's rule, and universal Peace </l>
                  <l>Lie like a
shaft of light across the land,</l>
                  <l>And like a lane of beams
athwart the sea,</l>
                  <l>Through all the circle of the Golden
Year.</l>
               </lg>
               <p>Glory be to the Father, and to the Son, and to the Holy
Ghost; as it was in the beginning, is now, and ever shall be, world
without end!</p>
               <pb n="22"/>
               <p>
                  <figure entity="boardman22">
                     <figDesc>22nd page
of Reverend George Dana Boardman's An Address in Commemoration of the
Re-Establishment of the National Flag at Fort
Sumter.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <pb n="23"/>
               <p>
                  <figure entity="boardman23">
                     <figDesc>23rd page
of Reverend George Dana Boardman's An Address in Commemoration of the
Re-Establishment of the National Flag at Fort
Sumter.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 id="boardman.003" n="APPENDIX" type="appendix">
               <head>APPENDIX.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">At the request of numerous friends, the
Order of Services observed on the 14th inst. is
subjoined.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>ORDER OF SERVICES.</p>
               <p>I.	THE LORD'S PRAYER.</p>
               <p>II. 	TE DEUM LAUDAMUS.</p>
               <p>III.	READING FROM THE HOLY SCRIPTURES</p>
               <p>THE TRIUMPHAL SONG OF
DEBORAH IN COMMEMORATION OF THE HEBBEW
	VICTORY OVER THE CANAANITISH CONFEDERACY, 1300 B.C.</p>
               <lg type="stanza">
                  <head>THE ODE.</head>
                  <l>Thus sang Deborah and Barak, Son of Abinoam,</l>
                  <l>In the day of victory thus they sang:</l>
               </lg>
               <lg type="stanza">
                  <head>THE PRELUDE.</head>
                  <l>For the avenging of Israel,</l>
                  <l>For the free self-offering of the people,</l>
                  <l>Praise ye Jehovah!</l>
                  <l>Hear, O ye kings! Give
ear, ye Princes!</l>
                  <l>I to Jehovah, even I will lift the song,</l>
                  <l>I will sound the harp to Jehovah, God of Israel.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg type="stanza">
                  <head>THE EXODUS.</head>
                  <l>O Jehovah! when Thou wentest forth
from Seir,</l>
                  <l>When Thou marchest through the fields of Edom,</l>
                  <l>Quaked the earth, and poured the heavens,</l>
                  <l>Yea, the clouds
poured down with water;</l>
                  <l>Before Jehovah's face the mountains
melted,</l>
                  <l>Sinai itself before Jehovah's face,</l>
                  <l>The God of Israel.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb n="24"/>
               <p>
                  <figure entity="boardman24">
                     <figDesc>24th page
of Reverend George Dana Boardman's An Address in Commemoration of the
Re-Establishment of the National Flag at Fort
Sumter.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <lg type="stanza">
                  <head>THE DISMAY.</head>
                  <l>In the days of Shamgar, Son of
Anath,</l>
                  <l>In Jael's days, untrodden were the highways;</l>
                  <l>Through the winding by-path stole the traveller;</l>
                  <l>Upon the
plains lay the deserted hamlets,</l>
                  <l>Till I, Deborah, arose,</l>
                  <l>Till I arose, a mother in Israel.</l>
                  <l>They chose gods that were
new;</l>
                  <l>Then war was in all their gates;</l>
                  <l>Shield was there
none or spear</l>
                  <l>Among forty thousand sons of Israel.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg type="stanza">
                  <head>THE SUMMONS</head>
                  <l>My soul is yours, ye chiefs of
Israel!</l>
                  <l>And ye, the self-devoted of the people,</l>
                  <l>Praise Jehovah!</l>
                  <l>Ye that ride on
white-dappled she asses,</l>
                  <l>Ye that sit to judge on rich
carpets,</l>
                  <l>Ye that plod in the way,</l>
                  <l>Come meditate the
song!</l>
               </lg>
               <lg type="stanza">
                  <l>From amidst the shouting of the dividers of the spoils,</l>
                  <l>Between the water-troughs and by the springing wells,</l>
                  <l>There
let them rehearse the righteous acts of Jehovah,</l>
                  <l>The righteous
acts of His headship in Israel,</l>
                  <l>And let the thronged gates
repeat the song!</l>
               </lg>
               <lg type="stanza">
                  <l> Awake, awake, Deborah!</l>
                  <l>Awake, awake, utter a song!</l>
                  <l>Arise, Barak, and lead captive thy captives,</l>
                  <l>Thou son of Abinoam!</l>
               </lg>
               <lg type="stanza">
                  <head>THE GATHERING TO THE RENDEZVOUS.</head>
                  <l>With Barak went
down a valiant force against the mighty;</l>
                  <l>With me, Deborah, went
down Jehovah's people against the strong;</l>
                  <l>First: Ephraim, from
the Mount of Amalek;</l>
                  <l>And after Ephraim the hosts of
Benjamin;</l>
                  <l>From Machir came down lawgivers;</l>
                  <l>From Zebulun
those that bear the marshal's staff;</l>
                  <l>And Issachar's brave
princes came with Deborah,</l>
                  <l>Issachar, the strength of Barak;</l>
                  <l>They burst into the valley in his footsteps.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb n="25"/>
               <p>
                  <figure entity="boardman25">
                     <figDesc>25th page
of Reverend George Dana Boardman's An Address in Commemoration of the
Re-Establishment of the National Flag at Fort
Sumter.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <lg type="stanza">
                  <head>THE RECREANTS.</head>
                  <l>By Reuben's fountains there was
deep debating;</l>
                  <l>Why sattest thou between the sheepfolds?</l>
                  <l>Was it to hear the piping of the flocks?</l>
                  <l>By Reuben's
fountains deep were the searchings of the heart;</l>
                  <l>And Gilead
beyond the Jordan lingered;</l>
                  <l>And Dan, why dwelled he among his
ships?</l>
                  <l>Asher reposed on the shore of the sea,</l>
                  <l>And in his
harbors dwelt.</l>
                  <l>But Zebulun was a death-defying people,</l>
                  <l>And Naphtali on the high places of the field.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg type="stanza">
                  <head>THE BATTLE.</head>
                  <l>Came the kings and fought,</l>
                  <l>Fought the kings of Canaan</l>
                  <l>By Taanach, on Megiddo's
waters;</l>
                  <l>Gain of silver took they not.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg type="stanza">
                  <l>From the heavens they fought;</l>
                  <l>The stars from their
courses</l>
                  <l>Fought against Sisera;</l>
                  <l>The torrent Kishon swept
them down,</l>
                  <l>The ancient torrent, the torrent Kishon.</l>
                  <l>Trample down, O my soul, their might!</l>
                  <l>Then stamped the
clattering hoofs of prancing horses</l>
                  <l>At the flight, at the
flight of the mighty.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg type="stanza">
                  <head>THE CURSE.</head>
                  <l>Curse ye Meroz, said the angel of
Jehovah;</l>
                  <l>Curse ye with a curse the inhabitants thereof;</l>
                  <l>Because they came not to the help of Jehovah,</l>
                  <l>To the help of
Jehovah, with the heroes!</l>
               </lg>
               <lg type="stanza">
                  <head>THE AVENGER.</head>
                  <l>Blessed above women be Jael,</l>
                  <l>The wife of Heber the Kenite,</l>
                  <l>O'er all the women blessed,
that dwell in tents!</l>
                  <l>Water he asked, milk she gave,</l>
                  <l>The
curded milk in her costliest bowl.</l>
                  <l>Her hand she stretched out
to the tent-pin,</l>
                  <l>And her right hand to the hammer of the
workmen.</l>
                  <l>Then Sisera she smote, she clove his head,</l>
                  <l>She
bruised, she pierced his temples;</l>
                  <l>Between her feet he bowed: he
fell: he lay:</l>
                  <l>Between her feet he bowed: he fell:</l>
                  <l>Where
he bowed, there he fell dead.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb n="26"/>
               <p>
                  <figure entity="boardman26">
                     <figDesc>26th page
of Reverend George Dana Boardman's An Address in Commemoration of the
Re-Establishment of the National Flag at Fort
Sumter.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <lg type="stanza">
                  <head>THE MOTHER OF SISERA.</head>
                  <l>Through the window stretched
forth and lamented</l>
                  <l>The mother of Sisera through the
lattice;</l>
                  <l>"Why is his car so long in coming?</l>
                  <l>Wherefore
tarry the wheels of his chariots?"</l>
               </lg>
               <lg type="stanza">
                  <l>The wise ones of her princesses answer,</l>
                  <l>Yea, she repeats
their answer to herself:</l>
                  <l>"Surely they are finding, are dividing
the prey;</l>
                  <l>One damsel, two damsels for each hero;</l>
                  <l>To
Sisera prey of divers colors,</l>
                  <l>A many-colored robe, and richly
broidered,</l>
                  <l>Many-colored, and broidered round the neck!"</l>
               </lg>
               <lg type="stanza">
                  <head>THE TRIUMPH.</head>
                  <l>So perish all Thine enemies, O
Jehovah!</l>
                  <l>But they that love Thee,</l>
                  <l>Are as the sun, when
he goes forth in his might.</l>
               </lg>
               <p>IV. SINGING, NATIONAL HYMN.-"My country, 'tis of thee." </p>
               <p>V. PRAYER-BY REV. THOMAS H. STOCKTON, D.D.</p>
               <p>VI. SINGING, THE
STAR-SPANGLED BANNER.</p>
               <p>VII. ADDRESS-BY THE PASTOR.</p>
               <p>VIII. SINGING, BATTLE-HYMN OF THE REPUBLIC.-"Mine eyes have seen
the glory of the coming of the Lord."</p>
               <lg type="stanza">
                  <head> DOXOLOGY.</head>
                  <l>Praise God from whom all blessings flow,</l>
                  <l>Praise Him all creatures here below,</l>
                  <l>Praise Him above, ye heavenly host,</l>
                  <l>Praise Father, Son, and Holy Ghost.</l>
               </lg>
               <p>IX. BENEDICTION-BY REV. J. NEWTON BROWN, D.D.</p>
               <pb n="27"/>
               <p>
                  <figure entity="boardman27">
                     <figDesc>1st page of Reverend George Dana
Boardman's Death, the Law of Life</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </p>
            </div2>
         </div1>
         <div1 id="boardman.004" n="Death, the Law of Life" type="text">
            <head> 
               <bibl> 
                  <title>Death, the Law of Life</title> 
                  <date>April 16,
1865</date> 
                  <pubPlace>First Baptist Church of Philadelphia</pubPlace>
                  <author>Boardman, Rev. George Dana</author> 
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Philadelphia</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Sherman &#x0026; Co.,
Printers</publisher>
                     <date>1865</date>
                  </imprint> 
               </bibl> 
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <p>"Man, thou Pendulum betwixt a Smile and
Tear."</p>
            </epigraph>
            <pb n="28"/>
            <p>
               <figure entity="boardman28">
                  <figDesc>2nd page of
Reverend George Dana Boardman's Death, the Law of
Life</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <pb n="29"/>
            <p>
               <figure entity="boardman44">
                  <figDesc>3rd page
of Reverend George Dana Boardman's Death, the Law of
Life</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <p>DEATH, THE LAW OF LIFE.</p>
            <p>A DISCOURSE,</p>
            <p>DELIVERED ON THE SUNDAY MORNING AFTER THE</p>
            <p>MURDER OF
PRESIDENT LINCOLN,</p>
            <p>IN THE METING HOUSE OF THE</p>
            <p>FIRST BAPTIST CHURCH OF PHILADELPHIA,</p>
            <p>April 16, 1865.</p>
            <p>BY THE</p>
            <p>REVEREND GEORGE DANA BOARDMAN,</p>
            <p>PASTOR.</p>
            <p>PHILADELPHIA:</p>
            <p>SHERMAN &#x0026; CO., PRINTERS.</p>
            <p>1865.</p>
            <pb n="30"/>
            <p>
               <figure entity="boardman30">
                  <figDesc>4th page
of Reverend George Dana Boardman's Death, the Law of
Life</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <pb n="31"/>
            <p>
               <figure entity="boardman31">
                  <figDesc>5th page
of Reverend George Dana Boardman's Death, the Law of
Life</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <div2 id="boardman.005" n="DISCOURSE" type="sermon">
               <head>DISCOURSE.</head>
               <p>WHAT a day, or rather night, is this, my countrymen! How
intolerable the burden that crushes us! What! Abraham Lincoln dead?
The idol of his countrymen, the true, the pure, the good, the loving,
the heroic, the great-souled father of his people dead, murdered, gone
away from us forevermore? O God! We cannot bear it! How can I stand
here with this great grief so fresh in my heart, and discourse to you
about it? It seems almost like sacrilege to attempt it to-day. On
another and more appropriate occasion, when my thoughts are calmer and
more orderly, I will offer my tribute to him who lies on the nation's
bier. This morning I ask you to pass from the darkened chamber of a
personal grief into a broader and serener temple, where the quivering
chords of our hearts may lose somewhat of this painful tenseness, and
where considerations of a more general and impersonal nature may raise
the soul to loftier and calmer heights. May the father of consolation
help us while we ponder those words of the Redeemer, which are
recorded in the twenty-fourth verse of the twelfth chapter of the
Gospel according to St. John:</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">"Verily, verily,
I say unto you: except a corn of wheat</hi>
                  <pb n="32"/>
                  <figure entity="boardman32">
                     <figDesc>6th page of Reverend
George Dana Boardman's Death, the Law of Life</figDesc>
                  </figure>
                  <hi rend="italic">fall into the ground and die, it abideth alone; but if
it die, it bringeth forth much fruit."</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I.  Thoughtless or dull must that man's spirit be which
does not feel a quickening influence in these spring days of
vegetative activity. He need not visit some great farm, or forest, in
order to be assured of the wonderful transformations going on in
nature around him. If he have but a single tree growing by his window,
or a single rose-bush, or a square foot of grass-plat in his yard, he
may discover, if he will, evidences of an activity as intense and
wonderful in its way as when a nation is engaged in the shock of
arms. Look abroad to-day on the vegetable kingdom around you. What
stupendous energies are at work, upheaving the soil, draining the
underground reservoirs of a continent, throwing the whole atmosphere
of earth into commotion, supplying the waste of animal expenditure by
vegetable growth, and carrying on that sublime paradox of compensation
in nature which preserves equilibrium by means of perturbations! But
not only are great transformations going on. Observe, also, the
intense <hi rend="italic">life</hi> everywhere prevalent. All nature is
instinct with the most vigorous vitality. An exuberance of vital force
is everywhere exhibited, from the loftiest pine to the tiniest
lichen. Behold the bursting seed, the protruding shoots, the opening
leaves, the unfolding buds of spring! Whence all this abounding life?
Next autumn you will put your hand to the sickle, and
<pb n="33"/>
                  <figure entity="boardman33">
                     <figDesc>7th page of Reverend
George Dana Boardman's Death, the Law of Life</figDesc>
                  </figure>
reap the golden ears. But whence will come your glorious crop? Ah! the
law of the harvest is death. "Except a kernel of wheat fall into the
ground and die, it abideth alone; but if it die, it bringeth forth
much fruit." It is because the seeds you plant in spring are dying
that your fields in autumn will be white to the harvest.</p>
               <lg type="stanza">
                  <l>My heart is awed within me when I think</l>
                  <l>Of the great
miracle that still goes on,</l>
                  <l>In silence, round me,--the
perpetual work</l>
                  <l>Of thy creation, finished, yet renewed </l>
                  <l>Forever. * * * * * </l>
                  <l>Lo! all grow old and die; but see
again,</l>
                  <l>How on the faltering footsteps of decay</l>
                  <l>Youth
presses,--ever gay and beautiful youth</l>
                  <l>In all its beautiful
forms. These lofty trees</l>
                  <l>Wave not less proudly than their
ancestors</l>
                  <l>Moulder beneath them. * * *</l>
                  <l>Life mocks the idle hate</l>
                  <l>Of
his arch enemy Death,--yea, seats himself</l>
                  <l>Upon the tyrant's
throne,--the sepulchre,</l>
                  <l>And of the triumphs of his ghastly
foe</l>
                  <l>Makes his own nourishment.</l>
               </lg>
               <p>II.  The like principle holds in the animal kingdom. The life of
the body depends on the destruction of its own material. No part of an
organism or living mechanism can act without wearing away. Every
action of the organism, whether in motion that is voluntary or
involuntary, whether in emotion or volition, involves attrition, the
wasting away, the absolute loss and death of animal material. The
processes of life are at the same time the processes of death. The
condition, the law of physical life, is physical death.</p>
               <pb n="34"/>
               <p>
                  <figure entity="boardman32">
                     <figDesc>8th page of
Reverend George Dana Boardman's Death, the Law of
Life</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <p>This, then, is the grand law of life that prevails in the
physical world, whether vegetable or animal. Death must precede
life. Death is the source, or, rather, the means of life. The death of
the seed is the law of the harvest. "Verily, verily, I say unto you,
except a kernel of wheat fall into the ground and die, it abideth
alone; but if it die, it bringeth forth much fruit."</p>
               <p>Now, this multiplication of the seed through its own death
our Lord uses as a most significant parable and lesson. As in the
physical world, so in the spiritual: <hi rend="italic">Death must
precede Life.</hi> Growth comes through decay; glory through disgrace;
joy through woe; peace through war; victory through defeat; life
through death.</p>
               <p>III.  Observe how this principle holds true of the Son of God
Himself. He could not, as <hi rend="italic">the Son of Man</hi>, become
perfect except through suffering. In fact, this is the primary and
very particular application of the parable of the kernel of wheat
dying, as our Lord Himself set it forth. While discoursing in the
temple on the Wednesday before He died, message was brought to Him
that certain Greek proselytes were waiting in the outer court to see
Him. They were Gentiles, who had given in adhesion to some of the
tenets of Judaism. They had heard of His fame, and of the triumphal
entry which He had just made into the City of the Great fling. And now
they themselves being in Jerusalem to attend the Passover, they wished
to see the illustrious Stranger for themselves, and learn by personal
acquaintance whether He were the Saviour their
<pb n="35"/>
                  <figure entity="boardman35">
                     <figDesc>9th page of Reverend
George Dana Boardman's Death, the Law of Life</figDesc>
                  </figure>
own hearts so sighed for. Deeply moved by this touching request of
these Gentile proselytes, our Lord accedes to their wish. In their
hearing he reveals, by means of this exquisite similitude we are
considering this morning, that Messiah's glory was to come through
Messiah's shame; Messiah's triumph through Messiah's defeat; Messiah's
throne through Messiah's grave. The kernel of wheat abideth alone,
unless it decay and die. It is only by decaying and dying that it adds
to itself, and brings forth fruit. Just here, men and brethren, does
this death of the kernel stand forth as a most wonderful shadow of
Christ's work. For the Son of Man died that He might rise again a
spiritual harvest of regenerate humanity. So long as Jesus remained on
earth without dying, the Divine life was confined to Himself: <hi rend="italic">He abided alone</hi>. It was only when He cast off, in
dying, the earthly integument, that liberty of growth became
possible. And when, at length, the harvest time shall come, Jesus will
be found, like the kernel of corn, which, having died, has passed
through its stages, first the blade, then the ear, then the full corn
in the ear, to be no longer "<hi rend="italic">alone</hi>," but to have
"<hi rend="italic">brought forth much fruit</hi>." The people, whose
sins He had borne on the accursed tree, will be gathered into the
heavenly garner, as the mighty harvest of the travail of His soul. The
heavenly seed was sown in the ground, and died, that it might evolve
itself into a mighty increment, and display itself in the glorious
blossom and fruitage of redeemed humanity. Verily, as He Himself said
to the
<pb n="36"/>
                  <figure entity="boardman36">
                     <figDesc>10th page of Reverend
George Dana Boardman's Death, the Law of Life</figDesc>
                  </figure>
Gentiles that sought His presence, the hour of His death was the hour
of His life; the hour of His defeat in crucifixion the hour of His
triumph in redemption.</p>
               <p>IV. Observe, again, how this principle holds true of man in all the
deeper aspects of his nature. If the Captain of our salvation could
not be made perfect except through suffering, how can He lead forth
His many sons unto glory, unless they, too, tread in the same path of
sorrow and agony? Oh, no! It is a law just as universal and inexorable
in the kingdom of moral growth as in that of vegetable, that the
spirit, like the seed, shall die before it can live. Let no human
being think he can gather in his heavenly harvest till he has passed
through trial, disaster, and death. And, in fact, the very next words
which our Lord utters, after delivering this parable of the dying
kernel, and as if in explanation of it, are these: "He that loveth his
life shall lose it; and he that hateth his life in this world shall
keep it unto life eternal." In other words, man's spirit must undergo
a certain sort of decay and dissolution, must pass through what the
world calls ignominy and defeat, before it can be quickened into the
new life, and enter on the fruitions of a bright eternity. Glance now
at some illustrations of this principle as applied to man's spiritual
nature.</p>
               <p>1.  Look, for instance, at the prime doctrine of
Regeneration. What, in fact, is the great mystery of the New Birth but
the decease of the spirit,--the old man dying, that it may rise again
the new man and the
<pb n="37"/>
                  <figure entity="boardman37">
                     <figDesc>11th page of Reverend
George Dana Boardman's Death, the Law of Life</figDesc>
                  </figure>
better? Ah! there are some of you present who know experimentally what
this parable of the dying seed means as applied to the great fact of
conversion. There was a time when you, dear child of God, died. There
was a decay of earthly hopes and prospects, of earthly devices and
methods of salvation; and such were the bitterness of your remorse,
and the depth of your penitence, and the agony of your spirit, that,
in very truth, in being born again, in being quickened by the
vitalizing energies of the Holy Ghost, you passed through what may
indeed be called the pangs of dissolution.</p>
               <p>2.  So, too, does our parable explain the meaning and the ministry
of affliction. There must be a bruising of the spirit--a lacerating,
tearing away of the tendrils that cling to earthly props--a blighting
and decay of the fondest hopes and plans--an utter abasement of pride
and self-confidence--a painful breaking down of the will--a dying
agony of spirit, before the soul can multiply its powers into any
glorious harvest. It is only when we are weak that we are strong. Oh,
think it not strange, then, my friend, that you, who have tried to
walk humbly before your God, have been called to pass through such
fiery trials. Ask that mighty oak, which has triumphantly breasted the
whirlwinds of centuries, how he became so colossal and strong; and he
will answer you, that once he was but a little acorn, lying idle on
the soil, and the heedless foot of a bounding deer tramped it beneath
the sod; and then it decayed and died, and its greatness and its
<pb n="38"/>
                  <figure entity="boardman38">
                     <figDesc>12th page of Reverend
George Dana Boardman's Death, the Law of Life</figDesc>
                  </figure>
glory date from its death. Think it not strange, then, that you should
endure trial and sorrow, and die years before your body reaches the
grave; for it is the law of the spiritual harvest. No man can become
spiritually great till he has spiritually died. The <hi rend="italic">only</hi> way to the heavenly crown is from the earthly
cross.</p>
               <p>V.  The same principle is applicable to nations. So far as mortal
penetration can go, God's universal method of governing is this:
Growth through decay; victory through defeat; life through death. And
nations are no exceptions. It is not possible that a nation should
achieve true greatness except through the discipline of defeat, and
the throes of a mortal agony. It is the law of growth and
establishment. There are no Christians like those who have been tried
in the fires of affliction. And there are no nations which attain such
true majesty of character as those which successfully burst through
the avenues of disaster and spiritual, heartfelt dissolution.</p>
               <p>Here, then, in this terrific war, in the desolations of our
homesteads, in the occasional disasters and humiliations of the
battle-field, and specially in this crushing blow which fell on us
yesterday morning, do I discover evidences of the Father's
loving-kindness. For, I do not believe, what many persons seem to
imagine, that all our disasters are wholly to be traced to human
agency. Could we lift up the curtain which conceals God's plan of
guiding this nation, I believe that we should discover that He had
employed a system of providential arrests and clogs, which should
hamper and sometimes sud-
<pb n="39"/>
                  <figure entity="boardman39">
                     <figDesc>13th page of Reverend
George Dana Boardman's Death, the Law of Life</figDesc>
                  </figure>
denly balk some of our best-laid schemes. I believe this, not because
our national history is an exception to God's general method of
administering human affairs, but because it is in harmony with it. The
observant reader, whether of biography or of history, must have been
impressed with the fact that God not only governs the affairs of men
and of nations, but also often advances their best interests by
confounding their wisest counsels, and suddenly tripping up their most
promising schemes. It is most unsagacious, then, to say the least of
it, to conclude that every national disaster, whether in the cabinet,
the Congress, or the field, is to be traced solely to human agency. To
do this, is to take a practically atheistic view of the great
campaign. No! God, as the Providential Disposer of incidents, can very
easily find some method by which to defeat us, and yet we be utterly
mistaken in assigning the cause of defeat. And this I believe He has
repeatedly done in our national history, specially in the conduct of
this war, our generals themselves being as much mistaken as to the
source of the defeat as we were. And, however broad in statesmanship
we may be, or energetic in purpose, or profound in strategy, or heroic
in the field, I believe that God will continue, ever and anon, to balk
suddenly, in some way for the present misunderstood by us, our most
consummate schemes, till the national heart feels at its very core
that the Lord God of Hosts is the real ruler of America, and that
President, Secretary of State, general, soldier, citizen, is strong
only as Almighty God
<pb n="40"/>
                  <figure entity="boardman40">
                     <figDesc>14th page of Reverend
George Dana Boardman's Death, the Law of Life</figDesc>
                  </figure>
stoops down from His throne, and helps him to be strong. And this is
the way our God is teaching us. Our wisest thinkers are but as blind
men groping after light and an open way. And the blessed thing is that
the dear God has taken our poor, stricken, pall-clad nation into His
own hands, bringing the blind by a way that they knew not, leading
them in paths that they have not known, hedging up their way with
briers, making a wall that they should not find the paths, alluring
them into the wilderness, that He may at last speak comfortably unto
them, and open for them in the Valley of Achor a door of hope.</p>
               <p>Glance, now, at some of the blessed fruits which the dying of the
nation has already yielded.</p>
               <p>1.  See, for instance, how the calamities of this war have tended
to reveal us unto ourselves. Prosperity is a miserable school for
self-knowledge. But adversity has a wonderful self-revealing
power. The nation understands itself a great deal better than it did
four years ago. We have not the same overweening vanity that made us
so ridiculous in the opening of this appalling struggle. Very
different is the national feeling to-day from what it was on that
eventful Sunday morning in July, 1861, when our army so recklessly and
vain-gloriously marched to the field of Bull Run, and almost every
paper in the North positively predicted an easy victory, which should
decide beyond cavil or peradventure, the issue of the war. We
understand ourselves better now. We are more humble. We feel more
<pb n="41"/>
                  <figure entity="boardman41">
                     <figDesc>15th page of Reverend
George Dana Boardman's Death, the Law of Life</figDesc>
                  </figure>
keenly our dependence on God for the happy issue of the
struggle. Hence, when victory perches on our banner, as when Richmond
fell and Lee surrendered, instead of rending the air with our boastful
and atheistic huzzas, as was our wont over our earlier successes, we
now instinctively gather together in reverent prayer and adoration,
and the song that swells on our lips, as was the case before
Independence Hall and in Wall Street, is the Doxology to the Father,
the Son, and the Holy Ghost. Our growing self-knowledge, learned in
the school of adversity, is gradually driving the nation nearer and
nearer to Him "from whom all blessings flow." And self-knowledge is
one of the grand elements of real greatness. The self-revealing power
of suffering is making us humbler, and, therefore, greater. For he
that humbleth himself shall be exalted. Thus does the dying seed
unfold into the golden harvest.</p>
               <p>2.  Another blessed fruit of this desolating war, and specially of
the awful tragedy which is ensanguining its final act, is, that it has
thrown us out of the benumbing routine of stiffening habits and
tendencies, thus limbering us afresh to the manifold purposes of
Divine Providence. We need, specially as a young, growing nation,
still in its formative stage, to be every little while powerfully
agitated, lest we become paralyzed through sheer monotony of action
and sentiment. Uninterrupted prosperity produces the same effect on
nations that it does on individuals; it tends to stunt the growth,
weaken the capacity, debase the nobility. Of all calami-
<pb n="42"/>
                  <figure entity="boardman42">
                     <figDesc>16th page of Reverend
George Dana Boardman's Death, the Law of Life</figDesc>
                  </figure>
ties, considered as affecting those who have capacity for growth,
nothing is more fatal than simple stagnation. It is a great blessing
to be convulsed and dislodged, whenever our wheels have worn so deep
as to preclude liberty of diversion. God's law for powers is progress;
and progress can take place only at the cost of convulsions and
throes. Every new crystallization implies a previous commotion and
effervescence. Better for the human spirit all the commotions of
change than the numb palsies of monotony.</p>
               <lg type="stanza">
                  <l>Better men should perish, one by one,</l>
                  <l>Than that earth
should stand at gaze, like Joshua's moon in Ajalon!</l>
                  <l>Through the
shadow of the globe we sweep into the younger day:</l>
                  <l>Better fifty
years of Europe than a cycle of Cathay!</l>
               </lg>
               <p>But aside from its being essential to progress, it is an admirable
thing to have the national heart ever and anon profoundly stirred; for
it is thus made sensitive to the quickening and plastic influences of
the Spirit of God. Calamities tend to make the human spirit flexible,
limbering and adjusting it to the movements of the Divine. Surveyed
from this point of view, the arousal of the national sensibility is of
inestimable value. It is good, and I say it in the presence of these
sad, funereal emblems, that a great tide of pathos should ever and
anon sweep over a people. In this view, the desolations and
bereavements of this war, and, specially the awful calamity before
which the nation now stands aghast, are, under God's providence, a
perturbing, loosening force, knocking away the bolts that imprisoned
the soul, and
<pb n="43"/>
                  <figure entity="boardman43">
                     <figDesc>17th page of Reverend
George Dana Boardman's Death, the Law of Life</figDesc>
                  </figure>
letting into its opened chambers and corridors the winnowing,
gladdening gales of the Spirit. Accordingly, I expect that, when the
immediate, turbulent excitements of this assassination and of the war,
as a whole, are over, a profound religious awakening will pervade the
country. I confidently look for greater triumphs of Messiah than those
which were won after the terrible financial commotions of 1857. The
national heart has been touched and laid bare by the finger of
Almighty God, and the lacerated organism wil1 be sensitive to the
Divine Breath. Brethren in Jesus! This is your hour with God! Be ye
princes with Him, and prevail!</p>
               <p>3.  Still another fruit of this devastating scourge, is the
development of the nation's true nobility. Never does a man know the
force or grandeur that is in him, till some mighty calamity or passion
has revealed his soul. Viewed in this light, war, terrible scourge as
it is, has its gains as well as its losses. Oh, no! The nations cannot
live, much less grow, without the severe, but quickening and unfolding
discipline of this terrible thing. The nation's heart must die before
it can blossom in beauty, or multiply its powers in harvest. And what
a harvest of spiritual magnificence has the national suffering and
death already yielded! What outbursts of generosity have there been!
What floods of sacred, lofty sensibility have surged over the land!
What splendors of heroism have lighted up the firmament, grandly
illustrating (may I reverently say?) Jehovah's sublime law of
vicarious suffering! Even the seed dies
<pb n="44"/>
                  <figure entity="boardman44">
                     <figDesc>18th page of Reverend
George Dana Boardman's Death, the Law of Life</figDesc>
                  </figure>
vicariously in order to the harvest. What a magnificent hecatomb has
been the nation's offering, not by compulsion, not in superstition,
but in solemn, rational, heroic joy! This mighty army, not of
conscripts, but to so very large extent, of volunteers, has not only
offered itself; it has been silently offered by countless hidden
hearts quite as heroic; by wives, mothers, sisters, lovers! Oh, I
thank the Lord of heaven and earth, that He hath so woven the web of
the nations as to permit the American people to set before the ages
the grandest <hi rend="italic">human</hi> illustration the world has
ever witnessed of that sublime principle which seems to pervade the
universe, and which lies as the very corner-stone of Redemption,--<hi rend="italic">Vicarious Sacrifice!</hi>
               </p>
               <p>4.  I have been speaking of the application of this principle, <hi rend="italic">life through death</hi>, to nations. Let me bring this
point stil1 nearer home, even to these bleeding hearts of ours that as
yet refuse to be comforted. The richly kerneled and tasselled stalk
springs from the death of the solitary seed. Even so, the nation's
triumph and greatness may spring from Abraham Lincoln's death. Had he
been permitted to live till the term of his great office had expired,
and, afterwards, in a green odd age, to die amidst the tranquillities
of his Illinois home, he would still have been the glorious nobleman
that God crowned him in his birth; but he might have <hi rend="italic">abided alone</hi>, fructifying into no national
harvest. We should still have revered him, as we revere all of God's
great ones; but no nation would have been born
<pb n="45"/>
                  <figure entity="boardman45">
                     <figDesc>19th page of Reverend
George Dana Boardman's Death, the Law of Life</figDesc>
                  </figure>
of him. But when, beneath the sufferance of an inscrutable Providence,
the assassin's bullet laid him low, the glorious seed died, that it
might no longer abide alone, but <hi rend="italic">bring forth much
fruit</hi>. Even here, in the cause of Liberty, as in the cause of the
Church, it shall be found that the blood of the martyrs is the seed of
the Republic. Take courage, then, my countrymen: for even now I see
springing from the tear-wet bier of Abraham Lincoln the green and
tender blades which foretell the birth of an emancipated, united,
triumphant, transfigured, immortal Republic. Even so, Father! For thus
it seemed good in Thy sight!</p>
            </div2>
         </div1>
         <div1 id="boardman.006" n="An Address in Commemoration of Abraham Lincoln" type="text">
            <head> 
               <bibl> 
                  <title>An Address in Commemoration of Abraham
Lincoln</title> 
                  <date>April 19, 1865</date> 
                  <pubPlace>First Baptist
Church of Philadelphia</pubPlace> 
                  <author>Boardman, Rev. George Dana
Boardman</author> 
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Philadelphia</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Sherman &#x0026; Co., Printers</publisher>
                     <date>1865</date>
                  </imprint> 
               </bibl> 
            </head>
            <pb n="46"/>
            <p>
               <figure entity="boardman43">
                  <figDesc>1st page of Reverend George Dana
Boardman's An Address in Commemoration of Abraham
Lincoln</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <pb n="47"/>
            <p>
               <figure entity="boardman47">
                  <figDesc>2nd page
of Reverend George Dana Boardman's An Address in Commemoration of
Abraham Lincoln</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <p>In Memoriam</p>
            <pb n="48"/>
            <p>
               <figure entity="boardman48">
                  <figDesc>3rd page
of Reverend George Dana Boardman's An Address in Commemoration of
Abraham Lincoln</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <pb n="49"/>
            <p>
               <figure entity="boardman49">
                  <figDesc>4th page
of Reverend George Dana Boardman's An Address in Commemoration of
Abraham Lincoln</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <p>AN ADDRESS</p>
            <p>IN COMMEMORATION OF</p>
            <p>ABRAHAM LINCOLN,</p>
            <p>PRESIDENT OF THE UNITED STATES,</p>
            <p>DELIVERED IN THE MEETING-HOUSE</p>
            <p>OF THE</p>
            <p>FIRST BAPTIST CHURCH OF PHILADELPHIA,</p>
            <p>ON THE DAY OF HIS FUNERAL AT THE NATIONAL CAPITAL,</p>
            <p>APRIL 19, 1865.</p>
            <p>BY THE</p>
            <p>REVEREND GEORGE DANA BOARDMAN.</p>
            <p>PASTOR.</p>
            <p>PHILADELPHIA</p>
            <p>SHERMAN &#x0026; CO., PRINTERS.</p>
            <p>1865.</p>
            <pb n="50"/>
            <p>
               <figure entity="boardman50">
                  <figDesc>5th page
of Reverend George Dana Boardman's An Address in Commemoration of
Abraham Lincoln</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <pb n="51"/>
            <p>
               <figure entity="boardman51">
                  <figDesc>6th page
of Reverend George Dana Boardman's An Address in Commemoration of
Abraham Lincoln</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <div2 id="boardman.007" n="ADDRESS" type="sermon">
               <head>ADDRESS.</head>
               <p>How different this scene, my countrymen, from that which was
witnessed last Friday morning within these walls!<ref target="boardman.007.1">*</ref> Then all was
gladness and triumph and festal song and gay festoon. Now all is grief
and apprehension and requiem and ebon drapery. Why this awful change?
Why this universal suspension of business, this awful stillness of the
cities and the hamlets? Why, if men appear in the streets, do they
walk with slow and measured tread, their hearts failing them through
fear, and a grief more crushing than fear? Why from countless spires
toll the funereal bells? Why from fort and arsenal and camp and
military academy and navy-yard and man-of-war mournfully boom the
half-hour guns? Why, from the Golden Gate in the far-off West to the
St. Croix, aye, to British Newfoundland in the far off East, from
every flagstaff and window and balcony and colonnade, from car and
engine and steed, float the funereal emblems, fluttering like the ebon
wings of countless death-birds? Why this darkness that has fallen on
all the land, a darkness so thick that
<note id="boardman.007.1" n="*" type="foot" anchored="yes"> This allusion is to the festive services in
commemoration of the re-establishment of the national flag at Fort
Sumter, April 14.</note>
                  <pb n="52"/>
                  <figure entity="boardman52">
                     <figDesc>7th page of Reverend
George Dana Boardman's An Address in Commemoration of Abraham
Lincoln</figDesc>
                  </figure>
it may be felt? Why this cry that goes up from every hearthstone, a
universal, piercing cry, such as there was none ever like it, nor can
be like it any more? It is because there is not a house in all the
land in which there is not one dead. The nation's Father has been
struck down in all his gentle kingliness. And we could almost ask the
very sky to quench its too bright sun, and come down to meet our
anguish, closing around and enshrouding in its celestial pall the
mighty heart that lies so still and cold and dead. O God! help us to
be strong to-day as we gaze on Abraham Lincoln lying dead on the
nation's bier!</p>
               <p>I cannot, stricken countrymen, speak long to you today. I trusted,
last Sunday, when I gave the announcement for this occasion, that, ere
this, I should have regained sway over myself. But in preparing for
this solemn hour I have felt the same indescribable stupefaction that
I felt on that dreadful Saturday morning. For an hour or two after I
read the curdling tale, I felt such a strangeness as I never had felt
before, and as I pray God I may never feel again. I felt no anger, not
even sadness. I read the awful intelligence over and over and over
again; and still it hardly affected me more than if I had never read
it at all. And thus an hour or two passed on, in which, like thousands
of my countrymen, the soul itself seemed benumbed. And though
subsequently the horrible stupefaction passed away, to be succeeded by
most poignant bitterness of soul, yet, in endeavoring to arrange my
thoughts for this dreaded
<pb n="53"/>
                  <figure entity="boardman53">
                     <figDesc>8th page of Reverend
George Dana Boardman's An Address in Commemoration of Abraham
Lincoln</figDesc>
                  </figure>
occasion, I have felt the same stupefying, freezing horror creeping
over me again. It seems to me that brain, heart, pen, are
paralyzed. Instead of attempting to say aught to-day, I feel like
escaping from the presence of my fellow-men into some secluded
forest-dell, where I may breathe out a sorrow too sacred for
words. All I can do is to bring the briefest tribute, and reverently
lay it, amidst the dew of your tears, at the feet of the mighty
dead.</p>
               <p>Abraham Lincoln was born of respectable parentage in Kentucky,
February 12, 1809. In 1816, his parents removed to Indiana, where in
their new home Abraham spent the next ten years in hard manual labor
on his father's farm. The only school education which he ever received
was that which he obtained at intervals during this time, amounting in
the aggregate to about a year. In 1830 he removed with his father to
Illinois, and in the following year was employed as one of the hands
in navigating a flat-boat down the Mississippi to New Orleans. On the
breaking out of the Black Hawk war, in 1832, he served his country for
three months as the captain of a volunteer company. On his return he
began the study of law, to which he devoted himself with most
persistent assiduity. In 1834 he was elected to the legislature by the
highest vote cast for any candidate in the State, which position he
held for six years in virtue of consecutive re-elections. Meanwhile he
had removed to the capital of the State, where he rapidly
<pb n="54"/>
                  <figure entity="boardman54">
                     <figDesc>9th page of Reverend
George Dana Boardman's An Address in Commemoration of Abraham
Lincoln</figDesc>
                  </figure>
rose to great distinction as an advocate in jury trials. In 1846, at
the age of 37, Illinois sent him as one of her representatives at
Washington. His Congressional career was marked by a scrupulous
devotion to the duties of his office, by an inflexible adherence to
principle, by a generous, intelligent sympathy with all measures of
reform, among which I may particularly mention the resolution which he
offered, on January 16, 1849, for the abolition of slavery in the
District of Columbia, on what he conceived to be a constitutional
basis. After the expiration of his Congressional term, he applied
himself ardently to his profession till that dark deed, the Repeal of
the Missouri Compromise, called him again into the political arena. He
was immediately acknowledged as one of the most prominent political
leaders in the State. In 1858 he was unanimously nominated by his
party as candidate for United States Senator in opposition to Judge
Douglas. You have not forgotten how these two remarkable men canvassed
the State together, with what extraordinary ability and courtesy the
debate was conducted on both sides, and how profound an interest the
canvass excited throughout the Union. The result of this contest was,
that though Mr. Lincoln received a popular majority of four thousand
votes, yet Mr. Douglas was elected Senator by the joint ballot of the
legislature. On May 18, 1860, he was unanimously nominated by the
Republican National Convention a candidate for President, which
nomination was ratified by the people on November 6, and, on the 4th of
<pb n="55"/>
                  <figure entity="boardman55">
                     <figDesc>10th page of Reverend
George Dana Boardman's An Address in Commemoration of Abraham
Lincoln</figDesc>
                  </figure>
March, 1861, having succeeded in reaching Washington in spite of the
most desperate obstacles to prevent it, was inaugurated the sixteenth
President of the United States. At twenty minutes past four o'clock on
the morning of April 12, 1861, the grand conspiracy inaugurated civil
war in America by opening the fire of one hundred and forty guns on
Fort Sumter, Major Robert Anderson commanding. Who needs to have the
tale, henceforth so harrowing, repeated? It is enough to think of the
dead President, without dwelling on the intervening years of mingled
woe and glory. One event, indeed, must be specialized; for it overtops
all the other great events of this unparalleled epoch, as towered the
Olympian Jove above the lesser gods of the Grecian heaven. Your own
swelling hearts have anticipated me when I tell you that it was the
Emancipation Proclamation of January 1st, 1863. Without
particularizing further, it is enough to say, that in the terrific and
long-continued tornado which burst upon the country on the bombardment
of Sumter, whenever the ship of state plunged most wildly amidst the
engulfing billows, or grated most heavily on the foundering reefs, or
echoed most hoarsely with the shrieks of the despairing, one man there
was who ever walked her deck with quiet intrepidity, his great heart
ever true and trustful, his clear brain ever vigilant and
wide-sweeping, his strong hand ever untrembling, towering, placid and
imperial, like Neptune's brow, above the white foam, and smiling it
into peace. After
<pb n="56"/>
                  <figure entity="boardman56">
                     <figDesc>11th page of Reverend
George Dana Boardman's An Address in Commemoration of Abraham
Lincoln</figDesc>
                  </figure>
a canvass of unexampled intensity, throughout which he preserved the
same calm beauty of soul, he was, on the 8th of November, 1864,
re-elected President of the United States by an almost unprecedented
electoral majority; and on the 4th of March, 1865, he reassumed the
executive functions in an Inaugural of most impressive yet gentlest
majesty. On the 14th of April, 1865, the national flag was by his
command re-uplifted on the ramparts of Sumter, as a symbol of the
re-establishment of the national sovereignty throughout the Republic;
and on the evening of that memorable day the kingliest man that ever
breathed the air of the Western hemisphere was laid low by a bullet
thrice accursed, for it was sped by an assassin, a traitor, and a
slavery worshipper.</p>
               <p>Such, in briefest terms, is an outline of the career of America's
foremost son. What more can be said as we gather in tearful reverence
around his bier? Without distinction of lineage, he gained a
distinction which no lineage could give. Born among and as one of the
common people, he ever retained, amidst a courtliness of power which
European dynasties a thousand years old might envy, a fellow-feeling
with the common people, by his own inherent greatness rising to be
their type aggregate, embodiment, and symbol. But passing over those
years of boyish poverty and struggle, and also the years of youthful
brain and will endeavor, and conquest too, let us gaze on him when, in
the ma-
<pb n="57"/>
                  <figure entity="boardman57">
                     <figDesc>12th page of Reverend
George Dana Boardman's An Address in Commemoration of Abraham
Lincoln</figDesc>
                  </figure>
turity of his powers, he wields a sceptre more august than that of
Roman Caesar. It is difficult to form a just estimate of his
character; for, its vast proportions are lost in its extraordinary
symmetry. For, as in entering for the first time St. Peter's basilica
at Rome, you are disappointed, because the grandeur of outline is
melted and lost in the exquisite adaptation of detail, so to the
thoughtless observer the character of the late President seems less
great than it really was, because lost in its perfect equipoise and
rounded globe. But let us proceed with our attempt at delineation. The
historian to be born a hundred years hence will, I judge, say of
Abraham Lincoln something as follows.</p>
               <p>He was not a man lustrously brilliant in any one direction. No one
faculty of brain markedly towered over another. But he was none the
less great in that his greatness was so rounded, having less the
transient dazzle of the meteor than the steady quiet sparkle of the
fixed star. His logic was intuitive rather than tentative, instinctive
rather than elaborative. He was wont to come to his conclusions less
by the laborious rowings of his reason than by the unconscious
floatings of his instinctive, inborn shrewdness and sagacity. Hence
the facility with which he detected the pivotal point in any question,
however complex. Hence the ease and precision with which he led the
people to catch the same point, leading them directly thither by the
avenue of a diction which, however peculiar and homely, was
<pb n="58"/>
                  <figure entity="boardman58">
                     <figDesc>13th page of Reverend
George Dana Boardman's An Address in Commemoration of Abraham
Lincoln</figDesc>
                  </figure>
as straightforward and pellucid as his own judgment. Hence, also, it
was that he so rarely made mistakes. Hence it was that every public
act or plan of his, however wide-spread or intense the execration with
which it was first received, was sure, sooner or later, to win the
applauding verdict of the people. Guided thus by a system of well-nigh
infallible instincts, by which he knew what he ought to do, and when
to do it, and how to do it, he might well have taken as his own motto
the heraldic bearing of the Earl of Buckinghamshire, <hi rend="italic">Nulla vestigia retrorsum</hi>.</p>
               <p>But because the <corr resp="editor">intellect</corr> of the late
President was intuitive rather than ratiocinative, it does not follow
that he was not intellectually great; for as, according to the
profounder theologians, the intuitive John was greater than the
syllogistic Paul, so it seems to me, that Mr. Lincoln, intellectually
surveyed, stands in the very first rank of those who have, in either
hemisphere, wielded the sceptre. He had an unusually comprehensive
mind, taking in at a glance all the aspects of the most many-sided
question, almost always coming unerringly to a conclusion, when an
inferior and less spherical mind would have been puzzled and paralyzed
by a seeming contradiction, as, for instance, when social or a
political necessity is balanced by a legal or constitutional
difficulty, or when a pressing moral obligation is offset by a present
practical impossibility. Seeing all sides of a question, and
intuitively just, he was enabled to equate the problem, thus steering
the ship of state safely be-
<pb n="59"/>
                  <figure entity="boardman59">
                     <figDesc>14th page of Reverend
George Dana Boardman's An Address in Commemoration of Abraham
Lincoln</figDesc>
                  </figure>
tween the Charybdis of fanatic propulsion and the Scylla of timorous
procrastination. The highest eulogy that can be pronounced on the
intellectual character of a ruler, in times of great civil convulsion,
is that it is his policy to have no policy, content with keeping his
ship trim as he permits her to sweep downwards with the precipitous
torrent. That eulogy the late President deserves beyond any ruler the
world has seen.</p>
               <p>And yet Mr. Lincoln was not wanting in executive force. Because he
made no pretensions to special firmness, and vaunted not his purposes,
people at first imagined that he was irresolute. But as time rolled on
we began to see that beneath that mild, unassuming exterior lay an
imperial will, that serenely swayed all who came in contact with him,
however high in the military or executive councils of the nation they
stood; and yet so quiet was this sway that they hardly knew that the
sceptre was over them. Observe the modest assurance with which he
rules the Secretary of State and the Lieutenant-General, placidly
reserving to himself every ultimate responsibility. Nor was his
inflexibility less than his force. All the powers of earth could not
drive him to take a step till he thought it was right; and when
convinced that it was right, all the powers of earth could not prevent
his taking it. And all this, too, was without the slightest
ostentation. Like a wire-bridge across a mountain gorge, he could sway
to the softest zephyr, yet, like the same wire-bridge, the whirlwind
could not uproot him.</p>
               <pb n="60"/>
               <p>
                  <figure entity="boardman60">
                     <figDesc>15th page
of Reverend George Dana Boardman's An Address in Commemoration of
Abraham Lincoln</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <p>Gifted with this intellectual judgment so instinctively infallible,
and this gentle steadfastness of will, the late President blended with
it a moral nature remarkably pure, keen, sensitive, and
controlling. He was the very soul of integrity. It were as much as a
man's liberty, certainly more than his expectations, were worth, to
enter the presence of Abraham Lincoln with either flattery, threat, or
bribe. Himself as transparent as crystal, he loathed whatever was
refractive or opaque. He was absolutely incorruptible. Shrewd beyond
most men, his shrewdness was the clear, piercing vision of a clean,
single heart, that knew not how to</p>
               <lg type="stanza">
                  <l>Spread its sails</l>
                  <l>With 'vantage to the gale of others'
passions.</l>
               </lg>
               <p>Conscious of personal integrity, self-reliant, constitutionally
genial, having an abiding faith in the instinct and persistence of the
people as a corporate whole, assured of the justice of the majestic
cause, and having a deep confidence in the overruling and merciful
God, he was enabled to retain, in hours of darkest gloom, a
cheerfulness of spirit, which often found vent in broadest and most
grotesque humors. I doubt not that this constitutional blithesomeness
of soul was one of the elements which contributed to the preservation
of his life beneath the most crushing responsibilities that ever fell
on man. And amidst all these distracting, hardening, shrivelling
cares, he ever retained the same freshness and tenderness of
soul. While just and kind to all, he
<pb n="61"/>
                  <figure entity="boardman61">
                     <figDesc>16th page of Reverend
George Dana Boardman's An Address in Commemoration of Abraham
Lincoln</figDesc>
                  </figure>
was, to the very last, in a special sense, the poor man's friend. And
among all those who weep over his untimely death, the chief mourners
of the land, next to the members of his own family, are the sable
millions whom his own hand had set free. I honestly believe that there
never trod the earth a more sympathetic, unselfish, large-hearted,
forgiving man than he. Whatever filled up the vast circumference of
that soul, the thought of Abraham Lincoln's own self was no occupant
of it. By one of those spontaneous consents of the people, which
spring up only on the soil of truth, he was instinctively styled <hi rend="italic">Father Abraham</hi>. He was indeed the father of the whole
American people, from the St. Lawrence to the Mexican Gulf, and he
lived only in his children. For them, east and west, north and south,
loyal and insurgent, he lived, and prayed, and schemed, and toiled,
taxing every power of his clear and comprehending brain, and every
sensibility of his delicate and boundless heart. I know not whether he
was a Christian. The All-seeing alone knows that. Accounts, however,
of his devotional habits have occasionally reached us too
well-authenticated to be set aside. Certainly he had a deep and
abiding sense of the holy authority of God, and an inspiring
confidence in His merciful providence. I could have wished, indeed,
that since he must fall, he had fallen elsewhere, engaged in a purer
service, which had some "relish of salvation in't." But let that glide
into oblivion. It is the solitary cloud that flecked the expanse of
his public career. 
<pb n="62"/>
                  <figure entity="boardman62">
                     <figDesc>17th page of Reverend
George Dana Boardman's An Address in Commemoration of Abraham
Lincoln</figDesc>
                  </figure>
If ever mortal obeyed Wolsey's dying counsel, it was Abraham
Lincoln:</p>
               <lg type="stanza">
                  <l>Cromwell! I charge thee fling away ambition;</l>
                  <l>By that sin
fell the angels; how can man, then,</l>
                  <l>The image of his Maker,
hope to win by 't?</l>
                  <l>Love thyself last; cherish those hearts that
hate thee;</l>
                  <l>Corruption wins not more than honesty.</l>
                  <l>Still
in thy right hand carry gentle peace,</l>
                  <l>To silence envious
tongues. Be just, and fear not!</l>
                  <l>Let all the ends thou aim'st at
be thy Country's,</l>
                  <l>Thy God's and Truth's! Then, if thou fall'st,
O Cromwell!</l>
                  <l>Thou fall'st a blessed martyr!</l>
               </lg>
               <p>And <hi rend="italic">this</hi> is the man so augustly rich in the
elements of an exalted manhood, who has suddenly been stricken down,
not by an adventurous invader from a foreign soil, seeking to avenge
his own nationality; not by a reckless highwayman, who must needs
replenish his empty purse; not by a staggering madman, crazed by his
potations; but by an American desperado, who, whether the appointed
and duly certified organ of conspirators or not, it matters little, is
nevertheless the actual summation and type of that slaveholding power,
which, rather than lose its grasp on the sable chattels made in God's
image, after His likeness, has been willing to drench a continent in
fratricidal blood. Oh, what a type and symbol of this whole
insurrectionary movement of the South, this assassination of President
Lincoln has been! If ever the genius of suicide took upon itself the
impersonation of a human form, it was when this colossal slaveholding
conspiracy was epito-
<pb n="63"/>
                  <figure entity="boardman63">
                     <figDesc>18th page of Reverend
George Dana Boardman's An Address in Commemoration of Abraham
Lincoln</figDesc>
                  </figure>
mized and became incarnate in the person of the diabolical miscreant,
whose only passport to immortality is, that, when the martyr President
fell, his descending shadow fell on <hi rend="italic">him</hi>, and set
his name in blackness of darkness forever more. And yet, were a
merciful Omnipotence to restore to life the dead President, I doubt
not that though some of us may at first have interpreted the voice of
his blood, like that of the world's first martyr by the gates of Eden,
as a cry for vengeance, yet, when those gentle lips moved again, we
should hear a voice, which, like the sweet cadence that softly
billowed the air on the first Good Friday, speaketh better things than
that of Abel. And I believe that even to-day there are thousands of
penitent ones in those desolated Southern homes, whose rebellious
pride has been subdued by this awful parricide, and who, were the
privilege allowed them, would come and</p>
               <lg type="stanza">
                  <l>Kiss dead Caesar's wounds,</l>
                  <l>And dip their napkins in his
sacred blood;</l>
                  <l>Yea, beg a hair of him for memory,</l>
                  <l>And,
dying, mention it within their wills,</l>
                  <l>Bequeathing it as richest
legacy </l>
                  <l>Unto their issue.</l>
               </lg>
               <p>Yes, it shall be said of the martyred President as was said three
thousand years ago of the grand old Hebrew judge and patriot, "The
dead which he slew at his death were more than they which he slew in
his life."</p>
               <p>My countrymen! I have woven my garland, simple and unworthy as it
is, and hung it on the bier. It is
<pb n="64"/>
                  <figure entity="boardman64">
                     <figDesc>19th page of Reverend
George Dana Boardman's An Address in Commemoration of Abraham
Lincoln</figDesc>
                  </figure>
scarce fitting to linger longer. For even now the sad cortege has
begun to move which shall bear to his last sleeping-place all that is
mortal of the martyr statesman, patriot, emancipator, and friend. And
as in the days of King Joash, when the body of the dead Israelite, on
being let down into the sepulchre of Elisha, and on touching the bones
of the mighty prophet, was revived and stood on its feet again, so may
God grant that as the nation's dead heart reverently touches to-day
the dead heart of the great patriot, it may be quickened into life
again, and stand before the astonished nations in all the strength and
splendor of a new-born majesty!</p>
               <p>Yes! move on in majestic state to thy Illinois tomb, amidst the
bowing ranks of a weeping nation, thou illustrious martyr for us all!
Thy dead, murdered corse is the watchword, and, with God's grace, the
victor paean of an emancipated, chastened, glorified Republic!</p>
            </div2>
         </div1>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI.2>