<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader><fileDesc>
         <titleStmt n="Personal Forgiveness and Public Justice">
            <title>  Personal
Forgiveness and Public Justice</title>
            <author>Booth, Robert
Russell</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Compiled and edited by</resp>
               <name>Beck Center</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent/>
         <publicationStmt><publisher>Lewis H. Beck Center</publisher><pubPlace>Emory University</pubPlace><address>
               <addrLine>Atlanta,
Georgia</addrLine>
            </address><availability>
               <p>1996 Emory
University. Permission is granted to download, transmit, or otherwise
reproduce, distribute or display the contributions to the work claimed
by Emory University for non-profit educational purposes, provided
this header is included in its entirety.  For inquiries about
commercial uses, contact the Director, 
Pitts Theology Library, Emory
University, Atlanta, Georgia 30322</p>
            </availability><date>1999</date></publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Lincoln
Sermons Project</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Booth, Robert
Russell. Personal Forgiveness and Public Justice. A Sermon Preached in
the Mercer Street Presbyterian Church, New York, April 23, 1865.
Published by Request of the Young Men's Association of the Church. New
York: Anson D. F. Randolph, No. 770 Broadway. 1865.</bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc><encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This text
derives from the Special Collections 
of Pitts Theology Library, Emory University, and is produced in 
collaboration with the Lewis H. Beck Center, the Emory 
Preservation Office, and Pitts Theology Library.</p>
            <p>TRANSCRIBER: Lewis H. Beck Center and Emory University Preservation Office.</p>
            <p>PRODUCER:  BookLab, Inc., 1606 Headway Circle, Suite 100, Austin, TX 78754</p>
            <p>CAPTURE DEVICE: XEROX DocuImage 620S flatbed scanner</p>
            <p>CAPTURE DETAILS: Scanner software: XEROX ScanTool version 4.2.3; no gamma correction; images are all bitonal.</p>
            <p>CHANGE HISTORY: Using the Adobe Photoshop Batch Processor, we interpolated  the original TIFF files to 8-bit grays, and altered the resolution to 144 dpi, producing screen images twice the original size.  We then saved them in JPEG format.  We produced GIF thumbnails from the JPEG files.</p>
            <p>RESOLUTION: 600 ppi</p>
            <p>COMPRESSION: Resolution 144 per inch with Constrain Properties to 72 per inch.</p>
            <p>SOURCE: Original documents.</p>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc><revisionDesc><change><name>Stewart Varner</name> transformed this document from p4 to p5 on <date when="2010-03-22">March 22, 2010</date></change><change xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><date>1999</date><label>Staff</label><name>Scott Ellis</name>SGML tags inserted in compliance
with TEI guidelines using TEILITE</change></revisionDesc></teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div1 xml:id="booth.001" n="Personal Forgiveness and Public Justice" type="text">
            <head> 
               <bibl> 
                  <title>Personal
Forgiveness and Public Justice</title> 
                  <date>April, 23 1865</date>
                  <pubPlace>Mercer Street Presbyterian Church, New York</pubPlace>
                  <author>Booth, Robert Russell</author> 
                  
                     <pubPlace>New
York</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Anson D. F. Randolph</publisher>
                     <date>1865</date>
                   
               <idno type="ark">http://pid.emory.edu/ark:/25593/15psm</idno></bibl> 
            </head>
            <p>
               <figure><graphic url=""/>
                  <figDesc>1st page of Robert Russell Booth's
Personal Forgiveness and Public Justice.</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <p>PERSONAL FORGIVENESS AND PUBLIC JUSTICE.</p>
            <p>A SERMON</p>
            <p>PREACHED IN THE</p>
            <p>MERCER STREET PRESBYTERIAN CHURCH,</p>
            <p>NEW YORK, APRIL 23, 1865.</p>
            <p>BY THE PASTOR,</p>
            <p>ROBERT RUSSELL BOOTH, D.D.</p>
            <p>PUBLISHED BY REQUEST OF THE YOUNG MEN'S ASSOCIATION OF THE
CHURCH.</p>
            <p>NEW YORK:</p>
            <p>ANSON D. F. RANDOLPH,</p>
            <p>No. 770 BROADWAY.</p>
            <p>1865.</p>
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>
               <figure><graphic url=""/>
                  <figDesc>2nd page of
Robert Russell Booth's Personal Forgiveness and Public
Justice.</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>
               <figure><graphic url=""/>
                  <figDesc>3rd page of
Robert Russell Booth's Personal Forgiveness and Public
Justice.</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <div2 xml:id="booth.002" n="SERMON" type="sermon">
               <head>SERMON.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <p>"Dearly beloved, avenge not yourselves, but
rather give place unto wrath: for it is written, Vengeance is mine; I
will repay, saith the Lord."-ROMANS xii. 19.</p>
                  <p>"Let every soul be subject unto the higher powers; for
there is no power but of God: the powers that be are ordained of
God. Whosoever therefore resisteth the power, resisteth the ordinance
of God; and they that resist shall receive to themselves
damnation."-ROMANS xiii. 1,2.</p>
               </epigraph>
               <p>In directing your attention to these two distinct
sentiments of Holy Writ, a few preliminary statements will further the
end we have in view, and will make their application more apparent.</p>
               <p>In times like these, the public good demands that the light
of God's word shall be thrown clearly upon the amazing succession of
events which commands the attention of men. We listen to the voices of
those who stand in places of power; we read the carefully-prepared
editorials of the public journals, and to a large degree our opinions
are moulded by the influences which these organs exert upon us. But
whatever may be the tone and direction of these, it is perfectly
evident that the pulpit has a duty to discharge in applying the truths
of the Bible to the great events of the hour, and if this is
<pb n="4"/>
                  <figure><graphic url=""/>
                     <figDesc>4th page of Robert Russell
Booth's Personal Forgiveness and Public Justice.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
not faithfully done, then the pulpit is false to its trust.</p>
               <p>We may not, indeed, claim for it the right-as, with but few
exceptions, its ministers have not the inclination-to interfere in
mere questions of policy; but whenever public affairs stand in the
area of those sublime and eternal moral principles which God has
affirmed, then the duty is plain-the truth must be uttered as it has
pleased God to reveal it. This is the more imperative in a country
like ours; under a form of government which rivets responsibility
directly upon the people, and which reflects the integrity of their
sentiments directly in the mirror of the public administration.</p>
               <p>True as this is at all times, it is especially true in the
presence of events such as these which now thrill our hearts. We must
be blind, indeed, and wilful, if we do not realize that God is now
speaking to us in solemn accents, and pointing out by His providence,
the path of our duty and the dangers that beset us.</p>
               <p>We have passed almost, if not altogether, through the Red
Sea of rebellion and civil war; we have witnessed the utter
discomfiture of our enemies and the overthrow of their unrighteous
cause; we have raised our song of victory and of praise for so great a
deliverance, and now each loyal heart thrills with
<pb n="5"/>
                  <figure><graphic url=""/>
                     <figDesc>5th page of Robert Russell
Booth's Personal Forgiveness and Public Justice.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
the consciousness that not only for ourselves, but for the whole human
race and for far-distant ages, has our nationality been raised from
the dust, cleared from the manifold embarrassments of the past, and
established anew on a basis of union and liberty.</p>
               <p>One shadow alone dims the grandeur and rapture of this hour
of triumph. But that is so deep and sombre that it has drawn away all
eyes from the constellation of beauty, which begins to shine again in
the firmament, to fix them upon the pale form which that shadow
covers.</p>
               <p>The death of the President, in the midst of the national
rejoicing--his murder at the very hour when he was bending the
energies of his clear head and generous heart to the great work of
healing the wounds of the nation and restoring the breaches made by
the rebellion--compels us to pause, not only for lamentation and woe,
but also to inquire what God has intended to teach us by His
permissive providence.</p>
               <p>Not without meaning, as I firmly
believe, has this deep sense of injury been inflicted upon us. Not
without a purpose of God has this last cruel blow been struck by those
who were in sympathy with the cause of treason and slavery. If we
cannot bring ourselves to think that God has ordained
<pb n="6"/>
                  <figure><graphic url=""/>
                     <figDesc>6th page of Robert Russell
Booth's Personal Forgiveness and Public Justice.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
it, at least we know that in permitting it He has had an end to
accomplish, a lesson to teach. What this lesson is, it behooves us to
consider.</p>
               <p>Incidentally, it has taught us much about the frailty of
man, and the vanity of all earthly greatness; and much about the
wickedness which the lost human heart can conceive and
accomplish. Incidentally, also, it has revealed, as never before, the
strength of our Republican Government; receiving as it did this deadly
wound full on the front, yet hardly reeling for a moment, but
standing, ere the shock had passed, like the prophetic Church of
God--"fair as the moon, clear as the sun, and terrible as an army with
banners."</p>
               <p>Yet, salutary and impressive as these lessons are, we
cannot doubt that the Divine purpose disclosed in this event is of far
more importance and points in a different direction. It reveals to us,
and was intended to reveal, the depths of darkness which were
concealed under the specious defenses of secession and slavery, and
the utter impossibility of any national compromise with the crimes
which they have committed.</p>
               <p>This I take to be the great lesson to which God, by His
providence, is now directing the attention of this stricken people.</p>
               <p>It can hardly be denied that, as a nation, we
<pb n="7"/>
                  <figure><graphic url=""/>
                     <figDesc>7th page of Robert Russell
Booth's Personal Forgiveness and Public Justice.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
were in a position of danger before this calamity befell us, through a
prevalent disposition to overlook the sanctions of law, and to treat
the authors of our political woes as if their crimes deserved to be
condoned rather than to be punished. The marvelous magnanimity of the
Government seemed almost prepared to disregard the great principle of
the Divine law, which requires the administration of justice, not only
for the punishment of the guilty, but also for the defense of the
innocent. In the brilliancy of our military success, the crime of
rebellion against a free constitutional government was beginning to be
lightly esteemed, and the restraints which must ever be the safeguard
of liberty were in danger of being more seriously broken down in the
hour of our triumph than even in the suspense of the conflict. Had
these lenient sentiments been exercised without interruption, it would
have been most unfortunate for the nation and for the world; the
largest indulgence would have been given to the leaders of anarchy and
misrule the world over, could they have been allowed to infer that the
failure of the infamous schemes would involve only their subordinates
in ruin, while they themselves might hope to get safely off in the
haze of their more daring criminality.</p>
               <p>In such a juncture our Government needed an
<pb n="8"/>
                  <figure><graphic url=""/>
                     <figDesc>8th page of Robert Russell
Booth's Personal Forgiveness and Public Justice.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
infusion of the Old Testament severity rather than of the New
Testament tenderness, and it seems clear that God has intended, by
this sudden and appalling calamity, to bring to our remembrance those
truths of distributive justice which stand out so clearly in His
dealings with Israel of old, and which do indeed underlie the whole
framework of Gospel salvation.</p>
               <p>There is a prevalent mistake concerning the bearing of that
old dispensation upon the Divine government as now administered. It is
regarded by many as entirely a thing of the past; abrogated when
Christ came to achieve our deliverance. It is supposed that justice,
as an attribute of God, has gone into abeyance, and that the only
example which is now binding upon us as individuals, and as nations,
is that of the gentle and forgiving Lamb of God. But can we forget
that Christ came not to destroy the law, but to fulfill it? How can we
miss the meaning of that great sacrifice on the altar of justice, by
which God can be just and yet justify those who believe in Jesus? That
Divine wrath against sin is not extinguished because sinners are
pardoned. That stern word of the law, "the soul that sinneth it shall
die," is as true in the light of the forgiveness conferred at the
cross, as it is in the darkness when there is "weeping and wailing
<pb n="9"/>
                  <figure><graphic url=""/>
                     <figDesc>9th page of Robert Russell
Booth's Personal Forgiveness and Public Justice.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
and gnashing of teeth." God did not remit the sanctions of His holy
law when He became reconciled to man through the blood of
atonement. Nor have the Old Testament ethics lost their application,
either to personal duty and destiny or to the guidance of nations. As
God passes before us now in his goodness, we hear the same voice which
Moses heard in the Mount, proclaiming, "the Lord, the Lord God,
merciful and gracious, long suffering, and abundant in goodness and
truth, keeping mercy for thousands, forgiving iniquity and
transgression, and sin, and that will by no means clear the guilty;
visiting the iniquity of the fathers upon the children, and upon the
children's children, unto the third and to the fourth generation."
Here is Justice standing on guard at the door of His temple of grace,
and vindicating His law to the letter, both to those whom He pardons
and to those whom He punishes. We must thus understand the New
Testament in the light of the Old, or we shall misunderstand it, and
we must conform our opinions and practices, as individuals and as a
nation, to these clear moral principles, or our morality will be
extinguished in license and all social order will be wrecked on the
insurgent passions of men.</p>
               <p>In view of these truths, we urge, therefore, that the
principle on which the Divine government is
<pb n="10"/>
                  <figure><graphic url=""/>
                     <figDesc>10th page of Robert
Russell Booth's Personal Forgiveness and Public
Justice.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
administered, is strictly applicable to the welfare of nations. <hi rend="italic">Deliberate sin must be punished according to law, or
forgiven only with the approval of justice</hi>.</p>
               <p>This is the process which is revealed to us, in the moral
government of the world, through the incarnation and atonement of our
Lord Jesus Christ. And this is the truth to which the hearts of this
nation have been solemnly turned in this season of mourning.</p>
               <p>There are <hi rend="italic">two distinct sentiments</hi>
which have been struggling together in our national councils, as the
question of the final adjustment of our difficulties has come
practically before us. The minds of Christian men have also been
exercised mightily concerning the true mode of harmonizing the Divine
law of forgiveness and goodwill to our enemies, and the Divine law of
punishment in the interest of justice and for the welfare of
society.</p>
               <p>It is evident, when we place side by side two passages like
those which I have read at the outset, that they are either in direct
contradiction, or that there is a rule of personal conduct laid down
in the Gospel which cannot be carried into strict operation in the
administration of public affairs.</p>
               <p>On the one hand, we meet those precepts of the Saviour and
His apostles which direct us to the
<pb n="11"/>
                  <figure><graphic url=""/>
                     <figDesc>11th page of Robert
Russell Booth's Personal Forgiveness and Public
Justice.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
most patient endurance of wrong, without a thought of revenge or an
attempt to make ourselves the executioners of justice.</p>
               <p>The first part of the text stands for an illustration of
these: "Dearly beloved, avenge not yourselves, but rather give place
unto wrath: for it is written, Vengeance is mine; I will repay, saith
the Lord. Therefore, if thine enemy hunger, feed him; if he thirst,
give him drink: for in so doing thou shalt heap coals of fire on his
head. Be not overcome of evil, but overcome evil with good."</p>
               <p>And following this directly we meet those mandates of
public justice, which gleam before us in the 13th chapter of the same
epistle; which represent the rulers of nations as ordained of God to
be a terror to all evil-doers; revengers to execute wrath upon all who
transgress their authority.</p>
               <p>Is there then a manifest contradiction in these two Divine
orders, or are we to understand that there is a law of public justice,
which must transcend altogether the dictates of personal and private
forgiveness? Undoubtedly the latter is the only tenable view, and it
can be justified and made perfectly plain, as soon as we consider what
human government really is, and how the sanctions of just human laws
are essential to the wellbeing of man.</p>
               <pb n="12"/>
               <p>
                  <figure><graphic url=""/>
                     <figDesc>12th page of
Robert Russell Booth's Personal Forgiveness and Public
Justice.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <p>In the first place, God meets us in the Gospel as members
of a lost race, individually guilty and individually condemned. As He
offers forgiveness for the sake of His Son, He bids us purge our
hearts from the old leaven of malice and selfishness and unrighteous
enmity, and to possess the Spirit of Christ, who died for us, "leaving
us an example, that we should follow His steps: who did no sin,
neither was guile found in His mouth: who, when he was reviled,
reviled not again; when He suffered, He threatened not; but committed
himself to Him that judgeth righteously." This is always <hi rend="italic">our personal rule</hi>; love to our enemies, forgiveness
of injuries, kindness of reproving their faults, generosity in
rewarding them with good for their evil.</p>
               <p>We are to take this golden rule and practice it, just as
far as God has applied, that is, in all personal relations. But it is
evident that it needs to be limited in certain respects. For, if it
stood alone or without limitation, it would be quite impossible to
justify war, or to engage in it without sin, no matter how righteous
the cause for which it was waged. Nay, more; if this golden rule stood
alone, we should find it impossible to sustain the integrity of the
social condition of man, or to arrest and punish malefactors and
criminals. So far as the Christian might be concerned, under this
<pb n="13"/>
                  <figure><graphic url=""/>
                     <figDesc>13th page of Robert
Russell Booth's Personal Forgiveness and Public
Justice.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
law alone, society would be dissolved into a chaos of impunity in the
commission of crime, and of suffering on the part of the purest and
best.</p>
               <p>But God has set the limitation at the right place. While
the individual is bound by these gentle precepts, governments are
organized on a different plan altogether. The State represents the
Divine sovereignty over the earthly conduct and interests of
associated individuals. Law is its basis, justice is its animating
principle, security is its end, punishment is its prerogative.</p>
               <p>Therefore, in the second place, we are not authorized to
bring these personal sentiments, which we cherish as individuals, into
the administration of public affairs; but must stand by the letter of
God's word as it applies to them, and must recognize Governments as
divinely commissioned to administer justice, in rewarding the good and
in punishing the evil.</p>
               <p>This principle runs clearly through the Old Testament
history, and is reaffirmed in the New. Just in proportion as this is
lost sight of does the State weaken, and the tendencies to misrule and
corruption increase.</p>
               <p>It is not indeed requisite that the strict letter of law
should always be observed in meting out punishment. Extenuating
circumstances continually modify its application. But unless the
ruling pur-
<pb n="14"/>
                  <figure><graphic url=""/>
                     <figDesc>14th page of Robert
Russell Booth's Personal Forgiveness and Public
Justice.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
pose is to honor the law and to administer government in the interest
of justice, the State is always in peril, and anarchy lies in wait at
the door.</p>
               <p>If we carry over these principles to the questions which
all men are pondering now, their bearing is plain:</p>
               <p>WE HAVE NO RIGHT AS INDIVIDUALS TO BE VINDICTIVE, BUT AS A
NATION WE MUST BE JUST. The sentiments and conduct which we could not
exercise, if we had been injured in our personal welfare, become
needful and proper, when we act in behalf of the State, whose majesty
has been defied, whose laws have been broken, whose very life has been
put in peril. We may obey the voice of the holy Apostle, in the first
of these passages, while we insist that the State shall obey his
precepts in the second.</p>
               <p>Personally every one of us has suffered irreparable wrongs
by this rebellion. Who or what can compensate for the loss of
treasure, for the fearful solicitudes, for the nights of agonizing
suspense, for the contemplation of those things which have passed
before us, in the sad years gone by. Many present have suffered also
in far deeper anguish. I have seen here the venerable old man,
tortured with ceaseless anxiety for his sons away in the war. I have
seen the widow bowing in heartbroken anguish for her only son slain on
the field. Fathers, too, have been mourning here like David for his
<pb n="15"/>
                  <figure><graphic url=""/>
                     <figDesc>15th page of Robert
Russell Booth's Personal Forgiveness and Public
Justice.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
lost Absalom. Twice have we gathered in our place of worship to bury
two of the noblest of our American youth. Nay, more than this; who of
us all is not in his own heart a mourner to-day? As we stand
awe-struck and tearful at the cruel fate of our Martyr-President, it
seems as though each family circle had lost its head; and from every
heart goes up a cry like that of Elisha: "My father, my father! the
chariot of Israel, and the horsemen thereof."</p>
               <p>And yet for us all, in this manifold experience of personal
injury, the Gospel law of forgiveness is emphatic and clear. Let the
mourners weep, but curse not, for, "Vengeance is mine; I will repay,
saith the Lord." He that cometh from Edom, with dyed garments from
Bozrah, all glorious in His apparel, is now travelling among us in the
greatness of His strength; and they that fear the Lord can leave their
cause in His care, as He moves through the land proclaiming by His
providence, "the day of vengeance is in mine heart, and the year of my
redeemed is come."</p>
               <p>But with this sentiment of personal forgiveness, it will
never do to confound the obligations which belong to us as members of
a commonwealth, or rather of a nation which has been set on the high
places of the earth by God himself, to maintain the
<pb n="16"/>
                  <figure><graphic url=""/>
                     <figDesc>16th page of Robert
Russell Booth's Personal Forgiveness and Public
Justice.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
interests of public justice, humanity and truth. At this point our
responsibility is drawn, not from the 12th but from the 13th chapter
of the Epistle to the Romans. It is drawn not from the gentle impulses
of personal piety, but from the stern mandate of the eternal law of
God. As members of a community, founded upon law, it is imperative
upon us to demand the administration of justice according to law.</p>
               <p>Nothing more vigorous or more comprehensive can be said on
this point than the utterance of President Johnson to the Illinois
delegation a few days ago: "The American people must be taught, if
they do not already feel, that treason is a crime, and must be
punished; that the Government will not always bear with its enemies;
that it is strong, not only to protect, but also to punish. When we
turn to the criminal code and examine the catalogue of crimes, we find
there arson laid down as a crime, with its appropriate penalty; we
find there theft and robbery and murder given as crimes, and there,
too, we find the last and highest of crimes--treason. With other and
inferior offenses our people are familiar, but in our peaceful
history! treason has been almost unknown. The people must understand
that it is the blackest of crimes, and will surely be punished."</p>
               <pb n="17"/>
               <p>
                  <figure><graphic url=""/>
                     <figDesc>17th page of
Robert Russell Booth's Personal Forgiveness and Public
Justice.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <p>These are brave words, and the nation is stronger to-day
than ever before, because they were uttered with the clear emphasis of
one in authority.</p>
               <p>Let no man forget that equity is the true, the Divine basis
of government, and that leniency to crime, in defiance of law, is an
open door into the treasury where the regalia of nations are lying. It
was for justice that the elder Brutus gave his two sons to the lictors
of Rome, and sat unmoved on his judgment-seat when they laid their
guilty heads on the block. It was for justice that George Washington
signed the death-warrant of the unhappy Andre, though his tender pity
made the tears run down his cheeks. It is the claim of justice that
the authors of this tremendous crime of rebellion against the
liberties of America, and of the enormous misery which has followed
it, should be condemned and punished, and the people must rise to the
stern virtue which will accept the claim, and cry "Amen" to its
fulfillment.</p>
               <p>This is essential, as much in the interest of private
security as of public justice. Unrestrained mercy to criminals is
always cruelty to the innocent. It is necessary for us to make
rebellion perilous and odious for all time to come. We cannot afford,
as a people, to invite by our leniency a new assault upon our union
and liberty.</p>
               <pb n="18"/>
               <p>
                  <figure><graphic url=""/>
                     <figDesc>18th page of
Robert Russell Booth's Personal Forgiveness and Public
Justice.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <p>It is well said by Samuel Rogers, in his "Sketches in
Italy," that whenever justice is ill-administered, the injured will
redress themselves. Robbery provokes to robbery, murder to
assassination. Resentments become hereditary, and what began in
disorder ends as if all hell had broke loose. Laws create a habit of
self-restraint, not only by the influence of fear, but by regulating
in its exercise the passion of revenge. If they overawe the bad by a
prospect of punishment, certain and well-defined, they console the
injured by the infliction of that punishment; and as the infliction is
a public act, it excites and entails no enmity. The laws are offended,
and the community, for its own sake, pursues and overtakes the
offender, often without the concurrence of the sufferer, sometimes
against his wishes.<ref target="#booth.002.n01">*</ref></p>
               <p>And now from this ground we are prepared to meet the final
inquiry to which all these principles converge.</p>
               <p>Who, then, are properly amenable to this claim which comes
before us in the second portion of our text?</p>
               <p>I answer, first, <hi rend="italic">the institutions</hi> in
the interest of which the rebellion has been organized, and this last
direful crime has been wrought; secession and slavery, the twin
horrors which have sought to</p>
               <note xml:id="booth.002.n01" n="*" place="foot" anchored="true">
                  <p>"Italy," Part II., Sect. 6.</p>
               </note>
               <pb n="19"/>
               <p>
                  <figure><graphic url=""/>
                     <figDesc>19th page of
Robert Russell Booth's Personal Forgiveness and Public
Justice.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <p>rule or to ruin this land--criminal in every aspect--barbarous,
ruthless, ruinous to the bodies and the souls of men. To sustain and
to perpetuate them, woes unutterable have been wrought among us. For
these, 300,000 men or more are lying cold beneath the sod to-day, or
bleaching under a southern sky. For these, as many more have been
brought home to live among us, maimed, mutilated and suffering. For
these, widows are weeping, children are defenseless, and the world is
filled with wonder for our shame. Secession and slavery have done this
work. Let them perish! In the grave of our murdered President, let the
last vestige of them be buried, and let their memory rot, never to be
spoken of with approval hereafter by a true patriot or Christian
man. Let the axe be laid to the roots of these deadly trees, and as
they fall for ever, heaven and earth will raise new hallelujahs to the
throne of the Most High.</p>
               <p>And besides these institutions, who are properly amenable
to the claims of justice? I answer, second, <hi rend="italic">those
leading men</hi>, whether of Northern or of Southern birth, who have
contrived and consummated all this crime and misery; those who enjoyed
the benignant nurture of the Government only to aim their murderous
hands straight to its throat; those who, to gratify a personal
ambition, rent the land
<pb n="20"/>
                  <figure><graphic url=""/>
                     <figDesc>20th page of Robert
Russell Booth's Personal Forgiveness and Public
Justice.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
asunder, and strode through tears and blood to transient years of
power; those who have fanned the flames of hatred between the people
who were once peacefully united; who have murdered helpless prisoners
by thousands; who have wrought outrages upon the loyal men of their
own section, beside which the horrors of the Sepoy mutiny seem like
the work of children; those who, through these four bitter years, have
known no end but to annihilate the union of our fathers, and who have
consummated all their foul misdeeds by laying low our gentle, generous
chief. Let them have justice, be they who they may, statesmen or
soldiers, editors, artizans or planters, open foes or treacherous
friends--let them have justice! This land is broad but it is not broad
enough for them and us. Henceforth, let them have no name, nor right,
nor memorial in Israel. "O my soul, come not thou into their secret;
unto their assembly, mine honor, be not thou united: cursed be their
anger, for it was fierce; and their wrath, for it was cruel; I will
divide them in Jacob, and scatter them in Israel."</p>
               <p>And are there others still, to whom this law of justice
appertains? Yes, but with another application of it altogether. There
is a nobler conquest yet before us at the South--the conquest of
light, and love, and generosity, and pity, over all those who
<pb n="21"/>
                  <figure><graphic url=""/>
                     <figDesc>21st page of Robert
Russell Booth's Personal Forgiveness and Public
Justice.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
have been misled by ignorance or maddened by lying words, or drawn by
force into the mad rush of battle. The helpless people, angry,
stubborn, willful though they may be still; they have a claim upon us
now, a claim of justice the claim which the weak have always on the
strong, and the miserable on the prosperous. As solemnly as we are
called to punish deliberate transgressors, are we called upon to
shelter and protect the ignorant transgressor. It is ours as a nation
to bid these dry bones live, to build up these waste places, to purge
corrupted institutions, to upheave the roots of bitterness and sow
upon the track of desolation the seeds of liberty and Christian
love. And this also will we do, if God assist us by His grace, until
ere long brighter harvests shall be waving on that sunny soil than
ever yet were planted there; until a nationality is builded there
which is bone of our bone and flesh of our flesh; with one temple for
the people, consecrated to law and justice and true religion; with one
loyal and fraternal impulse ruling the hearts of all who have come
forth from this great tribulation, and who will stand before the world
in brighter years to come, to proclaim the honors and to defend the
rights of constitutional freedom in America.</p>
               <p>This work of justice toward the people, which
<pb n="22"/>
                  <figure><graphic url=""/>
                     <figDesc>22nd page of Robert
Russell Booth's Personal Forgiveness and Public
Justice.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
the providence of God now lays upon us, is brought the more
impressively before us now, as we stand on the threshold of that civic
pageant which is to honor the memory of that great and good man whose
life was consecrated to the union of these States, and whose death has
sealed his glorious record.</p>
               <p>It will be ours, as a community, to receive tomorrow the
sacred dust, which comes to touch our hearts once more with pity, and
to speak to us, through those sealed lips, more solemnly than any
voice of eloquence or power could speak.</p>
               <p>Amid the tolling bells, the beat of muffled drums, the
mournful music, and the steady tramping of these long funereal
procession, the mortal part of Abraham Lincoln will be brought hither,
and will pass forth from us to his last resting-place beneath the
prairies of the West.</p>
               <p>Amid all the thrilling lessons of this heroic time, amid
all the strong incentives to patriotic self-devotion, and to humble
trust in God, which have been urged upon us, perhaps the most
impressive lesson, and the loftiest impulse will be connected with
these funereal honors to our martyred President; who, though dead, yet
speaketh, and evermore will speak, for the Union which he saved, for
the liberty he guarded, and for the oppressed millions whom he raised
to freedom.</p>
               <pb n="23"/>
               <p>
                  <figure><graphic url=""/>
                     <figDesc>23rd page of
Robert Russell Booth's Personal Forgiveness and Public
Justice.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <p>And if it is given unto those who have passed within the
veil which hides the eternal world from us to look back upon these
scenes, and to survey the progress of the work which fell unfinished
from their hands; if spirits of the blessed know the progress and
triumph of those interests for which they labored, who shall say that
our last martyr has not already had a recompense for all his patient
toil, and for his bitter death?</p>
               <p>Yes, from the everlasting hills surveying a nation
reunited, round the pale form which journeys through the land he loved
so well, doubtless he understands it all; and bowing before the
Saviour, to whom he gave his weary heart, among the graves of
Gettysburg, he joins with cheerful voice the song of those who have
gotten the victory over the beast, and over his image, and over his
mark, saying, as they stand on the sea of glass, having harps of gold,
"Great and marvelous are thy works, Lord God Almighty; just and true
are thy ways, thou King of saints!"</p>
            </div2>
         </div1>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>