<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader><fileDesc>
         <titleStmt n="Abraham Lincoln: The Just Magistrate, the Representative Statesman, the Practical Philanthropist">
            <title>Abraham Lincoln: The
Just Magistrate, the Representative Statesman, the Practical
Philanthropist</title>
            <author>Bullock, Alex. H.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Compiled and edited by</resp>
               <name>Beck
Center</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent/>
         <publicationStmt><publisher>Lewis H. Beck Center</publisher><pubPlace>Emory University</pubPlace><address>
               <addrLine>Atlanta,
Georgia</addrLine>
            </address><availability>
               <p>1996 Emory
University. Permission is granted to download, transmit, or otherwise
reproduce, distribute or display the contributions to the work claimed
by Emory University for non-profit educational purposes, provided
this header is included in its entirety.  For inquiries about
commercial uses, contact the Director, 
Pitts Theology Library, Emory
University, Atlanta, Georgia 30322</p>
            </availability><date>1999</date></publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Lincoln
Sermons Project</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Bullock,
Alex. H. Abraham Lincoln: The Just Magistrate, the Representative
Statesman, the Practical Philanthropist. Address by Alex. H. Bullock,
Before the City Council and Citizens of Worcester, June 1, 1865.
Worcester: Printed by Charles Hamilton, Palladium.</bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc><encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This text derives from the Special Collections 
of Pitts Theology Library, Emory University, and is produced in 
collaboration with the Lewis H. Beck Center a, the Emory 
Preservation Office, and Pitts Theology Library.</p>
            <p>TRANSCRIBER: Lewis H. Beck Center and Emory University Preservation Office.</p>
            <p>PRODUCER:  BookLab, Inc., 1606 Headway Circle, Suite 100, Austin, TX 78754</p>
            <p>CAPTURE DEVICE: XEROX DocuImage 620S flatbed scanner</p>
            <p>CAPTURE DETAILS: Scanner software: XEROX ScanTool version 4.2.3; no gamma correction; images are all bitonal.</p>
            <p>CHANGE HISTORY: Using the Adobe Photoshop Batch Processor, we interpolated  the original TIFF files to 8-bit grays, and altered the resolution to 144 dpi, producing screen images twice the original size.  We then saved them in JPEG format.  We produced GIF thumbnails from the JPEG files.</p>
            <p>RESOLUTION: 600 ppi</p>
            <p>COMPRESSION: Resolution 144 per inch with Constrain Properties to 72 per inch.</p>
            <p>SOURCE: Original documents.</p>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc><revisionDesc><change><name>Stewart Varner</name> transformed this document from p4 to p5 on <date when="2010-03-22">March 22, 2010</date></change><change xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><date>1999</date><label>Staff</label><name>Scott Ellis</name>SGML tags inserted in compliance
with TEI guidelines using TEILITE</change></revisionDesc></teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div1 xml:id="bullock.001" n="Abraham Lincoln: The Just Magistrate, the Representative Statesman, the Practical Philanthropist" type="text">
            <head> 
               <bibl> 
                  <title>Abraham
Lincoln: The Just Magistrate, the Representative Statesman, the
Practical Philanthropist</title> 
                  <date>June 1, 1865</date>
                  <pubPlace>Worcester</pubPlace> 
                  <author>Bullock, Alex. H.</author>
                  
                     <pubPlace>Worcester</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Printed by Charles
Hamilton, Palladium Office</publisher>
                     <date>[1865]</date>
                  
               <idno type="ark">http://pid.emory.edu/ark:/25593/15pvw</idno></bibl> 
            </head>
            <pb facs="bullock1.jpg"/>
            <p>ABRAHAM LINCOLN</p>
            <p>THE JUST MAGISTRATE, THE REPRESENTATIVE STATESMAN,</p>
            <p>THE PRACTICAL PHILANTHROPIST.</p>
            <p>ADDRESS</p>
            <p>BY</p>
            <p>ALEX. H. BULLOCK,</p>
            <p>BEFORE THE CITY COUNCIL AND CITIZENS OF WORCESTER,</p>
            <p>JUNE 1, 1865.</p>
            <p>WORCESTER:</p>
            <p>PRINTED BY CHARLES HAMILTON,</p>
            <p>PALLADIUM
OFFICE.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="bullock2.jpg"/>
            <p>City of Worcester,</p>
            <p>In City Council, June 1st, 1865.</p>
            <p>RESOLVED, That the unanimous thanks of the City Council are hereby
tendered to the Hon. ALEXANDER H. BULLOCK for his able and eloquent
Eulogy upon the Life and Services of the late PRESIDENT LINCOLN,
delivered, at the request of the Council, in Mechanics Hall this day,
and that he be requested to furnish a copy for publication.</p>
            <p>A copy.  Attest, </p>
            <p>SAMUEL SMITH, <hi rend="italic">City Clerk</hi>.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="bullock3.jpg"/>
            <div2 xml:id="bullock.002" n="EULOGY" type="sermon">
               <head>EULOGY.</head>
               <p>IT would be a painful suppression of one of the finest of human
instincts and an unbecoming disregard of the official proclamation of
the chief magistrate, if this city were not among the foremost to
accord its voice to the funeral cry of the nation. Never before, in
high joy or deep grief, has the normal simplicity of America given way
to such pageant grandeur. The great fountains of public sorrow have
been broken up, and a whole people have turned out to herald their
President returning in silence to the dust of the prairie. I look back
over forty centuries for the like of this. My eye discerns no fit
resemblance in anything which the conceits of heathen mythology have
transmitted,--not in that mythical sympathy of the Tiber for
Marcellus, fortunate recipient of such honor,--nor in the many
memorial Italian marbles and temples--nor in all the tasteful
<pb n="4" facs="bullock4.jpg"/>
pomp which has conducted French kings to their imperial sleep, and has
made their capital a vast lettered monument to its one great
departed,--nor in the drum-beat, and cathedral service, and royal
guard, which have escorted English monarchs from the palace to the
Abbey. The earliest and latest age alone meet now in comparison of
mournful pageantry. The Orient and the West, the third of Hebrew
patriarchs and the sixteenth President, four thousand years apart, are
pictured before us to-day in the same spectacle and lesson of a nation
following a just and true ruler to his tomb.</p>
               <p>I do not suppose that in all the intervening period,
fretted and gilded as it has been with art and culture, anything like
the passage of the herald-corpse of Jacob from his death-bed to the
field and cave of his fathers, in public turn-out, and general
lamentation, and sincerity of grief, has occurred before until now. To
the two thousand dependents of that deceased, to all those sent forth
by his premier-son, the most munificent of the line of Egyptian kings
ordered all the public men of his country to report for additional
escort on the long and patient and solemn march. Chariots and
horsemen, men and maidens, the grim visages of age and the dusky
beauty of youth, in lengthened procession, with palms, and music, and
benediction, in behalf of that early world paid the last tribute to a
great and just benefactor, to a builder
<pb n="5" facs="bullock5.jpg"/>
of empire. Measuring the days by their solemn tramp and their halts
for local condolence, the swarthy column moved on over two hundred
miles, and laid their treasured hero in the august depository of the
first and second of his line.</p>
               <p>That oriental retinue of bereavement and sublimity has been
matched and eclipsed within this last lunar month. Dying without the
consciousness but amid all the pathos of his Eastern exemplar and
progenitor, the foremost man of this western world has been carried to
his rural rest beyond the mountains and near the great river. Awhile
he lay in state at the capital where he fell, that all classes might
gather about, to learn the lessons of historical providence and
witness the presence of God. His dust, garnered beneath richest
canopies, preceded by raven waving plumes, and flanked by reverse arms
of the flower youth of the land, has been borne on triumphal route
through the chief cities of a continent. The Monumental City opened
her gates in love, which four years before would have closed them
against him, if she had known his coming. Independence Hall struck its
bell, and the dismal undulations spread through half-a-million of
hearts as he passed by. The great Emporium of the North, which had
made a jest of much of his life in office, bowed as a unit, like a
stricken child, and paid such honors to his passing shade as no where
have been witnessed on
<pb n="6" facs="bullock6.jpg"/>
the earth. Still onward and westward, a thousand miles yet to go,
surrounded by vast throngs, all and everywhere reverential, all and
everywhere casting choicest flowers upon the pathway of the dead,--as
if twenty millions had assembled to make ovation before the corporeal
symbol of a benefactor--your President was taken to his last abode,
where he shall rest till the dead shall rise at the call of the
archangel.</p>
               <p>The first shock of our calamity, the deep sensation of
horror which pervaded all our hearts when the "couriers of the air"
told us at midnight how suddenly and in what manner President Lincoln
had a few hours before been snatched away, has now subsided, and we
naturally pause and deliberate upon those qualities of character and
service, which, in the apparent judgment of this country, have already
assigned him a place only second in the long lineage of its
magistrates. However simple this analysis may seem, it falls entirely
outside the common range of our study of public men and events, and
does not belong to the usual analogies of biography or history. It
would be scarcely more irrational to compare the developments and
stages through which we have just passed with any or all the unlike
periods before, than to measure him who has been the central figure in
these civic and martial achievements by the personalities of the
past. He will be known and judged by the next age, not indeed without
regard to his abstract
<pb n="7" facs="bullock7.jpg"/>
quality, but more conspicuously and vividly as the one man, who, in
the unfolding of the panorama of these four years, everywhere appears
in front and in chief. Under the limitations of a single Presidential
term he must pass to his place among critics and annalists; but that
Presidential term was enough to have encircled an historic generation
in other ages, and to have circumscribed the life-long renown of other
statesmen. Safely then may we trust him to that judgment which shall
fall upon his own brief career of rule. Never any man, without public
thought or remembrance of his youth, or early life, or disciplinary
training, has mounted so quickly to the empyrean of fame. Think, for
example, in what manner we usually estimate Napoleon or
Washington. Their distinction dates from the beginning. The genius of
Napoleon is nearly the same to us whether we remember him as a child
playing with a cannon, or as a youth in the Academy, or at
twenty-eight dazzling the nations with his unprecedented
victories. Washington the youth is familiar to our school boys,
appears great in the French war, only greater in the Revolutionary and
Constitutional period which followed. But here is a plain man, since
April opened, gone into the alcoves of all generations to come and of
every race, as to all of his life save the last five years unknown to
half his countrymen and to the whole world beside. Such and so
exceptional
<pb n="8" facs="bullock8.jpg"/>
is our country and our time, such and so exceptional is Abraham
Lincoln.</p>
               <p>And yet he had a childhood and a youth. In that which I
call the first stage of his life, ending when he settled down as a
lawyer in Springfield, I think we may see that fitting, that
preparation, that nascent destination, which was the providential
prelude to the ultimate work. Cast into a sparsely inhabited wild at
eight years, fulfilling the measure of maternal ambition when at ten
he could read the sacred volume, exercising his first conscious power
in writing to his mother's traveling preacher to come and preach over
her grave, writing letters for the neighbors, attending the first
school in that country clad in buckskin, only too happy at length when
he could count as his property a copy of Bunyan and Aesop, a life of
Washington and Clay, behold him whose death forty-five years later
brought autograph letters from every crowned head of Europe. His
library might have been larger, but could it have been better? To his
apprehension of the Divine Word, learned when that was the only volume
in the cabin, we may owe the Cromwell-like second Inaugural, which was
only half appreciated by his countrymen until the praise of it came
from the other side of the water. Did a man ever reflect better the
light of youthful studies, then the President reflected Aesop and
Bunyan? No books are more likely to be remembered than they; Cowper
said that
<pb n="9" facs="bullock9.jpg"/>
his child-readings of the Pilgrim's Progress would abide with him till
memory should perish. And I confess it is to me a grateful fancy, in
looking back for the formative influences in the life of Lincoln, to
perceive in these two masterpieces of inventive and natural conception
such sources of thought and impression as would be best calculated to
produce that combination, which he so remarkably illustrated, and
which was not unrequisite for our time, the Puritan and the
Hoosier. Then we are to remember that in this school of Western life,
with books so few but so good, he acquired what Mr. Burke would call
"the rustic, manly, home-bred sense of this country,"--to have
polished whose ingenuous roughness would have cost us half the power
he has had during this war over the mass of his citizens. They have
liked him all the better, that his wisdom and speech were elementary
and enabled him to speak directly to their hearts. They have liked him
so much the more, that he did not pretend to be learned, while they
knew him to be original and wise. Paucity of opportunities in youth
favored modesty in high position. How many members of Parliament,
asked an English journal, would imitate the modest honesty of the
President and acknowledge that they had never read all parts of
Shakespeare? But he understood and remembered all that he had read.</p>
               <p>And now, before he opens his office of law, we
<pb n="10" facs="bullock10.jpg"/>
catch a glimpse of the young man of nineteen floating as super-cargo
on a flat-boat to New Orleans. It was his last act of rusticity and
adventure. He was now unconsciously completing that democratic type of
character which in its subsequent expansion and use has contributed so
largely to save the union of these States. It was indeed a typical
enterprise, for that voyage represented the unity of interest and
welfare which connects the North-west with the Gulf, and all the
States together from the Crescent round to Malabar. Upon his return he
would enter the gates of productive life, how eventful he then knew
not, nor any one of you. Suppose that in one of those transition
hours, as he was borne lazily on the great currents and by the solemn
forests, his unlettered mind rapt in the rhapsodies of the Prophets,
or the dreams of Bunyan, or the wit of Æsop, or the grandeur of
Washington, the angel of this dedicated youth had raised the curtain
and revealed to him, that before he should pass the ordinary prime of
life he should be elevated to the highest trust of this empire, lifted
on the shoulders of the people in ecstacy at the thought his own words
had kindled of making it all free,--that under his presiding the
issues of life and death to this Union should be unrolled on every
field of a continental war,--that he himself should sit in control
over larger armies than Europe north or south had ever seen,--that his
hand should touch the electric
<pb n="11" facs="bullock11.jpg"/>
wire which should awake four millions of the children of men to
liberty and immortality,--that the government of his country should at
last be sealed in his own blood to eternal security and glory, and
that he, almost yet young, should return to sleep with his fathers,
leaving to both hemispheres a name that shall be hailed with that of
Washington whose history he was even then reading, till time shall be
no more! He would have fallen prostrate before the Vision! And yet
under the beneficence of our institutions if this was to happen at all
it was as likely to happen to him as to any other, and he lived to
behold it, and died in an untimely hour at fifty-seven!</p>
               <p>Upon the second period, that which I call the brawn in his
life, these exercises will not permit me long to dwell. It bears the
journals of twenty years, from the raising of the attorney's sign in
'37 till he gave himself without reclamation to his country at the
opening of '58. They tell us he was an able lawyer, and I can believe
that; but he must have been elementary, not learned. They give us good
accounts of his professional successes; but other and greater scenes
make us forget them. The jurisprudence of the West in his day has
entitled few men to enduring distinction. We know, however, that he
distinguished himself in his own cases, and that he was a favorite
sought to manage the causes of the clients of others. In the
Legislature of his State he measured lances
<pb n="12" facs="bullock12.jpg"/>
with the rising Douglas and there for the first time caught the gleam
of his own future. Once he went into Congress, and left it without
great distinction,--but that should not be counted largely against
him. Yet it was then that he became considerably known in the
country. At that time I met him in the streets of Worcester. Congress
had just adjourned when our Whig State Convention assembled here in
1848. As the chosen head of the city committee of the party with which
he acted, I had called a public meeting in yonder hall for the evening
preceding the convention and had invited several gentlemen of note to
make addresses. None of them came. But as the sun was descending I was
told that Abraham Lincoln, member of Congress from Illinois, was
stopping at one of the hotels in town. I had heard of him before and
at once called upon him and made known my wish that he would address
the meeting in the evening, to which he readily assented. I further
suggested to him that as the party in whose cause we were then united
was largely in a minority here, and as there was an unusual bitterness
in the antagonistic politics of this community, he should practice
much discretion and leave our side as well in its prospects as he
could. His benignant eye caught my meaning and his gentle spirit
responded approval. His address was one of the best it has ever been
my fortune to hear, and left not one root of bitterness behind. Some of
<pb n="13" facs="bullock13.jpg"/>
you will remember all this, but not so distinctly as I do. I never saw
him afterwards. The next day the convention came; the genius-eloquence
of Choate, of blessed memory, was applauded to the echo, and the
stately rhetoric of Winthrop received its reward; but the member from
Illinois, though he remained in town surrounded by associate
congressmen, was that day and in that body unknown and unheard. But
where are they all now,--and where is he,--in the benedictions of his
countrymen, in the gratitude of an enfranchised race, in the love of
mankind!</p>
               <p>In 1858, only seven years ago, Mr. Lincoln was selected by
the Republicans of Illinois as the competitor of Mr. Douglas for a
seat in the Senate of the United States. Thus opened the third and
last period of his life. How strong he was at that time in the
empire-state of the West, is well shown by his having received every
vote in a ballot of twelve hundred chosen delegates in a state
convention. That was the hour of his consecration, of his sacramental
vow, in the service of the country. Then and there he became the
representative man. And now, after reading for the second time his
discussions with his eminent rival in that canvass, I can declare my
conviction that to the clear analysis which he constantly presented of
the purposes and the teachings of the founders of this government, to
the reverence with which he impressed the people for the humane
<pb n="14" facs="bullock14.jpg"/>
and benevolent intent of the Constitution, to the exalted moral
reasons upon which he predicated the new coming era, we are more
largely indebted, than to any other person, for the firm purpose and
high resolve which, two years later, united and inflamed the free
states against the further encroachments of slavery in this
country. You will consider the honorable courage of the man in the
positions he then took. The laws, the traditions, the systems of
Illinois, her southern geography and settlement, the memories and
prejudices of her people, were all against the theories and humanities
which he determined in the fear only of God to proclaim. But his soul
was ablaze with the enthusiasm of a christian statesmanship, and he
went forth in the panoply of immortal truth, which neither the
timidity of friends could strip from him, nor the darts of opponents
could penetrate. He sounded at the opening the bugle note of omen
which rang through the land: "A house divided against itself cannot
stand. I believe this government cannot permanently endure half slave
and half free. I do not expect the Union to be dissolved. I do not
expect the house to fall, but I do expect it will cease to be
divided. It will become all one thing or all the other." Many
elsewhere, some there, hesitated over the high doctrine; large numbers
of Republicans in the North were not unwilling to see Mr. Douglas
successful as a reward for his
<pb n="15" facs="bullock15.jpg"/>
brave contest with Buchanan. I confess that I felt so myself But the
newly invested champion looked over the fleeting hour and the mere
question of a senatorial chair, he saw farther than times or
localities, and pierced beyond the veil which too often shuts off
administrations from the vision of the beatitudes and the ages; he
knew the importance that the banner of a new party, which bore the
name of Freedom, should carry radiant inscriptions, and over all the
state, from her frozen springs to her Egyptian heats, he upheld</p>
               <lg type="stanza">
                  <l>"Th' imperial ensign, which, full high advanced,</l>
                  <l>Shone like a meteor streaming tot he wind."</l>
               </lg>
               <p>By this unwavering fidelity to his convictions, his hour having not
yet come, under the over-ruling of Providence he accomplished both
more and less than he set out for; he made his rival Senator, himself
President, and his country Free. As I look backward over the events of
that year which he so largely controlled; as I follow him sixty times
to the hustings, and hear him in language not one word of which, so
far as I can judge, he would wish to blot, urging those lessons which
the nation must then have received or have passed beneath the yoke of
perpetual humiliation,--as I see him rising from the autumn of '58 to
the spring of '60 to an ascendancy over all others as the advocate of
the primal principles of a free republic, and so recognized across the
whole northern belt from the great plains to the Atlantic frontier,--I
not only
<pb n="16" facs="bullock16.jpg"/>
count him most fortunate of men in the height to which all these
things soon after conducted him and us, but I conclude that if he had
gone then to the sleep in which he now reposes, he would have been
embalmed statesman-father of a new dispensation. The year eighteen
hundred fifty-eight had established him.</p>
               <lg type="stanza">
                  <l>"The boundless prairies learned his name,</l>
                  <l>His words the mountains echoes knew,</l>
                  <l>The Northern breezes swept his fame</l>
                  <l>From icy lake to warm bayou."</l>
               </lg>
               <p>Our greatest Olympiad opened in eighteen hundred sixty. I need not
sketch the preceding or attendant circumstances of the convention and
the nomination. Our first choice was another, and Massachusetts
followed the fine arts of New York to give it success. They have a
better and larger way at the West. While the men of the East were
ciphering at the hotels in Chicago, the men of the Mississippi, the
Ohio, and the Wabash were packing the wigwam and filling the square
with a myriad of large hearts and brazen throats ready to sound
another and a loftier chant. Their candidate took the votes, and the
voice of all rose to the sky like a chorus of nature. It was the echo
of the voice of God.</p>
               <p>Fortunate, providential selection! Any other apparently
would have shipwrecked the Ark of the Covenant. If you consider how
inevitable are the jealousies of the West towards the East, to which we
<pb n="17" facs="bullock17.jpg"/>
must always submit and which we must always palliate since we cannot
prevent or remove them,--if, especially, you reflect what a bond of
fate that Father of Waters is to us all, and how we must keep peace
and conciliation with those River gods if we expect unity, prosperity,
and glory,--if you freshly remember how, since this war began, the
people of the West, though their sons were dying in the same trenches
and in the same hospitals with ours, have thought and said that we
were reaping the greater benefits of the sacrifice,--you will agree
with me that none but a Western President could have kept our armies,
our voters, and our hearts united amid the afflictions and reverses
that have rolled their thunders and their floods over us. And so the
hand of our Fathers' God interposed against our calculations five
years ago at the city of the Lakes.</p>
               <p>Our departed hero accepted the nomination in written words
which are a model for practical religion and modern statesmanship. In
language which shows that the spirit of the Most High was upon him he
wrapped the resolutions around his heart, and in terms which should
have won every citizen from Key West to Richmond he gave himself to
the issue now so triumphant and so sad. It was an issue worthy of the
best days of any nation. As he received it from the convention that
framed it, and as he stated it in his letter of acceptance, it was a
system of policy and
<pb n="18" facs="bullock18.jpg"/>
statesmanship which Daniel Webster even on that memorable seventh of
March would have rejoiced to acknowledge, which Henry Clay in any of
his later and brilliant years would have gladly made resound as out of
a trumpet from the borders of Virginia through the length of Kentucky
to the River. It was a broad and generous platform,--such as Jefferson
would have decorated with an hundred theses of his philosophy,--such
as Washington would have stood upon and invoked the blessings of the
Almighty. And I have the honor to say here,--to be sure it is now
after the fulfillment of the declarations and the prophesies,--that if
Abraham Lincoln had not felt warranted to justify and stand upon the
Resolutions, then the North American republic was not deserving of
salvation. But he thought, as we thought, that there was a divinity in
the impending struggle, and we entered upon it together, all of us
rejoicing to have such a leader, and he only too willing to stake his
life on the support of such friends and on such a sublime restoration
and reconstruction of nationality.</p>
               <p>He was chosen; the men in the South of our country had
decided that he should be chosen, and that the precipitation of their
designs should attend with equal promptness the humanity and
patriotism of the North. The work of secession began at the instant,
and before the President elect had reached the Capital so many of the
slave states had already
<pb n="19" facs="bullock19.jpg"/>
declared themselves out of the Union as to make it certain that nearly
all the others intended to follow. Though Buchanan had remained in
office four months since the election,--let the curtain drop over all
that he did and over all that he neglected to do, and let us behold
the new President approaching the frowning scene which confronted
him.</p>
               <p>Such work was his as no man had ever put hand to. A nation
was dissolving, and half its territory was bristling with the arms of
revolt. In the loyal sections there was universal despondency, and
among those upon whom he must rely there was every variety of counsel,
from that which would permit the wayward sisters to depart in peace,
to that which would thrust the arm of the government in the moment of
its greatest weakness against the thick bosses of a rebellion of
thirty years preparation. The Czar, the Emperor, the King, would
marshal and march out his army and crush insurgency before the next
moon; but the constitutional republic had no army. Foreign nations
caught at the defect in a moment as fatal to our existence, and
adapted their own policy to the expectation of seeing the North
American Union disappear like a dream. In the general gloom which shut
down over the whole horizon good men everywhere were ready to exclaim,
HAIL, HOLY LIGHT,--if only it might come from any quarter. What kind
of statesmanship, or learning, or experience, could make
<pb n="20" facs="bullock20.jpg"/>
a magistrate equal to such a work? Diplomacy could not save the flag
then, eloquence could not start a throb beneath the ribs of that
death, an arm of flesh could not hold a charm over the engulfing
waters and the dismantling ship. History, civilization, nay, almost
the mercies of Heaven, we thought, were baffled in that day. Again,
then, I ask, what kind of a President was needed, and would prove best
appointed? You know how, for many months, before this man had got
rightly into the work, and before we could properly measure him, some
of you sighed for a Jackson and others for a Webster to take the helm;
yet we now all believe that we have had the man raised up by God for
this particular epoch, that few could have accomplished this mission
at all, and none so well.</p>
               <p>For he came to it devout, wise, patient, forecasting, and
rich with insight. I read his Inaugural as a key to his whole policy
for this strange time, and there I discern the dawn of the lustre of
his qualities for administration, which blended a certain Roman
firmness with a Christian mediatorial talent. His wisdom began in
this, that he knew he could not foresee all that might happen, and so
he would gather the arms of his countrymen around him, and would keep
step with the majestic marches of Providence. Never doubting that our
jurisdiction would be recovered, always believing the conflict would
be long and
<pb n="21" facs="bullock21.jpg"/>
varied, he promised just enough to keep the element of hope uppermost
in the country, and not too much to unfit the masses for their own
great part. Clay or Webster in his chair might have restored the old
Union a little sooner, with the loss of the moral sense of the world
and with the cost of another revolt hereafter; Jackson might have
struck quicker and heavier blows, but an untimely blow then, might
have shivered this Union like glass. Our man had that tact and
knowledge of men which only his training could have imparted. He knew
his own West, and kept his hand constantly on her pulse; he was in
sympathy with the conscience of the East, and honored her culture and
power; and by his cultivation of the one and the other he kept them
both in harmonious action to the end. The ancient countries affected
delight and amusement at the sight of this son of the prairies
succeeding to the work of kings and putting his hand to an undertaking
which comprised the destinies of a hemisphere. They could not
understand that the question he had to deal with could receive little
aid from state-craft or the previous education of a public man. They
could not believe that new men are best for great crises; that for
such a ruler and for such a period Bunyan is a better master than all
the Georges, and Æsop a keener teacher than both the Walpoles; that
in a trial of the national spirit and the national forces involving
<pb n="22" facs="bullock22.jpg"/>
the issue of death at once or life perpetual to a nation, the study of
Washington is higher than the schools; that in such an emergency a
single Cromwell is greater than a dozen earls out of Eton and
Oxford. They forgot the consolations of their own history; that
Marlborough had never read Xenophon, or later martial historians, but
somehow managed to triumph over veteran armies of France; that
Wellington was counted dull in his early life, and rose to victory and
fame only by the buffet of trial; and they did not stop to consider
that Lincoln might ascend as conspicuously, and bring with him a
Grant, a Sherman, a Sheridan, as quickly and as triumphantly. All
history, all examples, all instructions are at fault in revolutions;
and our enemies at home and abroad were making mockery of the
mysteries of providential interpositions all along the
century-processions of mankind, when they hesitated about our success
because our chief had no title save that which the Almighty had given
him, no signet save that of the cabin, no learning save that to which
the evening torch and the celestial orbs had lighted him. But he
disappointed them all, passed beyond the boundaries they had set for
him, within four years, the shortest space ever illustrated by such
distinction, triumphed over a civil war of imperial proportions, and
left a name to be recorded and repeated in the courts of St. Louis,
St. James, and St. Peter, among the inscrip-
<pb n="23" facs="bullock23.jpg"/>
tions of a thousand years past and to come. So simple and rudimental
in his origin and preparation, not learned by the side of the masters,
and not ignorant of himself, he came to a supremacy over the grandest
epic of all countries and gave triumphant direction to the greatest
war of human annals. It will be the task of the historian and
biographer to classify and present these high themes hereafter, but a
few words ought to be said about them now over his new-made grave.</p>
               <p>Having neither the taste nor the education of a soldier, he
so practiced his intuitions as to become master of the field of
war. If you consider how extended and complicated the objective field
soon became, and how in consultation and oversight he was its
director, it must occur to you in reading his correspondence with the
commanders, that his perceptions were clear and his judgment
elementary and profound. How many toilsome and anxious hours he passed
in the war department, and how well he understood all that was
transpiring and all that ought to transpire, is made apparent in the
letters he himself wrote to Gen. McClellan during the fifteen months
of his command. Read them and re-read them and you will agree that
they evince, in a remarkable degree for a civilian, the military
sense. Having committed to that officer an army of eight scores of the
flower of the land, he followed
<pb n="24" facs="bullock24.jpg"/>
it with an interest alike parental and patriotic, studying the map of
its marches and its hopes, breasting back while he could the
impatience of the country, at all times suggesting his advice kindly
to its chief, and finally, in those dark days which have made the name
of the Chickahominy historical, transmitting a series of dispatches
from his own pen which could not have been better if he had possessed
the genius of a soldier. He saw through the objective and the
consequential of campaigns quite as clearly and quite as far as most
of the generals who wore his stars. Under the pressure of military
repulses he rose large as the occasion, and when his commanders were
changing their base he held hopefully to his own. When retreat and
disintegration had destroyed the last chance of entering Richmond that
season, and his chieftain called many times again for reinforcements,
he telegraphed back a volume of present history and future destiny in
a few short, sharp, kind, hopeful words: "If we had a million of men
we could not get them to you in time. We have not the men. If you are
not strong enough to face the enemy, *** save the army at all events,
even if you fall back to Fort Monroe. <hi rend="italic">We still have
strength enough in the country</hi>, AND WILL BRING IT OUT." He had a
large power of patience, which this war required. The people of the
North demanded a change of generals after each misfortune, but he saw
difficulties they
<pb n="25" facs="bullock25.jpg"/>
could not see, and tried one after the other long and tolerantly till
he found the right one. That is the highest proof of administrative
talent, in war, which disregards a clamor, rejects instrumentalities
only after they have been exhausted, and feels its way along the
rounds of failure till it finds the choice that can sound the awful
charge of victory. And though his arch-rival at Richmond had the
consummate education and prestige of a soldier, the murmurs which
swelled from his councils and his fields against him had double the
volume of those which rose to the ears of your President from the
fretful loyalty of the North; and I venture the prediction, that if
that history can ever be fully written, as ours will be, in military
comprehension and appreciation, in that gift of insight which is the
product of nature quite as much as of art or the academy, which
reduces the involutions of armies and campaigns to simplicity and
analysis, even in this, all this, which belongs to arms, our plain
civilian will be proved to have outwitted the other, educated soldier
though he was.</p>
               <p>Then I cannot help thinking that, as a part of the military
questions he had to treat, there were such grave matters of what I may
call legislative jurisprudence as had not been thought of before. To
weaken the rebellion by the destruction of its civil rights, and this
alike for purposes of punishment to treason and of strength to
loyalty,--this, under our Constitu-
<pb n="26" facs="bullock26.jpg"/>
tion which never contemplated such a crisis as the present, and under
the mutual relations of national and state sovereignty, the delicacy
of which had not been apprehended until now, required a statesmanship
scarcely less than judicial. Would Heaven that our own Webster could
have lived for this, to have sat as premier by the side of Lincoln, to
have illustrated with unprecedented effect his colossal gifts! It was
a great thought--of withdrawing from half a people the rights of a
national citizenship and of indefeasible republican immunities. The
Congress and the President did not altogether agree. This is not the
time to decide between them. Congress spoke the policy of prompt and
final deliverance from the hateful aristocracy whose alleged rights,
if not utterly extinguished in war, might prove a clog to Freedom and
Nationality in peace. The President endeavored to blend and reconcile
the supposed elements of the discordant lights of rebels under the
Constitution and of loyalty in war. I only allude to the subject to
call your attention to the depth of the matter which underlay the
military policy of the administration, and to solicit your attention
to the message of President Lincoln, July, 1862, in which, while he
deferred in modesty to the representatives of the people, he stood
upon his own responsibility, displayed in bold relief the abilities of
a technical lawyer and a constitutional jurist. There has been no
better
<pb n="27" facs="bullock27.jpg"/>
passage in his life by which he could have illustrated his capacity
for the comprehensive field of an interstate and national war.</p>
               <p>And then I reckon it another striking feature of his
military administration, that under all circumstances he took
accountability and censure to himself. We may acknowledge, once for
all, that there was a modest, conscious power in that; for no
empirical experimentalist would have trusted himself to such a test,
and the man must be well grounded in the popular confidence who can
bear it. Point me to any one person in the British administration who
was willing to stand out solitary and responsible when the people
criticised the campaigns of their generals in the Peninsula of Spain
or the Crimea. Rather than that, the responsibility could only be
found distributed among the unknown and mystical impersonalities of
the Cabinet and the Privy Council. Your President on the other hand
sought no shelter from criticism. In the first year of the war, when
Congress passed a vote of censure upon one of his Department
Secretaries, he sent them a message assuming the responsibility to
himself; Jackson would have done the same, but no other man since his
day. In the second year, when another Secretary of War was arraigned
by large numbers of the people for having enforced the failure of
McClellan in the Peninsula by withholding reinforcements, Mr. Lincoln
came
<pb n="28" facs="bullock28.jpg"/>
gallantly to the response and claimed that the attack should be
pointed against his own breast; and his dispatches to that General,
since published, show that he could well afford to receive the
attack. He wrote his own messages, generally directed his commanders,
not regularly consulted his cabinet, and, I believe, frequently
over-ruled them when he did. He felt that he was personally
accountable to the people for the triumphant defence of the Union. He,
and no other, before his election, and in his inaugural, had drawn the
outlines within which the glory of his country might be found, and now
like a wise man he relied on his own prayerful study and on his own
keen instincts for ability to fill out the outlines with the colors
that shall give eternal beauty to the picture of united America. In
this I admire equally his magnanimity and his courage. Fortunate for
us that he was willing to take such responsibility. Many and many a
time, when cypress instead of laurel bound the eagles of the army,
happy and hopeful were we all if only we might believe that
Mr. Lincoln had ordered the risk and the shock; we cared little for
his ministers, but we trusted unsuspectingly in him; when our
reproaches rose almost to mutiny in the North, if only he would say,
<hi rend="italic">in me, in me vertite tela</hi>, from that moment as by
a charm the tumult subsided. It is a great relief in the
discouragements and troubles of war, to rest upon the one man who is
<pb n="29" facs="bullock29.jpg"/>
above all the others; it is a greater thing if that man can justify
and warrant such a rest and solace. In this power of impressment is a
good part of a ruler's greatness. And thus we trace to him even the
brilliant conduct of others; for since he willed it, they performed
it. It is the eulogy of Lincoln to say that much which others
performed he suggested and was willing to be held responsible for
it. Said the ablest of Englishmen: "The minister who does those things
is a great man--but the king who desires that they should be done, is
a far greater."</p>
               <p>How can I within the limits of these remarks speak fitly or
sufficiently of the part he bore in the cause of emancipation? Think
what height and depth stood in the way, how history and providence
only shed darkness over his approaches, how the free states were rent
by conflicting opinions, how he had to institute a new policy, which,
if it might succeed, would invest the government with immortal life,
but if it should fail, would wreck the nation and shroud his own name
in ignominy forevermore. It was a necessity which he had not
anticipated. It took fifteen months of war to discover the strength of
the rebellion and the weakness of the government, and when the
alternative came at length it presented sombre and frightful
proportions. To destroy slavery he had not been elected, nor for that
had he called the people to arms; the only duty for him, and that
<pb n="30" facs="bullock30.jpg"/>
which he judged most pleasing to God, was to save this Union from
dissolution You remember how after our flag had begun to trail in
defeat, voices here and there raised this issue upon him in terms
alike beseeching and threatening. Still what could he do better or
more than balance the conflict of magisterial ethics, study the
contradictory omens of the sky, feel the heart of his country, and
search after the will of the last arbiter? Undoubtedly, he thought the
necessity of emancipation might come, probably it would come; but it
would come as a question of arms and must be supported by public
opinion. That was the day of all which tried him as a statesman.</p>
               <p>In the presence of such a question, large enough to occupy
the thoughts and agitations of a generation, behold the unambitious
practical statesmanship of Abraham Lincoln. No age has been blessed
with a better. We are constantly looking back through the coloring
medium of distance to the brilliant lights of the past, and desponding
over the present and the future. But the statesmen of one age are
unfitted for the requirements of another. Peel was as great for his
time as Chatham or Bolingbroke for theirs. From the magnificent
success of our late President we have learned the right definition of
a wise ruler. If it be his labor to initiate a measure that shall
stand out among the beneficent acts that mark historical periods, it
is his still more painful and vexatious work
<pb n="31" facs="bullock31.jpg"/>
to commend it to public approval; he has to enlighten the ignorance of
some, and to convince the intelligence of others; he has to combat
honest prejudices, and modify interested opposition; if he would move
with strength and certainty towards the success which is ahead, he has
to halt in his steps, and clip his propositions, and qualify his
words, and emasculate his theories; if he would be strong to place his
country among the positions his genius has pictured for her, he must
apparently enfeeble his policy to conciliate one class and clog it
with burdens to satisfy another. The modern statesman must combine
patient temper, persevering will, and sound knowledge of men; he must
discern the present tone and probable direction of public opinion; he
must distinguish between intelligent and unintelligent censure, and he
must know how much of public outcry can safely be disregarded, as well
as that amount which he cannot afford to withstand.</p>
               <p>Such statesmanlike qualities Mr. Lincoln illustrated in
those many months of hesitation, anxiety, seeming then almost
inability to act, which ushered in that day on which he emerged from
his closet, bearing in his own arms the effulgent guidon of
EMANCIPATION. I religiously believe that he was right, all along, from
the stammering beginning to the clarion-like finality. You goaded him
too soon, too often, and too long: he was the while in consultation
with the counsellors
<pb n="32" facs="bullock32.jpg"/>
around him, with his little learning and his large reflection, with
all of history he had read, with the fathers and the prophets. While
editors and orators stirred strife and commotion in the country and in
the Senate Chamber over his long withholding of the decree, he
continued impassive in his purpose, and remembered that one of the
instructive characters in his favorite Bunyan was "a grave and
beautiful damsel named Discretion." And so I conceive that he was
right upon this question in that which some of us thought his
dalliance with the states of the border, right also when he
countermanded Fremont's military order of freedom--right again when he
recalled the similar rescript of Hunter,--right as well in his letter
to Mr. Greeley,--and right at last when the angels announced the hour
and he sent forth the Decree of Emancipation triumphant and
irrevocable while the earth shall stand. Then he said: "I have done
this after a very full deliberation, and under a very heavy and solemn
sense of responsibility. I can only trust in God I have made no
mistake. It is now for the country and the world to pass judgment."</p>
               <p>Yes, yes, that judgment his country and the world have
already passed. His returning armies share their laurels with him and
pay their resounding fusilade over the turf which covers their father
and their friend! But higher honors await him! A nation rescued from
the tyranny whose roots
<pb n="33" facs="bullock33.jpg"/>
have spread over two centuries, never relenting, never appeased, a
race delivered from thraldom and elevated to the hopes of civilization
and Christianity, shall walk to the beat of peaceful marches about his
tomb till the resurrection! And wherever Freedom shall have a home, or
America a name, or Washington a praise, over the whole globe, mankind
shall revere the memory of him who sealed the baptism of emancipation
with his own blood!</p>
               <p>And I desire for myself to express the opinion that no
monument that may be erected to commemorate his name can rise so high
or endure so long, as that whose foundations shall be laid in those
immutable and universal rights of man for which he gave his life. As
the emancipation of four millions became the necessity of his policy
for the preservation of the Union, so let us extend to the emancipated
race all the rights of citizenship if we would make our safety certain
and final. If under a democratic government universal suffrage is
worth anything in the North, then is universal suffrage a paramount
necessity in the South. Is it republican, democratic or safe, to
exclude from the polls a majority of the loyal population of the
Southern States? Your sons have been maimed and slain in vain, if the
aristocracy which was the cause and support of the war shall not be
shorn
<pb n="34"/>
                  <figure><graphic url=""/>
                     <figDesc>34th page of
Alex. H. Bullock's Abraham Lincoln: The Just Magistrate, the
Representative Statesman, the Practical
Philanthropist.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
of every distinction, if the oligarchy shall not have its roots
plucked to their uttermost fibre out of the land.</p>
               <p>I do not forget to-day that probably one-half of all those
who now help to extend the funeral train, have at one time or another
in four years pronounced their complaint that Mr. Lincoln was too much
the follower, not sufficiently the leader of public opinion. The stern
tribunal of history adjusts all such accounts as that. The immortal
Washington opened his mission at Cambridge under the same necessities
of limitation that have bounded the horizon of Lincoln. He entered the
war in advance of the issue, and had to await the developments of
events which made separation and independence the sublime ultimatum. I
concede that the late President waited on public opinion; and when you
reflect how abnormal and stupendous was the cause he had to manage, I
will thank you to tell me if waiting on public opinion was not waiting
on Providence itself. Tell me, if the success or loss of the whole, to
us and to distant generations, did not depend on the spirit of the
people. Public sentiment is the arbiter of republican destinies. But
public sentiment,--what is it here with us but the product, not
precisely the average quantity, but the result and the product of the
intuitions, instincts, sagacities, and reflections of the millions of
America,--the crystalization of the myriad forces of democracy,--to be
<pb n="35" facs="bullock35.jpg"/>
ascertained by the President only after incessant labor, and study,
and retrospection,--then, when with satisfactory certainty
ascertained, to be not only consulted, but to be received and accepted
as in the nature of inspiration and decree to the magistrate. He who
keeps pace with this requistion is neither quite a leader nor quite a
follower, but a representative, administrator, and executor,--all and
everything which a democratic constitution will ask for or can
permit. Mr. Lincoln understood and adopted this construction of
statesmanship better than I can analyze it. He sought neither to lead
public opinion, nor consented to follow it. No man could with greater
force or justice than he could, repeat the remark which Edmund Burke
made in his own justification to his constituents,--that he did not
follow public opinion, but only went out to meet it on the way. This
alone gave your President his power. I do not forget that there are
occasions in which the statesman, like the leader in the field, may
organize and direct the strategic movements of public action. But in
the march of civilization, issues ripen, events come, and men advance
to the conflict. A man, an accident, a trifle, hastens or retards the
battle, but the single man does not make the revolution nor quell the
storm. In the significant epochs of history or final clash of arms,
the statesman can discern the occasions, the opportunities, and the
necessities of the hour, but his greatness
<pb n="36" facs="bullock36.jpg"/>
and glory are largely the product of the times. An English journalist
has just said of the lamented Mr. Cobden, that "his limitations as a
statesman constituted his greatness as a representative thinker." I
like the expression and the philosophy of it. I could coin no better
phrase with which to define the wise statesmanship of Mr. Cobden's
friend on this side of the water. SEEKING NOT TO TRANSCEND HIS
LIMITATIONS AS A STATESMAN, HE MADE HIMSELF THE REPRESENTATIVE THINKER
OF HIS COUNTRY AND HIS TIME. That is his glory to-day, and can never
become his weakness or his shame. Of course such an understanding of
the policy and the duty of a national magistrate subjects him, as
Mr. Lincoln for a time was subjected, to the imputation of
over-cautious timidity; but a just posterity, nay, the sagacious
present generation, will expunge the criticism and open to him the
pathway to justice. So, if I remember correctly, the policy of Fabius
was by some called cowardice, or at least timidity, in his day; but I
believe it prepared the way for the avenging armies of Scipio. So, as
I have read, the venerable Washington was characterized and criticised
in his time also; but I have the impression that Yorktown, and the
Constitution, and eight years of magisterial glory, constituted his
vindication. So, as I have observed, Lincoln was summoned to submit to
the same test of fame; and so we all see this day that his name
ascends henceforth among the stars.</p>
               <pb n="37" facs="bullock37.jpg"/>
               <p>His speech, though not uniform, was not unworthy of his
action. Consider how opposite are the requisitions in this respect
which empires make upon their rulers, and take the two leading powers
of the East and the West for the illustration. The Czar of
Russia,--blessed be his fortunes evermore for that early and timely
friendship which he bestowed upon our country and our President, when
the cabinets on either shore of the fitful and vengeful Channel
offered us only the scowling welcome of intimidation and
hypocrisy,--to whom, some day, in the alternations of our
inter-nationalities, the shade of assassinated innocence shall stalk
in terror and retribution over all the seas they arrogate; that Czar
of Russia, all the way from Peter or Catharine to the latest
Alexander, wields dominion with action and without words. That is the
condition of his rule, nor is it our business or our pleasure to find
fault with it there. The genius of America is another. Here the
President is the selected agent of the people, and must respond
whenever they call for his reasons. No President before Lincoln ever
had so many and such calls. They came from Congress, from every State,
from associations, from delegations, from individual men, from
spontaneous assemblages under a hundred moon-lights on the lawn around
the Executive mansion. He had a word for them all. True it is, he had
still that greatest gift of a magistrate, the power of reticence, the
<pb n="38" facs="bullock38.jpg"/>
masterly talent of suppression, whenever the occasion required it. He
let them off with his joke and his western wit, whenever that was all
they ought to have. In this sometimes, and too frequently, he reduced
the dignity of his office; but it was the relief-valve which he had
received from his Maker. Yet, beside all this, so many were his
necessities of public speaking, that no one of his predecessors had
been tried in that way so often. He spoke good things from the windows
of the White House, as he had spoken them before on the prairies. They
shall be handed over to you and your children, and you shall say that
I do not praise them too highly. You shall find some shade and beauty
beneath their pine and oaken leaves. You shall say that he spoke and
wrote with much of the simplicity, quaintness and power of Franklin,
and the elemental mastery of our tongue. Many were his occasional
speeches, and one of them at least will be imperishable for its
felicity and brevity. Lord Macaulay assures us that barrister Somers
in a speech of five minutes in the Court of King's Bench established
the enduring fame of an orator. Mr. Lincoln by a speech of only that
duration at Gettysburg divided the honors of the day with the
transcendent Everett, and inscribed his name on the tombstone of every
soldier whose ashes there await the rising of the quick and the
dead. His state papers are more lasting than these. His messages to
Congress have
<pb n="39" facs="bullock39.jpg"/>
already passed into the national literature; they were read at the
time in the courts of France and England; and though they may have
been obliterated or obscured there by royal art, they will reappear
for luminous and prophetic reading when Europe and America shall
settle their accounts.</p>
               <p>In these state papers posterity will recognize a style of
power that is not more unique in its form than in its produced
effect. It is in sympathy with the national characteristics and with
the traditional choice of the people. His mind was acute, logical, and
subtle; and that they appreciate. In the time of her casuistry and
refinement the public teachers of Greece found no heartier reception
than wit and reason find now in America from Maine to
Nevada. Mr. Lincoln had studied the first and second sight of his
countrymen, till he could address them with a direction that seldom
failed. Then he secured their favor, and I may say pleased their
senses, by a genially and humor which smoothed their asperities,
conquered their prejudices, and attracted their hearts to him and his
cause. Even in the winter of their discontent, when arms were
unsuccessful and taxes were high, he led them as through the
gorgeousness and serenity of an Indian summer, to new campaigns, and
heavier burdens, and coming victories. From '62 to '64 such was the
power of his written and spoken words. In statement and argument he
struck deeper
<pb n="40" facs="bullock40.jpg"/>
and richer veins than his supposed education would have suggested. I
think we are quite apt to be in error as to this whole matter of
education. When and where did Hamilton acquire his--for he left
college a boy, before his time, and saw no schools afterwards save the
camp, the cabinet, and the bar; yet he proved the finest intellect of
his time. Inform me, if you can, whence came the education of Lincoln,
who never trod the floors of a college. I only know that we do not
know what may have been his study in a lazy, unlimited, unconditioned
western life. I do know, what he stated when last he was in New
England five years ago, on the eve and in the expectation of his
honors, that, after he had tried the study of the law and had found
himself cornered, he went into retirement for some months and studied
Euclid till he understood it from root to outermost branch. And so
doubtless he went through more than we know of the struggle and
ecstacy of educating himself. However that may have been, and whenever
or wherever he may have acquired the power, you and I know that he
could reason with a straightforwardness and incisiveness which Harvard
or Princeton might be proud to honor. This is not the extravaganza of
eulogy; peruse, as I have perused, his written and spoken addresses,
from Illinois in '58 to his last and singular Inaugural, and you shall
say the same. I will not particularize out of them all, save one. Take
<pb n="41" facs="bullock41.jpg"/>
up and read critically his published letter to Erastus Corning and his
committee, covering the whole question of the suspension of the <hi rend="italic">habeas corpus</hi> and the subjection of the civil to
military law, and it shall be your impartial judgment that in a broad
statement of public safety and historical law it is not unworthy of
Hamilton; in purity and legitimacy of style it is scarcely inferior to
the papers of the same master; and in just comprehensiveness and
ingenuous patriotism it would reflect credit upon the tender heart and
robust nationalism of Washington. I admired it when it first appeared,
and now after a second and third reading I think it to be the best of
all his papers.</p>
               <p>The moral and humane qualities of the good President set
off and gilded his term. Did you ever know a potentate whose rule bore
such blazonry of events, civic and martial, and whose daily life was
so simple, plain and temperate? I believe that not Sir Matthew Hale
kept sterner vigil over private and official hours, over the shrine of
the domestic sanctuary. Success was his aim and duty his guide, and he
saw little time for display, or amusement, or ostentation. In four
years of labor, which would have broken like a reed any man of less
iron cast, he not once got time to revisit the state and city of his
love, seldom left the capital unless to visit the tents, hospitals or
graves of his soldiers, and once only came so far as the
<pb n="42" facs="bullock42.jpg"/>
North to consult on the national safety with a retired chieftain. He
gave attentive ear to humblest men and women, was as faithful in small
acts of kindness as in great acts of justice, as amiable in little
things in private as in high matters of state.</p>
               <p>His magnanimity became proverbial. His soul was no nursery
for a brood of resentments. He conferred the bars, and stars, and
eagles of war generously upon those who had not given him a vote or a
sympathy, if only they were true to the flag. He bared his own breast
to the brunt of many an assault aimed at Cameron, or Stanton, or
McClellan, allowed them the honors, and took to himself the swarming
reproaches. In a serenade on the evening after his second election,
when the impassioned majority would have dishonored the name of his
rival, he spoke for him grand words of charity and justice. A specific
instance of his truthful magnanimity I must unfold to you as it has
been related to me upon the best of authority. On a certain morning
many months before Chief Justice Taney died, his immediate decease was
pronounced in Washington as certain. In anticipation of the supposed
impending death our senior senator called upon Mr. Lincoln and
discussed with him the importance of appointing Mr. Chase to fill the
expected vacancy. The President at length gave the assurance. But the
Chief Justice renewed his lease of life, and many months lapsed
away. Mean-
<pb n="43" facs="bullock43.jpg"/>
while, between Mr. Lincoln and Mr. Chase, in the council of
administration, divergences arose. At length in July, '64, the latter
laid the key of the exchequer upon the President's table. He accepted
the resignation without hesitation. Then came Senators to his room to
urge the reappointment or restoration of Mr. Chase to the
Treasury,--for that juncture reflected dark shadows over our
finances. "No, no," said Mr. Lincoln, "for between him and me there is
an incompatibility for the same council. But this, you will bear in
mind, would not prevent me from honoring Mr. Chase in any other high
sphere of the government." Half a year afterwards the Chief Justice
died, but not before Mr. Chase had sprinkled along his travels in New
England sharp and disparaging words of criticism upon the
President. And yet the same President, faithful to his promise and his
duty, forgetful of wrong and injustice to himself, conferred upon his
late secretary the appointment, and placed the jurisprudence of the
United States and the rights of human nature under perpetual
obligations to his magnanimity.</p>
               <p>He believed in God. You know how he left his home for
Washington in February, '61, in his parting words requesting that his
neighbors would array in his support the mysterious power of the
legions of prayer; and after he had assumed his high trust at the
Capital he cultivated that religious life which is
<pb n="44" facs="bullock44.jpg"/>
the best guaranty of a nation's triumph. While war, according to its
prescriptive laws, opened all the avenues of inconsideration and
levity to others, he drew his consolations and refreshed his courage
at the never-failing fountains of divine mercy. It was this, added to
his humorous and sunny views, which bore him upward and onward through
such a regime of four years as never had been allotted to a head that
wore a crown. And therefore all the people believed in him. More
distinctly than any other President since Washington he irradiated the
official pathway at all times and in all places with the conspicuous
publicity of Christian ethics. When Canning in Parliament opposed the
humanity of slavery-abolition, he declared in classic words that it
was impracticable to apply to politics those pure abstract principles
which are indispensable to the excellence of private ethics. That was
English, and almost worthy of a court whose official philanthropy is
now proved to have been another name for the ambition of commercial
and political ascendancy. Accordingly Great Britain could not conceal
surprise at the novelty of Mr. Lincoln's theory of Christian ethics as
a rule for official conduct; and the difference between us will have
to be postponed to the adjustments which are yet to come of American
and European ideas.</p>
               <p>Your President was kind and tender to a fault. 
<pb n="45" facs="bullock45.jpg"/>
This led him into some mistakes, but his magnanimity corrected
them. So he yielded somewhat to the rebel Campbell at Richmond, and
gave what might have proved a fatal order to Weitzel, but revoked it
on the last day of his life when he discovered his error. I suspect,
that if he had lived for the reconstruction, he would have made
several such mistakes; but I know that he would have rectified and
retrieved them. I do not think he would have executed the traitor who
set up as his rival for history, but I trust that his successor
will. Yet, after all, as the morning of victory opened on his sight,
and as the hour of his own translation drew nigh, I love to recur to
the benignity of his purposes towards the most wicked of men. In his
last consultation with his cabinet, a few hours before his departure,
his heart melted before the appalling claims of JUSTICE. I think,
however, he only meant to say:--</p>
               <lg type="stanza">
                  <l>"I shall temper so</l>
                  <l>Justice with Mercy, as may illustrate</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi rend="italic">Them</hi> fully satisfied, and <hi rend="italic">then</hi> appease."</l>
               </lg>
               <p>Nay, more, I catch the language of his last Inaugural for his
eulogy:--"WITH MALICE TOWARD NONE, WITH CHARITY FOR ALL." Lofty words!
He knew not what those men had in preparation for him, and the Lord in
his infinite mercy was preparing him to go at their bidding,
whispering as he ascended, "Father, forgive them, for they know not
what they do!"</p>
               <pb n="46" facs="bullock46.jpg"/>
               <p>As you look backward along the galleries of history, you
are surprised when you think how few are found whose fame has outlived
their period or country, how few have passed into the constellations
of immortal light. Those only are privileged with that imperishable
distinction whose record gleams forth above the wreck of contemporary
annals, whose labors place an entire nation, or many generations, or
all mankind, under the remembrance of debt and obligation. To that
judgment, ubiquitous and everlasting, Washington passed sixty-five
years ago. From that day to ours, out of the long list of American
Presidents, however marked their own talent or their own period, no
one of them all before has, in the full sense of universal humanity
and fame, given special dignity, or unlimited praise, or immortal
renown, to America through time and space. But such has been the
mission of Abraham Lincoln. However we should have estimated him four
years ago as to the limitation of his previous life, or his natural
parts, or his acquired culture, now that the four years have passed it
has become apparent that Almighty God had selected him for world-wide
honor and benignity.</p>
               <p>I appropriate to him the language of our own fellow-citizen
and historian, Mr. Motley, which he applied to William of Orange:</p>
               <p>"No man was ever more devoted to a high purpose:
<pb n="47" facs="bullock47.jpg"/>
no man had ever more right to imagine himself, or less inclination to
pronounce himself, entrusted with a divine mission. There was nothing
of the charlatan in his character. His nature was true and
steadfast. No narrow-minded usurper was ever more loyal to his own
aggrandizement, than this large-hearted man to the cause of oppressed
humanity. Yet it was inevitable that baser minds should fail to
recognize his purity. It was natural for grovelling natures to search
in the gross soil of self-interest for the sustaining roots of the
tree beneath whose branches a nation found its shelter. What could
they comprehend of living fountains or of heavenly dews?"</p>
               <p>But his untimely hour had come. You remember the fatal
evening only too well already, and I do not desire to disturb your
sensibilities by anything more than this allusion to it. In our
poetry, and art, and annals, that fourteenth of April shall henceforth
be known and remembered as the <hi rend="italic">noche triste</hi>--the
sorrowful night. The just and good magistrate then went away out of
our sight.</p>
               <p>The flag on spire, pinnacle, and cottage, had scarcely been
restored from its depression of mourning, nor the muffled drum had
ceased to beat, when the rival of the dead, the representative cause
of our sorrows, was overtaken by retribution. He enjoys this evening
his reflections upon history, and providence, and judgment, in the
hospitality of the noblest
<pb n="48" facs="bullock48.jpg"/>
Fortress of the Union, on a bed around which the shade of the murdered
President would fain marshal "angels and ministers of grace" to
protect him. Who in all the earth cares now what shall become of him?
But whenever, or wherever, or however his time shall terminate,
between him and the vile dust to which he shall descend there is only
the brief hour of the life of a criminal, to be succeeded by the
reproaches of his contemporary countrymen, North and South, the
heavy-pressing judgments of all posterity and of the eternal God. No
matter when, or where, or how Jefferson Davis shall die,--his death
cannot be less ignominious than that of the assassin who performed his
purpose,--and all generations shall welcome him to the immortality of
the representative Traitor of the race!</p>
               <p>But another guerdon awaits our president. He sought to
save, not to destroy. He labored to uphold the pillars of the Temple
whose grace and beauty, if magistrates prove faithful, can never
decay. He studied policy and wisdom day and night in a civil war which
cost him his life, that his country might live, and fought treason on
every line and in every trench over half the states, that democratic
government in America might shine forth to cheer and animate and guide
mankind to the remotest bounds of the world and of time. He ransomed
four millions of his own countrymen from the thraldom of two
<pb n="49" facs="bullock49.jpg"/>
hundred years, and died under the blow of slavery in the ecstacy of
the sight. No matter when, or where, or how death should come to
him,--for ABRAHAM LINCOLN has completed the work which GEORGE
WASHINGTON began,--to HIS victories, great and unapproachable, he has
added such triumphs as war never contemplated before,--to the broad
field of HIS civic glory he has imparted a still broader
radiance;--and he now goes from our presence into the presence of
other ages, garlanded with the double honor of RESTORER and
LIBERATOR!</p>
            </div2>
         </div1>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>