<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader><fileDesc>
         <titleStmt n="The Martyr President">
            <title>The Martyr President</title>
            <author>Butler, J. G.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Compiled and edited by</resp>
               <name>Beck
Center</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent/>
         <publicationStmt><publisher>Lewis H. Beck Center</publisher><pubPlace>Emory University</pubPlace><address>
               <addrLine>Atlanta,
Georgia</addrLine>
            </address><availability>
               <p>1996 Emory
University. Permission is granted to download, transmit, or otherwise
reproduce, distribute or display the contributions to the work claimed
by Emory University for non-profit educational purposes, provided
this header is included in its entirety.  For inquiries about
commercial uses, contact the Director, 
Pitts Theology Library, Emory
University, Atlanta, Georgia 30322</p>
            </availability><date>1999</date></publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Lincoln
Sermons Project</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Butler,
J. G. The Martyr President. Our Grief and Our Duty. Washington, D. C.:
McGill &amp; Witherow, Printers and Stereotypers. 1865.</bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc><encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This text
derives 
from the Special Collections 
of Pitts Theology Library, Emory University, and is produced in 
collaboration with the Lewis H. Beck Center a, the Emory 
Preservation Office, and Pitts Theology Library.</p>
            <p>TRANSCRIBER: Lewis H. Beck Center and Emory University Preservation Office.</p>
            <p>PRODUCER:  BookLab, Inc., 1606 Headway Circle, Suite 100, Austin, TX 78754</p>
            <p>CAPTURE DEVICE: XEROX DocuImage 620S flatbed scanner</p>
            <p>CAPTURE DETAILS: Scanner software: XEROX ScanTool version 4.2.3; no gamma correction; images are all bitonal.</p>
            <p>CHANGE HISTORY: Using the Adobe Photoshop Batch Processor, we interpolated  the original TIFF files to 8-bit grays, and altered the resolution to 144 dpi, producing screen images twice the original size.  We then saved them in JPEG format.  We produced GIF thumbnails from the JPEG files.</p>
            <p>RESOLUTION: 600 ppi</p>
            <p>COMPRESSION: Resolution 144 per inch with Constrain Properties to 72 per inch.</p>
            <p>SOURCE: Original documents.</p>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc><revisionDesc><change><name>Stewart Varner</name> transformed this document from p4 to p5 on <date when="2010-03-22">March 22, 2010</date></change><change xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><date>1999</date><label>Staff</label><name>Scott Ellis</name>SGML tags inserted in compliance
with TEI guidelines using TEILITE</change></revisionDesc></teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div1 xml:id="butler.001" n="The Martyr President" type="text">
            <head> 
               <bibl> 
                  <title>The Martyr
President</title> 
                  <date>1865</date> 
                  <pubPlace>St. Paul's Lutheran
Church</pubPlace> 
                  <author>Butler, J. G.</author> 
                  
                     <pubPlace>Washington, D. C.</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>McGill &amp;
Witherow, Printers and Stereotypers </publisher>
                     <date>1865</date>
                   
               <idno type="ark">http://pid.emory.edu/ark:/25593/15pw1</idno></bibl> 
            </head>
            <p>
               <figure><graphic url=""/>
                  <figDesc>1st page of J. G. Butler's The
Martyr President.</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <p>THE MARTYR PRESIDENT.</p>
            <p>OUR GRIEF AND OUR DUTY.</p>
            <p>BY J.G. BUTLER,</p>
            <p>PASTOR OF ST. PAUL'S LUTHERAN CHURCH.</p>
            <p>WASHINGTON, D.C.:</p>
            <p>McGILL &amp; WITHEROW, PRINTERS AND
STEREOTYPERS.</p>
            <p>1865.</p>
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>
               <figure><graphic url=""/>
                  <figDesc>2nd page of
J. G. Butler's The Martyr President.</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>
               <figure><graphic url=""/>
                  <figDesc>3rd page of
J. G. Butler's The Martyr President.</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <p> LETTER OF REQUEST.</p>
            <p>WASHINGTON, <hi rend="italic">April</hi> 17, 1865.</p>
            <p>REV. J. G. BUTLER</p>
            <p>DEAR SIR: The undersigned members and friends of your
church and congregation, who listened to the earnest, patriotic, and
eloquent address, called forth by the foul assassination of President
Lincoln, delivered by you in St. Paul's Church on Easter morning, 16th
instant, and regretting that a report of the same which appeared in
the papers was so meager and unsatisfactory, most respectfully request
a copy for publication, in pamphlet form, that the expressed desire of
many to preserve it may be gratified, and with a firm belief that the
cause of good government and pure and undefiled religion will be
subserved by a wider dissemination of the great truths so ably and
fully set forth therein.</p>
            <p>J. A. RHEEM,                               A. NOERR,<lb/>
JOS. F.KELLEY,                             A. S. PRATT,<lb/>
A. F. WILLIAMS,                            A. HOWLAND LEE,<lb/>
A. C. SPAULDING,                           S. A. PEUGH,<lb/>
CHAS. PITCHER,                             G. W. MARTIN,<lb/>
W. H. SIGSTON,                             N. ACKER,<lb/>
C. LEPLEY,                                 M. .M. ROHRER,<lb/>
THOMAS CRUX,                               WM. H. FRY,<lb/>
J. G. WEAVER,                              J. N. BURKET,<lb/>
J. H. REISS,                               J. H. KUEHLING,
                                           <lb/>LEWIS HEYL.</p>
            <p>REPLY.</p>
            <p>GENTLEMEN: The discourse for which you so kindly ask was
wholly extemporaneous, inspired by the deep grief which so suddenly
overwhelmed our nation. I have, amid pressing duties, hastily
endeavored to reproduce it. The times call for earnest thoughts and
earnest men. When the
<pb n="4"/>
               <figure><graphic url=""/>
                  <figDesc>4th page of J. G. Butler's
The Martyr President.</figDesc>
               </figure>
nation's life is in danger, silence is treason. God has wrought
wonderful deliverances for us; and though the strife of the
battle-field be well nigh ended, the <hi rend="italic">great sin</hi>
which has occasioned all this blood yet struggles for being. If my
voice or life can in any degree strengthen our Government and promote
Truth and Freedom, I am not my own, but yours and Truth's and
Christ's. The manuscript is at your disposal.</p>
            <p>I am, gentlemen, very truly, for God and our country,
yours,</p>
            <p>J. G. BUTLER,
                                             <lb/>
               <hi rend="italic">Pastor of St. Paul's Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>ST. PAUL'S PARSONAGE, <hi rend="italic">April</hi> 24, 1865.</p>
            <p>To Messrs. J. A . RHEEM, J. F. KELLEY, A. NOERR, A. S. PRATT,
Dr. A. H. LEE, and others.</p>
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>
               <figure><graphic url=""/>
                  <figDesc>5th page of
J. G. Butler's The Martyr President.</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <div2 xml:id="booth.002" n="OUR GRIEF AND OUR DUTY." type="sermon">
               <head>OUR GRIEF AND OUR DUTY.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <p>THE GOSPEL FOR THE DAY FROM THE 24TH CHAPTER OF LUKE WAS
READ.</p>
               </epigraph>
               <p>These badges of mourning, in the Sanctuary to-day, direct
our thoughts to the terrible tragedy which has filled our city, our
whole land, with sorrow. And though this be our Communion season, I
feel that the improvement of this sad Providence furnishes the theme
of discourse to-day. I am inadequate to the occasion. My heart has
been well nigh paralyzed by the startling Providence. I feel that I am
in deep sympathy with you, and with the loyal heart of this entire
land. Even treason will blush with shame at this assassination. I
would prefer to be silent today--to commingle my tears with those of
the stricken household--with the tears of the great American people. I
would prefer to hear others speak--to be still, and suffer God alone
to speak; but rebellion and treason have culminated in the murder of
our beloved and noble Chief Magistrate. This is not the time to be
silent. I would be untrue to you, untrue to myself as a citizen of
this great Republic, as an Ambassador of truth, a servant of Christ,
untrue to the promptings of my own deeply moved heart, unworthy the
confidence and love you have ever reposed in me, did I fail to speak
forth the words of truth and soberness.</p>
               <p>This is resurrection day; the day upon which the Church,
during all her history, commemorates the rising from the grave of Him,
who, but the third day before, had been crucified. In this drapery we
have combined here to-day the emblems of sorrow and of joy. Nature is
putting on her Easter robes--the grass is beginning to spring forth,
the buds to swell, the leaves are unfolding, and the trees are covered
with their varied blooms. After the long and dreary nights of winter,
all nature has revived, and holds forth
<pb n="6"/>
                  <figure><graphic url=""/>
                     <figDesc>6th page of J. G. Butler's
The Martyr President.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
to our admiring eyes an immense bouquet, filling the air with
fragrance and the soul with gladness.</p>
               <p>These weeds of mourning, reminding us of the murder of our
honored President on the <hi rend="italic">Crucifixion day</hi> of our
now risen Lord, are appropriately wreathed with beautiful flowers,
preachers of the resurrection, entwined with evergreen, pointing to an
immortality in a tearless land</p>
               <p>The plotting enemies of our glorious Redeemer supposed the
nailing to the Cross ended all pretensions to the establishment of His
kingdom among the kingdoms of earth. Unable to resist the power of His
truth, they vainly hoped to bury all--even his very memory--in the new
made, rock-bound sepulchre. Our Lord crucified, His own friends--His
chosen disciples, gave up all for lost. We supposed, said they, that
it had been He that should have redeemed Israel. They were looking for
the yoke of the Roman oppressor to be broken; but, their Lord put to
death, every one in despair went to his own home. The Church
to-day--this Christian congregation--the whole Church Catholic, in our
land, in all lands, with her Bible, her Ministry, her thousand
agencies for good, shows how false were the hopes, and how groundless
the fears of enemies and friends.</p>
               <p>Though our beloved Chief Magistrate lies in the chilling
embrace of death to-day, and our honored Prime Minister of State
lingers in pain beneath the assassin's blow, our Government still
lives. <hi rend="italic">Men may die</hi>--be murdered--but <hi rend="italic">truth never</hi>. Jesus may, by wicked hands, be
crucified, but His cause lives. That is a part of God's plan. Abraham
Lincoln has fallen a martyr to truth, to principle, to freedom, to law
and order, and good Government. But whilst our hearts are bleeding,
our hopes are not crushed. This foul deed of the assassin upon which
Heaven frowns, and of which Satan would be ashamed, may fill the land
with mourning; but it nerves the heart with fresh resolve and more
invincible purpose to contend for the truth, even at the price of
life. We have been laying upon our country's altar our most precious
treasure. It is all covered with the blood of our husbands and
fathers, and sons and brothers--coined into the price of liberty. And
now, when rebellion is well nigh crushed, when our armies, flushed
with victory, are pursuing a fleeing foe, treason nerves her fiendish
<pb n="7"/>
                  <figure><graphic url=""/>
                     <figDesc>7th page of J. G. Butler's
The Martyr President.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
arm to strike down our Moses, who, under God, has led us through the
wilderness, as he stands upon Pisgah, in full view of the Promised
Land, the land flowing with milk and honey.</p>
               <p>The most guilty of the murderers of our Lord were not the
men who made the Cross, or plaited the crown of thorns, or drove the
nails, or thrust the spear; not the Centurion and his hundred men, as
they guarded that innocent victim of hellish malice. They were the
least guilty. They were but the hand of the power that enacted and
expounded the law. Judas was guilty. Herod was guilty. Pilate was
guilty--the Sanhedrim, with Caiphas, the Chief Priests, and Scribes;
the populace, crying "Crucify, crucify Him"--these all were
guilty. Their pride and envy, and malice and revenge, were all
embodied, <hi rend="italic">vitalized</hi>, in that one act, the murder
of the King of the Jews.</p>
               <p>The poor, miserable, wicked assassin, whose name is not
worthy of mention, though he has gone out with a mark deeper than the
mark of Cain upon him, and who cannot escape the justice that awaits
him, was but the representation and instrument of the enemies of the
Heaven-blessed Government, whose Head they have stricken down.</p>
               <lg type="stanza">
                  <l>Our father's God, to Thee,</l>
                  <l>Author of Liberty,</l>
               </lg>
               <p>though crushed and humbled in the very dust, to Thee we lift our
hearts with confidence, and hope, and thanksgiving, that though the
great, and good, and wise man whom Thou did'st give us, to govern; has
been stricken down, the people, the government, the eternal principles
of Truth, and Freedom, and Righteousness, <hi rend="italic">still
live.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I call you to witness to-day, my brethren, that this pulpit
has offered no uncertain sound, during these four years of treason and
blood. Neither by <hi rend="italic">silence</hi>--for <hi rend="italic">silence</hi> is treason, when the life of the nation is
endangered--by thought, look, word, or act, has your pastor given aid
and comfort to that thirst for power which has culminated in the
murder of Abraham Lincoln. The loyalty of this pulpit has not been
begotten amid the victorious battles of our noble men by land and by
sea, nor in the presence of the crumbling ruins of rebellion. But the
position of your pastor to-day is what it was at the firing of the
first gun
<pb n="8"/>
                  <figure><graphic url=""/>
                     <figDesc>8th page of J. G. Butler's
The Martyr President.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
upon our glorious flag of Sumter. Though Southern by birth, and by
residence, during his entire ministry, his loyalty is not a thing of
prejudice or passion, but takes its inspiration from this blessed <hi rend="italic">Book</hi>, which teaches us to <hi rend="italic">obey
Magistrates, and that the powers that be are ordained of God</hi>. I
thank God to day, that I have had no part nor lot in this matter; that
He enabled me, in the dark days of our national struggle, when the
faint-hearted warned me, and the disloyal hated, and forsook my
ministry, that God gave me strength and courage to speak the truth. No
man has ever weakened the arm of the government and given courage to
the enemy from the inspiration of this sacred desk. This pulpit is in
no sense chargeable with the blood of Abraham Lincoln.</p>
               <p>When aroused from my midnight slumbers, by the alarming
intelligence, that our President had been assassinated--even now we
can scarcely realize that he, from whose facile pen we were but a few
days since receiving despatches of victories; whose pleasant, placid
face is so familiar to many of us; who has just been telling us, and
the nation, and the world, of prospective peace, and speaking healing
words, words of gentleness and forbearance and forgiveness and love,
healing the deep wounds of the nation's heart; the tender and earnest
Intercessor, pleading with us, who have given our very life-blood to
save Truth, and Freedom, and Government, entreating us to forgive our
enemies, and forget the strong blows aimed at our very vitals--that
<hi rend="italic">he</hi> should be stricken down, the <hi rend="italic">friend</hi> of the offending rebel, we can hardly
realize. Yet it is so. His tall, manly form lies in the cold embrace
of death today; and as we stand weeping over his mortal remains, the
heart of the nation is nerved with new purpose to suppress, at every
cost, this costly rebellion, and remove from the land <hi rend="italic">that</hi> which has given it inspiration and life. But for
that, rebellion would never have had being. <hi rend="italic">This</hi>
inspires the pride and tyranny which would make every will subject to
its own, which must <hi rend="italic">rule or ruin</hi>. The verdict of
the American people to-day, as it looks upon the spilled blood of the
great Champion of human rights, the friend of the oppressed, the
emancipator of four millions of bondmen, is, that the land must be <hi rend="italic">free</hi>--an open Bible, a free pulpit, a free press,
free speech, a free people.</p>
               <pb n="9"/>
               <p>
                  <figure><graphic url=""/>
                     <figDesc>9th page of
J. G. Butler's The Martyr President.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <p>These millions, enamored of their chains, may, as the delivered
Israelites in their straits, murmur against Moses and against God, and
say, would God we had remained in bondage. We may not be able to
answer all the hard questions which may arise as to our duty towards
the freedman, though God, who has accomplished their deliverance, will
teach us; but the one purpose is formed, that the whole land must be
free. The voices of God and of the people are one in this verdict. His
work is done. I thank God that his sun was not eclipsed during the
dark days of our history, when clouds appeared to gather around our
starry banner; but when it floated upon the soil of every rebel
state--all covered with glory--when the clouds are rolling away and
peace is rapidly rising to the zenith. He longed to see this day. He
saw, and was glad. Ah! yes, and though our hearts are sad to-day we
are glad too--thankful that God gave so good, so wise, so humane a
ruler, and spared him to us so long, crowning his government with the
prospect of an early, a righteous, and permanent peace.</p>
               <p>Our blessed Lord, once called to the death chamber in the
Ruler's house, said of the maid, "not <hi rend="italic">dead</hi>, but
sleepeth." And these words of Jesus, on this resurrection day, inspire
hope as we stand in the presence of the lifeless Ruler now. <hi rend="italic">Not dead</hi>; no, he is not dead. He needs no marble
shaft to perpetuate his memory, to tell future generations that he
lived. He lives not only in the hearts of the four millions of
freedmen, from whom he has broken the shackles of bondage, but in the
heart of this entire nation his name is embalmed in honor and love. In
all future history this name will stand beside that of Washington. If
he was the father of his country, under God, Abraham Lincoln was its
<hi rend="italic">saviour</hi>. He sleeps, as we have reason to know,
not an unbeliever, but as one who feared God and wrought
righteousness. He lives where the martyred men of all ages live--we
believe, where the Great Martyr, our Lord Jesus, lives--in that
heavenly City, whose air is not pregnant with treason and malice and
death; but, where the heart, cleansed and inspired by the blood and
spirit of Jesus, is in perfect and eternal sympathy with the great
Redeemer, whose name is <hi rend="italic">love</hi>. May these precious
memories and hopes sustain and comfort his stricken widow and
fatherless
<pb n="10"/>
                  <figure><graphic url=""/>
                     <figDesc>10th page of
J. G. Butler's The Martyr President.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
children. May the heavy affliction be sanctified by Him who makes all
things to work together for good, and makes even the wrath of man to
praise Him.</p>
               <p>In a government other than Republican, the assassination of
its Head might paralyze its energies or incite revolution. But the
affairs of the Republic roll on to-day steadily--guided, under God, by
a true and loyal heart, and by an arm strong and resolute. Sustained
by the patriotism and wisdom of the nation, as well as by the prayers
of God's people, though our joy has been turned into sorrow, the
future, inspired by holy resolve, is no less hopeful and bright than
when the whole land was flushed with victory. The patriot and
christian heart of the nation should, and will, now encourage and make
strong the arm of the President of the United States, whilst we embalm
in memory the surpassing worth of the fallen Chieftain.</p>
               <p>In partaking of this bread and wine, we are carried back to
the <hi rend="italic">Betrayal night</hi>. And here, in the most solemn
manner, we renew our consecration to our Divine King. This is a
consecration act. We say by it that we are not our own--that we belong
to Jesus, who redeemed us by the price of His own blood--that
henceforth we are to live not unto ourselves, but unto Him that died
for us. As we approach this table to-day, is it not proper, with the
remembrance of the spilled blood of this great human Representative of
truth and freedom, and humanity and love, before us, that we come as
<hi rend="italic">patriot</hi> Christians, renewing <hi rend="italic">first</hi> our allegiance to Jesus, <hi rend="italic">then</hi> to our country--first to the Cross, then to our
Flag. The times in which we live call for earnest consecration to
Jesus in the cause of our country. Our land has a mission. Our whole
history shows God's hand with us. We are to teach the world the Bible
taught truth, that <hi rend="italic">man is capable of
self-government</hi>. We are to be the light of the world. In the
light of our life the thrones of despots will tremble, and the power
of the oppressor be broken. Drawing our patriotism, and philanthropy,
and religion from this great fountain of Divine Truth, we are to
proclaim to the nations of the earth, through a free pulpit, a free
press, free schools, and free people, the truth which only the despot
in Church or State fears; and the oppressor ought to fear and tremble,
for he is weighed in the balance and is found wanting.</p>
               <pb n="11"/>
               <p>
                  <figure><graphic url=""/>
                     <figDesc>11th page of
J. G. Butler's The Martyr President.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <p>But that our mission may be fulfilled, we must be a <hi rend="italic">consecrated people</hi>--a people consecrated to the great
principles of free government--to the teachings of Jesus, who came not
only "to preach the Gospel to the poor, and heal the broken hearted,
but to proclaim deliverance to the captives, and the opening of the
prisons to them that are bound."</p>
               <lg type="stanza">
                  <l>"Hail to the <hi rend="italic">Lord's
anointed</hi>,</l>
                  <l>Great David's greater Son!</l>
                  <l>Hail in the time appointed,</l>
                  <l>His reign on earth begun.</l>
                  <l>He comes to break oppression,</l>
                  <l>To set the captive free,</l>
                  <l>To take away transgression,</l>
                  <l>And rule in equity.</l>
                  <l>He comes with succor speedy,</l>
                  <l>To those who suffer wrong;</l>
                  <l>To help the poor and needy,</l>
                  <l>And bid the weak be strong;</l>
                  <l>To give them songs for sighing,</l>
                  <l>Their darkness turn to light,</l>
                  <l>Whose souls, condemned and dying,</l>
                  <l>Were precious in his sight."</l>
               </lg>
               <p>The Church--the whole body of <hi rend="italic">believers</hi>, of every name--is the living
representative of Jesus in a rebel world, to teach the truth He
taught, to live the life He lived, and, if need be, to die the death
He died, that the kingdom of ignorance, and oppression, and sin may be
destroyed.</p>
               <p>The bloody struggle of the past four years, of which this
tragic deed is one of the closing acts, is full of
significance. Nations, as well as individuals, may have their second
birth--<hi rend="italic">must be born again</hi>--before they are
prepared for a pure, vigorous, and useful manhood. Our nation <hi rend="italic">has</hi> been born again, amid the terrible carnage of the
battle-field, and baptized by the tears and blood of the entire
land. Our noblest sons have been laid upon the great sacrificial
altar. Heaven--the God of truth and justice and mercy, the God of
battles--has accepted the offering, and now, as we rise to the purity
and dignity and responsibility of our renewed nationality, we must
offer this last sacrifice, and thank God that our President's dying
eyes rested, not upon the ruins of a once mighty Republic, but upon
the land redeemed, regenerated, ennobled, prepared for the great
mission upon which the King of Kings sends her forth.</p>
               <pb n="12"/>
               <p>
                  <figure><graphic url=""/>
                     <figDesc>12th page of
J. G. Butler's The Martyr President.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <p>We have come forth, not enfeebled by the death agony
through which we have passed, but <hi rend="italic">stronger</hi> than
when we entered upon our life trial. God has smiled upon the nation in
her noble struggle. Agriculture, manufactures, commerce, religion, all
share the divine blessing. A flood of prosperity has rolled over us,
in which we are in danger of forgetting God. And yet the religious
life of the land has never been so vigorous--our sanctuaries thronged,
our treasuries full, souls converted, and the whole Church aroused
from her lethargy and pouring forth her treasure and talent not only
in strengthening the bulwarks of Zion, but, above all, in ministering
to the wants, bodily and spiritual, of our brave defenders, and even
remembering those whose parricidal hand aimed a death blow at the very
vitals of our Government.</p>
               <p>The life of the nation is healthy, vigorous, to-day--nerved
with holy resolve.</p>
               <p>As the war-cloud rolls away from the rebel States, we shall
witness the desolations of civil strife. Not only are governments
disorganized, but the Church, too, needs reconstruction. The Southern
pulpit, forgetting the Apostolic injunction, has fired the Southern
heart and strengthened the arm of the rebel government, by preaching
treason and resistance to rightful authority. The terrible desolations
of civil war have swept over these States. All is disorder there, in
the family, the church, and the government.</p>
               <p>In the midst of our sorrow to-day, our hearts should
overflow with thanksgiving that the hand of the destroyer has not
paralyzed the arm of our industry nor polluted our altars. A glance at
our Southern land shows what our cities and towns would be had the
boast of the destroyer been realized, and the slave roll been called
upon Bunker Hill. But God has given us the victory, blessed be His
holy name! Glory be to the Father and to the Son and to the Holy
Ghost, as it was in the beginning, is now, and ever shall be, world
without end!</p>
               <p>We must now address ourselves, as patriot Christians, to
the duties of the hour. It is ours to strengthen the arm of the
Executive, to encircle him with our sympathies, our confidence, and
our prayers. It is ours to remember the brave men who have stood as a
wall of fire between us and our enemies; to care for the
<pb n="13"/>
                  <figure><graphic url=""/>
                     <figDesc>13th page of
J. G. Butler's The Martyr President.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
widow and orphan of the slain soldier; to feed the hungry and clothe
the naked of our country's enemies; to educate and elevate, so far as
sanctified knowledge can elevate, the four millions of freedmen from
whom the fetters have been broken, by the wise counsel of our
President and the valor of our arms; to raise to new life the Church,
wounded, sundered, bleeding, dying, amid the flames of rebellion; to
teach the people to render unto Caesar the things that are Caesar's,
and to God the things that are God's--not to revenge and exasperate,
but to forgive, to heal, to help, and bind in one common brotherhood
all the states of this Union--to kill the fatted calf upon the return
of the penitent, needy, and humbled prodigal. Though the diabolical
hand of the assassin has felled the noble President, around whom the
heart of the nation gathered, in this work of reconciliation and
healing, revenge must not fire our heart. But whilst the dignity of
the law and the honor of the Government must be vindicated, the spirit
of the fallen One, his humanity, his forbearance, his slowness to
wrath, his love of peace, must animate our hearts. Our erring
brethren; whilst being taught that treason is <hi rend="italic">crime</hi>, must yet know that only the love of order and
peace insists upon its penalty; that justice is tempered with mercy;
that righteousness and peace may kiss each other.</p>
               <p>In the memorial of our Saviour's death, and with these
emblems of our national sorrow, we must anew consecrate ourselves
to-day to these works of Christian philanthropy. Though we be not able
to see alike upon all the great questions that have agitated the land,
yet with treason and rebellion concentrated in the fell blow of the
assassin, as patriots and Christians we must forget our differences,
and rise superior to our prejudices. We must meet the issues of the
day as <hi rend="italic">men</hi>, planting ourselves upon the Bible, as
we stand beside the Cross, and unfurl our starry banner, now draped in
mourning, with the undying resolve, that, in God's name, <hi rend="italic">the right shall triumph, though our own blood pay the
price</hi>.</p>
               <p>God has taught us, during this struggle, what we can do,
when deeply in earnest. The Christian and the patriot, sparing not
their own sons, have, with them, freely given of their treasure and
labor to bind up the wounds and pour in oil and wine. The millions of
treasure that have cheered our suffering soldiers may
<pb n="14"/>
                  <figure><graphic url=""/>
                     <figDesc>14th page of
J. G. Butler's The Martyr President.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
now be expended to restore the ruin of war and heal heart wounds which
have estranged the North and the South. There is not before us a
season of rest, though the clash of arms is soon to cease, but of
labor--self-denying, constant, and earnest. The work so auspiciously
begun, so successfully prosecuted by our martyred President, must be
carried on, until the world shall enjoy that freedom wherewith Christ
makes the people free.</p>
               <p>The adage is no more trite than true, that the "blood of
the martyrs is the seed of the Church." The disciples scattered,
during the first century, by the persecution and martyrdom of our
Lord, and His defenceless ones, did not go with sealed lips, but
opened their mouth boldly, declaring the truth. And with our land
regenerated by fire, the arm of the oppressor broken, our noble and
beloved Leader slain, shall not our tongue be fired with holy zeal,
not for party, nor section, but for <hi rend="italic">truth?</hi> Shall
loyalty be timid and shrinking in the presence of treason? Shall
freedom hide her head for fear of the oppressor? Shall the press be
fearful and compromising? Shall the pulpit give an uncertain sound in
this day of battle? Though the atmosphere be poisoned with the miasm
of oppression and treason, if <hi rend="italic">this</hi> sacred desk
fail to speak forth the truth in love, may my heart forget her
cunning, and my tongue cleave to the roof of my mouth.</p>
            </div2>
         </div1>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>