<TEI.2>
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt n="A Sermon on the Death of Abraham Lincoln, April 15th, 1865.">
            <title>  A Sermon on the Death of Abraham Lincoln, April 15th,
1865.</title>
            <author>Daggett, O. E.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Compiled
and edited by</resp>
               <name>Beck Center</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent/>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Lewis H. Beck Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Emory
University</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Atlanta,
Georgia</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>1996 Emory
University. Permission is granted to download, transmit, or otherwise
reproduce, distribute or display the contributions to the work claimed
by Emory University for non-profit educational purposes, provided
this header is included in its entirety.  For inquiries about
commercial uses, contact the Director, 
Pitts Theology Library, Emory
University, Atlanta, Georgia 30322</p>
            </availability>
            <date>1999</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Lincoln Sermons Project</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Daggett, O. E. A Sermon on the Death of Abraham Lincoln, April
15th, 1865.  Preached in the First Congregational Church, Canandaigua,
N. Y.  Sunday Morning, April 16th, 1865, And Again, by Request, the
Following Wednesday Evening, by the Pastor, O. E. Daggett.
Canandaigua, N. Y.  N. J. Milliken, Printer-Ontario County Times
Office.  1865. </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This text derives from the Special Collections 
of Pitts Theology Library, Emory University, and is produced in 
collaboration with the Lewis H. Beck Center a, the Emory 
Preservation Office, and Pitts Theology Library.</p>
            <p>TRANSCRIBER: Lewis H. Beck Center and Emory University Preservation Office.</p>
            <p>PRODUCER:  BookLab, Inc., 1606 Headway Circle, Suite 100, Austin, TX 78754</p>
            <p>CAPTURE DEVICE: XEROX DocuImage 620S flatbed scanner</p>
            <p>CAPTURE DETAILS: Scanner software: XEROX ScanTool version 4.2.3; no gamma correction; images are all bitonal.</p>
            <p>CHANGE HISTORY: Using the Adobe Photoshop Batch Processor, we interpolated  the original TIFF files to 8-bit grays, and altered the resolution to 144 dpi, producing screen images twice the original size.  We then saved them in JPEG format.  We produced GIF thumbnails from the JPEG files.</p>
            <p>RESOLUTION: 600 ppi</p>
            <p>COMPRESSION: Resolution 144 per inch with Constrain Properties to 72 per inch.</p>
            <p>SOURCE: Original documents.</p>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>1999</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Scott Ellis</name>
               <resp>Staff</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <item>SGML tags
inserted in compliance with TEI guidelines using TEILITE</item>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div1 id="dagget.001" n="A Sermon on the Death of Abraham Lincoln, April 15th, 1865." type="text">
            <head pn="1">
               <bibl>
                  <title>A Sermon on the Death of Abraham Lincoln, April 15th,
1865.</title> 
                  <date> Sunday Morning, April 16th, 1865, And Again, by
Request, the Following Wednesday Evening.</date> 
                  <pubPlace>First
Congregational Church, Canandaigua, N. Y.</pubPlace> 
                  <author>Pastor
O. E. Daggett</author>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Canandaigua, New York</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>N. J. Milliken,
Printer-Ontario County Times Office.</publisher>
                     <date>1865</date>
                  </imprint>
               </bibl>
            </head>
            <p pn="1">
               <figure entity="dagget1">
                  <figDesc>1st page of O. E. Daggett's A Sermon
on the Death of Abraham Lincoln.</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <p pn="1">A SERMON</p>
            <p pn="1">ON THE DEATH OF</p>
            <p pn="1">ABRAHAM LINCOLN,</p>
            <p pn="1">April 15th, 1865,</p>
            <p pn="1">PREACHED IN THE FIRST CONGREGATIONAL CHURCH,</p>
            <p pn="1">CANANDAIGUA, N.Y.</p>
            <p pn="1">Sunday Morning, April 16th, 1865,</p>
            <p pn="1">AND AGAIN, BY REQUEST, THE FOLLOWING WEDNESDAY EVENING,</p>
            <p pn="1">BY THE PASTOR,</p>
            <p pn="1">O.E. DAGGETT.</p>
            <p pn="1">CANANDAIGUA, N.Y.</p>
            <p pn="1">N.J. MILLIKEN, PRINTER-ONTARIO COUNTY
TIMES OFFICES</p>
            <p pn="1">1865</p>
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p pn="2">
               <figure entity="dagget2">
                  <figDesc>2nd page of
O. E. Daggett's A Sermon on the Death of Abraham
Lincoln.</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <p pn="2">CANANDAIGUA, APRIL
17TH, 1865.  <lb/>O.E. DAGGETT, D.D.,
			<lb/>Dear Sir:-The undersigned, for themselves,
and many others, whose pleasure and satisfaction it was to listen to
your timely and patriotic discourse, the 16th inst., on the melancholy
events which have so appalled us in common with the whole American
people, respectfully request a copy of that discourse for publication. 
					<lb/>Yours respectfully,<lb/>
L.B. GAYLORD,							WM. H. LAMPORT,<lb/>
F.J. CASTLE,							J. ALBERT
GRANGER,<lb/>
H.N. JARVIS,							GIDEON
GRANGER,<lb/>
J.B. HAYES,								HARVEY
JEWETT,<lb/>
H.W. TAYLOR,							A.G. COLEMAN,<lb/>
MERRICK
MUNGER,							GEO. COOK,<lb/>
J.C. FAIRCHILD,							CHARLES
COY.</p>
            <p pn="2">L.B. GAYLORD, AND OTHERS:
	<lb/>
               <hi rend="italic">Gentlemen</hi>:-The sermon on President
LINCOLN'S death I submit to, your disposal, though of course it cannot
excite in the reading the same interest that was expressed by those
who heard, it while the theme was altogether new. As printed, I prefer
it should keep the form it had on Sunday morning, and hence I omit the
allusion, on Wednesday evening, to that day as the time of the
obsequies and the memorable 19th of April, inserting, however, near
the close, as on the latter occasion, a paragraph inadvertently
omitted in the first hasty preparation. 
					<lb/>Yours respectfully
								<lb/>O. E. DAGGETT.</p>
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p pn="3">
               <figure entity="dagget3">
                  <figDesc>3rd page of
O. E. Daggett's A Sermon on the Death of Abraham
Lincoln.</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <div2 id="dagget.002" n="SERMON" type="sermon">
               <head pn="3">SERMON</head>
               <epigraph pn="3">
                  <p pn="3">
                     <hi rend="italic">"That your faith and hope
might be in God.</hi>"-1 PET., 1, 21.</p>
               </epigraph>
               <p pn="3">We are one with the millions who, having partaken of a common joy,
this day partake of a common grief. The nation's heart is throbbing
through our hearts. The past week has come and gone like a wondrous
dream, yet a momentous reality. What other ever brought such
vicissitudes, what other will have left such ineffaceable memories? No
sooner had the last Lord's day passed with us quietly, though
pleasantly stirred as by ripples of the wave of joy that had just
rolled over the land with the tidings of victory from Richmond and
Petersburg, than Monday brought another and higher surge of joy from
the surrender of the chief rebel army; and so the week began with the
ringing of bells, and roar of cannon, and waving of banners, and
processions, prayers, addresses, and every spontaneous signal of
patriotic hilarity, fitly crowned at night with such illumination as
never flashed through our quiet village before. Then yesterday, with
the last day of the same week, there came upon us, and upon our whole
land yet palpitating with its new hope and courage, a stroke of sorrow
so sharp, so sudden, so appalling, that we were as if stunned. Instead
of our jubilant thanksgiving, we stood in silent wondering sorrow. The
bells that had rung out so merrily tolled in lament. Our beloved flags
were draped in mourning. The journals that of late had flamed with
announcements of victories, now bore their black lines of
grief. "President Lincoln is shot-there is no hope of his recovery;"
yet after these telegrams some
<pb n="4"/>
                  <figure entity="dagget4">
                     <figDesc>4th page of
O. E. Daggett's A Sermon on the Death of Abraham
Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
of us would hope, until there came another, "The President is
dead."<ref target="dagget.002.n01">*</ref>
Similar tidings came too, though not so hopeless, of his chief
adviser, the Secretary of State, before prostrate on his bed, yet
stabbed at the same hour. We have hardly known what to say or
think. How can these things be, and what can come of them? Where is
the divine Providence? What cloud is this that has burst over us; what
emissaries from hell have broken forth at the hour of our triumph?
Such questions we have asked, and neither we nor others could
answer.</p>
               <p pn="4">All this bewilderment seemed to me a strange preparation for this
Lord's day. But then I thought, so much the more is this day needed,
its silence, its worship, its meditation. Whither should we go in such
sorrowful confusion, but to the house of prayer? To whom should we
look but to God who is our refuge? Yet this day in particular is kept,
in the greater part of Christendom, as Easter Sunday, in joyful
commemoration of our Lord's resurrection from the grave, and I had
intended, in one of our services, to occupy you with that topic. How
mingle such sad thoughts of death, and such cheerful thoughts of life?
How sing the Lord's song under the shadow of bereavement that has just
fallen over our dear country? But, again I have said to myself, we the
more need this very theme of Jesus and the resurrection, to allay the
tumult of thought, to soothe the wounded spirit, to stay our faltering
trust, with a fresh assurance to be thence drawn of the solid
foundation God has given us for confidence not in man but in
Himself. So I would still keep that theme in sight, with a view to the
effect which the apostle Peter sets forth as means to be produced, by
our Lord's resurrection, in the minds of his followers. They are thus
addressed:-"Who by him (Christ) do believe in God who raised
<note pn="4" id="dagget.002.n01" n="*" place="foot" anchored="yes">He was shot on Friday at 10 P.M., but died Saturday,
April 15th, at 7:22 A.M. The first intelligence came here in the
Rochester paper, and the latter by telegraph, some hours later.</note>
                  <pb n="5"/>
                  <figure entity="dagget5">
                     <figDesc>5th page of
O. E. Daggett's A Sermon on the Death of Abraham
Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
him up from the dead, and gave him glory, <hi rend="italic">that your
faith and hope might be in God</hi>."</p>
               <p pn="5">The result described in these last words is the very confidence we
always need, and never more than under the shock of sudden
disaster. True Christians may be staggered by ill tidings, but ought
never to be, prostrated. Their faith and hope ought to be of such a
quality,--that is, ought to have such a ultimate objects and reasons,
and grasp them so firmly,--as never to be helpless. This is our
confidence, so far as it is in God. In the face of calamity, whether
private or public, individual or national, we are made to feel what
that good is which; above all things else we hope, for, and what the
ground or reason is on which we hope for it, and hence to ascertain
our true foundation. If this be in God, it, may be shaken but it
cannot be overthrown. No events can utterly confound us. Our hope for
our country ought thus to have God, his will and glory, for its object
and security, in order to resist all vicissitudes and trials. It is to
me a source of satisfaction that in adapting my instructions and
exhortations here to the various aspects of our great national
struggle, I have always made this thought prominent. When public
affairs looked bright, I have aimed to lead you to give God the glory,
and when they have seemed darkest I have urged you still not the less
to trust and rest in him. Now that we have been checked midway in the
joy of new exulting prospects by a sudden disappointment and grief
that partake of a personal as well as public character, what better
counsel can I give you than to say still, As surely as we are on the
Lord's side, He is on ours: "the Lord of hosts is with us!" See to it
that this principal design of Christianity be realized in you; that
your faith and hope be in God!</p>
               <p pn="5">It is not a new thing for death to enter the highest place in our
land,-we may say the post of highest honor in the world,-and to choose
for his victim a President
<pb n="6"/>
                  <figure entity="dagget6">
                     <figDesc>6th page of
O. E. Daggett's A Sermon on the Death of Abraham
Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
of the United States. President Harrison died in 1841, a month after
his inauguration, and President Taylor held the office but little over
a year, dying in 1850. But not so suddenly, not so fearfully, came the
destroyer then. It was with the slow steps and premonitions of
disease. The nation had made itself in part ready for the issue; bent
its ear to listen for the tidings. For the first time we are appalled
by the assassination of a President of the United States. A crime of
pagan Rome, of Mohammedan Turkey, of revolutionary France, wounds,
dishonors, bereaves our republic, through its trusted, beloved
Head. Nor have we now, as then, the mere frustration of an experiment
beginning to be tried, the cutting short of a new administration; nor
are these the same tranquil times for our country and our
government. The world knows what the past four years have been; how
this nation has striven and bled; how its government has stood for its
life against a ferocious rebellion, marshalling host against host in
millions, on a hundred battle-fields, and overshadowing the insurgent
coast with the mightiest navy of the world; how its brave men have
fought and fallen, and its noble women have wrought, and its Christian
people have prayed; how, though slowly and with reverses, it has year
after year regained lost territory, fortresses, and cities, ever
holding fast what it has once reconquered. And the world has noted
how, after four years of such strife, the nation again put into the
chief magistracy the man under whom it had been conducted from the
beginning,--as high a tribute to his fidelity as human minds could pay
or devise. It is scarcely more than a month since he entered on his
new term; yet how have blessings crowned it already, what territory
has been mastered, what battles fought, what cities won, what a
surrender received of the most formidable of the rebel chiefs and
armies, and how has our loyal land rung with shouts of triumph, and
leaped for joy in the prospect of re-union
<pb n="7"/>
                  <figure entity="crane7">
                     <figDesc>7th page of O. E. Daggett's
A Sermon on the Death of Abraham Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
and peace! At such a time, for him in whom centered so many hearts and
hopes, to fall by a murderer's hand,-for the pilot who has steered the
ship through such storms so near to the desired haven, to be struck
down at the helm, by an assassin,-this is our disappointment and
wonder and grief. No other death has so thrilled, or could so thrill,
this nation at once with a sense of bereavement and with horror.</p>
               <p pn="7">It is not my purpose, if now it were so soon possible for me, nor
is this the time or place, to review formally the administration of
our lamented President, or to set forth his history or delineate fully
his character. This will be done by many with ample time and means,
and will be no small part of the history of his country and of this
age. There is an increasing unanimity among the loyal people of the
United States in a high estimate of his services and worth as proved
by time. I have no doubt at all as to the judgment of posterity. On
this occasion I shall but briefly advert to some things in his
character and course that make his sudden death so memorable an
affliction to us and to our nation.</p>
               <p pn="7">Abraham Lincoln rose to his high position from the utmost
obscurity, by virtue of native intellectual power, and indomitable
moral energy. He was an eminently wise and good man, strong in his
integrity, faithful to his high obligations, devoted to his country's
good, patient in his toils, true to his friends, lenient to his
enemies, hopeful and firm in the face of disaster, magnanimous in the
hour of triumph. Placed at the head of the government in the opening
of our national crisis, he has been true to his official vows in
behalf of the Union of these States, and in as active sympathy as his
position allowed with suffering patriots and with the victims of
southern oppression. It was a thing of course that there should be
differences of honest opinion about sundry measures of his
administration, and especially as to the conduct of the war in its
different stages. Never
<pb n="8"/>
                  <figure entity="dagget8">
                     <figDesc>8th page of
O. E. Daggett's A Sermon on the Death of Abraham
Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
was a magistrate set to a more difficult task than his, involving more
delicate questions, complicated with more diverse, conflicting
influences. Never was a public man more severely tried, or more fully
acquitted of all selfish ambitious, or sordid aims. I remember seeing
him as he went through Broadway in New York, in a procession attended
and cheered by throngs of citizens, on his way to his first
inauguration, and I remember wondering what was before him, and
imagining the responsibility that lay upon that tall, stalwart
frame. But that burden proved to be even greater than I feared, and
that frame has stood up longer and more manfully under it than could
have been confidently predicted of any man even more fully
tried. Among all these difficulties of his work, amidst all inevitable
differences and oppositions, of interests and opinions and passions,
finding the ship of state at once half dismantled and beaten by a
tempest, and having both to equip and manage it, he has done his work
bravely, so as to command wonderfully the confidence of this great
people and the respect of the world. To the qualities I have named
must be added, or, we must reckon rather as their joint product, a
certain moderation of temper. which is conceded by all,--a rare and
invaluable qualification for public men in critical times, though not
the most brilliant, or imposing, and eminently befitting his high
post, at a such a season. Herein he resembled Washington, as in his
unquestioned fidelity to his momentous trust. In such circumstances it
would have been clearly impossible for any President at once to suit
all parties; and by reason of this very moderation he could not at
once satisfy all factions of the party that had elected him. He did
not propose to himself any abstract theory for the conduct of his
administration, to which he would subordinate events, but rather this
one end, to put down the rebellion and to restore the Union of the
States, and hence from time to time he adjusted himself to new
emergencies with the
<pb n="9"/>
                  <figure entity="dagget9">
                     <figDesc>9th page of
O. E. Daggett's A Sermon on the Death of Abraham
Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
practical wisdom that alone deserves the name. Neither to the more
radical nor yet to the more conservative of his strongest partizans
did he yield himself, whether supinely or impulsively, and hence at
times displeasing each class, he at length won the more confidence
from both, and the increasing respect of the mass of those whose
opinions had differed most widely from his own. As he had to encounter
conflicting judgments and partialities, so it was a thing of course
that amidst the excitements of the day he should be misunderstood,
misrepresented and reproached. It now seems hardly possible, yet it is
true, that the illustrious Washington in his own time was subject to
the harshest aspersions upon his personal capacity and worth, and even
within this generation an aged traveler, in a stage coach on the
Hudson river, pointed out a spot where he said, "the American army in
the Revolution was well nigh ruined by the pusillanimity of
Mr. Washington",--that traveler being Aaron Burr. As I cannot doubt
that Abraham Lincoln was proved by long and fiery trial to be a man
raised up by Providence for the station he filled, so it must be
conceded by all that he honestly aimed to shape his course by the
indications of Providence.</p>
               <p pn="9">And nothing more plainly illustrates these thoughts than his course
on the whole subject of emancipation. From first to last, as I have
said, he proposed to himself, with the simplicity of a religious vow,
this one end, the restoration of the Federal government in its
integrity and unity, even to the repossession of every post, not
feeling himself authorized by his, vows to assail any institution of
any State for any other purpose; but when he believed the time had
come that slavery must die in order that the Union might live, as a
President of the Union he addressed himself, by proclaiming the slaves
free in all the insurgent territory, to the destruction of that which,
so virulently assailed the union. While some might think, with
Mr. Everett, when consulted on the subject, that
<pb n="10"/>
                  <figure entity="dagget10">
                     <figDesc>10th page of
O. E. Daggett's A Sermon on the Death of Abraham
Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
such a measure was constitutional but not yet expedient, none can deny
that he employed it in perfect consistency with his avowed patriotic
and constitutional aim. The world abroad, that cannot so well
appreciate his love and our love of the Union, has not failed to
accord him for this measure the highest honor, and posterity will
surely reckon it his brightest monument. Therefore it is, to day, that
while a loyal nation mourns for him dead with no common sorrow, a
whole race within this nation yields him even a more touching
tribute. I seem to see their millions bending reverently, their
shackles broken, while with plaintive prayers and songs they lament
him as their deliverer, hallowing his memory with their tears.</p>
               <p pn="10">Such being the personal qualities conceded to our President, it was
the good pleasure of Providence, within the past few months, to crown
his administration with such signal successes, and of late to
accumulate such victories for our arms, that the people at large, with
all their diversities of judgment or preference, had come into a
fuller and kindlier appreciation of his services and his merits than
could have been possible through any more limited experience. They had
learned to honor him full well while yet he lived, and now that he is
dead he has the tribute of a universal sorrow not from this nation
only but from the friends of freedom in every land. Patriotism and
philanthropy will pay homage together at his grave.</p>
               <p pn="10">The elements of character thus indicated, in connection with the
manner of his death and, with our recent triumphs and joys, give to
our sense of the occasion almost a personal quality not felt at every
public loss. We think of the dead not merely in his official aspect,
but in a closer relation, somewhat as of our brave men for whom he has
mourned with us. Indeed he is himself added to our "noble army of
martyrs." He too has fallen in his country's service, though not by a
soldier's hand but an assassin's. From his high position he has
<pb n="11"/>
                  <figure entity="dagget11">
                     <figDesc>11th page of
O. E. Daggett's A Sermon on the Death of Abraham
Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
gone higher to the rank of his country's sacrifices. To him belongs
now the tribute which he paid to them with most simple touching
eloquence on the field of Gettysburg. Of the myriads of graves which
this war has filled, none will be more sacred or inspiring than
his. It remains for the people, as he then taught, to be dedicated by
his example to the work for which he wrought and fell.</p>
               <p pn="11">Death ever has a peculiar solemnity when it enters the high places
of the world, not only for its contrast with earthly dignity, but
because it suggests the common footing on which we all stand in
relation to the unseen world. I have not the materials, if it were
proper, to form any estimate of Mr. Lincoln's religious views and
feelings, farther than they may be inferred from the moral traits
already indicated, and from incidents uncertainly reported. It is
pleasant now to remember that more than four years ago, on leaving his
western home, not knowing that on his way to the Capital he was
exposed to the same peril that has now proved fatal, he asked the
prayers of the neighbors and friends about him. It is pleasant now to
believe the story of his early morning devotions and reading of the
Scriptures, and that other account of his avowal that after his
domestic bereavement, and still more decisively at the dedication of
the Gettysburg cemetery, he had consecrated himself to the Savior. We
see what those things are which we most love to recall concerning the
dead. It seems easy for us to believe that one who has been so
faithful to such an earthly trust, when suddenly called to a higher
than human tribunal, has received the testimony, "Well done, thou good
and faithful servant!"</p>
               <p pn="11">We are conscious of another emotion under our national
bereavement. Besides sorrow for a faithful servant of his country in
her highest office, that country is thrilled with horror at the crime
which bereaves her, and indignation toward his murderer. If there be
on earth
<pb n="12"/>
                  <figure entity="dagget12">
                     <figDesc>12th page of
O. E. Daggett's A Sermon on the Death of Abraham
Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
a man who rejoices in or approves of this atrocity, that man is
himself an assassin. If in all our loyal States there be one who is
indifferent, we must leave him to God's mercy, for on such a man his
country and humanity can have none. We first thought, this is the
insanity of fanaticism; but since two murders were attempted at the
same hour., we must reckon it the worn of bribed conspirators. On
either supposition, there lives the man, we hope already arrested and
doomed, into whom entered the foulest of unclean spirits, and who has
done the demoniac work of his master. A gust of malignant fire from
the pit has swept over our high places, and blasted him whom the
nation delighted to honor. "Vengeance belongeth unto God," yet it is a
righteous indignation that burns within us toward the dastardly
assassin. Nor are we forbidden to say of a miscreant who has wrought
such a crime against a nation in her peril, what Paul could say of one
who had done him "much evil,"--"The Lord reward him according to his
works."<ref target="dagget.002.n02">*</ref></p>
               <p pn="12">The atrocity of the crime by which this affliction is brought on
our country must not lead us to think of the event out of its
connection with the providence of God. Events are providential not
merely sometimes as independent of human agency, but always as never
independent of the divine control; as always under God's permission,
and within the scope of his plan, and hence provided for in his all
comprehending administration, so as never to frustrate his purposes,
or ultimately to confound the confidence that is fixed on him. As no
contingencies can be so sudden or so disastrous, so no agencies can be
so violent or so malignant as to defeat or surprise his government of
the world. The crimes that He most abhors, when not prevented, are yet
overruled in subordination to his cause, and against their guilty
authors. The Son of God was "crucified and slain by wicked hands" on a
Friday, more than eighteen centuries ago
<note pn="12" id="dagget.002.n02" n="*" place="foot" anchored="yes">2 Tim. 4., 14.</note>
                  <pb n="13"/>
                  <figure entity="dagget13">
                     <figDesc>13th page of
O. E. Daggett's A Sermon on the Death of Abraham
Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
yet was He "delivered by the determinate counsel and foreknowledge of
God." <ref target="dagget.002.n3">*</ref> Let not this new crime in out annals, wrought on the day kept
as the anniversary of that day, seem to us as if it had not been
foreseen, and permitted, however mysteriously, by him in whom we
trust, and would not be made subservient to the very good it was
intended to destroy.</p>
               <p pn="13">Some things I have noted as giving us a measure of relief in the
aspect of this national disaster. It is well that our President did
not fall in Richmond, where he had been so recently exposed. It might
then have been said or thought that he was out of his place, incurring
needless danger, and the coincidence would have put into the mouths of
our enemies a taunt that we could not but deplore. Still more do I
rejoice and thank God that he did not fall a few months sooner. Would
that he might have been permitted to see the consummation of the train
of events so gloriously begun, and to retire, at the end of his
presidency, with the satisfaction and honor of happily completing the
whole part that seemed assigned to him, himself rejoicing in union and
peace restored, and receiving the tribute now to be rendered to his
memory. But since this might not be, we rejoice that he was permitted,
after all his patient toils, to ascend the mount and see the land of
promise from which the clouds were so far lifted off to his eyes and
ours. He lived to do the chief part of his work, and to be assured of
its success. He lived till our arms had swept unresisted through the
heart of the southern confederacy, and recaptured nearly all the
cities and fortresses wrested from us by the enemy; till our old flag
waved again over the birth place and the capital of the rebellion,
borne to that supremacy by faithful champions from among those whom
that rebellion would have trodden down forever; till the ablest rebel
leader had surrendered with his army; nor did he die till he could say,
<note pn="13" id="dagget.002.n3" n="*" place="foot" anchored="yes">Acts 2., 23.</note>
                  <pb n="14"/>
                  <figure entity="dagget14">
                     <figDesc>14th page of
O. E. Daggett's A Sermon on the Death of Abraham
Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
Already this day has that old flag gone up to its place, and been
flung out in the free air over Fort Sumter by the heroic hands that
held it there so valiantly to the last four years ago. I thank God for
this.</p>
               <p pn="14">If now it be still asked again, as we have all asked, Why must the
Chief Magistrate of this republic, in this day of triumph, fall by the
hand of an assassin, and what are God's designs in permitting it? I
freely answer, I cannot tell; and just because I cannot, therefore the
faith I have is not in events, but in God. "He giveth not account of
any of his matters."<ref target="dagget.002.n4">*</ref> It may be that this stupendous wrong, as also
the inhumanity shown to our soldiers in rebel prisons, was permitted
to show us and the world one more characteristic fruit of this wanton
rebellion; that in the assassination of such a man, might be seen also
the Satanic ambition and brutal barbarism, not of the rebellion alone,
but of that foul system of slavery from which it sprang,-one more
accursed offshoot from that which itself, root and branch, must needs
be accursed.</p>
               <p pn="14">It may be also that particularly at this time there was need of a
certain effect to be produced on the public mind in the loyal States,
which required some such astounding development of the spirit of the
southern rebellion. Already we see it working a more entire unanimity
of sentiment among all loyal people. Like the first cannon-shot
against Fort Sumter, this atrocity has struck the heart of our
nationality, and vehemently aroused all patriotic minds with a common
impulse of indignation against the common foe. A righteous resentment
is kindled over the land. There was need of such a sentiment to be
somehow kindled, to counteract the ascendancy of a certain
sentimentalism that prevails too much in our days. There has been what
one writer called a "rose water philanthropy," which protested against
all capital punishment, on the plea of the sacred-
<note pn="14" id="dagget.002.n4" n="*" place="foot" anchored="yes">Job 33:13.</note>
                  <pb n="15"/>
                  <figure entity="dagget15">
                     <figDesc>15th page of
O. E. Daggett's A Sermon on the Death of Abraham
Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
ness of human life in a murderer, though losing sight of its
sacredness in his victim. But how many can be found to say that if the
Washington assassins can be caught, they ought not to die, and what
imprisonment for life could satisfy justice in their case, and what
penalty short of that which hands them over at once to God's tribunal?
Still more widely has there been among loyal people an excessive
leniency, naturally growing with our prospects of success, on the
question what ought to be done with the authors of this rebellion. We
should be unworthy of such a President as we have lost if we were not
ready to receive back the southern people to the fellowship of the
Union as soon as they will partake of it in good faith; but as to
their instigators, plotters and leaders God forbid that in any event
they be again heard in our councils, or allowed the right they have
betrayed of a vote. God forbid that their chief conspirators should
ever be suffered to breathe again the pure air they have polluted;
that we should deal more mildly with the arch assassins of the nation
than we would with the assassin of its most honored Head! It is here
that the public mind needed to be stiffened and sharpened to a due
sense of the enormity of treason, and the damnation it merits in deeds
as well as words. And it may be to this end that this last crime has
been permitted to thrill with horror the universal heart.</p>
               <p pn="15">But this we know, that whatever lesson we may learn from the
calamity we now deplore, that lesson it was designed to teach. And how
could we be more startlingly admonished of the uncertainty of all
human expectations, and the necessity laid on us for fixing our faith;
and hope, not in the outward aspect of passing events, not in so much
as we can see of present promise, but in God? How little do we know
what is before us, what even "a day may bring forth?" How a single
week or day may be crowded with lights and shades, with rejoicings and
lamentations! And how can we dare to lay up
<pb n="16"/>
                  <figure entity="dagget16">
                     <figDesc>16th page of
O. E. Daggett's A Sermon on the Death of Abraham
Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
any trust in man when man himself is so perishable, and God is the
only Being on whom it can be placed so as never to be confounded?
Every nation has reason to thank God for its wise and good men in
public life, and ought to honor them; but such men die, whether by
disease or violence, so that only their memory can be honored, for
this end, if for no other, that our dependence on God may be felt more
intensely, and we may look to him accordingly. Thus it was in Israel
of old, for that people had their chiefs and prophets, but they were
specially warned against relying on them though raised up by God, as
well as on foreign alliances, to the disparagement of their hope in
the God of Israel. "Cease ye from man whose breath is in his
nostrils." "It is better to trust in the Lord than to put confidence
in man. It is better to trust in the Lord than to put confidence in
princes." This terrible war has taught us such lessons again and
again. This one revolting crime, bereaving of our tried leader,
teaches it to us anew. Our country, the Union, human freedom, peace,
do not depend on man, on Presidents, or Councilors, or Generals,
except under God; and as surely as we are on his side, whatever may
take place, He is with us, and will fashion and furnish his
instruments, and agents. It is wisdom and piety for nations, as for
individuals, to solicit and rely on God's care with a faith that stops
short of nothing but his throne. Let every Christian patriot say for
himself and for his country,-
		<lb/>I know not the way I am going,
			<lb/>But well do I know my Guide! 
		<lb/>With a child-like trust do I give my hand
			<lb/>To the mighty Friend by my side:
		<lb/>And the only thing, that I say to Him,
			<lb/>As He takes it, is, 'Hold it fast,
		<lb/>Suffer me not to lose my way,
			<lb/>And lead me home at last'!"</p>
            </div2>
         </div1>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI.2>