<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader><fileDesc>
         <titleStmt n="Eulogy of Abraham Lincoln">
            <title>Eulogy of Abraham Lincoln</title>
            <author>Deming, Henry Champion</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Compiled and edited by</resp>
               <name>Beck
Center</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent/>
         <publicationStmt><publisher>Lewis H. Beck Center</publisher><pubPlace>Emory University</pubPlace><address>
               <addrLine>Atlanta,
Georgia</addrLine>
            </address><availability>
               <p>1996 Emory
University. Permission is granted to download, transmit, or otherwise
reproduce, distribute or display the contributions to the work claimed
by Emory University for non-profit educational purposes, provided
this header is included in its entirety.  For inquiries about
commercial uses, contact the Director, 
Pitts Theology Library, Emory
University, Atlanta, Georgia 30322</p>
            </availability><date>1999</date></publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Lincoln
Sermons Project</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Deming, Henry
Champion. Eulogy of Abraham Lincoln.  Before the General Assembly of
Connecticut, at Allyn Hall, Hartford, Thursday, June 8th,
1865. Hartford: A. N. Clark &amp; Co., State Printers. 1865.</bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc><encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This text
derives 
from the Special Collections 
of Pitts Theology Library, Emory University, and is produced in 
collaboration with the Lewis H. Beck Center a, the Emory 
Preservation Office, and Pitts Theology Library.</p>
            <p>TRANSCRIBER: Lewis H. Beck Center and Emory University Preservation Office.</p>
            <p>PRODUCER:  BookLab, Inc., 1606 Headway Circle, Suite 100, Austin, TX 78754</p>
            <p>CAPTURE DEVICE: XEROX DocuImage 620S flatbed scanner</p>
            <p>CAPTURE DETAILS: Scanner software: XEROX ScanTool version 4.2.3; no gamma correction; images are all bitonal.</p>
            <p>CHANGE HISTORY: Using the Adobe Photoshop Batch Processor, we interpolated  the original TIFF files to 8-bit grays, and altered the resolution to 144 dpi, producing screen images twice the original size.  We then saved them in JPEG format.  We produced GIF thumbnails from the JPEG files.</p>
            <p>RESOLUTION: 600 ppi</p>
            <p>COMPRESSION: Resolution 144 per inch with Constrain Properties to 72 per inch.</p>
            <p>SOURCE: Original documents.</p>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc><revisionDesc><change><name>Stewart Varner</name> transformed this document from p4 to p5 on <date when="2010-03-22">March 22, 2010</date></change><change xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><date>1999</date><label>Staff</label><name>Scott Ellis</name>SGML tags inserted in compliance
with TEI guidelines using TEILITE</change></revisionDesc></teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div1 xml:id="deming.001" n="Eulogy of Abraham Lincoln" type="text">
            <head> 
               <bibl> 
                  <title>Eulogy of
Abraham Lincoln</title> 
                  <date>June 8th, 1865</date> 
                  <pubPlace>Allyn
Hall, Hartford</pubPlace> 
                  <author>Deming, Henry Champion</author>
                  
                     <pubPlace>Hartford</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>A. N. Clark &amp;
Co.</publisher>
                     <date>1865</date>
                   
               <idno type="ark">http://pid.emory.edu/ark:/25593/15q2t</idno></bibl> 
            </head>
            <p>
               <figure><graphic url=""/>
                  <figDesc>1st page of Henry Champion
Deming's Eulogy of Abraham Lincoln.</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <p>EULOGY</p>
            <p>OF</p>
            <p>ABRAHAM LINCOLN,</p>
            <p>BY</p>
            <p>HENRY CHAMPION DEMING,</p>
            <p>BEFORE THE</p>
            <p>GENERAL ASSEMBLY OF CONNECTICUT</p>
            <p>AT</p>
            <p>ALLYN HALL, HARTFORD, THURSDAY, JUNE 8th, 1865.</p>
            <p>HARTFORD:</p>
            <p>A. N. CLARK &amp; CO., STATE PRINTERS.</p>
            <p>1865.</p>
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>
               <figure><graphic url=""/>
                  <figDesc>2nd page of
Henry Champion Deming's Eulogy of Abraham
Lincoln.</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>
               <figure><graphic url=""/>
                  <figDesc>3rd page of
Henry Champion Deming's Eulogy of Abraham
Lincoln.</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <p>COMMITTEE ON DEATH OF PRESIDENT LINCOLN.</p>
            <p>Hon. Mr. HARRISON. </p>
            <p>Messrs. PRATT of Norwich,</p>
            <p>OAKLEY  of Bristol, </p>
            <p>MERRITT of Greenwich, </p>
            <p>PAYNE of North Haven,</p>
            <p>AMSBURY Of Killingly,</p>
            <p>HART Of  Cornwall, </p>
            <p>HUNGERFORD of East Haddam, </p>
            <p>PAINE  of Woodstock.</p>
            <p>GENERAL
ASSEMBLY,</p>
            <p>MAY
SESSION, A. D. 1865.</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italic">Resolved</hi>, That the thanks of this General
Assembly are hereby tendered to the Hon. HENRY C. DEMING, for his
able, eloquent and patriotic Address on the life and character of
ABRAHAM LINCOLN.</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italic">Resolved</hi>, That
thirty-five hundred copies of said address be printed for the use of
this Assembly.</p>
            <p>IN
SENATE,  June 9th, 1865.</p>
            <p>Passed.</p>
            <p>WM. T. ELMER, <hi rend="italic">Clerk</hi>.</p>
            <p>HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES, JUNE 9th, 1865.</p>
            <p>Passed.</p>
            <p>JOHN R. BUCK, <hi rend="italic">Clerk</hi>.</p>
            <pb n="4"/>
<!-- blank page -->
<!--            <p>
               <figure entity="deming4">
                  <figDesc>4th page of
Henry Champion Deming's Eulogy of Abraham
Lincoln.</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p> -->
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>
               <figure><graphic url=""/>
                  <figDesc>5th page of
Henry Champion Deming's Eulogy of Abraham
Lincoln.</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <div2 xml:id="deming.002" n="EULOGY" type="sermon">
               <head>EULOGY.</head>
               <p>By authority of a joint resolution, the Select Committee on the
Death of President Lincoln, invited the Hon. Henry Champion Deming, of
Hartford, Member of Congress from the First District, to deliver
before the General Assembly a eulogy upon the life, character and
services of the lamented President.</p>
               <p>The invitation was accepted by the honorable gentleman, and the
eulogy was delivered at Allyn Hall, in the city of Hartford, on the
evening of June 8th, 1865.</p>
               <p>The Hall was festooned with flags and mourning, and music was
furnished by Colt's Band.</p>
               <p>The meeting was called to order by Hon. H. Lynde Harrison, Senator
from the Sixth District, who announced the following officers:</p>
               <p>PRESIDENT.</p>
               <p>HIS EXCELLENCY, WM. A. BUCKINGHAM.</p>
               <p>VICE-PRESIDENTS.</p>
               <p>(On the part of the Senate.)<lb/>
Hon. ROGER AVERILL, President,	Hon. SAMUEL ROCKWELL,
 <lb/> "   EDWARD I.  SANDFORD,	         	  	"   SYLVESTER
SMITH,
  <lb/>"   CHARLES H. MALLORY,                      	"   JOHN
T. WAITE,
<pb n="6"/>
                  <figure><graphic url=""/>
                     <figDesc>6th page of Henry Champion
Deming's Eulogy of Abraham Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
                  <lb/>
Hon. BENJAMIN POMEROY,                       Hon. CHARLES
W. BALLARD, <lb/>  "    EDWIN H. BUGBEE,
"   ORLANDO J. HODGE, <lb/>  "    HENRY W. PECK,
"   ROBBINS BATTELL, <lb/>  "    WILLIAM E. CONE,
"   JASPER H. BOLTON,
                                           Hon. CHARLES A. ATKINS.</p>
               <p>(On the part of the
House.)  <lb/>Hon. E.K. FOSTER, Speaker,
Mr. HENRY B. HARRISON, <lb/>Mr. H.K.W. WELCH,
"   JOHN S. RICE, <lb/>  "    FRANKLIN CHAMBERLIN,
"   HARRIS B. MUNSON,
 <lb/> "    OLIVER S. WILLIAMS,                             	"
FREDERICK J. KINGSBURY,  <lb/>  "    RIAL CHANEY,
"   SAMUEL MOWRY, <lb/>  "    CHARLES W. SCOTT,
"   DAVID P. NICHOLS,
 <lb/> "    PHINEAS T. BARNUM,                               	"
MYRON L. MASON,
 <lb/> "    SAMUEL G. BEARDSLEY,                           	"
EDWARD L. CUNDALL,
 <lb/> "    HENRY HAMMOND,                                   	"
DAVID GALLUP,
 <lb/> "    CHARLES OSGOOD,                                     	"
DAVID E. BOSTWICK, <lb/>  "    ABIJAH CATLIN,
"   ANDREW B. MYGATT,
 <lb/> "    HENRY S. BARBOUR,                                  	"
WILLIAM G. COE,
 <lb/> "    LUTHER BOARDMAN,                                	"
WILLIAM R. CLARK,
 <lb/> "    GEORGE KELLOGG,                                     	"
JULIUS CONVERSE.</p>
               <p>SECRETARIES,
       <lb/>(On the part
of the Senate.) <lb/>Hon. FREDERICK W. RUSSELL,
Hon. FRANCIS A. SANFORD.</p>
               <p>(On the part of
the House.)  <lb/>Mr. SAMUEL J. DAY,
Mr. EDWARD S. SCRANTON,
 <lb/> "   ALONZO F. WOOD,
"   ALBERT L. AVERY,
 <lb/> "   F. ST. JOHN LOCKWOOD,                               	"
APOLLOS COMSTOCK,
 <lb/> "   OSCAR TOURTELOTTE,                                 	"
LUCIAN CARPENTER,
 <lb/> "   GEORGE M. WOODRUFF,                                 	"
LEWIS CATLIN, <lb/>  "   JOHN M. DOUGLAS,
"   GEORGE D. HASTINGS.</p>
               <pb n="7"/>
               <p>
                  <figure><graphic url=""/>
                     <figDesc>7th page of
Henry Champion Deming's Eulogy of Abraham
Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <p>On taking the chair, Governor Buckingham was loudly applauded. He
said:</p>
               <p>LADIES AND GENTLEMEN:--</p>
               <p>It is difficult for us to review the past and contemplate the rapid
and marvelous changes which have crowded the events of generations
into a few passing months, without inquiring whether it all has not
been a dream; and yet our minds and hands have been so much occupied,
and our hearts so deeply affected by the scenes through which we have
passed, that our judgment and consciousness decide the question, and
assure us that we have not been moved by visions and dreams, but by
realities.</p>
               <p>The rebellion has been a reality. The power of the government has
not been imaginary. The organization of armies, their conflict upon a
thousand battle-fields, the overthrow of our national enemies, the
suppression of the rebellion, and the emancipation of the enslaved,
are all real events, which have surprised ourselves and astonished the
civilized world. But events alone do not make history. It is read in
the character and lives of those who have been active participators in
the scenes which have transpired. There can be no correct history of
the Israelites, of their oppression and deliverence, of their passage
through the sea and through the wilderness, without the lives of
<pb n="8"/>
                  <figure><graphic url=""/>
                     <figDesc>8th page of Henry Champion
Deming's Eulogy of Abraham Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
Moses and Joshua. There can be no true history of the twenty-five
years of European war, commencing with the French revolution and
ending with the battle of Waterloo, without the life of Napoleon. Nor
can there be a correct history of this nation, as it has passed
through this great struggle for existence, without the life of Abraham
Lincoln, and without connecting his name with that immortal
proclamation which gave freedom and manhood to four millions of
bondmen.</p>
               <p>The General Assembly has properly invited a gentleman of
distinguished ability, who was intimately acquainted with Mr. Lincoln,
to present to us this evening, and to weave into our nation's history,
the life and character of our late President, so that all may see
those qualities of heart and mind by which he endeared himself to the
people, and which stamped his official acts with a purity and
patriotism which command universal respect and admiration. No one can
draw his character in lines of more distinctness and accuracy, or
present it in more attractive and life-like colors, or show more
clearly the precise influence which he exerted over public affairs
during this period of danger, than the orator of the evening, whom I
now introduce--the Hon. Henry C. Deming.</p>
               <pb n="9"/>
               <p>
                  <figure><graphic url=""/>
                     <figDesc>9th page of
Henry Champion Deming's Eulogy of Abraham
Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <p>Mr. Deming was received with long continued applause. He said:</p>
               <p>MAY IT PLEASE YOUR EXCELLENCY, AND GENTLEMEN OF THE GENERAL
ASSEMBLY:--</p>
               <p>FROM the seat of our Republican Empire which, during the last four
years and for all coming time, he has preserved from the spoiler by
his wisdom and address; through avenues of weeping myriads who have
thronged the thoroughfare, all the way from the Potomac to the
prairie, to look on his bier, bear his pall, and to scatter on his
casket the fragrant offerings of affection; through great
commonwealths which, with all the pomp and circumstance of mournful
state, have received him on their threshold and attended him, with
uncovered heads, and with every oblation of sorrow from border to
border; through magnificent cities draped from cornice to basement in
all the emblems and wailing with every motto and articulation of woe;
to the sighing of the air, over the groaning earth; to the booming of
minute gun, to muffled drum and the plaintive burst of martial music;
to dirge, anthem and lamentation, ABRAHAM LINCOLN has reached that
silent home of all the living, which "buries every error, covers every
defect, extinguishes every resentment."</p>
               <pb n="10"/>
               <p>
                  <figure><graphic url=""/>
                     <figDesc>10th page of
Henry Champion Deming's Eulogy of Abraham
Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <lg type="stanza">
                  <l>After life's fitful fever he sleeps well,</l>
                  <l>Treason has done his worst, nor steel nor poison,</l>
                  <l>Malice domestic, foreign levy, nothing</l>
                  <l>Can touch him further!</l>
               </lg>
               <p>With ampler honors, and with more of the symbols and ceremonial of
universal love and veneration, than this continent ever paid before to
any of her sons, the funeral pageant had scarcely reached the portals
of the tomb, before the posthumous tributes of another Hemisphere are
borne across the Ocean. The suffering of her eldest born fairly melts
into sympathy the estranged heart of our haughty Island Mother, and
England mourns, as when Nelson expired in the arms of victory, or as
when the gates of her Great Abbey, closed upon the ashes of the
greatest of her warriors. The generous Queen draws upon her own
inconsolable domestic grief, for consolation to a wife and mother,
like herself bereaved, and pens with her own royal hand a letter of
condolence. The brazen lips of the impassive Emperor break their grim
silence to utter sententious panegyric. From the mountains of
Switzerland, which have for centuries broken the waves of oppression,
we have free, generous, intelligent homage to a LIBERATOR, whom
William Tell would have been proud to recognize as a brother. Ancient
cities, which might have wept, when at the base of Pompey's statue
<pb n="11"/>
                  <figure><graphic url=""/>
                     <figDesc>11th page of Henry
Champion Deming's Eulogy of Abraham Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
great Caesar fell, have, by their representatives, hung in all the
trappings of grief the august Hall, wherein they are now legislating
for regenerated Italy. The free towns and corporate guilds of
Netherlands and Germany, which wrung their charters from Charles the
Bold, and rocked European freedom in its cradle, vie with each other
in canonizing a child of the people, who leads the Great Republic from
darkness and bondage, to light and liberty. The Prussian Chamber of
Deputies, receive with enthusiastic applause, the eloquent eulogium of
a personal acquaintance of the PRESIDENT, and affirm a most earnest
resolution of respect by unanimously rising from their seats, in token
of superlative courtesy, and the Lower House of the Austrian
Reichsrath which conducts its stately proceedings, according to forms
and usages handed down from the Feudal Ages, is as wild and
demonstrative, upon the receipt of the sad intelligence as an
Indignation Meeting of Loyal Leagues in Union Square. Indeed, for
ABRAHAM LINCOLN one cry of universal regret is raised all over the
civilized earth.</p>
               <p>It is difficult to descend from the fervor of these first
impassioned outbursts of a world wide grief, to cool analysis and
historic delineation. And yet that is the task before me. I should
violate the proprieties of this occasion, if I indulged in mere
rhapsodies,
<pb n="12"/>
                  <figure><graphic url=""/>
                     <figDesc>12th page of Henry
Champion Deming's Eulogy of Abraham Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
however grand and well deserved, for I am to present an estimate of
character to a Legislative body, and I can not forget that it
habitually dwells in the mild atmosphere congenial to deliberation,
that it solicits unvarnished statement instead of rhetorical flourish,
and records its own judgment in the composed style of fact and
argument.</p>
               <p>In these days of photographs, it is almost superfluous to paint in
speech the portrait of a distinguished man, but as the resources of
the language have been exhausted in depreciation of MR. LINCOLN'S
person, I am unwilling that he shall pass into history, in any shape,
which may repel the enthusiasm due by posterity, to exalted merit and
heroic achievement. Let us at all events place on record the image
which he really wore that he may not descend the ages according to
malicious caricature. MR. LINCOLN'S person was not one to move their
applause, to whom an Apollo or an Antinous are the only ideals of
physical humanity, or whose undeviating types of manliness are found
on the canvas of a Reynolds or a Stuart, but it was not uninteresting
for those to contemplate who regard the human form and face, as a
veritable record of life's experiences, and to some extent, an index
of character. It was not unsuited to one who was born from a rude
stock, in a wild forest, and was nurtured and moulded by
<pb n="13"/>
                  <figure><graphic url=""/>
                     <figDesc>13th page of Henry
Champion Deming's Eulogy of Abraham Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
constant warfare, with wilderness life, and iron fortune, and frontier
hardships. Conceive a tall and gaunt figure, more than six feet in
height, not only unencumbered with superfluous flesh, but reduced to
the minimum working standard of cord, and sinew, and muscle, strong
and indurated by exposure and toil, with legs and arms long and
attenuated, but not disproportionately so to the long and attenuated
trunk; in posture and carriage not ungraceful, but with the grace of
unstudied and careless ease, rather than of cultivated airs and
high-bred pretensions. His dress is uniformly of black throughout, and
would attract but little attention in a well dressed circle, if it
hung less loosely upon him and the ample white shirt collar was not
turned over his cravat in the western style. The face that surmounts
this figure is half Roman and half Indian, bronzed by climate,
furrowed by life struggles, seamed with humor, the head is massive and
covered with dark, thick and unmanageable hair, the brow is wide and
well developed, the nose large and fleshy, the lips full, cheeks thin,
and drawn down in strong corded lines, which, but for the wiry
whiskers, would disclose the machinery which moves the broad jaw. The
eyes are dark gray, sunk in deep sockets, but bright, soft and
beautiful in expression, and sometimes lost and half abstracted, as if
their glance
<pb n="14"/>
                  <figure><graphic url=""/>
                     <figDesc>14th page of Henry
Champion Deming's Eulogy of Abraham Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
was reversed and turned inward, or as if the soul which lighted them
was far away. The teeth are white and regular and it is only when a
smile, radiant, captivating and winning as was ever given to mortal,
transfigures the plain countenance, that you begin to realize that it
is not impossible for artists to admire and woman to love it.</p>
               <p>As the world has rung with ridicule of the ungainliness of his
manners, I may be permitted to say, that without any pretensions to
superfine polish, they were frank, cordial, and dignified, without
rudeness, without offence, and without any violation of the
proprieties and etiquettes of his high position. As fastidious and
keen a master of such nice matters as Mr. Everett has said, "I
recognize in the PRESIDENT, a full measure of the qualities which
entitle him to the personal respect of the people. On the only social
occasion on which I ever had the honor to be in his company, viz: the
Commemoration at Gettysburg, he sat at the table at the house of my
friend David Willis, Esq., by the side of several distinguished
persons, ladies and gentlemen, foreigners and Americans, among them
the French Minister at Washington, since appointed French Ambassador
at Madrid, and the Admiral of the French Fleet, and that in
gentlemanly appearance, manners and conversation he was the peer of
any man at the table."</p>
               <pb n="15"/>
               <p>
                  <figure><graphic url=""/>
                     <figDesc>15th page of
Henry Champion Deming's Eulogy of Abraham
Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <p>To borrow one of his own conversational phrases he did'nt brag on
deportment. He was not a Turveydrop or Sir Harcourt Courtly or General
Banks. It would have puzzled him to stand in tableau for the Earl of
Chatham, or the Pompeian Ajax. He was not proud of his leg, like
President Dwight, nor was he a George the Fourth at a bow. He stood,
and moved, and bowed, without affectation, and without obtrusive
awkwardness, pretty much as nature prompted, and as if he regarded <hi rend="italic">carriage</hi> as about as bad a criterion as <hi rend="italic">color</hi> of genuine nobility of soul. He was not
overcareful of his dignity, feeling assured that his dignity could
take care of itself, and consenting to rend the web of official
formalities, and to waive all ceremony and precedence which might bar
his passage to a good deed by the most expeditious route. He has been
convicted in contempt of "the divinity which doth hedge a king," of
conferring with his counsellors in a great emergency, and of
performing an act of kindness and mercy, enveloped in no robe of state
but a cotton nightgown of scanty pattern, and on one memorable
occasion he even presumed to solve an enigma, raised in a congress of
ambassadors, by the little story of "root hog or die." He was what
Dr. Johnson calls a thoroughly "clubbable" man, eminently social and
familiar; in private interviews and sometimes in public, overflowing
with
<pb n="16"/>
                  <figure><graphic url=""/>
                     <figDesc>16th page of Henry
Champion Deming's Eulogy of Abraham Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
illustrations of every theme, always apt and racy, and frequently
humorous, with a habit like the Doctor himself, of upsetting a
pedantry or a sophism by an epigram or an anecdote, and with a story
telling method of reasoning like our own Doctor Franklin. While
unrivaled as a raconteur in the pith and variety of his store, he was
not half so broad in his narratives as many an assuming Chesterfield
on both sides of the water. It is the weak invention of false friends
and open enemies, to lay at his door all the prurient jokes which
their foul imaginations conceived and to falsely asseverate that he
was in the habit of indulging in unseemly jest and repartee on grave
and solemn occasions. I can adopt and endorse the precise language of
Mr. F. B. Carpenter, who as an artist had free access to MR. LINCOLN'S
presence, and was for several months an inmate of the White House,
when he says, "I feel that it is due to Mr. Lincoln's memory to state,
that during my residence in Washington, after witnessing his
intercourse with all classes of people, including Governors, Senators,
Members of Congress, Officers of the Army and familiar friends, I can
not recollect to have heard him relate a circumstance to any one of
them all that would have been out of place if uttered in a lady's
drawing room. I am aware that a different impression may prevail,
founded it maybe in some instances on facts, but
<pb n="17"/>
                  <figure><graphic url=""/>
                     <figDesc>17th page of Henry
Champion Deming's Eulogy of Abraham Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
where there is one fact of the kind, I am persuaded that there are
forty falsehoods at least."</p>
               <p>Of his intellectual capacity, Mr. Lincoln gave the most signal
proof, in that memorable contest with Judge Douglas, and his speeches
are in no sense inferior to his rivals--the Charles James Fox of our
forum, by universal consent the most athletic and expert offhand
debater who ever graced the United States Senate. The PRESIDENT'S mind
was so original and self dependent, so unwilling to borrow knowledge
and opinion, that he fairly scorned all adventitious support and
external auxiliaries. No President ever leaned so lightly upon his
Cabinet. No man reproduces less in official documents, the argument
and thought which he imbibes at consultations, and it is a marvelous
fact that no sentence is to be found in any of his state papers, which
suggests the suspicion of any other impress but that of his own mint,
or where he attempts to strengthen or vindicate a position, by quoting
from any book or citing any authority. And his greatness, his
greatness! is the most original and <hi rend="italic">bizarre</hi> in
the world's history, shaped after no model, suggesting as a compact
whole no pattern, no parallel--not even a resemblance, contravening
every antique and modern standard of Hero-worship,--a greatness which
admits of no exact analysis and can only be loosely described as com
<pb n="18"/>
                  <figure><graphic url=""/>
                     <figDesc>18th page of Henry
Champion Deming's Eulogy of Abraham Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
posed of great simplicity, great naturalness, great bonhomie, great
shrewdness, great strength, great devotion, great equanimity, and
great success, on the greatest theatre ever offered to such qualities
for exhibition. He appears like an erratic streaming comet amid the
fixed orbs of greatness, a fiery meteor plunging and howling through
their subdued and chastened atmosphere. Ennobled by no patent but that
of nature, with no diploma but his record; crowned, as it were, with
the wild flowers of the forest and with all its flavor and freshness
upon him, he walks into the surprised Pantheon of the world's great
men, a huge, grotesque Backwoodsman, but with credentials to admission
which can not be challenged or disallowed; like the hirsute and half
naked Brennus striding into the grave and reverend decorums of a Roman
Senate; like Hans Luther's plebeian and beetle-browed son confronting
the stoled, mitered and ermined Diet of Charles the Fifth; like a
red-nosed, cropped and mail-clad Cromwell shuffling through the silken
splendors, the Vandyke dresses, the perfumed love-locks, and the
fastidious etiquette of outraged Whitehall; like St. Artegans' iron
soldier marching, with his invincible flail, into the startled and
shrinking ranks of vulnerable and pain suffering warriors. It may be
said of him, as has been said of another indigenous American type of
manliness, that
<pb n="19"/>
                  <figure><graphic url=""/>
                     <figDesc>19th page of Henry
Champion Deming's Eulogy of Abraham Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
he taught the world "a new idea of greatness." It is somewhat
surprising that with all his superabundance of wit and humor, he was
but frugally endowed with imagination and fancy, without wing for the
air, with not even enough like the ostrich to aid him along the
earth. He never uses a figure of speech to decorate or enliven his
style, and but seldom for the purpose of illustrating a thought or
exposing a fallacy. He contemned all the elegancies of diction, using
only plain homespun English, aiming at direct and compact statement in
the fewest words, and those sometimes chosen with more respect to
convenience than precision.</p>
               <p>His education was self-acquired and unpretending, and, in the
department of History, wherein the Past by experience and example
instructs and exhorts the Present, and therefore so essential to
genuine statesmanship, it was somewhat narrow and defective. It must
be constantly borne in mind, that a superlative, kindness and a
disposition to oblige every body, were fairly autocratic in him,
sometimes holding in complete subjection all the other powers and
forces of his nature, and frequently controlling, against their
protest, his opinions and actions. "I have never willingly planted a
thorn in any man's bosom," is the accurate description which he gives
of himself. The domination of this amiable disposition must be con
<pb n="20"/>
                  <figure><graphic url=""/>
                     <figDesc>20th page of Henry
Champion Deming's Eulogy of Abraham Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
stantly remembered, and carried along with you into the development
and estimate of his public career, which I am attempting to
present.</p>
               <p>The chief mental equipments which he brought to the mighty task
before him, were that downright uncompromising common sense which
seems to divine its way through the most intricate problems, a keen
insight into human nature, an intimate acquaintance with the spasmodic
movements of the American mind, a natural aptitude, improved by
professional discipline, in chaining premise to conclusion, and in
detecting the occult relations of political cause to political effect,
great caution in forming opinions, honesty and sincerity of purpose,
inflexible persistence in what he regarded as public duty, and a
coscientious sense of his responsibility to the country and to
mankind. He had a temper habitually cheerful, but not, as some have
falsely assumed, inflexibly so, for in my brief acquaintance with it,
I have seen it wear every shade from exultation to despair. Laughter
in abundance was in him but tears were also there. To these
characteristics should always be added, an intuitive comprehension of
the precise line which divides Right from Wrong, and implicit reliance
upon the goodness and wisdom of Almighty God.</p>
               <p>Let us now see how this peculiar organization
<pb n="21"/>
                  <figure><graphic url=""/>
                     <figDesc>21st page of Henry
Champion Deming's Eulogy of Abraham Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
addressed itself to the tremendous task which he has just triumphantly
achieved. And what a creative task it was? Armies, navies, cash,
credit, opinion, all to be created, heroism to be evolved from
money-making thrift, pluck from pusilanimity, steadfast principle from
vacillating expediency, constancy and endurance from over-sanguine and
vain-glorious dreams--and millions of self-willed and arrogant despots
to be humbled forever. He began by almost re-creating himself.</p>
               <p>In one of the brief speeches which ABRAHAM LINCOLN made, when as
President elect, and in the full flush of life, he traveled the same
road upon which he has recently returned, in the habiliments of the
grave, he says to his countrymen: "In my view of the present aspect of
affairs, there need be no bloodshed or war. There is no necessity for
it. I am not in favor of such a course, and I may say in advance that
there will be no bloodshed unless it be forced upon the government,
and then it will be compelled to act in self-defence." This brief
sentence furnishes us with the first insight into his mind, when
contemplating the task before him, and it unlocks all the mystery and
explains the purely defensive course of his administration, during the
first two months of its existence.</p>
               <p>At the same time Jefferson Davis, on his progress
<pb n="22"/>
                  <figure><graphic url=""/>
                     <figDesc>22nd page of Henry
Champion Deming's Eulogy of Abraham Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
to Montgomery, to install a hostile government, thus proclaims his
setiments:--"The time for compromise has passed, and we are now
determined to maintain our position, and make all who oppose us smell
southern gunpowder and feel southern steel." And this short utterance
epitomizes the spirit and temper of the Chief Conspirator, when he was
commencing the despotic reign which has just been so ignominiously
closed by Col. Pritchard at Irwinsville. By the light of events we now
learn, what was not surmised by the most sagacious at the time, that
the Rebellion was all armed, equipped, in line of battle and thirsting
for the sanguinary fray, before the future Conqueror of the Rebellion
had convinced himself that any blood would be shed, or had
systematised any plan of counteracting the revolutionary agencies,
which were threatening his own and the nation's life. So far, however,
from regarding the hesitancy of the PRESIDENT at the outset, to avow
any radical or even any methodized policy, of dealing with the
rebellion, as proof of imbecility, I accept it as conclusive evidence
of genuine greatness and strength. He was ignorant of its implacable
determination like every other man guileless of complicity with it,
and a premature radical policy would have subjected him instantly, to
the reproach from a vast majority of his countrymen, of stimulating an
undeveloped
<pb n="23"/>
                  <figure><graphic url=""/>
                     <figDesc>23rd page of Henry
Champion Deming's Eulogy of Abraham Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
and embryo crime, which conciliation and caution might strangle; and
<hi rend="italic">any</hi> policy, while the insurrection was
unorganized, would have clearly convicted him of the hollowness and
insincerity of the mere pretender. It would have implied superhuman
prevision, sublime conceit, or arrant quackery. He was about assuming
the helm of Government, when the tempest was abroad in its fury, when
every headland was buried in storm and darkness, when every Pharos as
well as the eternal lights of Heaven were extinguished, when the
needle was no longer true to the pole, when all prognostics failed,
when all charts and tables of previous navigators were at fault, and
the laboring ship must be steered over the wide and pathless ocean by
conjecture alone. This was no time for laying out her bearings and
course for a four years' voyage, and our wise and truthful PILOT,
avowing manfully his infirmity, in such an unparalleled tornado, and
reverently invoking divine guidance, prudently abstained, during that
memorable progress, from committing himself to any rigid and
inflexible theory, which would prevent him afterwards, from adapting
his measures to the growth and development of the monstrous anomaly,
and of justifying his policy by its frighful vicissitudes and
crime.</p>
               <p>Nor is the language of his Inaugural much more decisive. His temper
and spirit towards it is most
<pb n="24"/>
                  <figure><graphic url=""/>
                     <figDesc>24th page of Henry
Champion Deming's Eulogy of Abraham Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
forbearing and admirable. He is not yet authorized to treat it as a
maniac, and therefore addresses it as a perverse but accountable
creature. So far as the Rebellion had evinced its character and
intentions, just so far his plan of dealing with it was therein
frankly and unmistakably announced. It undertook to vindicate its
revolutionary attitude, by pretending to fear an unauthorized
destruction of Slavery in the States, and the new PRESIDENT, as in
duty bound, in his first official address disclaimed for himself and
his supporters any such purpose, both by a full and pointed denial,
and by ample citation of the antecedent and recorded declarations of
the Republican party and its Chief. In prosecution of its purposes the
rebellion had already seized Forts, Navy Yards, Custom Houses,
Arsenals, and had prohibited the collection of duties, and he calmly
but decisively declares, that "the power confided to him will be used,
to hold occupy and possess the property and places belonging to the
Government, and to collect the duties and imports." And that this
might not seem too threatening a declaration, he adds the important
qualification, that "beyond what may be necessary for these objects,
there will be no invasion, no using of force against or among the
people anywhere." In deference to the irritation which prevailed in
the insurrectionary
<pb n="25"/>
                  <figure><graphic url=""/>
                     <figDesc>25th page of Henry
Champion Deming's Eulogy of Abraham Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
States, he expressly foregoes the right of appointing obnoxious
strangers to Federal offices within their limits, and promises that
the mails shall be furnished to all parts of the Union, until they are
violently repelled.</p>
               <p>In this brief statement, I have condensed all the foreshadowings of
a policy, which this wise and unfaltering PRESIDENT vouchsafed to the
world, when consciously entering upon the most perilous era of our
history, and assuming the most momentous responsibilities. While we
have in it but one sentence, which even the over-sensitive chivalry
could construe into a menace, we are prodigally furnished with
conciliatory promises, and with such winning arguments and admonitions
only, as a tender father might employ with a wayward offspring. Up to
the time when he took the oath of office upon the eastern portico of
the Capitol, he had pushed forbearance beyond the point where it
ceases to be a virtue, and it is perfectly apparent that it had not
yet dawned upon him, that his hand was soon to wield a scourge,
terrible enough to chastise two God-defying centuries of crime, or
that his chief mission to this earth was to conduct a nation through
the jaws of death and the gates of hell, to regenerated and immortal
life.</p>
               <p>Let me now attempt to ascertain, at what precise
<pb n="26"/>
                  <figure><graphic url=""/>
                     <figDesc>26th page of Henry
Champion Deming's Eulogy of Abraham Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
period he abandoned this preconceived and cherished idea of
compromising the embroilment by a mere warlike demonstration, and let
me also attempt to analyze the difficulties, which, a resolution in
favor of uncompromising and aggressive hostilities, encounters from
his conservative habits, from his peculiar emotional and intellectual
organization, and reproduce, as far as I am able, the arguments, which
persuaded his placable and scrupulous mind to the unhesitating and
implacable purpose of exercising all the tremendous powers conferred
upon him by the Rights of War and of grasping every weapon in its
terrible arsenal.</p>
               <p>The Time, when this decided change in his purpose first appears,
was more than a month after our flag was struck from Sumpter's
crumbling battlements, more than a month after that bugle blast which
summoned seventy-five thousand men to arms, a month at least after the
bloody baptism of Massachusetts troops in the streets of Baltimore. We
have his own authentic manifestoes to demonstrate, that as late as the
first of May, 1861, he had not abandoned temporizing expedients, and
we learn by evidence equally conclusive, that before the month had
closed, he had finally resolved to turn upon the inveterate Rebellion
the unbridled wrath of War. The hour, when doubt and hesitancy first
yielded to
<pb n="27"/>
                  <figure><graphic url=""/>
                     <figDesc>27th page of Henry
Champion Deming's Eulogy of Abraham Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
the stern command of remorseless duty, must have been the soberest,
saddest, solemnest of his faithful life, not from doubt of the result,
though that was sufficiently perplexing; not from fear of the
consequences, though these were appalling enough; not from the weight
of responsibility, though that might have staggered the most
unyielding determination, but it was sad and solemn, because ABRAHAM
LINCOLN, above and beyond all other men, loved Peace and hated War;
because seiges, battles, strife, swords, bayonets, rifles, cannon, all
the paraphernalia and instruments of brute force, were abhorrent to
his enlightened and benevolent nature. Shall we raise the latch, and
enter in to the secret chamber of that capacious and genial soul, when
this fell resolve was first reached, when the frightful vision of War,
in all its terrors clad, supplants there the hope of conciliation and
the dream of peace? I speak, what I heard from his own lips when I
say, that it was reached after sleepless nights, after a severe
conflict. with himself, and with extreme reluctance. By a strange and
cruel freak of fate, the duty of waging the bloodiest war in history
was imposed upon the most peace loving and amiable ruler in all time,
upon a man whose maxim was (in the language of one of his favorite
texts,) "let the potsherd strive with the potsherds of the Earth"-and
into whose mind, had
<pb n="28"/>
                  <figure><graphic url=""/>
                     <figDesc>28th page of Henry
Champion Deming's Eulogy of Abraham Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
been thoroughly ingrained that traditional notion of our politics,
that the first drop of blood, shed in a sectional strife, was the
death-knell of the American Union.</p>
               <p>Let us enter in, where that now disembodied spirit was, in the
recesses of its clay tenement, in stormy debate with itself. What
throes, what agony do we witness! What heart rending sobs, what heaven
piercing prayers that the cup may pass from his lips! Here was that
conservative mind, trained to habits of professional caution, with the
strongest bias towards legality and moderation, which had uniformly
steered itself by the certain lights of jurisprudence, which had
invoked no remedies but the peaceful ones of the Courts, the
Constitution and the Law, which had never combated Error but with
reason and persuasion alone, and had abjured the ordeal of battle and
the arbitrament of force, as obsolete and heathenish enormities. Here
are all these mature, earnest opinions and prepossessions, all
dominant from fifty years of undisputed sway, wrestling impotently
with the War ideas and the overmastering War Revelation of
yesterday. What an unwelcome intruder the conviction is to the serene
virtues, which had hitherto exclusively occupied this holy
sanctuary. Domesticated here are Justice and Mercy, ("and earthly
power is likest God's when Mercy seasons Justice.") 
<pb n="29"/>
                  <figure><graphic url=""/>
                     <figDesc>29th page of Henry
Champion Deming's Eulogy of Abraham Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
Justice and Mercy, which hold the balances quite evenly, but the
hair's weight which oscillates them, uniformly found in Mercy's scale,
and how repulsive it is to these righteous and discriminating
attributes, to let loose upon the people a wild and furious Avenger
that devours alike innocence and guilt? Here too dwell sensibilities
and affections so acute, that they fling wide open the doors of the
soul to every one who approaches in Misfortune's name, grant the
prayer of Sorrow before it is half uttered, and which the small
inarticulate wail of infancy instantly melts into tears of most
compassionate tenderness; how are these sensitive fibers wrung and
tortured when it suddenly flashes upon them, that the loving hand
which has only learned to soothe and relieve the miserable, is
commissioned by inexorable fate, to break the fourth seal of the
Apocalypse, and, "behold a pale horse! and his name who sat on him was
Death and Hell followed him; and power was given unto them over the
fourth part of the earth, to kill with the sword and with hunger and
with Death and with the beasts of the earth." Movelessly, movelessly
rooted also in this great heart, is a superfine sense of humor,
craving hilarity and harmless mirth, and joy-inspiring wit and
anecdote, as the only effectual relief to an over-anxious spirit and
an over-tasked brain, and how reluctantly does
<pb n="30"/>
                  <figure><graphic url=""/>
                     <figDesc>30th page of Henry
Champion Deming's Eulogy of Abraham Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
this part of his nature admit to close companionship, the gloomy
forebodings, the bitter memories, the dreadful uncertainties, the
everlasting shrieks, dirges, vengeful tragedies, and heart-rending
atrocities of War.</p>
               <p>In addition to the protest of these conservative habits, and
amiable emotions, upon his adoption of any radical and thorough-going
policy of grappling with the Rebellion, he was also, like many others,
held back for a season, by the legal scruples which his reflecting
faculties were constantly suggesting. "Beset," as it has been well
said, "by fanatics of principle, on one side, who would give no heed
to the limitations of his written authority, and by fanatics of party,
on the other, who were not only deaf to the obligations of justice,
but would hear of no policy large enough for a revolutionary
emergency, MR. LINCOLN never forgot, for an instant, that he was a
constitutional ruler." The Constitution of the United States which it
takes but twenty minutes to read, can be studied for twice twenty
years, without exhausting its meaning, or comprehending its vast
treasury of express and implied power. Like most of our statesmen the
attention of the PRESIDENT, had been exclusively turned to the PEACE
side of the instrument, to the provisions which address themselves to
conditions of unbroken amity, domestic tranquility,
<pb n="31"/>
                  <figure><graphic url=""/>
                     <figDesc>31st page of Henry
Champion Deming's Eulogy of Abraham Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
to the preservation of amicable relations between the States, and to
the development, under their auspices, of commerce, industry,
manufactures and trade. The powers it grants over internal
improvements, over foreign and inter-State commerce, currency, duties
and imposts, territories, naturalization, taxation, bankruptcy, as
well as the extent of constitutional limitations upon the General
Government, and of constitutional prohibitions upon the States, have
not only been subjects of constant individual study, but have been
illustrated and defined, by a long, luminous and comprehensive series
of judicial determinations, which have the same authority and validity
as if they were incorporated into the Constitution itself. We can all
see, at a glance, how greatly these investigations and decisions have
contributed to consolidate the Union and to enlarge and strengthen the
influence of the National government. But Courts and individuals have
alike ignored the WAR side of the Constitution, or drawn but feebly
upon that slumbering element in our system, which holds each revolving
planet in complete subjection to the sun.</p>
               <p>What are its powers over States which abjure allegiance, and
conspire together for its destruction and overthrow, and raise armies,
and wage War against it, was, fortunately, a question which no
judicial tribunal had been called upon to adjudi-
<pb n="32"/>
                  <figure><graphic url=""/>
                     <figDesc>32nd page of Henry
Champion Deming's Eulogy of Abraham Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
cate, which no curious theorizer had even mooted, and which
MR. LINCOLN himself for the first time investigated in the third month
of his administration--that parturiant and groaning May. He then
concentrated his attention upon the War powers of our organic law, and
found in this <hi rend="italic">terra incognita</hi>, unexpected
resources which never yet had contributed to the weight, and vigor,
and terror of the Federal arm. The elements of strength and power
which were hid away, in the weighty clauses, which give to the
PRESIDENT and Congress the issues of Peace and War, were dragged to
light and employed for the salvation of the Republic.</p>
               <p>By the middle of May the doubt and haze which had settled upon the
legal relation of the Insurgent States to the Government, began to
disappear. On the sixth of that month, the Confederate Congress at
Montgomery, declared war against the United States, and MR. LINCOLN'S
position, at this time, towards the gigantic peril which threatened
our national existence, was described with legal exactness and
accuracy, when it was said to him by an eminent civilian--"If the
whole unvarnished truth is told you, sir, you are confronted by a <hi rend="italic">de facto</hi> Rebellion, and a <hi rend="italic"> de
facto</hi> War, and you are justified in treating it as the one, as
the other, and as both." With equal truth it was shortly afterwards
said, in the United States Senate, "it is a Rebellion swollen
<pb n="33"/>
                  <figure><graphic url=""/>
                     <figDesc>33rd page of Henry
Champion Deming's Eulogy of Abraham Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
to the proportions of a War, and it is a War deriving its life from
Rebellion. It is no less of a Rebellion because of its full blown
grandeur, nor is it less a War because of the traitorous source from
whence it draws its life." What are my constitutional resources
against this new strange, and double headed monster? was the first
question which MR. LINCOLN put to himself, and this question, grave,
severe, and momentous as was ever submitted to human arbitrament, he
was called upon, without precedent, without authority, and from his
habits of mind without assistance, forthwith to determine by his
peculiar process of divination.</p>
               <p>The Constitution, does it not? establishes in law and in fact, an
independent government. By that act alone, all the belligerent rights,
which from time immemorial, by international law belong to independent
governments, were instantly conveyed to the new born nation. Yes, yes,
they were all ours by the title which secured us a place in the family
of nations. In abeyance during peace, they instantly vest with the
first act of War, and with full grown vehemence and power surrender
themselves to execute our behests, against all of our public enemies
whether they rally under the bastard banner of an Insurgent State, or
the legitimate flag of a recognized nation.</p>
               <pb n="34"/>
               <p>
                  <figure><graphic url=""/>
                     <figDesc>34th page of
Henry Champion Deming's Eulogy of Abraham
Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <p>But not only did MR. LINCOLN find full belligerent rights,
according to the laws and usages of nations, and against all armed
foes implied in the independent government which the Constitution
creates and endows with the powers of self-defence, but he found,
also, that they all directly and necessarily flow from the express
provisions of the instrument. What is War? oh doubting Didymus!
According to the books, it is "contention by force for the purpose of
paralyzing an enemy." Congress has power, has it not? "to declare
war," and what is this but lifting the gate and opening the sluiceway
which sets in motion all the legitimate machinery which is required to
paralyze an enemy? Congress has power, has it not? "to grant letters
of marque and reprisal"; and what is this but commissioning two of the
peculiar agencies of war, to follow the property of the enemy wherever
it flees, for the purpose of punishing and impoverishing him. Congress
has power "to make rules concerning captures on land and water," and
what is this but providing directly for the exercise of seizure,
forfeiture, contribution, confiscation, liberation. In the power
conferred upon Congress, to raise and support armies," "to provide and
maintain a navy," "to make rules for the government of the land and
naval forces," "to provide for the calling forth of the militia, to
execute the laws of the Union,
<pb n="35"/>
                  <figure><graphic url=""/>
                     <figDesc>35th page of Henry
Champion Deming's Eulogy of Abraham Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
suppress insurrection and repel invasions," and, in the clinching and
decisive clause which empowers it "to make all laws necessary and
proper" for carrying these enumerated powers into execution, he found
plenary authority for employing, in its extremest rigor, every right
of war against rebels in arms.</p>
               <p>Turning away then, from the pages of the Constitution which confer
<hi rend="italic">belligerent rights</hi>, he reperused the article
which deals with Rebellion <hi rend="italic">as a crime</hi>, and
provides for it a criminal punishment, to be enforced in the Courts,
by the peaceful processes of the <hi rend="italic">municipal</hi> law;
and he finds that levying war against the United States and adhering
to their enemies is <hi rend="italic">treason</hi>, and is liable to all
the pains, penalties and forfeitures which are visited upon that <hi rend="italic">crime</hi>.</p>
               <p>From this long review, MR. LINCOLN rose with the conviction, that
for the overthrow of the rebels he might draw upon two fountains, and
a double source of power, <hi rend="italic">the Constitution</hi> and
the <hi rend="italic">rights of war</hi>; that as criminals he might
pursue them by the slow and guarded processes of the first, but that
as <hi rend="italic">enemies</hi>, he could wither them with all the
dread agencies and summary vengeance of the last, and he rose, too,
with the full determination from which he never afterwards deflected
to draw upon both magazines, to fight from both batteries, and with
all their thunder.</p>
               <pb n="36"/>
               <p>
                  <figure><graphic url=""/>
                     <figDesc>36th page of
Henry Champion Deming's Eulogy of Abraham
Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <p>The powers thus claimed, are all indubitably conferred, and may be
all unquestionably used, unless in behalf of rebels in arms, you urge
the preposterous plea that they are not <hi rend="italic">enemies,</hi>
because they are <hi rend="italic">traitors</hi>, thereby constituting
broken faith, violated oaths, and avowed treason, titles to immunity
from the penalties of war, and thus disfranchise an independent nation
of every belligerent right against those foes, who have once owed it
allegiance, and to the guilt of treason have added that of unjust
war.</p>
               <p>If, in addition to the considerations I have urged in favor of
these positions, time would permit me to cite the judgments of the
Supreme Court, I could present precise points, raised in admiralty
appeals, and ruled by such judges as Marshall, Livingstone, Tilghman,
Taney, Grier and Nelson, which establish the principle, that the
United States engaged in suppressing an insurrection of its citizens,
may with entire consistency treat them as <hi rend="italic">criminals</hi>, as <hi rend="italic">enemies</hi>, and as
<hi rend="italic">both</hi>, and may, with equal consistency, also act
in the two-fold capacity of <hi rend="italic">sovereign</hi> and <hi rend="italic">belligerent</hi>, according to the several measures
resorted to for the accomplishment of its purpose. By inflicting,
through its agent the Judiciary, the penalty which the law affixes to
the capital crimes of treason and piracy, it treats them as <hi rend="italic">criminals</hi>, and acts in its capacity as a <hi rend="italic">sovereign</hi>, and its courts are but enforcing its <hi rend="italic">municipal</hi>
                  <pb n="37"/>
                  <figure><graphic url=""/>
                     <figDesc>37th page of Henry
Champion Deming's Eulogy of Abraham Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
regulations. By instituting a blockade of the ports of its rebellious
citizens, invading their territory, sequestrating their property, and
emancipating their slaves, the Government treats them as <hi rend="italic">enemies</hi>, and exercises its rights as a <hi rend="italic">belligerent</hi>, and its courts, in their adjudication
upon capture, seizures, and forfeitures, are organized as courts of
prize, under the <hi rend="italic">law of nations</hi>.<ref target="#deming.002.n01">*</ref></p>
               <p>I have dwelt longer, than may be deemed judicious by some, upon the
process by which ABRAHAM LINCOLN'S mind was gradually led, from vague
and undefined notions, to defined and accurate views of the relations
of the armed insurgent to the Federal Government, because it lies at
the very root of his Administration of the War, because it vindicates
his Constitutional fidelity, because, just as the future forest once
lay in the acorn's cup, just as the full grown Rebellion once lay, in
the pestilent heresy of Calhoun, just so clearly and conspicuously its
inevitable death lay, in the fundamental and germinant idea, that as
<hi rend="italic">criminals</hi> they were subject to all the penalties
of the Constitution, and as enemies to all the legal consequences of
War.</p>
               <p>In that classic drama, which first revealed to the world the
masterly genius of Talford, unhappy Ion</p>
               <note xml:id="deming.002.n01" n="*" place="foot" anchored="true">
                  <p>Upton's Maritime Warfare and Prize,
p. 212.</p>
               </note>
               <pb n="38"/>
               <p>
                  <figure><graphic url=""/>
                     <figDesc>38th page of
Henry Champion Deming's Eulogy of Abraham
Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <p>proceeds upon the task, to which he was called by the audible voice
of the gods, with a firm hand and unfaltering will, but with supreme
pity and tenderness towards the father he was doomed to slay. With as
compassionate a heart, with as complete exemption from all vengeful
passions, but with as unswerving and constant a determination, this
gentle PRESIDENT now dedicates his arm to the destruction of the
Rebellion. And from this time forward all vascillation, compunction,
and even debate, apparently disappear from his mind, as if he had
accepted and surrendered himself to a vengeful destiny, or as if he
regarded himself as the mere instrument of working out a great cause,
which he was constrained to recognize, but powerless to
control. Forthwith, rise like exhalations that impregnable cordon of
earthworks in which Washington has securely reposed, forthwith the
guns of Fort McHenry, and the broadside of a man of war admonish the
Plug Uglies of Baltimore, that the main thoroughfare to the Capital
must hereafter be inviolate, forthwith the Ohio contingent is ordered
to sweep every hostile banner from the mountain fastnesses of West
Virginia, forthwith Butler, from Fortress Monroe, hurls a forlorn hope
against the counterscarps of Big Bethel, forthwith the tented villages
disappear, like snow flakes, from the surrounding fields of the
Metropolis, and the rumbling
<pb n="39"/>
                  <figure><graphic url=""/>
                     <figDesc>39th page of Henry
Champion Deming's Eulogy of Abraham Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
of artillery waggons upon every bridge, and the long lines of
glittering bayonets which reflect the waters of the Potomac, proclaim
that the Rubicon is passed, and the sacred soil invaded, forthwith, in
his first message, he informs Congress, that "he has invoked the War
power," and calls for four hundred thousand men and four hundred
millions of dollars, that "the conflict may be short and decisive,"
and when it passes the Non-Intercourse Act, the Confiscation Act, the
Suspension of the Habeas Corpus, they are forthwith approved, for in
determining that the Government was endowed, in time of War, with
unabridged belligerent rights, he had settled a principle which
underlies all these controverted measures.</p>
               <p>In the seven months which follow, he evinces an administrative
vigor that would have satisfied Napoleon the Great, but it was all
alas! counteracted, by a military imbecility in his Generals that was
fairly sublime. It is the era of almost unrelieved disaster,
commencing with the ineffaceable disgrace of Bull Run and terminating
only with the capture of Fort Donelson, which first introduced to the
country an immortal name, and initiated a career which has steadily
marched on from victory to victory, and from Alp to Alp, up to the
crowning summit of military grandeur, where Ulysses S. Grant now
stands unchallenged and secure.</p>
               <pb n="40"/>
               <p>
                  <figure><graphic url=""/>
                     <figDesc>40th page of
Henry Champion Deming's Eulogy of Abraham
Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <p>How nobly the PRESIDENT bore himself, during this interval of
darkness that could be felt, when bold men trembled at every click of
the telegraph, let two tributes offered by unfriendly voices to his
Stoicism attest the first, is from no less a master of it than
Napoleon the Third, who epigramatically says: "MR. LINCOLN'S highest
claim upon my admiration, is a Roman equanimity, which has been tried
by both extremes of fortune and disturbed by neither;" the second, is
from a hostile Englishman who says, that "tried by years of failure,
without achieving one great success, he not only never yielded to
despondency or anger, but what is most marvellous, continually grew in
self-possession and magnanimity." I once myself ventured to ask the
PRESIDENT, if he had ever despaired of the country? and he told me,
that "when the Peninsular Campaign terminated suddenly at Harrison's
Landing, I was as nearly inconsolable as I could be and live." In the
same connection I inquired, if there had ever been a period in which
he thought that better management, upon the part of his Commanding
General, might have terminated the War? and he answered that there
were three that the first was at Malvern Hill where McClellan failed
to command an immediate advance upon Richmond, that the second was at
Chancellorville, where Hooker failed to reinforce
<pb n="41"/>
                  <figure><graphic url=""/>
                     <figDesc>41st page of Henry
Champion Deming's Eulogy of Abraham Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
Sedgwick, after hearing his cannon upon the extreme right, and that
the third was after Lee's retreat from Gettysburg, when Meade failed
to attack him in the bend of the Potomac. After this commentary I
waited for an outburst of denunciation, for a criticism at least upon
the delinquent officers, but I waited in vain; so far from a word of
censure escaping his lips, he soon added, that his first remark might
not appear uncharitable, "I do not know that I could have given
different orders had I been with them myself; I have not fully made up
my mind how I should behave, when minnie balls were whistling and
these great oblong shells shrieking in my ear. I might run away." The
interview, which I am recalling, was last summer, just after
Gen. Fremont had declined to run against him for the Presidency. The
magnificent Bible, which the negroes of Washington had just presented
him, lay upon the table, and while we were both examining it, I
recited the somewhat. remarkable passage from the Chronicles;
"Eastward were six Levites, northward four a day, southward four a day
and towards Assuppim two and two, at Parbar westward, four at the
causeway and two at Parbar." He immediately challenged me to find any
such passage as that in <hi rend="italic">his</hi> Bible. After I had
pointed it out to him, and he was satisfied of its genuineness, he
asked me if I
<pb n="42"/>
                  <figure><graphic url=""/>
                     <figDesc>42nd page of Henry
Champion Deming's Eulogy of Abraham Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
remembered the text which his friends had recently applied to Fremont,
and instantly turned to a verse in the first of Samuel, put on his
spectacles, and read in his slow, peculiar and waggish tone,-"And
every one that was in distress, and every one that was in debt, and
every one that was discontented gathered themselves unto him; and he
became a Captain over them: and there were with him about four hundred
men." I am here reminded of an impressive remark, which he made to me
upon another occasion and which I shall never forget. He said, he had
never united himself to any church, because he found difficulty in
giving his assent, without mental reservation, to the long complicated
statements of Christian doctrine, which characterize their Articles of
belief and Confessions of Faith. "When any church," he continued,
"will inscribe over its altar, as its sole qualification for
membership the Saviour's condensed statement, of the substance of both
law and Gospel, 'Thou shalt love the Lord thy God with all thy heart,
and with all thy soul, and with all thy mind, and thy neighbor as
thyself,' that church will I join with all my heart and all my soul."
The books which he chiefly read, in his leisure hours were, the Bible,
Shakspeare, the peasant poet of Scotland, with whom his sympathies
were very acute, and those peculiar off-shoots of American wit, of
which Orpheus
<pb n="43"/>
                  <figure><graphic url=""/>
                     <figDesc>43rd page of Henry
Champion Deming's Eulogy of Abraham Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
C. Kerr, Artemas Ward, and Doesticks are types. I frequently saw all
these books in his hands, during a voyage of three days upon the
Potomac, when the party consisted only of the President and his
family, the Secretary of War and his aid and myself.</p>
               <p>The ten months which divide the fall of Fort Donelson, (February
16th, 1862,) from the battle of Fredericksburg, (December 13th, 1862,)
constitute the depressing era of military uncertainty. Administrative
ability, executive resolution and hardihood, were never more
impressively displayed than during this disheartening period, but in
spite of it, inconstant victory seems to vibrate between the hostile
banners.</p>
               <p>The encouraging results of Iuka and Corinth, and the opening of the
Upper Mississippi, inspire the national heart with new confidence in
the protection of Heaven and in the heroism of our western
soldiers. Brave old Farragut earns the grade of Admiral, and the
soubriquet of Salamander, by leading his thundering Armada, through
the <hi rend="italic">feu d' enfer</hi>, which belched from Fort Phillip
on the right, and Fort Jackson on the left, and the martial and
financial heart of rebellion in the Southwest, is palsied when the
guns of his fleet sweep the streets of New Orleans, and the Tamer of
Cities hangs up its scalp in his wigwam. War surges and resurges over
the
<pb n="44"/>
                  <figure><graphic url=""/>
                     <figDesc>44th page of Henry
Champion Deming's Eulogy of Abraham Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
devoted plains of Missouri and Arkansas. The Peninsula Campaign, with
its chequered fortunes, alternately excites exultation and wailing,
but its final failure plants in the National heart the seeds of
despair, while the whirlwind which devours the army of Pope,
constrains us to doubt the justice of God. The victories of South
Mountain and Antietam, fairly costing their weight in gore, and
turning to ashes in our grasp, failed to reanimate our hopes, while
Pittsburg Landing and Shiloh, are more than counterpoised by the heart
rending butchery of Fredericksburg.</p>
               <p>The progress of MR. LINCOLN'S mind from his plan of colonizing the
slave, and after that was abandoned, to compensated liberation, and
from this expedient to unconditional emancipation, is analogous to the
deliberate advance, which I have already detailed, from a conservative
to a thorough going policy, in the prosecution of the war. Unlike the
first, however, in these last transitions he meets with no resistence
from the philanthropies of his nature, but encouraged and stimulated
by the complete accord of emotion and reason. To be self-willed in a
revolutionary crisis, and to exclaim "Justice shall be omnipotent
though the Heavens fall," are unquestionably sublime manifestations,
but in such imminent peril, it is rather the sublimity of madness than
<pb n="45"/>
                  <figure><graphic url=""/>
                     <figDesc>45th page of Henry
Champion Deming's Eulogy of Abraham Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
of wisdom. I can not withhold my tribute of gratitude and admiration,
to the caution and address, with which MR. LINCOLN has felt his way,
timeing his march to the beat of the popular heart, and answering no
requisitions of the popular will until it was thoroughly mature and
unmistakably pronounced. He had settled the principle upon which
emancipation is defended, and was unquestionably ripe for it himself,
when he first resolved to exercise the belligerent rights which
belonged to the Government, in time of war, but he was deterred from
exercising <hi rend="italic">the right of liberation</hi>, from the
apprehension of a counter revolution in the North, and that his fears
were not entirely groundless, that remarkable political revulsion, in
the fall elections which immediately follow his preliminary
proclamation, abundantly demonstrates. When, however, his convictions
of the justice of emancipation were enforced, by the logic of
continued failure, and by the incisive reasoning of the enemy's
unyielding sword, he was led up, in spite of his fears, to the height
of that transcendent Edict, which constitutes his strongest claim upon
universal and unending gratitude and remembrance. He assumed the
Presidential chair, with a solemn disavowal of any constitutional
right to interfere with slavery in the States, and if they had
continued faithful to the Constitution, their cherished
<pb n="46"/>
                  <figure><graphic url=""/>
                     <figDesc>46th page of Henry
Champion Deming's Eulogy of Abraham Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
barbarity, condemned as it was by all his moral instincts, would have
been safe in the inviolable sanctity of his oath. But when they
appealed to War, and voluntarily renounced the safeguards of the
Constitution, they instantly handed over the abhorrence of
civilization to uncovenanted mercy, and disengaged two belligerent
rights, one of which is fatal to it, if slaves are <hi rend="italic">chattels</hi>, and the other fatal if slaves are men. By
the most meliorated construction of the international code, the
private property of an enemy on the land is still liable to capture,
<hi rend="italic">under circumstances constituting a necessity</hi>, of
which the conqueror is the sole judge; while the old and austere
authority of Vattel establishes the indisputable right in one
belligerent, to break the chains of any oppressed people which the
other belligerent is depriving of liberty, for the purpose of
completing and ennobling victory. Of these weapons, MR. LINCOLN chose
the first, which is called military necessity. The conditional
proclamation was for some time postponed, awaiting the impending
engagement in Maryland, and was finally promulged only five days after
Antietam. MR. LINCOLN required that the military urgency upon which it
was based, should not only be plausible, but real and imperious, and
it is now well understood that if victory had perched more signally on
our banners, and Lee's army had
<pb n="47"/>
                  <figure><graphic url=""/>
                     <figDesc>47th page of Henry
Champion Deming's Eulogy of Abraham Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
been more thoroughly crippled and demoralized in that battle, the
proclamation which restores to millions of living men, and to unborn
generations, the rights of manhood, would have been postponed to an
indefinite future.</p>
               <p>Are we not here able to interpret and explain one of those purposes
which are sometimes called mysterious and inscrutable? I can almost
see a mighty arm, stretching out of the unfathomable blue, hastening
the fugitive in his flight, holding back the feet of the pursuer, and
arresting the waves of destruction which are pouring upon the dismayed
and broken ranks, that the abyss which is yawning for the mightiest of
slavery's hosts, may not swallow up the elect of liberty and the
redemption of a long suffering race. Assembled here, to-day, to
devoutly recognize that Providence, which guided the great liberator,
"by ways which he knew not and by paths which were not known, may we
not all of us, without a discordant voice, and with the hope that his
own ransomed spirit is not unconscious of the oblation, unite in the
invocation which closes the imperishable manifesto, "UPON THIS ACT,
BELIEVED TO BE AN ACT OF JUSTICE WARRANTED BY THE CONSTITUTION UPON
MILITARY NECESSITY, I INVOKE THE CONSIDERATE JUDGMENT OF MANKIND AND
THE GRACIOUS FAVOR OF ALMIGHTY GOD."</p>
               <p>The definitive proclamation of emancipation was
<pb n="48"/>
                  <figure><graphic url=""/>
                     <figDesc>48th page of Henry
Champion Deming's Eulogy of Abraham Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
promulged on the first of January, 1863, and it seems instantly to
have been visited with that "gracious favor" which it so reverently
implores. From that eventful date Federal ascendency flows surely and
steadily on to the capture of Richmond and the surrender of
Lee. Reverses and checks, it is true, intervene, but they are only
eddies in the Amazon. During these twenty-seven controlling months of
the war, into which more general engagements were crowded, than into
any equal period of the world's history, the loss of but one, attests
the advent of higher inspiration and divine re-enforcement to our
struggling cause. The ink with which the proclamation is written is
scarcely dry upon the parchment, before the decisive victory of
Murfreesboro expels invasion from imperiled Tennessee. On the nation's
birthday which next follows it, propitious heaven almost visibly
intervened, by breaking the last barrier which prevents the loyal
father of waters, from flowing free and unobstructed through the
divided rebellion; and by sweeping back, from the bristling hills of
Gettysburg, the army of the alien on its last desperate raid into the
bosom of the North. Away up in mid air, on the cloud capped crests of
the south-eastern Alleghanies, there is the roar and lurid flame of
battle, as if the pent up fires of the cavernous earth were bursting
<pb n="49"/>
                  <figure><graphic url=""/>
                     <figDesc>49th page of Henry
Champion Deming's Eulogy of Abraham Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
from their thunder-riven summits, while down, down in the deep valley,
it seems as if the elements of nature were battering chasms and
pathways through their granite foundations. The gates of Georgia yield
to the flushed battalions of the Cumberland, and from the Altamaha to
the Cape Fear, three great states of the Confederacy soon "feel the
victim's tread and know the conquered knee." Hood is hurled, by his
infatuated Chieftain, against the battlements of Nashville only to be
dashed back broken and destroyed. The vale of the Shenandoah is swept
by the besom, and scourged by the wrath of Sheridan. Over the forest
which sweeps from the Rapidan to the James, there hangs, in early
Spring time, a dark and portentous cloud; the Wilderness is red as if
untimely Autumn had purpled its foliage. We dimly hear, far in its
resounding depths, that awe-inspiring roll, that sharp suggestive
rattle which forewarns and terrifies nations, and ever and anon a
woe-begone messenger, such as</p>
               <lg type="stanza">
                  <l>"Drew Priam's curtain at the dead of night</l>
                  <l>And told him
half his Troy, was burned"--</l>
               </lg>
               <p>breaks from the sequestered thicket, with a tantalizing tale, of
the fierce, sanguinary, but indecisive shock and recoil of embattled
hosts. What weeks of heart-rending suspense! But finally, from the
Saturnalia of death and butchery long rampant in its 
<pb n="50"/>
                  <figure><graphic url=""/>
                     <figDesc>50th page of Henry
Champion Deming's Eulogy of Abraham Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
sombre and haunted recesses, he of the iron will and inflexible
tenacity, at length emerges in the resplendent robes of Victory, and
day after day for persistent months, unmoved by clamor, undismayed by
failure, unwearied by resistance, slowly tightens an irresistible
coil, round the wailing Capital of sin, until faint and gasping, it
falls into the arms of a negro brigade. City after city, harbor after
harbor succumbs. The coast is hermetically sealed from Norfolk to
Galveston, and the magazines and arsenals of England and France no
longer pour their strengthening tides into the decaying veins of the
worn out Confederacy. Sheridan rolls up the Confederate right like a
scroll and hangs on its flying flank with the scent of a hound and the
snap of a terrier. Lee surrenders his decimated horde, and over the
old endeared, precious inheritance from the Rappahannock to the
Sabine, up flies the banner, down droops the rag.</p>
               <p>ABRAHAM LINCOLN'S work was finished, when unheralded and almost
unattended, leading his little son by the hand, he walks into the
streets of humiliated Richmond. If upon that auspicious morn, the
crowning benediction had descended upon him, he might have well wished
to die. What more could he ask for on earth? Assailed by the strongest
conspiracy 
<pb n="51"/>
                  <figure><graphic url=""/>
                     <figDesc>51st page of Henry
Champion Deming's Eulogy of Abraham Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
that ever threatened a nation's life, after a four years' struggle,
his triumph over it was complete and overwhelming, conquering liberty
for a class and national existence for a people. Was not this honor
enough for one man? He had survived ridicule, he had outlived
detraction and abuse, he had secured the commendation of the world for
purity of purpose, constancy in disaster, clemency in triumph, and the
praise even of his armed foes, for gentleness and mercy. In times more
troubled, he had administered Government with more ability than
Cavour, and War with more success than Napoleon the Third. He had
paled the lory of Hastings in preserving an empire, and had earned
comparison with Hampden for self-command and rectitude of intention,
while as the emancipator of a race, he stood alone in solitary glory,
without a rival and without a parallel. If fame had approached him
with the laurels of a conqueror, if power had offered him a sceptre,
and ambition a crown, he would have scorned them all. He asked from
man, he asked, from God but one culminating boon, peace, peace on the
bloody waters and the blighted shore.</p>
               <p>Alas! such an enviable consummation to his career was denied. There
are mysterious conferences of suspicious and guilt-laden men, ominous
flittings of a bat-like flock from Washington to Richmond, and
<pb n="52"/>
                  <figure><graphic url=""/>
                     <figDesc>52nd page of Henry
Champion Deming's Eulogy of Abraham Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
from Richmond to Canada, midnight interviews lurking spies,
correspondence in cypher; a conspiracy against his life has long been
maturing, in minds capable of such things, and finally the day is
named, the place is appointed, and the parts of the bloody drama all
distributed. On the evening of the 14th of April, 1865, at Ford's
theatre in the City of Washington the trigger of a pistol is pulled by
a sneaking murderer who had crept up behind him all unwarned, and the
report resounds through the startled assembly. From the private box
which the PRESIDENT was known to occupy, an excited wretch, with a
swart visage torn and convulsed by every passion, leaps upon the stage
where he had last played the blood-thirsty Apostate, and brandishing a
dagger in his outstretched hand, and exclaiming "sic semper tyrannis,"
vanished into night and darkness, leaving behind him horror, terror
and woe. The nation stands aghast! the crime of the Dark Ages has
entered our History--stealthy assassination has broken the sacred
succession of the people's anointed-the life of the best beloved of
Presidents is oozing from a murderous wound--the soul of Abraham
Lincoln is transferred from Earth to Heaven.</p>
               <p>Whether the Confederate Government is legally guilty of
MR. LINCOLN'S murder, is a question yet to be determined, but of one
thing we are sure, that
<pb n="53"/>
                  <figure><graphic url=""/>
                     <figDesc>53rd page of Henry
Champion Deming's Eulogy of Abraham Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
no crime is too bad, too bold, too infamous, too execrable, for that
state of society which was willing to unchain the fiends of war, to
incarnadine sea and land, to immolate a Republic that is to the
victims of misgovernment the only pledge of ransom, and to the
victimizer the only warrant of retribution, to bore into Pandemonium
itself and surge this consecrated earth with its sulphurous seas of
flame, that it might continue to batten forever on slavery, and
perpetuate eternally "such abominations as are buried under the waters
of the Dead Sea." Assassination belongs to the same ruffian family of
crime in which that society exulted previous to the war, and to the
same degree of infernal turpitude with those which it had encouraged
and applauded, during its prosecution.  Without compunction or
hesitation, it could coolly plot to pile hecatomb upon hecatomb of
victims, infancy and age, guilt and innocence, in one smouldering
heap, by the midnight conflagration of our crowded metropolis. It
could stealthily conduct the infection of a devouring pestilence, as
electricity by the wires, into the healthy atmosphere of the North
that all who breathed it might die. It could deliberately compose the
fiendish plan, and day after day, hour after hour, composedly weigh
and measure out to helpless prisoners, the precise ration which was
sure to produce their slow starvation. What a
<pb n="54"/>
                  <figure><graphic url=""/>
                     <figDesc>54th page of Henry
Champion Deming's Eulogy of Abraham Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
burlesque to see such a society shrink back affrighted and horror
struck, at shooting one Abolitionist in the head and stabbing another
in the heart! In the name of Christianity it justifies Human Bondage,
in the name of the Constitution it justifies its overthrow, in the
name of Chivalry it justifies the Bloodhound and the Barracoon, why
not in the name of Patriotism justify Assassination, and approve and
ratify the hired murderer's lying epitaph upon himself when with the
price of blood in his pocket he says, "tell my mother I died for my
country." What a record of lawlessness and infamy has slavery written
for itself from MR. LINCOLN's election to his death! Appealing to the
Ballot, it abjures the verdict of the people, appealing to Public
Opinion, it defies the decree of the civilized world, appealing to
Arms, it tramples on the Code of War and summons Starvation, the
Torch, and the Plague, to aid the impotency of its sword. Too wicked
to live in peace, too weak to succeed in war, too enraged to accept
defeat, too corrupt to die with honor, too putrid to rise again, it
gathers up its expiring strength to strike an assassin's blow that it
might die as it had lived, violating every law, human and divine, and
accursed by God and man.</p>
               <p>"Useless, useless," said the dying Thug, as his shrieking ghost
fled from the angry earth to the
<pb n="55"/>
                  <figure><graphic url=""/>
                     <figDesc>55th page of Henry
Champion Deming's Eulogy of Abraham Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
vengeful skies. Yes, yes, crime always fails in its purpose,
assassination is everlastingly a blunder. Caesar is assassinated and
imperial sway emerges in full armed despotism from his tomb--Henry the
Fourth is assassinated, but the edict of Nantes Survives for nearly a
century the dagger of Ravaillac, and religious toleration is
invigorated by its blow--William the Silent is assassinated, but the
republic of the Netherlands breaks the double fetters of superstition
and tyranny, and expands into a great and flourishing
commonwealth--Buckingham, is assassinated, but Protestant Rochelle is
soon delivered up to the vengeance of Richelieu--Capo D'Istria is
assassinated, but the European dynasties control the policy and elect
the kings of Greece--LINCOLN is assassinated, but the branded
confederacy cowers beneath the maledictions of the civilized world,
and onward, onward, roll the mighty wheels of victory and
vengeance. "Useless," and didst thou dream, impious malefactor, that
it was in the power of thy puny arm to reach the great life of our
virtuous DELIVERER? He lives! he lives! he lives to-day, in his
imperishable example, in his recorded words of wisdom, in his great
maxims of liberty and enfranchisement. The good never die; to them
belongs a double immortality, they perish not upon the earth, and they
exist forever in heaven. The good of the
<pb n="56"/>
                  <figure><graphic url=""/>
                     <figDesc>56th page of Henry
Champion Deming's Eulogy of Abraham Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
present live in the future, as the good of the past are here with us
and in us to-day. The great primeval law-giver, entombed for forty
centuries in that unknown grave, in an obscure vale of Moab, to-day
legislates in your halls of State, and preaches on your Sabbath in all
your synagogues. Salem's royal singer indites our liturgies and leads
our worship. Socrates questions Atheists in these streets. Phidias
sculptures the friezes of Christian temples--the desecrated tongue of
mangled Tully arraigns our Catalines--against the Philip of to-day the
dead Demosthenes thunders--the dead Leonidas guards the gates of every
empire which wrestles for its sovereignty--the dead Justinian issues
in your courts the living mandates of the law--the dead Martin Luther
issues from your press the living oracles of God--the dead Napoleon
still sways France from that silent throne in the Invalides--the dead
George Washington held together through wrangling decades this
brotherhood of States, and the dead ABRAHAM LINCOLN will peal the
clarion of beleaguered nations and marshal and beckon on the wavering
battle line of liberty, till the last generation of man-</p>
               <lg type="stanza">
                  <l>" Shall creation's death
behold</l>
                  <l>As Adam saw her prime."</l>
               </lg>
               <p>His fame will grow brighter and grander, as it descends the ages,
and posterity will regard him as
<pb n="57"/>
                  <figure><graphic url=""/>
                     <figDesc>57th page of Henry
Champion Deming's Eulogy of Abraham Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
the incarnation of democracy, in its pure childhood, as the embodiment
of those ideas of universal emancipation, which were the glory of its
youthful epoch. In remote futurity, as far removed from us as we are
from the Chaldeans, when the massive walls of our Capitol shall no
more exist than the palace of Nebuchadnezzar, and all that is mortal
in our civilization and polity shall live only in memory, and when the
ingenuous child, gazing adown the dark infinity of time, will be
obliged to ask "where is the nineteenth century?" "There, there," the
sage will reply, "where you see that full orbed and splendid HESPERUS
of the West." When the race shall have finally climbed to the lofty
table land of UNIVERSAL BROTHERHOOD, to which it is inevitably
destined by the paramount law of its own development, and shall turn
backward its wistful eyes for those who have led its weary pilgrimage,
through passes the most perilous, and over wastes the most
disheartening, they will instinctively seek the uncourtly figure of
that forest born LIBERATOR, who by one glorious edict restored to
humanity all the divine equalities enfeoffed upon it, when of one
blood all the children of men were made, and thus incorporated into
harmonious fraternity all the estranged and repellant complexion's of
mankind. With reverent and grateful hearts they will pour their
choicest frankincense at the feet, 
<pb n="58"/>
                  <figure><graphic url=""/>
                     <figDesc>58th page of Henry
Champion Deming's Eulogy of Abraham Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
crown with unfading amaranth the brow, and by eulogy, statue, column
and obelisk, and every aid to enduring remembrance transmit to new and
ever rising futurities, the irradiated name of the first President of
the regenerated Republic, that Martyr to Liberty and Law, whom, on
this shore and border of Time's immensity we deplore to-day, ABRAHAM
LINCOLN Of  Illinois.</p>
            </div2>
         </div1>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>