<TEI.2>
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt n="The Sin of Reviling, and Its Work">
            <title>The Sin of Reviling, and Its Work</title>
            <author>Gordon, W. R.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Compiled and edited by</resp>
               <name>Beck
Center</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent/>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Lewis H. Beck Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Emory University</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Atlanta,
Georgia</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>1996 Emory
University. Permission is granted to download, transmit, or otherwise
reproduce, distribute or display the contributions to the work claimed
by Emory University for non-profit educational purposes, provided
this header is included in its entirety.  For inquiries about
commercial uses, contact the Director, 
Pitts Theology Library, Emory
University, Atlanta, Georgia 30322</p>
            </availability>
            <date>1999</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Lincoln
Sermons Project</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Gordon,
W. R. The Sin of Reviling, and Its Work. A funeral Sermon, Occasioned
by the Assassination of President Lincoln, April 14th, 1865. Preached
on May 7, 1865. Published by Request of Consistory. New York: John A
Gray &#x0026; Green, Printers, 16 &#x0026; 18 Jacob Street. 1865.</bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This text derives from the Special Collections 
of Pitts Theology Library, Emory University, and is produced in 
collaboration with the Lewis H. Beck Center a, the Emory 
Preservation Office, and Pitts Theology Library.</p>
            <p>TRANSCRIBER: Lewis H. Beck Center and Emory University 
Preservation Office.</p>
            <p>PRODUCER:  BookLab, Inc., 1606 Headway Circle, 
Suite 100, Austin, TX 78754</p>
            <p>CAPTURE DEVICE: XEROX DocuImage 620S flatbed scanner</p>
            <p>CAPTURE DETAILS: Scanner software: XEROX ScanTool 
version 4.2.3; no gamma correction; images are all bitonal.</p>
            <p>CHANGE HISTORY: Using the Adobe Photoshop Batch Processor, 
we interpolated  the original TIFF files to 8-bit grays, 
and altered the resolution to 144 dpi, producing screen 
images twice the original size.  We then saved them in 
JPEG format.  We produced GIF thumbnails from the JPEG files.</p>
            <p>RESOLUTION: 600 ppi</p>
            <p>COMPRESSION: Resolution 144 per inch with Constrain 
Properties to 72 per inch.</p>
            <p>SOURCE: Original documents.</p>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>1999</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Scott Ellis</name>
               <resp>Staff</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <item>SGML tags inserted in compliance
with TEI guidelines using TEILITE</item>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div1 id="gordon.001" n="The Sin of Reviling, and Its Work" type="text">
            <head> 
               <bibl> 
                  <title>The Sin of
Reviling, and Its Work</title> 
                  <date>May 7, 1865</date>
                  <pubPlace>Ref. Prot. Dutch Church of Schraalenberg, N. J.</pubPlace>
                  <author>Gordon, W. R.</author> 
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>John A Gray &#x0026; Green, Printers</publisher>
                     <date>1865</date>
                  </imprint> 
               </bibl> 
            </head>
            <p>
               <figure entity="gordon1">
                  <figDesc>1st page of W. R. Gordon's The
Sin of Reviling, and Its Work.</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <p>THE SIN OF REVILING, AND ITS WORK.</p>
            <p>A</p>
            <p>FUNERAL SERMON,</p>
            <p>OCCAISONED BY THE ASSASSINATION OF</p>
            <p>PRESIDENT LINCOLN.</p>
            <p>APRIL 14TH, 1865.</p>
            <p>BY</p>
            <p>W.R. GORDON, D.D.,</p>
            <p>PASTOR OF THE REF. PROT. DUTCH CHURCH OF SCHRAALENBERG, N. J.</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italic">Preached on May 7,1865.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>PUBLISHED BY REQUEST OF CONSISTORY.</p>
            <p>New York:</p>
            <p>JOHN A. GRAY &#x0026; GREEN, PRINTERS,16 &#x0026; 18 JACOB
STREET.</p>
            <p>1865.</p>
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>
               <figure entity="gordon2">
                  <figDesc>2nd page of
W. R. Gordon's The Sin of Reviling, and Its
Work.</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>
               <figure entity="gordon3">
                  <figDesc>3rd page of
W. R. Gordon's The Sin of Reviling, and Its
Work.</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <div2 id="gordon.002" n="SERMON" type="sermon">
               <head>SERMON.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <p>ACTS 23: 5. 
<lb/>
IT is written, Thou shalt not speak evil of the Ruler of thy
people.</p>
               </epigraph>
               <p>THE connection of this text contributes much to make it
emphatic. Paul had been rescued from the violence of a Jewish mob by a
military force, whose captain had subsequently assembled the Sanhedrim
to try his case. The High-Priest then presiding was bound to protect
the prisoner in the right of making his defence, but he was guilty of
the outrage of commanding them that stood nearest to smite him on the
mouth. Paul's instinctive indignation prompted him to return this
answer: "God shall smite thee, thou whited wall; for sittest thou to
judge me after the law, and commandest me to be smitten contrary to
the law?"</p>
               <p>Horrified by this unexpected display of daring boldness,
some of the members of that notable court thus remonstrated: "Revilest
thou God's high-priest?" Paul, not recognizing his claim to that
office illegally procured, or having been so long absent from
Jerusalem that he was not aware of the change made in the incumbent,
immediately said in extenuation of his haste: "I wist not, brethren,
that he was the high-priest; for it is written, Thou shalt not speak
evil of the ruler of thy people." This special prohibition is found in
Ex. 22: 28: "Thou shalt not revile the judges, nor curse the ruler of
thy people."</p>
               <p>God is the author of civil society. He has ordained laws
for its protection and government, and a magistracy for their
execution. He has also made special enactments, such as Paul quoted,
for its safety in the execution of political trust,
<pb n="4"/>
                  <figure entity="gordon4">
                     <figDesc>4th page of W. R. Gordon's
The Sin of Reviling, and Its Work.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
throwing around the office the solemn sanction of his authority. This
was so well understood among the Jews, that however obnoxious any
particular magistrate might become, his office was sure to protect him
from wanton insult as well as from personal danger. Hence the
exclamation, "Revilest thou? Had not Paul explained, he would have
been held guilty of a grave offence, since it was contrary to the law
of Moses to speak ill of a magistrate, even in a clandestine
manner. The highest office of government was especially held in
reverence. Those who from neglect failed to render the veneration due
to his character, had given offence to the king, were liable to the
infliction of capital punishment. Now there are many forms of
evil-speaking, all of which are condemned in the word of God, but the
special form of the sin here spoken of, is that of REVILING.</p>
               <p>But what is reviling? It is treating a person with vile
epithets of language cursing him, wishing him harm, and loading his
character with reproaches and railing accusation. Whoever did this
among the Hebrews, respecting their Chief-Magistrate, though in
private, subjected himself, upon discovery, to the penalty of
death. How such revilers were regarded, and with what sentiments of
abhorrence their sin was looked upon, we learn from scripture. The
general law which should regulate public opinion on this point is thus
expressed by Solomon: "Curse not the King, no not in thy thoughts." A
king is simply the chief-magistrate in a monarchy, and bears the same
general relation to it that a president bears to a republic; and as
the Bible is for all nations, it is evident that the law of God
respecting magistracy is applicable to all forms of government among
men. Keeping this in view, we shall readily understand that the
teachings of Scripture must be supremely regarded by all Christian
men, in the discharge of their civil as well as religious duties.</p>
               <p>"My son, fear thou the Lord and the king; and meddle not
with them that are given to change." (Prov. 14: 21.)</p>
               <p>"Whosoever will not do the law of thy God and of the king,
let judgment be executed speedily upon him, whether it be unto death,
or to banishment, or to confiscation of goods: or to imprisonment."
(Ezra 7: 26.)</p>
               <pb n="5"/>
               <p>
                  <figure entity="gordon5">
                     <figDesc>5th page of
W. R. Gordon's The Sin of Reviling, and Its
Work.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <p>"Let every soul be subject unto the higher powers, for
there is no power but of God: the powers that be are ordained of
God. Whosoever, therefore, resisteth the power, resisteth the
ordinance of God; and they that resist shall receive to themselves
damnation." (Rom. 13: 1, 2.)</p>
               <p>"Submit yourselves to every ordinance of man for the Lord's
sake; whether it be to the king as supreme, or unto governors as unto
them that are sent by him for the punishment of evil-doers, and for
the praise of them that do well. For so is the will of God, that with
well-doing ye may put to silence the ignorance of foolish men: as
free, and not USING LIBERTY FOR A CLOAK OF MALICIOUSNESS, but as the
servants of God. Fear God. Honor the king." (1 Peter 2: 13-17.)</p>
               <p>"The Lord knoweth how to deliver the godly out of
temptation, and to reserve the unjust unto the judgment-day to be
punished; but CHIEFLY them that walk after the flesh in the lust of
uncleanness, and despise governments. Presumptuous are they,
self-willed, they are not afraid to speak evil of dignities; whereas
angels which are great in power and might bring not railing accusation
against them before the Lord; but these, as natural brute beasts made
to be taken and destroyed, speak evil of the things that they
understand not; and shall utterly perish in their own corruption." (2
Peter 2: 8-12.)</p>
               <p>Paul thus enjoins the <hi rend="italic">duty of political
preaching</hi> upon ministers: "Put them in mind to be subject to
principalities and powers, to obey magistrates, to be ready to every
good work, to speak evil of no man, to be no brawlers, but gentle,
showing all meekness unto all men." (Tit. 3: 1, 2.)</p>
               <p>Thus you will perceive, that God, having clothed magistracy
with divine sanctions, has not only enforced obedience, but sternly
denounced the sin of traducing those of high official character. The
Thirty-seventh Article of Faith of the Reformed Dutch Church
accordingly has this language: "It is the bounder duty of every one,
of what state, quality, or condition soever he may be, to subject
himself to the magistrates; to pay tribute, to show due honor and
respect to them, and to obey them in all things which are not
repugnant to the word of God; to supplicate for them in their
prayers. Where-
<pb n="6"/>
                  <figure entity="gordon6">
                     <figDesc>6th page of W. R. Gordon's
The Sin of Reviling, and Its Work.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
fore we detest the Anabaptists<ref target="gordon.002.n01">*</ref> and other seditious people, and in
general all those who reject the higher powers and magistrates, and
would subvert justice, and confound that decency and good order which
God has established among men."</p>
               <p>From the authority quoted, we are warranted to make this
general deduction: REVILING THE PRESIDENT OF THE UNITED STATES, IS A
CRIME AGAINST GOD, AND AGAINST THE GOVERNMENT. This we prove from two
considerations.</p>
               <p>1. The practice of reviling is an abuse of the faculty of
speech, and altogether reprehensible. It discovers in the guilty a
bitterness of spirit, an envious nature, a malicious disposition, the
indulgence of which is sure to recoil upon themselves. It makes them
injurious members of society, corrupting in their influence, and
dangerous to public morals. Hence, according to Paul, such persons are
not to be tolerated in the Church of God. "I have now written unto you
not to keep company, if any man that is called a brother, be a
fornicator, or covetous, or an indolater, or a RAILER--with such an
one, no not to eat." "For neither thieves, nor covetous, nor
drunkards, nor REVILERS shall inherit the kingdom of God." This text
puts such persons in the worst of company, because they work iniquity
in the most dangerous way, "using liberty for a cloak of
maliciousness;" or as the Psalmist expresses it, they "whet their
tongues like a sword, and bend their bows to shoot their arrows, even
bitter words." The reviler labors to fabricate a public sentiment
which shall ultimately injure the man against whom he speaks. This is
his direct object. Solomon says, "Death and life are in the power of
the tongue, and they that love it shall eat the fruit thereof;" that
is, they that love to use the power of the tongue, shall reap the
fruit of their speech, according as it is influential to the death or
life of the person of whom they speak, "for by thy words thou shalt be
justified, and by thy words thou shalt be condemned."</p>
               <p>In the Sermon on the Mount, our Saviour thus discourses:
"Ye have heard that it was said by them of old time, Thou shalt not
kill, and whosoever shall kill, shall be in danger of</p>
               <note id="gordon.002.n01" n="*" place="foot" anchored="yes">
                  <p>A seditious sect of the sixteenth
century.</p>
               </note>
               <pb n="7"/>
               <p>
                  <figure entity="gordon7">
                     <figDesc>7th page of
W. R. Gordon's The Sin of Reviling, and Its
Work.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <p>the judgment; but I say unto you, that whosoever is angry with his
brother without a cause, shall be in danger of the judgment, and
whosoever shall say to his brother, Raca"--a word of bitter
contempt--"shall be in danger of the council: but whosoever shall say,
THOU FOOL, shall be in danger of hellfire." The original of the term
translated "thou fool," is a very different thing from that word as
now commonly used among us. It signifies all those bad qualities that
make one an enemy of God and man. We have no single term in our
language that can translate it. It combines the ideas of impiety,
apostasy, tyranny, odiousness of character, and hell-desert. Whosoever
uses these expressions of reviling to brand with infamy the fair name
of any man, according to the exposition of Christ, is a murderer in
his heart, and in danger of hell-fire. Hence John says: "Whosoever
hateth his brother is a murderer."</p>
               <p>2. Crimes are great or small in accordance with their
issues, and the relative standing of those against whom they are
committed. The life of a man may be mainly valuable to himself, or
beyond himself to a family, or beyond a family to a nation. Should he
be murdered, the act is the same, whatever relations he may have held;
but the iniquity of the act must be graduated by the value of the
life, services, and position of the person thus felled by the hand of
violence. This seems to have been always generally understood, for we
find comparatively few instances in history of the assassination of
men in high positions of political power. Julius Caesar was thus
murdered in the Roman Senate, March fifteenth, forty-four years before
Christ. William, Prince of Orange, the founder of Dutch freedom, whose
venerated name will ever be a blazing star in history, was
assassinated at the instigation of the Jesuits, July tenth,
A.D. 1584. Henry the Fourth, said to be the best king that ever
occupied the throne of France, who granted to his Protestant subjects
entire religious freedom by the Edict of Nantes, was also assassinated
by the Jesuits, A.D. 1610. Our own noble Lincoln, the victim of an
execrable conspiracy, was thus deprived of life, April fourteenth,
A.D. 1865.</p>
               <p>Between each of these horrible tragedies there is, more or
less, a long series of years; and the inference is natural, that while
assassins have been numerous, and murders multiplied
<pb n="8"/>
                  <figure entity="gordon8">
                     <figDesc>8th page of W. R. Gordon's
The Sin of Reviling, and Its Work.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
in every age, few have been found of courage sufficiently desperate
and despicable to strike at the lives of men in high official
position, notwithstanding greater exposure to the shafts of
enmity. This has been owing, in a large measure, to the fact, that the
common-sense of mankind has always been impressed with reverence for
the office of chief ruler. He who strikes at him who holds it, must
first strike at the office before he can reach the officer; and as a
preparatory step, they who encourage the assassin by <hi rend="italic">reviling</hi> his victim, must be guilty of treasonable
language against the government itself with whose interests the
officer is intrusted. This is clear from the awful tragedy that has
recently overflowed our cup of affliction. No one had any <hi rend="italic">personal</hi> quarrel with Mr. Lincoln, but as President,
he was reviled; as President, he was hated; as President, he was
murdered.</p>
               <p>No matter to what party our Chief-Magistrate may belong, no
matter what policy he may adopt in the sworn execution of his trust,
the simple facts of his election and assumption of the oath of office
imply a corresponding obligation upon the part of the whole people
whose common service he enters, to protect him from defamation as well
as from danger. This principle lies at the basis of all law, for
however we may separate them in thought, government and its
administration practically are indivisible; for one without the other
is a mere abstraction. A political heresy is afloat, that the
government and its administration are so entirely different, that the
former shall not suffer, though the latter be assailed and hurled from
its place. This is absurd. You might as well say, life and the
machinery of life are two different things, therefore the machinery
may be disarranged without the life being endangered. No, the office,
and the officer legally installed, must share the same protection. Now
as reviling a ruler and his official acts leads to wrath, and wrath to
conspiracies, and conspiracies to personal danger, it is clear that
this reviling is criminal, because it is both incipient treason and
the support of felons, who plead it in extenuation of their
crimes. Moreover, as treasonable words lead to treasonable deeds, even
to the extent of overt crime, as in the case of our late President,
the guilt of the latter fearfully recoils upon all who, in violation
<pb n="9"/>
                  <figure entity="gordon9">
                     <figDesc>9th page of W. R. Gordon's
The Sin of Reviling, and Its Work.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
of the citizen's obligation while enjoying his privileges, have abused
and persecuted the honest ruler who has fallen a victim to consequent
violence, because they have helped to manufacture a treasonable public
sentiment pervading a mischievous faction, which has issued in the
blackest crime.</p>
               <p>Therefore while in human law there was but one murderer of our
Chief-Magistrate, according to divine law there are hundreds of them,
and perhaps thousands who survive the single wretch. That the doctrine
of the Scriptures on this point is not misstated, we prove by brief
references. Paul says: "Be not partaker of other men's sins." That
this does not refer merely to busy accomplices, we prove from 2 John
11: "<hi rend="italic">He that biddeth him God speed, is partaker of his
evil deeds</hi>." Now here is the annunciation of a general principle
whose spirit pervades the whole Bible--Ps. 51: 14; Acts 8: 1; Luke 23:
51; and in the light of it, we say that whoever applauds this crime,
or feels a secret satisfaction that it has been done, or thinks well
of it, as a happy stroke by which the hated ruler has been put out of
the way, is a murderer in his heart, and as such he is regarded and
held by the law of God. Thus we think it becomes evident, that
reviling the President of the United states is a crime against God,
and against the Government under which we live, and should meet with
its proper punishment; for if a bad magistrate must be protected in
his office until legally removed, what must be the guilt of that
portion of any people who, "using liberty as a cloak of
maliciousness," revile a good magistrate, until his innocent life be
taken by some villain whose bloody work is an agreeable surprise to
their criminal hearts?</p>
               <p>That Abraham Lincoln was a good magistrate is the unanimous
verdict of all competent to pronounce upon the subject. His qualities
of intellectual and moral worth have shone all the more conspicuously
for incessant use, and the friction of hard trials. We do not intend
to speak of him as a private citizen, but as the Ruler of his
people. Called to the administration when the horrible crime of the
South, which had been maturing for more than thirty years, had
culminated in treason no less wide-spread than malignant; beset with
unusual difficulties and novel dangers, and a man untried and unknown
to
<pb n="10"/>
                  <figure entity="gordon10">
                     <figDesc>10th page of
W. R. Gordon's The Sin of Reviling, and Its Work.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
the mass of the people, he was at the mercy of that power for good and
evil, the public press. By the hostile portion of it he was bitterly
assailed in a reviling spirit, and before he had entered upon the
discharge of his duties, this reviling had prepared for him the pistol
and dagger of the assassin; but having made his way though danger to
the Capitol, he fearlessly took the oath of office amid a multitude of
political friends and foes. During the delivery of his first inaugural
address, the lamented Douglas, his rival, beautifully showed by a
courteous act, that political opposition need not be in conflict with
personal friendship. The feeling was mutual. One of our neighbors<ref target="gordon.002.n02">*</ref>
visited the President last May, and during the interview, informed him
that at his first election he had voted for his opponent, whereupon
Mr. Lincoln led off in a eulogy upon Mr. Douglas, declaring a purpose
to employ his own pen in doing justice to his character. We mention
this only to show, that opposition to a chief-magistrate purely on
principles of administrative policy is perfectly fair, and by no means
inconsistent with the honor or duty of any citizen. Oh! if all men had
followed the example of these political opponents who thought and
spoke well of each other, our country would not now be draped in
mourning for the death of her Chief, nor humbled by the crime of
parricide. But the deed is done, and a nation's flowing tears and
expensive testimonials are demonstrative of the fact that no ruler
exalted to the highest seat of honor in the wide world, has ever been
so lovingly clasped by millions of hearts whose affections were drawn
out by the attractions of his character.</p>
               <p>Our martyr patriot was providentially placed, from the very
outset, in the midst of the strangest and most embarrassing
difficulties that ever arose in our country. His novel situation awoke
the liveliest interest in his behalf, as well as great anxiety as to
his fitness for the perilous exigencies of the hour. His enemies were
multiplied by the revilings of the adverse portion of the press, which
had succeeded in exciting some little fear among his friends; but the
first thing that assured their confidence was his farewell address
when he left</p>
               <note id="gordon.002.n02" n="*" place="foot" anchored="yes">
                  <p>Hon. Thomas H. Herring</p>
               </note>
               <pb n="11"/>
               <p>
                  <figure entity="gordon11">
                     <figDesc>11th page of
W. R. Gordon's The Sin of Reviling, and Its
Work.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <p>his Illinois home. In that speech, on February eleventh, 1861, he
said:</p>
               <p>"A duty devolves upon me which is perhaps greater than
that which has devolved upon any man since the days of Washington. He
never would have succeeded except for the aid of Divine Providence,
upon which he at all times relied. I feel that I cannot succeed,
without the same divine aid which sustained him; and on the same
Almighty Being I place my reliance for support, and I hope you, my
friends, will all pray that I may receive that divine assistance
without which I cannot succeed, but with which success is
certain."</p>
               <p>This earnest, touching appeal made its way directly
to every Christian heart. It drew out the sympathy of the wise and the
good of other lands besides our own, as the morning sun draws vapors
from the earth; and from that hour the breath of prayer has been
burdened for him, until he reached the happy place where dangers no
more cluster, where prayer is no more needed.</p>
               <p>It was not long before the private life of ABRAHAM LINCOLN
became familiar to the people. Made to pass under the severest
scrutiny of a merciless investigation, like the unfallen snow, it was
found spotless, his enemies being judges. This result of their
diligence ought to have operated in his favor, but it did not seem in
the least to abate their rancor or reviling. If not as bad as he might
be, he must be made out worse than he was, purely as a political
measure! Though reviled, he reviled not again, but uncomplainingly and
patiently set to work to subdue a gigantic rebellion the like of which
the world never saw. Fully impressed with the stupendous issues to be
determined by this conflict, he rose to the dignity of the position,
realized its vast responsibility, and with an unfaltering trust in
God, pursued a steady course marked by wisdom, and revealing the
patriotic purpose to restore peace to our land preserved from the
execution of the horrid design of the most desperate foe. How well he
succeeded, none need now be told. Whatever may have been said to the
contrary, circumstances, purposes, plans carried out, conquests, and
steady progress have proved that he was a man exactly adapted to the
situation: of quick perception;
<pb n="12"/>
                  <figure entity="gordon12">
                     <figDesc>12th page of
W. R. Gordon's The Sin of Reviling, and Its Work.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
of calm and sound judgment; and of great intellectual and executive
ability. His integrity of heart, honesty of aim, truthfulness of
nature, his gentleness in firmness, his thoughtful prudence, his
loving-kindness and social turn, his subordination of all to an
incorruptible patriotism, and his hearty reliance on God for every
thing needed to insure success, not only expressed publicly and in
private, but manifested by daily expositions of conduct, formed the
rarest assemblage of dignifying qualities that ever shone in human
character, as a constellation in mid-heaven.</p>
               <p>Four years of hard trial only served to burnish the gold
and remove the dross. The hearts of the people lodged full confidence
in him, and this they proved to him by the immense majorities with
which he was carried into the second term of office. He was so devoid
of ambition, so fully in love with the right, so bent upon doing his
whole duty, so devoted to the best interests of his country, and yet
so mercifully inclined toward the rebels, that the people saw at once,
by the light of the past, that he was the best one to trust for the
future, until our calamities should vanish away. If any additional
pledge for this popular confidence was needed, it was given in his
second inaugural, which, alas! proved to be his farewell address. He
concluded it in these memorable words:</p>
               <p>"With malice toward none, with charity for all, with
firmness in the right, as God gives us to see the right, let us strive
to finish the work we are in, to bind up the nation's wounds, to care
for him who shall have borne the battle, and for his widows and his
orphans, to do all which may achieve and cherish a just and lasting
peace among ourselves and with all nations."</p>
               <p>Shortly after this, he had the satisfaction to see the
rebellion broken down; but O our misfortune! Only one month and ten
days elapsed, when the assassin reached and took his life: yet his
work was done, and well done, and ABRAHAM LINCOLN, washed with tears,
was embalmed in the imperishable love of a grateful people.</p>
               <p>That he was not only a good magistrate, but also a
Christian man, I must believe from two facts. His sterling honesty was
proverbial, and had become so inwrought in his nature by
<pb n="13"/>
                  <figure entity="gordon13">
                     <figDesc>13th page of
W. R. Gordon's The Sin of Reviling, and Its Work.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
long habit, that he never could have been a successful hypocrite, if
he had tried; therefore his uniform out-spoken faith in God's favoring
providence, hope in his goodness, trust in his mercy, must be accepted
as proof of his Christianity. Never since my remembrance, and perhaps
never, have we had a President so free from the common frailties of
men top-mast in position, and so liberal of devout sentiment evidently
real, in his public utterances. His pastor surely is a competent
witness. "I speak," said he, "what I know, and testify what I have
often heard him say, when I affirm that God's guidance and mercy were
the props on which he humbly and habitually leaned; that they were the
best hope he had for himself and for his country." "Never shall I
forget the emphasis and the deep emotion with which he said in this
very room to a company of clergymen and others who called to pay him
their respects in the darkest day of our civil conflict: 'Gentlemen,
my hope of success in this great and terrible struggle rests on that
immutable foundation, the justness and goodness of God. And when
events are very threatening, and prospects very dark, I still hope
that in some way which man cannot see, all will be well in the end,
because our cause is just, and God is on our side.'"</p>
               <p>But, it is said, Mr. Lincoln perished in a theatre. We
readily grant that he ought not to have been there. We regret it,
because we believe the theatre to be the devil's schoolhouse; but at
the same time we lament to say many professing Christians have been
there before him, by whose base example he might have been misled. We
do not excuse him; but we must state in fairness to all concerned,
that he was there, more from a desire not to disappoint an expectant
audience, than from any self-prompting.</p>
               <p>Passing this, we adduce, in further proof of his Christian
character, this fact, as given by Rev. Mr. Carey, of Illinois:</p>
               <p>"A gentleman, having recently visited Washington on
business with the President, was, on leaving home, requested by a
friend to ask Mr. Lincoln <hi rend="italic">whether he loved
Jesus</hi>. The business being completed, the question was kindly
asked. The President buried his face in his handkerchief, turned away,
and wept. He then turned, and said: 'When I left
<pb n="14"/>
                  <figure entity="gordon14">
                     <figDesc>14th page of
W. R. Gordon's The Sin of Reviling, and Its Work.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
home to take the chair of state, I requested my countrymen to pray for
me: I was not then a Christian. When my son died, the sorest trial of
my life, I was not a Christian. But when I went to Gettysburgh, and
looked upon the graves of our dead heroes, who had fallen in the
defence of their country, I then and there consecrated myself to
Christ. <hi rend="italic">I do love Jesus</hi>.'"</p>
               <p>Such is the living character of this good man and honest
ruler upon whom reviling tongues and pens hounded the assassin. As far
as known, he never had a personal enemy until he undertook to save his
dear Columbia from assassination, and when he had succeeded, and
because he had succeeded, he was assassinated himself. Faithful
Lincoln died; Columbia his passionate lover lives, and weeps upon his
coffin. Henceforth, Mount Vernon and Oak Ridge Cemetery shall share
her love, and be kept green by the watering of her tears.</p>
               <lg type="stanza">
                  <l>"In the God of battles trust!</l>
                  <l>Die we may--die we must;</l>
                  <l>But oh! where can dust to dust</l>
                  <l>Be consigned so well,</l>
                  <l>As where heaven its dews shall shed</l>
                  <l>On the martyred patriot's bed,</l>
                  <l>And the rocks shall raise their head</l>
                  <l>Of his deeds to tell?"</l>
               </lg>
               <p>Of all the distinguished rulers of the earth, no other one
has ever been borne to the tomb amid such extensive preparations to do
him honor. His funeral procession may be said to have been more than
one thousand miles long! On each side of the track over which the
escort passed, mourning citizens did all that the ingenuity of
affection could devise, by day and by night, to testify their sense of
the great loss sustained; and in that portion of it which streamed
through the city of New-York, taking hours to pass a given point, none
had a better right than the lowly company of blacks representing the
freedmen, who regarded the President as their "good friend." They
carried a plain white banner, bearing these touching mottoes: "Our
Emancipator." "To thousands of bondmen he gave liberty." Yes, the poor
tortured
<pb n="15"/>
                  <figure entity="gordon15">
                     <figDesc>15th page of
W. R. Gordon's The Sin of Reviling, and Its Work.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
slave never drew more largely upon any heart that ached for his
relief. Mr. Lincoln believed in universal freedom to all God's
creatures. He showed how deeply he felt, that</p>
               <lg type="stanza">
                  <l>"Fleecy locks and black complexion</l>
                  <l>Cannot forfeit nature's claim;</l>
                  <l>Skins may differ, but
affection</l>
                  <l>Dwells in black and white the same."</l>
               </lg>
               <p>God rules, and most fearfully has he answered the prayers,
and the groans, and the tears of millions in this land, who have lived
and died the victims of heart-rending oppression. God has so combined
circumstances in his wonder-working providence, that the mad
fanaticism of slavery insulting freedom should be the means of its own
extinction amid the execrations of the world; and the <hi rend="italic">terrible retribution</hi> comes by the hands of one
elevated to honor and power from among the most despised class of the
Southern population! History, in doing justice to our "Great
Emancipator," will inscribe upon his tablet the sentiment of Cowper to
Wilberforce:</p>
               <lg type="stanza">
                  <l>"Enjoy what thou hast won, esteem and love,</l>
                  <l>From all the just on earth, and all the blest above."</l>
               </lg>
               <p>But it will no doubt be said, that superlative eulogy upon
the departed must be expected from his admirers; and while the late
catastrophe will dispose all to silent acquiescence, yet the proper
discount must not be forgotten in the due estimate of his
character. To meet this in advance, we shall seek our justification in
quotations from those very prints that have done the most for his
defamation. A worldwide celebrated sheet, well known for the
bitterness of its opposition to Mr. Lincoln when he was alive, upon
the announcement of his tragic death put on mourning; and, under the
date of April seventeenth, thus soberly discoursed:</p>
               <p>"When the most experienced and reputable statesmen of the
country came to opposite conclusions, it is creditable to the
strength, solidity, and modesty of Mr. Lincoln's mind that he acted
with a cautious and hesitating deliberation proportioned rather to a
sense of his great responsibilities than to a
<pb n="16"/>
                  <figure entity="gordon16">
                     <figDesc>16th page of
W. R. Gordon's The Sin of Reviling, and Its Work.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
theatrical notion of political stage effect." "If we look for the
elements of character which have contributed to the extraordinary and
constantly growing popularity of Mr. Lincoln, they are not far to
seek. The kindly, companionable, jovial turn of his disposition, free
from every taint of affectation, puerile vanity, or <hi rend="italic">parvenu</hi> insolence, conveyed a strong impression of
worth, sense, and solidity, as well as goodness of heart. He never
disclosed the slightest symptom that he was dazzled or elated by his
great position, or that it was incumbent upon him to be any body but
plain Abraham Lincoln." "His freedom from any such upstart
affectations was one of the good points of his character; it betokened
his genuineness and sincerity." "The total abstinence from
Mr. Lincoln's sentiments and bearing of any thing lofty or chivalric,
and the hesitating slowness of his decisions, did not denote any
feebleness of character. He has given a signal proof of a strong and
manly nature in the fact, that although he surrounded himself with the
most considerable and experienced statesmen of his party, none of them
were able to take advantage of his inexperience and gain any
conspicuous ascendency over him. All his chief decisions have been his
own; formed, indeed, after much anxious and brooding consultation, but
in the final result, the fruit of his own independent volition." "The
loss of such a man, in such a crisis; of a man who possessed so large
and growing a share of the public confidence, and whose administration
has recently borrowed new lustre from the crowning achievements of our
armies; of a ruler whom victory was inspiring with the wise and
paternal magnanimity which sought to make the conciliation as cordial
as the strife has been deadly: the loss of such a President, at such a
conjuncture, is an afflicting dispensation which bows a disappointed
and stricken nation in sorrow more deep, sincere, and universal than
ever before supplicated the compassion of pitying Heaven."</p>
               <p>This is, well said, and has only the disadvantage of being
<hi rend="italic">extorted</hi> truth. Coming from the editorial columns
of the print referred to, and put in contrast with its former
relentless persecution of this good man, and now confessedly,
well-deserving President, it must be perfectly amazing to all those
<pb n="17"/>
                  <figure entity="gordon17">
                     <figDesc>17th page of
W. R. Gordon's The Sin of Reviling, and Its Work.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
who have accredited it with honesty, and have yielded their feelings
to its guidance.</p>
               <p>Again, we take up another widely circulated daily newspaper
of the same date, still more remarkable for its vituperative
language. About a month before his death, referring to the President
and Vice-President, it informed us that we had "a <hi rend="italic">jester</hi> and a <hi rend="italic">drunkard</hi>: at the
head of the Government." But now we find it in mourning too, and
pouring out incense to the former victim of its gross abuse. We read
the following:</p>
               <p>"It is as if a pall overhung the land, and in the shadow of
it dwelled a chilled and awe-struck people. A brotherhood of
sorrow--sorrow so poignant that it makes strong men weep, and veteran
soldiers shudder--has brought all classes and all parties to the drear
level of companions in misfortune." "And indeed it has rarely happened
that a people have been visited with such cause for lamentation. Had
it pleased God, by disease or accident, to take from us our
Chief-Magistrate, the stroke would have been less; but to see him
stricken down by the brutal rage of an assassin, murdered at the very
threshold of the gate of peace he was about to open, abruptly hurled
from his sphere of usefulness at the crisis of the Republic's fate, in
such a misfortune, all that is horrible and pitiable and calamitous
has been concentrated into one fatal moment to overwhelm the country
with affliction." "Mr. Lincoln, of those in power, was the best friend
of the South. In his kind-heartedness, he withstood and baffled the
vindictiveness and fanaticism of the radicals of his party. It is
known that he had prepared and was about to publish a Proclamation of
General Amnesty, so conciliatory in its tone, and so honorable in its
conditions, that it would have been acceptable to a large portion of
the South, as well as the conservative people of the North." "No
fitter requiem to Abraham Lincoln than the song of peace swelling from
the grateful hearts of his countrymen."</p>
               <p>These editorials go to the extreme of eulogy, and while
they are gratifying to the friends of the deceased, though coming in
strange contrast with previous ones of a very opposite character from
the same source, they must be amazing
<pb n="18"/>
                  <figure entity="gordon18">
                     <figDesc>18th page of
W. R. Gordon's The Sin of Reviling, and Its Work.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
to his enemies, whom they thus acknowledge to have deceived by a false
presentation and cruel persecution of a character the most illustrious
among men. The formers and leaders of opinions which have been
encouragement to "Knights of the Golden Circle," and to traitors of
every hue, present beautiful sketches of the moral and official worth
of the man whom, when living, they reviled; when dead, they affect to
honor!</p>
               <p>In the progress of the latter panegyric, we meet the
exclamation: "O the disgrace of it, the shame of it, the peril, if
ever that crime should be identified with the American character!"
Now, with the American character it can never be identified; the loyal
masses have taken care of that: but with those who have employed the
press, in the detestable service of <hi rend="italic">reviling</hi> must
be identified by the law of God, and the rectified opinion of people
betrayed into a vindictive feeling against the ruler of our
country. Did the bullet of the assassin suddenly change a <hi rend="italic">tyrant</hi> into "the best friend of the South"? "O shame!
where is thy blush?"</p>
               <p>Although these utterances, if honest, can be considered
only as intonations of the penitence of remorse, we gladly accept them
as confirmatory of what has been said in simple justice to the
distinguished character of the honored dead. "He rests from his
labors, and his works do follow him." "The righteous shall be held in
everlasting remembrance; but the name of the wicked shall rot."
"Blessed are they which are persecuted for righteousness' sake, for
theirs is the Kingdom of God." While American literature shall last,
Bryant's beautiful commemorative poem shall live:</p>
               <lg type="stanza">
                  <head>ABRAHAM LINCOLN.</head>
                  <l>O slow to smite, and swift to spare,</l>
                  <l>Gentle, and merciful
and just!</l>
                  <l>Who in the fear of God didst bear</l>
                  <l>The sword of
power, a nation's trust!</l>
               </lg>
               <lg type="stanza">
                  <l>In sorrow by thy bier we stand,</l>
                  <l>Amid the awe that hushes
all,</l>
                  <l>And speak the anguish of a land</l>
                  <l>That shook with
horror at thy fall.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb n="19"/>
               <p>
                  <figure entity="gordon19">
                     <figDesc>19th page of
W. R. Gordon's The Sin of Reviling, and Its
Work.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <lg type="stanza">
                  <l>Thy task is done; the bond are free;</l>
                  <l>We bear thee to an honored grave,</l>
                  <l>Whose proudest
monument shall be</l>
                  <l>The broken fetters of the slave.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg type="stanza">
                  <l>Pure was thy life; its bloody close</l>
                  <l>Hath placed thee with the sons of light,</l>
                  <l>Among the
noble hosts of those</l>
                  <l>Who perished in the cause of
Right.</l>
               </lg>
               <p>Before closing, I wish to impress upon my hearers that I
speak from no partisan feeling, nor in the interest of any party or
administration as such, but in the behalf of our Government and the
Rulers of our people. Any other course would be a desecration of
Sabbath and Pulpit, and an imposition upon my audience. But let it be
understood, that while party politics must not be brought into the
sphere of religion, religion must be carried into politics, because
God has commanded it. All the old Prophets were politicians, and the
leaders of political opinion. They gave constant instruction to the
people, on the subject of their political duties; and Paul, the
Apostle, as you have heard, is very emphatic on this point. Every
gospel minister is bound, by his example, to enforce in the pulpit the
great principles of Christian obligation to the State, applicable to
all alike, leaving it to the conscience and honesty of every man to
carry them out by the loyalty of his conduct, in any party with which
his own convictions of duty shall lead him to operate. Whatever others
may do, it is the duty of the men of the Church to listen to the voice
of the pulpit on this point, so long as the moral law is made a
subject of exposition, and so long as the precept of Christ is
binding: "Render unto Caesar the things that are Caesar's, and unto
God the things that are God's."</p>
               <p>We are now called to mourn over a mighty calamity, which
demands that the pulpit shall speak out. Humiliated by the present
dreadful state of public morals, as they relate to politics, it
becomes us to reflect upon the direful causes which have contributed
to this awful tragedy. We have more reason to weep for ourselves than
we have to mourn for our never-to-be-forgotten President, who fell a
victim to villainy in the rightful discharge of his duties. If this
treasonable spirit
<pb n="20"/>
                  <figure entity="gordon20">
                     <figDesc>20th page of
W. R. Gordon's The Sin of Reviling, and Its Work.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
which pervades the North, in complicity with Southern rebellion, is
not speedily put down, it will not be long before a reign of terror,
like that which desolated France in former days, shall be roaring like
a tornado over the land. The struggle for party purposes and power
among us, is carried on too often irrespective of the means by which
they should be attained, and of the legitimate end for which parties
exist. Therefore it becomes every good man to reform or leave every
party that is guilty of this perversion. What but party rancor and
wrath have brought about this deplorable state of things? And oh! what
an absurdity! Are we not all brethren? Are we not all bound up in the
same great nationa1 interest! Is it wise to let the ship of state run
upon breakers, because of a contest about who shall hold the helm?
Shall mutiny among the mariners be allowable, when the possible result
may be the destruction of ship and cargo and all on board? Surely we
must see that instant reformation must be made, or all will be
lost. Every man of us has therefore a duty to perform toward the Ruler
of his people and all in official subordination, which he cannot evade
and be guiltless.</p>
               <p>1. When any party succeeds in placing its men in power, it
is the duty of all to cease opposition, and make the best of it. We
are responsible to God, who is the Author of civil society, for our
conduct in the political relations of life we hold. He is a God of
order and not of confusion, and those who work confusion in civil
society meet with stern rebukes in his word. Our Government is God's
production. The administration of it is a solemn trust from Him to us,
and woe to the man who feloniously interferes with its legitimate
operations. Rival parties are well enough, so long as they serve as
mutual checks; but whatever party is in power, it is the solemn duty
of its antagonist to protect it in the enjoyments of its rights, and
aid it in compassing the ends of good government and human
happiness. If errors of administration occur, reviling is not the way
to correct them; nor breeding confusion the way of promoting the
public interest.</p>
               <p>2. It is the duty, inseparable from moral order, of every
man to refrain from speaking evil of the Ruler of his people.</p>
               <pb n="21"/>
               <p>
                  <figure entity="gordon21">
                     <figDesc>21st page of
W. R. Gordon's The Sin of Reviling, and Its
Work.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <p>The President of our country is placed in possession of an
important trust, the honorable and conscientious discharge of which,
so far as can be, is secured by his oath of office. Now, when he takes
this oath, every citizen comes under a corresponding obligation,
underlying and implied in the privilege of citizenship, to obey in all
things the requirements of law; and this involves the further duty of
rendering such a personal respect for his office's sake, that the
President shall not be reviled by tongue or pen; because all such
reviling contributes to the damage of his official character and to
his personal danger.</p>
               <p>Had all our Northern people acted according to this obvious
duty, I believe Mr. Lincoln would not have met a violent death. Some
may say that the immediate tools of the rebellion killed him; but when
we are horrified by many of the North feloniously clapping hands over
his murder, how can we avoid the conclusion that much of the dreadful
sentiment responsible for the bloody deed originated at the North? May
God forgive all his detractors, and wash away their murderous sin!</p>
               <p>The safety of our institutions and the strength of our
Government depend upon the intelligence and moral honesty of the
masses. Nowhere has the Christian a better opportunity for doing good
than in his political relations. Let him carry the influence of his
religion into this great rolling sea of human conflict. Let his agency
be especially directed to allay the fierceness of party strife, and by
his colloquial powers and meekness of deportment aim to quiet the
turbulence of those whose intemperance of language and violence of
action always exert an evil influence dangerous to the
Government. This country is largely indebted for its political
greatness to the Church of Christ. From the beginning, religious and
civil freedom have gone hand in hand for mutual protection and the
common welfare. And unless the spirit of the religion of Christ
continue to shed its benignant influence in regulating and directing
public opinion with regard to official stations, our republican
government will soon find its grave in the anarchy of infidel
recklessness and disregard of human rights. Conflicting opinions and
rival ambitions, uncontrolled by a supreme regard to the authority of
God and the majesty of
<pb n="22"/>
                  <figure entity="gordon22">
                     <figDesc>22nd page of
W. R. Gordon's The Sin of Reviling, and Its Work.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
law, and directed by the unholy aims of the ill-designing, will bring
down to the dust our political fabric, to the joy of all despots and
the disgrace and ruin of the theory of democracy.</p>
               <p>Now there is nothing to prevent this but the diffusion of
intelligence and the religious enlightenment of the public
conscience. This is a sphere of action in which every Christian and
good citizen will find a large work for himself to do. Hitherto, the
wonderful transmission of the Administration of this great Government
from one party to another, by the quiet power of the ballot-box,
without the intimidation of armed men, and bloody scenes enacted by
lawless desperadoes, has been almost regarded as a miracle by the
powers of Europe. But now, for the first time in our history, the wild
fury of party strife has brought upon us humiliation and disgrace in
the eyes of the world. Oh! it is a fearful precedent; and unless the
needed reformation be at once begun, by those who stand at the head of
public influence, and who so largely control public opinion, diffusing
by the press a spirit of loyalty or insubordination, as they see fit;
unless every well-meaning man does his duty toward the general
Government, no matter what party administer it, we have the gloomy
prospect that the reign of terror, by the agency of wickedness, will
soon put the extinguisher upon republican freedom. Let, then, the sins
of the <hi rend="italic">reviling tongue</hi> be checked, and the
dangers from the spirit of treason will be evaded. Let the pure
principles of the Gospel more pervadingly enter our political affairs
and economical arrangements, and our beautiful country shall outride
the storm that has so fearfully endangered her existence. Hitherto she
has proved a safe asylum for all who have come to her
shores. Religious persecution may be almost said never to have
disgraced our land. Liberty of conscience and civil rights we have
been always taught to respect, and the march of improvement has never
been called to a halt. We therefore owe it to God, we owe it to
ourselves, we owe it to the world, that every man be a sentinel upon
the walls of freedom, ever ready to do his whole duty to his country
and her rulers.</p>
               <p>"As ye would that men shall do to you, do ye even so to
them." This simple all-comprehensive rule, is the best safe-guard of
public and private rights; and if it be deeply impressed upon
<pb n="23"/>
                  <figure entity="gordon23">
                     <figDesc>23rd page of
W. R. Gordon's The Sin of Reviling, and Its Work.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
the public conscience, and made the basis of action in our political
duties, the smiles of heaven shall be our sunshine, and happiness and
peace be domiciled in every habitation. Invoking the blessing and
guidance of God upon all our rulers and our people, we close with this
command and promise: "<hi rend="italic">Loose the bands of wickedness,
undo the heavy burdens</hi>, LET THE OPPRESSED GO FREE, BREAK EVERY
YOKE. <hi rend="italic">Then</hi> shall thy light break forth as the
morning, and Thine health shall spring forth speedily; and thy
righteousness shall go before thee; the glory of the Lord shall be thy
rearward." (Is. 58: 6, 8.)</p>
               <p>A REMINISCENCE</p>
               <p>THE unhappy close of life to our beloved President, has
given to the following poem an impressive interest, and has suggested
the propriety of its appearance in the present connection.</p>
               <p>Mr. F. B. Carpenter, the artist, referring, in a letter to
the <title>Evening Post</title>, to a certain occasion when
Mr. Lincoln spoke feelingly of this poem observing that he would give
a great deal to know who wrote it, says: "Then, half closing his eyes,
he repeated to me the lines which I inclose to you. Greatly pleased
and interested, I told him I would like, if ever an opportunity
occurred, to write them down from his lips. He said he would some time
try to give them to me. A few days afterward he asked me to accompany
him to the temporary studio of Mr. Swayne, the sculptor, who was
making a bust of him at the Treasury Department. While he was sitting
for the bust, I was suddenly reminded of the poem, and said to him
that then would be a good time to dictate it to me. He complied, and
sitting upon some books at his feet, as nearly as I can remember, I
wrote the lines down, one by one, from his lips."</p>
               <q direct="unspecified">
                  <text>
                     <body>
                        <head>OH! WHY SHOULD THE SPIRIT OF MORTAL BE PROUD?</head>
                        <lg type="stanza">
                           <l>Oh! why should the spirit of mortal be proud?</l>
                           <l>Like a
swift, fleeting meteor, a fast-flying cloud, </l>
                           <l>A flash of the
lightning, a break of the wave, </l>
                           <l>He passeth from life to his
rest in the grave.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <lg type="stanza">
                           <l>The leaves of the oak and the willow shall fade, </l>
                           <l>Be
scattered around and together be laid: </l>
                        </lg>
                        <pb n="24"/>
                        <p>
                           <figure entity="gordon24">
                              <figDesc>24th page of
W. R. Gordon's The Sin of Reviling, and Its Work.</figDesc>
                           </figure>
                        </p>
                        <lg type="stanza">
                           <l>And the young and the old, and the low and the high</l>
                           <l>Shall
moulder to dust, and together shall lie. </l>
                        </lg>
                        <lg type="stanza">
                           <l>The infant a mother attended and loved; </l>
                           <l>The mother that
infants affection who proved; </l>
                           <l>The husband that mother and
infant who blessed--</l>
                           <l>Each, all, are away to their dwellings of
rest. </l>
                        </lg>
                        <lg type="stanza">
                           <l>The hand of the king that the sceptre hath borne; </l>
                           <l>The
brow of the priest that the mitre hath worn; </l>
                           <l>The eye of the
sage and the heart of the brave</l>
                           <l>Are hidden and lost in the
depths of the grave. </l>
                        </lg>
                        <lg type="stanza">
                           <l>The peasant, whose lot was to sow and to reap; </l>
                           <l>The
herdsman, who climbed with his goats up the steep; </l>
                           <l>The beggar,
who wandered in search of his bread, </l>
                           <l>Have faded away like the
grass that we tread. </l>
                        </lg>
                        <lg type="stanza">
                           <l>So the multitude goes, like the flower or the weed</l>
                           <l>That
withers away to let others succeed; </l>
                           <l>So the multitude comes,
even those we behold, </l>
                           <l>To repeat every tale that has often been
told. </l>
                        </lg>
                        <lg type="stanza">
                           <l>For we are the same that our fathers have been; </l>
                           <l>We see
the same sights our fathers have seen-- </l>
                           <l>We drink the same
stream and view the same sun--</l>
                           <l>And run the same course our
fathers have run. </l>
                        </lg>
                        <lg type="stanza">
                           <l>The thoughts we are thinking our fathers would think; </l>
                           <l>From the death we are shrinking our fathers would shrink; </l>
                           <l>To the life we are clinging they also would cling; </l>
                           <l>But it
speeds for us all, like a bird on the wing. </l>
                        </lg>
                        <lg type="stanza">
                           <l>They loved, but the story we cannot unfold; </l>
                           <l>They
scorned, but the heart of the haughty is cold; </l>
                           <l>They grieved,
but no wail from their slumber will come; </l>
                           <l>They joyed, but the
tongue of their gladness is dumb. </l>
                        </lg>
                        <lg type="stanza">
                           <l>They died, ay! they died; we things that are now, </l>
                           <l>That
walk on the turf that lies over their brow, </l>
                           <l>And make in their
dwellings a transient abode, </l>
                           <l>Meet the things that they met on
their pilgrimage road. </l>
                        </lg>
                        <lg type="stanza">
                           <l>Yea! hope and despondency, pleasure and pain, </l>
                           <l>We mingle
together in sunshine and rain; </l>
                           <l>And the smile and the tear, the
song and the dirge, Still follow</l>
                           <l>each other, like surge upon
surge. </l>
                        </lg>
                        <lg type="stanza">
                           <l>'Tis the wink of an eye, 'tis the draught of a breath; </l>
                           <l>From the blossom of health to the paleness of death, </l>
                           <l>From
the gilded saloon to the bier and the shroud- </l>
                           <l>Oh! why should
the spirit of mortal be proud? </l>
                        </lg>
                     </body>
                  </text>
               </q>
            </div2>
         </div1>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI.2>