<TEI.2>
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt n="President Lincoln's Death: Its Voice to the People">
            <title>President Lincoln's Death: Its Voice to the People</title>
            <author>Hall, Gordon</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Compiled and edited by</resp>
               <name>Beck
Center</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent/>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Lewis H. Beck Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Emory University</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Atlanta,
Georgia</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>1996 Emory
University. Permission is granted to download, transmit, or otherwise
reproduce, distribute or display the contributions to the work claimed
by Emory University for non-profit educational purposes, provided
this header is included in its entirety.  For inquiries about
commercial uses, contact the Director, 
Pitts Theology Library, Emory
University, Atlanta, Georgia 30322</p>
            </availability>
            <date>1999</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Lincoln
Sermons Project</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Hall,
Gordon. President Lincoln's Death: Its Voice to the People. A
Discourse.  Preached in the First Church, Northampton, April 19,
1865. Northampton, Mass. Trumbull &amp; Gere
. . . . . Printers. 1865.</bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This text derives from the Special Collections 
of Pitts Theology Library, Emory University, and is produced in 
collaboration with the Lewis H. Beck Center a, the Emory 
Preservation Office, and Pitts Theology Library.</p>
            <p>TRANSCRIBER: Lewis H. Beck Center and Emory University 
Preservation Office.</p>
            <p>PRODUCER:  BookLab, Inc., 1606 Headway Circle, 
Suite 100, Austin, TX 78754</p>
            <p>CAPTURE DEVICE: XEROX DocuImage 620S flatbed scanner</p>
            <p>CAPTURE DETAILS: Scanner software: XEROX ScanTool 
version 4.2.3; no gamma correction; images are all bitonal.</p>
            <p>CHANGE HISTORY: Using the Adobe Photoshop Batch Processor, 
we interpolated  the original TIFF files to 8-bit grays, 
and altered the resolution to 144 dpi, producing screen 
images twice the original size.  We then saved them in 
JPEG format.  We produced GIF thumbnails from the JPEG files.</p>
            <p>RESOLUTION: 600 ppi</p>
            <p>COMPRESSION: Resolution 144 per inch with Constrain 
Properties to 72 per inch.</p>
            <p>SOURCE: Original documents.</p>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>1999</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Scott Ellis</name>
               <resp>Staff</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <item>SGML tags inserted in compliance
with TEI guidelines using TEILITE</item>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div1 id="hall.001" n="President Lincoln's Death: Its Voice to the People" type="text">
            <head pn="1"> 
               <bibl> 
                  <title>President
Lincoln's Death: Its Voice to the People </title> 
                  <date>April 19,
1865</date> 
                  <pubPlace>First Church, Northampton </pubPlace>
                  <author>Hall, Gordon </author> 
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Northampton,
Mass.</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Trumbull &amp; Gere . . . . . Printers</publisher>
                     <date>1865</date>
                  </imprint> 
               </bibl> 
            </head>
            <p pn="1">
               <figure entity="hall1">
                  <figDesc>1st page of Gordon Hall's President
Lincoln's Death: Its Voice to the People.</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <p pn="1">PRESIDENT LINCOLN'S DEATH;</p>
            <p pn="1">Its Voice to the People.</p>
            <p pn="1">A DISCOURSE</p>
            <p pn="1">BY</p>
            <p pn="1">GORDON HALL, D.D.,</p>
            <p pn="1">Pastor of the Edwards Church.</p>
            <p pn="1">PREACHED IN THE FIRST CHURCH, NORTHAMPTON,</p>
            <p pn="1">April 19, 1865.</p>
            <p pn="1">NORTHAMPTON, MASS.</p>
            <p pn="1">TRUMBULL &amp; GERE PRINTERS</p>
            <p pn="1">1865.</p>
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p pn="2">
               <figure entity="hall2">
                  <figDesc>2nd page of
Gordon Hall's President Lincoln's Death: Its Voice to the
People.</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p pn="3">
               <figure entity="hall3">
                  <figDesc>3rd page of
Gordon Hall's President Lincoln's Death: Its Voice to the
People.</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <p pn="3">NORTHAMPTON, APRIL
20TH, 1865.</p>
            <p pn="3">REV. GORDON HALL, D. D.,</p>
            <p pn="3">Dear Sir:</p>
            <p pn="3">In common with our
fellow-citizens, we listened with great interest to your discourse
delivered on the 19th inst., co-temporaneously with the funeral
obsequies of the late lamented President of the United States.</p>
            <p pn="3">Whatever may be the ultimate verdict of contemplative minds
on the suggestions contained in that discourse, we hesitate not to say
that they are deserving of the most serious consideration, and we
respectfully solicit a copy for publication. Your compliance with this
request will gratify great numbers of your fellow-citizens.</p>
            <p pn="3">WM. ALLEN, D.D., First
Cong. Church,
					<lb/>E. WILLIAMS, Deacon
do.		do. 
					<lb/>ERASTUS HOPKINS, Edwards
Church,
					<lb/>W. H. STODDARD, Deacon
do. 
					<lb/>JOSIAH D. WHITNEY,	do. 
					<lb/>L. MALTBY,			do.
					<lb/>HENRY BRIGHT, Episcopal Church,
					<lb/>A. P. PECK,		Second
Cong. Church,
					<lb/>CHRISTOPHER CLARKE,	do. 
					<lb/>LEWIS PHELPS, Methodist
Church,
					<lb/>J. S. BAKER, Deacon
Baptist Church.</p>
            <p pn="3">TO PRES. WM. ALLEN, D.D., and others.</p>
            <p pn="3">The discourse which you
request for publication was, as you are aware, hastily prepared. Some
of its points are not propositions or averments, but to use your own
expression, "suggestions," not positive opinions in my own mind. If
you believe that good would come of publishing the discourse, it is at
your service.</p>
            <p pn="3">Yours very
respectfully,</p>
            <p pn="3">GORDON
HALL.</p>
            <p pn="3">Northampton, April 21st, 1866.</p>
            <pb n="4"/>
<!-- blank page -->
<!--            <p>
               <figure entity="hall4">
                  <figDesc>4th page of
Gordon Hall's President Lincoln's Death: Its Voice to the
People.</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p> -->
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p pn="5">
               <figure entity="hall5">
                  <figDesc>5th page of
Gordon Hall's President Lincoln's Death: Its Voice to the
People.</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <div2 id="hall.002" n="PRES. LINCOLN'S DEATH--ITS VOICE T0 THE PEOPLE." type="sermon">
               <head pn="5">PRES. LINCOLN'S DEATH--ITS VOICE T0 THE PEOPLE.</head>
               <epigraph pn="5">
                  <p pn="5">PS. XLVI: 10.--BE STILL AND KNOW THAT I AM GOD.</p>
                  <p pn="5">PS. XXXVI: 6.--THY JUDGMENTS ARE A GREAT DEEP.</p>
                  <p pn="5">JOB XXVI: 14.--LO THESE ARE PARTS OF HIS WAYS; BUT HOW LITTLE A
PORTION IS HEARD OF HIM?</p>
               </epigraph>
               <p pn="5">GOD'S PROVIDENCE SOVEREIGN--UNSEARCHABLE--INSRUCTIVE,--these are
the thoughts to occupy us.</p>
               <p pn="5">THERE are times when we can only be still, wonder and
adore. We are awe-struck. We cease from man and are thrown entirely
upon a sovereign God. The only voice we hear bids us be still and know
that it is God.</p>
               <p pn="5">When, on wings of lightning, the intelligence went abroad
that our honored and beloved President had been assassinated, we were
speechless with amazement and horror. We thought of God upon the
throne,--of God as appointing all events. For the moment we forgot the
pistol, the wound, the assassin, and in silent reverence bowed before
the ever-living, only wise and sovereign God.</p>
               <p pn="5">Then the distressing fact began to take possession of
us. We realized it. The plot had succeeded. The assassin's weapon had
done the deed. Murder accomplished--other murders
attempted--blood-shedding not more extensive, only because frustrated
by a merciful Providence.</p>
               <pb n="6"/>
               <p pn="6">
                  <figure entity="hall6">
                     <figDesc>6th page of Gordon
Hall's President Lincoln's Death: Its Voice to the
People.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <p pn="6">Assassination in our Capital! The victim, the nation's
President! Even so. We had thought, we had feared, he might die of
over-exertion and fatigue, and of disease thus induced. We had not
forgotten the attempt made upon his life on the way from his western
home to his seat of magistracy. But since that time there had been no
demonstration against him, and we were not expecting him to fall by
the murderer's stroke. 
	But now--that head, so full of noble and generous thought, has
been penetrated by the cruel bullet. That heart whose every beat was
loyalty to the constitution, and patriotic love, beats no more. That
pulse whose every throb was an energy for the country's good, is still
in death. 
	Is this God's Providence? Can he have foreseen and permitted
it? "Be still and know that I am God." 
	Perhaps here was a great national danger--that we were
installing man in the place of God. We had come almost to lean upon
our President--to make him our reliance--so honest, so good, so
wise. He was at the helm, <hi rend="italic">therefore</hi> we were
safe. One man and another,--civilian or general--we distrusted. But we
settled down upon the thought, Mr. LINCOLN holds the helm. All will be
managed well--<hi rend="italic">so we felt safe</hi>. Our temptation was
disclosed in the question which so many of us have heard and asked,
What shall we now do? What is to become of us now? Much as is the
throne of heaven were vacated. "God is a jealous God. His glory he
will not give to another."</p>
               <p pn="6">Perhaps it would have been too much glory for one man to
have conducted us quite through the perils and difficulties of these
times. It was enough for Moses to lead the Lord's hosts through the
wilderness. At the borders of Canaan his office ceased. Joshua must
put God's elect into possession of the land of promise, and so Jehovah
is seen the God of both Moses and Joshua.</p>
               <p pn="6">Thus is God A SOVEREIGN. He can raise up an
instrumentality--employ it so long as seems good to him--then set it
aside for another; while we, impotent, astounded, can only behold in
silence, be still and know that it is God.</p>
               <pb n="7"/>
               <p pn="7">
                  <figure entity="hall7">
                     <figDesc>7th page of Gordon
Hall's President Lincoln's Death: Its Voice to the
People.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <p pn="7">Not only SOVEREIGN is God's Providence, but UNSEARCHABLE. As it is
above our power, so is it beyond our comprehension.</p>
               <p pn="7">How wonderful the raising up of this man! How few of us had
thought of him as a candidate for the chief magistracy, before his
nomination. And when the telegraph announced him as the man selected
for the vote of the nation, how many of us inquired, Why? What have
been his antecedents? What are his claims? What fitness has he for
this supremely honorable and responsible position?</p>
               <p pn="7">But what remarkable qualifications he developed!
Conscientiousness--practical
wisdom--independence--firmness--magnanimity and
generosity-gentleness--power of endurance--control of men. We came to
see why Providence placed him in the chair. Some men of courtly
manners and courtly expression criticised his homely ways and style of
language; but the people loved him, trusted him, and his clear,
strong, sound utterances carried conviction. Polished diplomatists
abroad and proud aristocrats spoke contemptuously of his proclamations
and state papers, but they had come to regard him as an able and
sagacious ruler. And now that he is deceased we shall find them using
towards him terms of high respect. Here, among ourselves, criticisms
are hushed, political differences forgotten, party rancor nobly
subdued and we are all one great family of mourners.</p>
               <p pn="7">We had, I said, feared at times for his life. Early in his
administration we had trembled, lest that same spirit which aimed a
death-blow at the nation's life should strike for the life of its
President. But so kindly had he been protected and spared, amid such
malignity and perils, that we had become confident, much as if we
supposed him to possess a charmed life, under the divine
guardianship. Then he was stricken down. Jehovah's judgments are a
great deep.</p>
               <p pn="7">Taken away, just when we wanted his practical
sagacity--when great, difficult questions were coming up, calling for
his wise intuitions. How common was it for our public prints to touch
upon matters of vast concern soon to demand solu-
<pb n="8"/>
                  <figure entity="hall8">
                     <figDesc>8th page of Gordon Hall's
President Lincoln's Death: Its Voice to the People.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
tion, and then dismiss them with the conclusion, the President's good
sense will guide him to the right result; better that, even, was
sometimes said, than the deliberations of Congress.</p>
               <p pn="8">We do not know why God has taken him just now--and why he
allows such vindictive malice to triumph. God's ways are SOVEREIGN and
UNSEARCHABLE. "Be still and know that I am God. Humble thyself under
his mighty hand."</p>
               <p pn="8">And yet God's ways are INSTRUCTIVE to us. We profoundly
acknowledge the truthfulness of Job's exclamation, "How little a
portion is heard of him;" but it is also true that these are "parts of
his ways." Part of his plan we can understand. His ways and meaning we
can interpret to some extent.</p>
               <p pn="8">Among the lessons plainly taught us, this is one:--</p>
               <p pn="8">That the Most High is not dependent upon instrumentalities
which seem to us indispensable. If consulted, we should have said
ABRAHAM LINCOLN is the man, <hi rend="italic">the only man</hi>, for the
place he occupies. We do not see upon whose shoulders his mantle could
fall. We have used our liberty of fault-finding. I have. You
have--doubtless. But when I faced the question, <hi rend="italic">For
whom</hi> would you displace him, my complainings were hushed. I knew,
of course, that perfection was not to be expected. Nor was my standard
of perfection to be accepted as faultless. No, after all, God save
ABRAHAM LINCOLN. I do not know the man in whom I could so largely
confide; for his true heart, unselfish aim, good judgment and steady
hand. I almost thought Providence could not set forth the man. But the
Infinite One is teaching us that he can work out his own plans--can
lead on our republic to its destiny--without being limited to servants
who seem to us indispensable.</p>
               <p pn="8">Another part of God's way which we understand is the lesson
of submission, and trust in him. Not a doubt this is a part of the
instruction God would give us. We are to submit--and it is not to the
treasonable plot that we submit, to the vindictiveness or malice of
man, but to the sovereign, un-
<pb n="9"/>
                  <figure entity="hall9">
                     <figDesc>9th page of Gordon Hall's
President Lincoln's Death: Its Voice to the People.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
searchable will of God. "Shall there be evil in a city and the Lord
hath not done it?" This momentous event has not taken place unbeknown
to God. He is not surprised or taken at unawares. He has not been
false to the rectitude and goodness of his character. For <hi rend="italic">some good end</hi> he has suffered it--<hi rend="italic">he
knows why</hi>--we submit and we trust.</p>
               <p pn="9">Another plain lesson from the event which brings us
together is the call to thankfulness that our honored President was
spared to do his great work. To conclude entirely this gigantic
conflict--to adjust the terms of reconstruction --to bring the
revolted states back to their allegiance--this it seems was not
included in his work. But, to preside over the country in its greatest
troubles --to be commander-in-chief of our armies in its bloodiest and
most perilous times--to stand at the head of the nation when foreign
powers were most unfriendly--to do all this with consummate ability
and success, until the southern ports were in our hands, and he could
declare the blockade at an end--till the chief commander of the
insurgents had surrendered with his forces, and the confederate
capitol was in our hands--till the war was virtually ended and he
could demand of foreign powers to treat us as a sovereign nation who
had subdued the great rebellion--this was his work in our behalf. And
NOW instead of complaining that we are bereaved of him, we will thank
a favoring Providence that he was so long spared, to achieve for us
blessings so invaluable.</p>
               <p pn="9">Another lesson. We are called to gratitude that we have
hope for our deceased President as a christian man. We have not loved
him in a manner altogether selfish--have we? Simply for what he was to
us? We wished him good. It was a sincere ejaculation often uttered,
"God bless ABRAHAM LINCOLN." We meant it--that God would bless him,
not only that he might bless, but that he might be blessed. And we
believe God did bless him, with the divine guidance and acceptance,
and indwelling grace. That he was a diligent student of the scriptures
we know. That he committed his
<pb n="10"/>
                  <figure entity="hall10">
                     <figDesc>10th page of Gordon
Hall's President Lincoln's Death: Its Voice to the
People.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
ways to God in prayer, and loved the Savior, he testified. That he
rested his hope on the Great Redeemer, we believe, and that he has
been called up higher,--his warfare accomplished,--the crown of the
faithful bestowed upon him by the Prince of glory.</p>
               <p pn="10">Furthermore, we know that <hi rend="italic">Mr. LINCOLN'S
continuance in office would not have been so favorable to God's plan
as his removal</hi>. How do we know that? Because God removed
him. This proves it.</p>
               <p pn="10">Now, my friends, I have a few plain, honest words to
say. And be pleased not to misunderstand neither misrepresent. Honest
words should be spoken and honestly received at the funeral of honest
ABRAHAM LINCOLN.</p>
               <p pn="10">I have, I trust, a conscientious regard for charity. I make
a broad distinction between the instigators and leaders--the
influential, responsible conspirators in this great rebellion and
their deluded instruments. With the great mass of the common people at
the South--what would I do? Hang them?-- exterminate them? I would
not. With the rank and file in the Confederate army, the ignorant, the
misled, the conscripted--what would I do? Exile them?--imprison them?
By no means. The women,--bitter as many of them have been--the
children--would I fire their houses, and consign them to desolation?
No such thing. All these I would treat tenderly and afford them every
facility, every inducement to return to allegiance and live
comfortably again under the old flag of the union. I am willing to
overlook the past and call such my Southern brethren.</p>
               <p pn="10">But when it is proposed that the intelligent, deliberate,
persistent authors and master-spirits of this rebellion--the
intentional and voluntary assassins of the nation, should be released
from punishment--when you ask this, you ask me, for the sake of
sparing traitors, myself to turn traitor to justice and my
country. You ask too much.</p>
               <p pn="10">But how much has this to do with
Mr. Lincoln's death? I do not know. Perhaps nothing. I do not claim to
have had
<pb n="11"/>
                  <figure entity="hall11">
                     <figDesc>11th page of Gordon
Hall's President Lincoln's Death: Its Voice to the
People.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
access to heaven's counsels. Mark me, I do not assert,--I only
inquire. Would the policy of Mr. LINCOLN have been too lenient? Was he
tending, out of his great and good heart, to the extreme of mercy?</p>
               <p pn="11">But is not <hi rend="italic">mercy a sacred thing</hi>? Yes,
and I will tell you <hi rend="italic">what else is sacred</hi>. IT IS
JUSTICE. Is not the Gospel full of mercy? Yes, and I will tell you
why. Because atonement has been made--because justice was first
satisfied--the law was first "magnified and made honorable." "Without
the shedding of blood was no remission."</p>
               <p pn="11">I believe it should be said, in truth, that at the outset
of this war, the great study was how to restore the union without
harming slavery--the great study among our public men. And lately, it
was getting to be the great question, how to reconstruct the union
without harming rebels--prominent rebels--without harming their
persons, property or feelings. Our loyal colored troops must not
parade in captured Richmond. Why? Because there were enemies of our
country there whose delicate nerves would be injured. Black men--true
hearts--who had rushed to the defense of our government, and fought
bravely under the stars and stripes--of whom many had fallen a
sacrifice--whose blood was shed in warring with traitors--colored
forces, the very men who first entered the city and planted the
national banner there, must not be seen parading the streets, lest it
should interfere with the prejudices and sensibilities of traitors.</p>
               <p pn="11">For the same reason prayer must not be offered up in
Richmond for our President--and this was connived at. Well, <hi rend="italic">prayer was not offered; and a little after the President
was assassinated.</hi>
               </p>
               <p pn="11">It was even attempted to call back the flying rebels to ask
their advice as to how we should reconstruct Virginia's government. I
am not rehearsing fables. These are sober facts.</p>
               <p pn="11">I am forced to believe we were on the way to a mischievous
policy--well-meant, perhaps, but a mistaken and ruinous policy--one
which would have brought back upon us a refluent wave of corruption,
convulsion and distress. Treason was to be passed over as trivial. The
penalty of confiscation
<pb n="12"/>
                  <figure entity="hall12">
                     <figDesc>12th page of Gordon
Hall's President Lincoln's Death: Its Voice to the
People.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
was to be remitted. The great plantations were to be untouched. Upon
these great estates, the blacks, whether free or slave, were to be the
laborers. The large estate-owners would have immense patronage. They
would thus control the vote of their working-freedmen--or vote
themselves upon the basis of the old representation. The planters,
with their thousands of acres and thousands of serfs--with their old
spirit intensified and embittered, naturally would, and easily could,
league together and be masters of state action. They could make their
way back to Congress, renew covenant with unprincipled politicians of
the South, and we should have all the intrigue and corruption, and
violence and perils and war and blood-shed of days already past.</p>
               <p pn="12">Perhaps God meant us better things--so took his own way and
time to call us to vigilance and action. He showed us anew the temper
of this conspiracy. Its ruthless malignity was to be disclosed in the
assassination of our President. Who killed Mr. LINCOLN? The man that
fired the pistol? He was a mere agent--one factor in a great plot. He
was a mere out-growth of this great rebellion. The spirit which
attempted that same life four years ago--which has massacred and
starved our soldiers, which has shot down union men, has now
culminated in the horrible deed of the President's assassination.</p>
               <p pn="12">And this comes just at the time when the great military
leader of the rebellion, with his associate officers and forces was
let off, unhumbled even. How desperately we had fought! what
sacrifices! what rivers of blood, to reach the advantage we had
gained! what prayers had been offered that the great
conspirator-chieftain might be given into our power! The Almighty at
last had given Lee into our hands--reduced him to such weakness and
extremity that we could take him on our own terms; and we release him
as a man of honor and a gentleman. Who is General Lee? A man less
dishonorable than some of his followers? He has been the military
genius and bulwark of the rebellion. Against the country that
nourished and educated him and made him what he is, he used his every
talent and resource. He took sides with the traitors
<pb n="13"/>
                  <figure entity="hall13">
                     <figDesc>13th page of Gordon
Hall's President Lincoln's Death: Its Voice to the
People.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
--protracted the war as long as there was a gleam of hope--did all he
could to destroy our government, liberties and nation. And was this
the man to be treated with scrupulous courtesy?--to be dismissed as
having committed a venial offense? Was the great advantage God had
given us to be thus made light of? The rebel-chieftain is let go with
the honors of war. Then our President is stricken down in death. Did a
voice from on high say, "Let this man go and thy life for it?" I do
not affirm. I do not know.</p>
               <p pn="13">But of this I am confident, that the Almighty has
undertaken in behalf of the enslaved, oppressed millions of the
South. And this I know, that it is a dark day for the blacks when
Northern leaders and the arch-conspirators of the South fraternize,
and we take the hands that are reeking with the blood of our brothers
and sons and husbands. That was a dark cloud rising. Perhaps God meant
to scatter it with the winds and bolts of his righteous
indignation.</p>
               <p pn="13">It <hi rend="italic">is</hi> scattered. This awful atrocity
in our capital--this outbreak--this dread omen of the dangers which
slumber beneath us will stir up the cry for vigor and justice. NOT FOR
REVENGE, BUT JUSTICE. I am addressing men of sense. You know there is
a difference between revenge and justice. Do not allow yourselves to
be imposed upon by a juggle of words.</p>
               <p pn="13">Oh! the nation's heart is reached when the nation's Father
is murdered--that very man who most earnestly and tenderly sought the
best interests of those, his Southern children, who, with parricidal
arm, have laid him low in death. It was a second firing upon Sumter--a
firing upon the national life, which has fired the people anew to
self-defense--to see that gentleness with such traitors is a suicidal
crime, and to demand that they be put beyond the power of doing
further mischief.</p>
               <p pn="13">It is an event too which places in the chair a man whose
failing probably will not be a weak leniency.</p>
               <p pn="13">We have just had reported to us views of our now President
Johnson, expressed at a meeting of Iowa citizens in
<pb n="14"/>
                  <figure entity="hall14">
                     <figDesc>14th page of Gordon
Hall's President Lincoln's Death: Its Voice to the
People.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
Washington, Saturday evening, and communicated to the public through
Gov. Stone. He would pursue no policy, he said, which would prevent
the government from visiting condign punishment upon the guilty
authors of this rebellion. He regarded it as due to the loyal people
of the country, and to the memory of the thousands of brave men who
had fallen in defense of the union during this struggle, and to the
claims of justice and freedom throughout the world, that treason
should still be regarded as the highest crime under our constitution
and flag, and that treason should be rendered infamous for all time to
come. While he entertained these views, he should endeavor to gain the
confidence of the deceived and betrayed masses of the southern people,
regarding them as the proper material for reconstructing the Southern
states. For them he expressed deep sympathy--the betrayed and deluded
masses--earnestly desiring their return to allegiance and their
restoration to their former peace and prosperity.</p>
               <p pn="14">The same views he expressed in a speech made just after the
taking of Richmond. "Death, he says, to the conspirators--clemency to
their victims. I am in favor of leniency; but in my opinion evil-doers
should be punished. I say this--the halter for intelligent,
influential traitors. But to the honest boy, to the deluded man, who
has been deceived into the rebel ranks, I would extend leniency. I
would say, Return to your allegiance, renew your support to the
government and become a good citizen. But the leaders I would
hang."</p>
               <p pn="14">These are sound sentiments and the people will support him
in them. It verily seems as if the time was at hand when other
interests were to be held as precious as the honor and pride, the
property and the sensibilities of traitors.</p>
               <p pn="14">Perhaps Mr. LINCOLN died not only in God's good time but in
his own best time. I yield to no one in my veneration for that
wonderful man. I know not whether I would assign him a place inferior
even to that of Washington. But no man is infallible. What he would
have done I do not know. My confidence in him had become so great,
that it seemed to me 
<pb n="15"/>
                  <figure entity="hall15">
                     <figDesc>15th page of Gordon
Hall's President Lincoln's Death: Its Voice to the
People.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
he would be guided anything and everything. This much we know. He has
done his work nobly. And he has not lived to mar it. Had his virtue of
clemency become his failing--had his magnanimous, tender spirit
constrained him to propitiate the rebels instead of subduing them and
stripping them of power for further mischief--thus throwing away very
much of what our brave men earned upon the hard fought and bloody
field, and in the horrible prison--very much for which the
freedom-loving wait and long, the world over--his memory would not
have been that glorious, admirable record which will now stand upon
the page of history and the hearts of a grateful country. Now he has
not only served his country, but died for it. Too good, I almost
think--too kind to deal with unscrupulous, truculent traitors--he has
been taken to heaven, where there is a call only for gentle and loving
ministries.</p>
               <p pn="15">It becomes us to look earnestly at our own duty touching the
interests of justice--justice to the traitor--to the colored man--to
our country. There are times when God insists upon the infliction of
justice. His ancient covenant people he visited with defeat and
disaster until Achan was brought to justice. And Saul was removed from
the kingdom because he spared the king of the Amalekites, whom Jehovah
had sentenced to death. I am not an inspired Joshua or a prophet
Samuel to say, this man must be stoned and that man hewed in
pieces. But I cite these cases to show that there are times when God
demands that justice shall be executed. Has he determined that <hi rend="italic">justice shall be done</hi>,--to the black man? to the
rebel conspirators?--that our country shall suffer till this
consummation be reached? I do not know. But it may be. Take care that
we do not stand in the way of the Almighty's purposes. Some meaning
and intent God doubtless has. It is not wrong to do justice. It may be
wrong to withhold it.</p>
               <p pn="15">It may be the duty of the people to hold meetings in their
respective towns, to frame resolutions or petitions, calm,
<pb n="16"/>
                  <figure entity="hall16">
                     <figDesc>16th page of Gordon
Hall's President Lincoln's Death: Its Voice to the
People.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
firm, wise, and through their representatives at Washington to make
their voice heard in our high places.</p>
               <p pn="16">You and I shall not live
to see any other crimes so great as have been perpetrated by the
instigators of this rebellion. It is not in human power to commit such
crimes but once in many centuries--crimes so vast, far-reaching and
terrible. And if there is no call for JUSTICE, PENALTY, now, strike
these words forever from your vocabulary--let no man ever again hear
them pass your lips. Oh! a God of righteousness and equity must be
incensed at seeing us execute the poor, ignorant deserter, while we
excuse the clear-headed, deliberate, arch-traitor, and the eminent
rebel-general at whose doors lies the blood of thousands.</p>
               <p pn="16">It is comforting, I remark in closing, to reflect that God
can raise up for us men suited to our emergency. He who called Moses
from the desert of Midian to conduct the Exodus of Israel--who called
David from the sheep-fold to be a victorious and illustrious
Ruler--who raised up our late President, our wise men and counsellors,
our able Generals and gallant Admirals, can still supply our
wants. "They shall not be ashamed that wait upon him."</p>
               <p pn="16">We must rally around and support him who is now our
President. By the constitution of the land and by the Providence of
God, Mr. Johnson is now the President of this American Republic. We
must accept such testimony in his favor as that of Gen. Burnside and
Mr. LINCOLN, and give him our confidence, our prayers, our
encouragement in every good word and work.</p>
               <p pn="16">And now as our almost adorable ABRAHAM LINCOLN lies cold in
death--a benignant smile, it is said, resting upon his fixed and
pallid countenance--Thou Great Departed, Emancipator and Patriot, we
will adopt thy noble utterance, "Charity to all and malice for
none"--consecrating ourselves over thy precious dust, in a chastened,
sanctified patriotism, to "<hi rend="italic">do justly</hi> and love
mercy and walk humbly before God."</p>
            </div2>
         </div1>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI.2>