<TEI.2>
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt n="A Discourse Occasioned by the Death of Abraham Lincoln">
            <title>A Discourse Occasioned by the Death of Abraham Lincoln</title>
            <author>Hathaway, Warren</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Compiled and edited by</resp>
               <name>Beck Center</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent/>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Lewis H. Beck Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Emory University</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Atlanta,
Georgia</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>1996 Emory
University. Permission is granted to download, transmit, or otherwise
reproduce, distribute or display the contributions to the work claimed
by Emory University for non-profit educational purposes, provided
this header is included in its entirety.  For inquiries about
commercial uses, contact the Director, 
Pitts Theology Library, Emory
University, Atlanta, Georgia 30322</p>
            </availability>
            <date>1999</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Lincoln
Sermons Project</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Hathaway,
Warren. A Discourse Occasioned by the Death of Abraham Lincoln:
Preached at Coxsackie, on Wednesday, April 19, 1865.  Albany:
J. Munsell, 78 State Street. 1865.</bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This text derives from the Special Collections 
of Pitts Theology Library, Emory University, and is produced in 
collaboration with the Lewis H. Beck Center a, the Emory 
Preservation Office, and Pitts Theology Library.</p>
            <p>TRANSCRIBER: Lewis H. Beck Center and Emory University 
Preservation Office.</p>
            <p>PRODUCER:  BookLab, Inc., 1606 Headway Circle, 
Suite 100, Austin, TX 78754</p>
            <p>CAPTURE DEVICE: XEROX DocuImage 620S flatbed scanner</p>
            <p>CAPTURE DETAILS: Scanner software: XEROX ScanTool 
version 4.2.3; no gamma correction; images are all bitonal.</p>
            <p>CHANGE HISTORY: Using the Adobe Photoshop Batch Processor, 
we interpolated  the original TIFF files to 8-bit grays, 
and altered the resolution to 144 dpi, producing screen 
images twice the original size.  We then saved them in 
JPEG format.  We produced GIF thumbnails from the JPEG files.</p>
            <p>RESOLUTION: 600 ppi</p>
            <p>COMPRESSION: Resolution 144 per inch with Constrain 
Properties to 72 per inch.</p>
            <p>SOURCE: Original documents.</p>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>1999</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Scott Ellis</name>
               <resp>Staff</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <item>SGML tags inserted in compliance
with TEI guidelines using TEILITE</item>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div1 id="hathaway.001" n="A Discourse Occasioned by the Death of Abraham Lincoln" type="text">
            <head> 
               <bibl> 
                  <title>A Discourse
Occasioned by the Death of Abraham Lincoln</title> 
                  <date>Wednesday,
April 19, 1865</date> 
                  <pubPlace>Coxsackie</pubPlace> 
                  <author>Hathaway,
Warren</author> 
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Albany</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>J. Munsell</publisher>
                     <date>1865</date>
                  </imprint> 
               </bibl>
            </head>
            <p>
               <figure entity="hathaway1">
                  <figDesc>1st page of Warren Hathaway's A
Discourse Occasioned by the Death of Abraham
Lincoln.</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <p>A</p>
            <p>DISCOURSE</p>
            <p>OCCAISONED BY THE</p>
            <p>DEATH OF ABRAHAM LINCOLN:</p>
            <p>PREACHED AT COXSACKIE,</p>
            <p>ON WEDNESDAY, APRIL 19, 1865,</p>
            <p>BY</p>
            <p>WARREN HATHAWAY.</p>
            <p>ALBANY</p>
            <p>J. MUNSELL, 78 STATE STREET.</p>
            <p>1865.</p>
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>
               <figure entity="hathaway2">
                  <figDesc>2nd page of
Warren Hathaway's A Discourse Occasioned by the Death of Abraham
Lincoln.</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <p>CORRESPONDENCE.</p>
            <p>COXSACKIE, April 20,
1865.</p>
            <p>We, the undersigned, citizens of Coxsackie, respectfully
request you to prepare and furnish a copy of your discourse delivered
at the Methodist Episcopal Church, on Wednesday, April 19th, 1865, on
the death of Abraham Lincoln, late President of the United States, for
publication.</p>
            <p>Very respectfully yours,</p>
            <p>STEPHEN P. HALLOCK,           SIMPSON S. BELL,
	            <lb/>JAMES W. HISEREL,             J. B. BRONK,
	            <lb/>GEO. REED,                    S. A. DWIGHT,
	            <lb/>GILDERSLEVE BEDELL,           H. D. BEDELL,
	            <lb/>R. COOK,                      J. T. BEDELL,
	            <lb/>F. C. DEDRICK,                MARCUS WING,
	            <lb/>N. C. BEDELL,                 ISAAC BROWN,
	            <lb/>E. O. BEATTY,                 F. S. GREENE,
	            <lb/>B. F. BEATTY,                 R. E. BUCKBEE,
	            <lb/>JAMES E. GREENE,              HIRAM BROWN,
	            <lb/>MICHAEL, KRUBE,               CASPER
I. COLLIER.</p>
            <p>WEDNESDAY, April
21, 1865.</p>
            <p>Gentlemen:--The hurried preparation of the discourse, to
which you refer, would lead me to withhold it from publication; still,
I do not feel at liberty to refuse your request from the earnest
desire I have to do all that is possible to honor the memory of our
lamented President--all that I can to have the people feel and
understand the solemn duties of the hour.</p>
            <p>I am, most respectfully yours,</p>
            <p>WARREN
HATHAWAY.</p>
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>
               <figure entity="hathaway3">
                  <figDesc>3rd page of
Warren Hathaway's A Discourse Occasioned by the Death of Abraham
Lincoln.</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <div2 id="hathaway.002" n="DISCOURSE" type="sermon">
               <head>DISCOURSE.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <p>As appropriately expressing the sad, calamitous
event that has called us together--and also expressing our
circumstances and feelings as a nation, we have selected the following
Scriptures for our text:</p>
                  <p>II SAMUEL i, 19.--The beauty of Israel is slain upon the
high places: how are the mighty fallen;</p>
                  <p>II SAMUEL xix, 2.--And the victory that day was turned into
mourning unto all the people.</p>
               </epigraph>
               <p>We have congregated with an assembled nation, to attend the
funeral of the chief magistrate of the United States. Probably such a
day of grief--of vast assemblages and bitter mourning as this, was
never seen before in the annals of time. It is no ordinary event that
moves a continent, that bows millions in tears, but to day the Great
Republic is bereaved, and its mourning has all the elements of
sublimity.</p>
               <p>Nations have often buried their rulers: gilded hatchments
have often graced the royal hearse: the marble tomb which pride and
ambition has prepared, has often been unsealed to receive the great,
the kingly and the wise; for Death, whose mission is, "to tread out
empire and to quench the stars," with equal pace and power knocks at
the palace and the cottage.</p>
               <p>But when did millions bow in mourning as they bow to-day?
When before has friend and foe, sire and son, freeman and bondman,
rich and poor, lofty and lowly,
<pb n="4"/>
                  <figure entity="hathaway4">
                     <figDesc>4th page of Warren
Hathaway's A Discourse Occasioned by the Death of Abraham
Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
struck hands in companionship of sorrow, and joined in a concert of
tears.</p>
               <lg type="stanza">
                  <l>Our soldiers on the field of battle,</l>
                  <l>Our heroes on the main,</l>
                  <l>The merchant prince and negro chattel,</l>
                  <l>All swell the sad refrain:</l>
                  <l>"Man of the millions, thou art lost too
soon!"</l>
               </lg>
               <p>Since last Friday night, so far and fast as the tidings of
the <hi rend="italic">more</hi> than <hi rend="italic">regicide</hi> have
flashed upon the telegraphic wires, there has been in every heart and
upon every tongue but one theme; and today, throughout our land, from
the lakes to the gulf, from granite New England to the prairied west,
from the Atlantic to the Mississippi: in one grand, mournful, weeping
procession--the nation follows the mangled form and gloomy hearse of
ABRAHAM LINCOLN. Unexpected, sudden as a bolt from a clear sky, the
nimble lightning flashed the sad news, the awful story of the
assassination of our President. We are, and have been for days, a
saddened, bewildered, terrified people! Certainly no event ever
transpired in the United States that has subdued and bereaved so many
hearts, caused so many groans of anguish, cast upon our land such a
shower of tears.</p>
               <p>Suddenly, like the gloom of the dark day of 1780, when the
sun was blotted out, and night came at noon, a pall of darkness has
fallen over all our land; and God looks upon a stricken, afflicted
people--such sorrowing as he never saw occasioned by the death of any
Hebrew or Gentile ruler before.</p>
               <p>Can it be possible, that he upon whom rested the confidence
and hopes of the nation in this hour of bitter trial--<hi rend="italic">is gone!</hi>
               </p>
               <lg type="stanza">
                  <l>One day along the electric wire</l>
                  <l>His words of love and mercy sped;</l>
               </lg>
               <pb n="5"/>
               <p>
                  <figure entity="hathaway5">
                     <figDesc>5th page of
Warren Hathaway's A Discourse Occasioned by the Death of Abraham
Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <lg type="stanza">
                  <l>We came next morn: that tongue of fire</l>
                  <l>Said only, "He who spake is dead."</l>
               </lg>
               <lg type="stanza">
                  <l>Dead! while his voice was living yet,</l>
                  <l>In echoes round the pillared dome!</l>
                  <l>Dead! while his blotted page lay wet</l>
                  <l>With themes of state and loves of home!</l>
               </lg>
               <lg type="stanza">
                  <l>Dead! he so great, and strong, and wise,</l>
                  <l>While the mean thousands yet draw breath;</l>
                  <l>How deepened, through that dread surprise,</l>
                  <l>The mystery and the awe of Death!</l>
               </lg>
               <lg type="stanza">
                  <l>Through him we hoped to speak the word</l>
                  <l>Which wins the freedom of a land!</l>
                  <l>And lift for human right, the sword</l>
                  <l>Which dropped from Hampden's dying hand.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg type="stanza">
                  <l>We seemed to see our flag unfurled,</l>
                  <l>Our champion waiting in his place</l>
                  <l>For the last battle of the world--</l>
                  <l>The Armageddon of the race. * * * *</l>
               </lg>
               <lg type="stanza">
                  <l>We sweep the land from hill to strand,</l>
                  <l>We seek the strong, the wise, the brave!</l>
                  <l>And, sad of heart, return to stand</l>
                  <l>In silence by a new made grave!</l>
               </lg>
               <p>The world at large will mourn with us. The good, the brave,
the liberty loving--those who desire the elevation and happiness of
our race, will feel they have lost a brother and a friend. The
enthralled of Italy and Hungary--the oppressed of every land--will
mourn: for one who loved mankind and labored for universal freedom,
has fallen!</p>
               <p>A few days ago the land was filled with joy; a series of
brilliant victories crowned the efforts of the Federal armies. You
remember with what breathless anxiety we waited to hear from SHERMAN;
he reported at last,
<pb n="6"/>
                  <figure entity="hathaway6">
                     <figDesc>6th page of Warren
Hathaway's A Discourse Occasioned by the Death of Abraham
Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
and his <hi rend="italic">bulletin</hi> was the record of a triumph. We
paused a moment, feeling that the crisis of our nation and the war had
come; then the "On to Richmond" of four years ago--<hi rend="italic">now</hi> the more sublime--"<hi rend="italic">On to
Freedom</hi>," was consummated, and the old flag, unstained with
wrong, but battle-torn, waved proudly from the defiant ramparts of
Richmond--dropping <hi rend="italic">bread</hi> and <hi rend="italic">mercy</hi> from its ample folds upon the guilty, famishing
foe.</p>
               <p>We had hardly time to express our loyal joy, when there
came the tidings that our modest, peerless GRANT, had received the
sword of Robert E. Lee and the surrender of the grand army of the
rebellion. The land was filled with joy. It was a complete contrast to
April, 1861, when the flag of the Republic trailed in the dust, and
traitors were jubilant; the starry banner was waving in victorious
triumph--cannon were uttering cheering salvos--drum and fife and
bugle, were uttering prophesies of peace and national integrity. The
hearts of millions were beating high with hope as they looked upon the
dark folds of the storm-cloud of battle, rolling slowly away, fringed
with amber and gold, giving promise in its bow of beauty that the
bloody tempest of treason was spent and that we should soon enjoy the
calm of national peace and fraternity. There was thankfulness to
almighty God, and the pure offerings of praise ascended from hill top
and valley from hamlet and city; even New York felt the joyous
Pentacost, and "Wall St. spake in unknown tongues," as there swelled
amid her Mammon temples the grand old Doxology--the "<hi rend="italic">Te Deum</hi>" of a nation's deliverance.</p>
               <p>There was no indulging in feelings of vengeance, no gloating
in gladness over the sorrows and chagrin of a fallen foe; but disposed
to let "the lifted thunder of
<pb n="7"/>
                  <figure entity="hathaway7">
                     <figDesc>7th page of Warren
Hathaway's A Discourse Occasioned by the Death of Abraham
Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
justice drop," extend the hand of mercy and love, the people
temperately rejoiced. It was not a Roman saturnalia; but a patriotic,
Christian jubilee.</p>
               <p>But alas, how changed! Now, grief and indignation, soreness
of heart and vengeance of purpose, are blended in the American mind:
and as we survey our nation to day we look upon "a sea of glass
mingled with fire." The victorious flag droops in mourning, drums are
muffled, songs of gladness have suddenly ceased; end throughout the
laud, there is mourning for the dead. Strong men weep as they never
wept before, hopeful men sigh, good men pray and look to God for
strength, loyal men are appalled, the bitter partizan is a contrite
mourner, none but heartless traitors can rejoice. Truly, "in the day
of victory the people mourn."</p>
               <p>Why this intense and bitter feeling of sadness? Not because
death is so strange--we are familiar with its bereavements. Earth is a
wilderness of graves, and all mankind are marching to the tomb. During
the last four years Death has held carnival; noblest bravest lives
have been sacrificed, the bloom and ripeness of our land has
fallen.</p>
               <p>Neither is it simply because our Chief Magistrate is
dead. This not a new experience for the nation. Twice before has Death
entered the White House. We are not without a ruler; already the
mantle o office has fallen upon one worthy to be the servant and
representative of the American people. Yet we feel we have lost the
man, who above all others is needed in this time of national
peril. The man who above all others seemed chosen of God to lead us
through the Red Sea of rebellion, and guide us to the promised land of
liberty and peace.</p>
               <p>But this is not all; there are noble, devoted patriots
<pb n="8"/>
                  <figure entity="hathaway8">
                     <figDesc>8th page of Warren
Hathaway's A Discourse Occasioned by the Death of Abraham
Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
that we can trust; but alas! we stand in the presence of a mangled
corse! Our ears tingle with the tidings of a most foul assassination!
We have pressed upon our attention an awful crime. Our Chief
Magistrate has fallen a victim--basely, cruelly murdered! Shall we be
safe? Shall our roof-trees blaze, our hearth stones run with blood?</p>
               <p>The most sacred person in the nation has fallen by the hand
of a ruffian!  No wonder the heart strings of the nation vibrate with
strange agony. This is something new. This is a sad, bitter lesson for
the Republic. We are reminded of the bloody, stormy days of Rome; when
the dagger controlled affairs of State, and Anarchy was on the
throne.</p>
               <p>But why does this <hi rend="italic">murder</hi> so deeply
affect us? It <hi rend="italic">does</hi> affect us most
peculiarly. When we heard the news of this assassination, we felt
humbled--subdued in spirit. There was a feeling of oppressive sadness,
loneliness. We have been proud of the name American, and as we have
looked upon <hi rend="italic">that</hi> starry banner, now draped in
mourning, we have rejoiced in its short but glorious history; felt
that more sacred truth and principle were symbolized in <hi rend="italic">that</hi> bunting, than in any other national
ensign. Beneath it stood Washington and the Spirit of Liberty, and we
were hopeful, that soon, wherever it floated, <hi rend="italic">all</hi>
should be free.</p>
               <p>Murders have occurred before. We know that wicked men will
do wickedly. Men have often been murdered for their money, been
murdered to gratify the spirit of revenge, because of enmity and
ambition; but none of these motives led to the base deed that has
plunged the nation in the deepest sorrow.</p>
               <p>One thing the assassin has gained--an immortality of
infamy, by striking down "the foremost man of all the world." But let
me plainly state if I can the <hi rend="italic">mean-</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="9"/>
               <p>
                  <figure entity="hathaway9">
                     <figDesc>9th page of
Warren Hathaway's A Discourse Occasioned by the Death of Abraham
Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">ing</hi> and <hi rend="italic">terror</hi> of <hi rend="italic">this</hi> deed of blood. Let me state my feelings and
convictions. Let me discharge my duty in this solemn hour.</p>
               <p>We have come together, as mourners, to show our respect for
the departed--without reference to religious sect, or political
party. Far be it from me to utter a word to injure the feelings of any
<hi rend="italic">loyal</hi> man; as to <hi rend="italic">traitors</hi>,
God forbid that I should please them; but I would withhold no word
that condemns national iniquity, that would have a tendency to
convict, and convert from political wrong, from organic
wickedness. Standing before God, the judge of nations, and in the
presence of the mangled form of our late President, it is a time and
fraternity. Let citizens be brothers. Let Americans be united, let
them heed the farewell words that trembled from the lips of
Washington, as they bend over the remains of Abraham Lincoln.</p>
               <p>We shall mention four things as points of interest and
instruction. <hi rend="italic">First</hi>, THE SAD EVENT.</p>
               <lg type="stanza">
                  <l>"How are the mighty fallen!"</l>
               </lg>
               <p>This was the language of David when the tidings came of the
death of Saul and Jonathan. Inspired genius never uttered a more
eloquent eulogium, a more tender and touching tribute to departed
greatness, than he pronounced on that occasion. Indeed, he seems to
eclipse himself in this impassioned funeral ode.</p>
               <p>In this noble panegyric, we are led to admire the <hi rend="italic">spirit</hi> of David.</p>
               <p>Unambitious, forgiving, he seems more good than great. We
scarcely know which to admire most, his long heart or his princely
intellect. Irresistible with his sword, sweeping the harp with a
master's
<pb n="10"/>
                  <figure entity="hathaway10">
                     <figDesc>10th page of Warren
Hathaway's A Discourse Occasioned by the Death of Abraham
Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
hand, unrivalled as poet and king, his greatness is only equalled by
his goodness, while his virtues outshine his crown.</p>
               <p>You should remember that the only obstacle between David
and the throne was removed by the death of Saul. The fallen king had
treated him with the utmost cruelty for years, seeking his life with
relentless hatred. A price had been set upon his head, and he had been
"hunted like a partridge in the mountains." Yet forgetful of self he
buries the wrongs he has suffered, in the grave of Saul. Instead of
hailing as a friend the stranger who brings the bracelet and crown of
the murdered king, he treats him as a regicide and orders his
immediate execution. He had lifted his hand against the head of a
government. Saul was the Lord's anointed. His person was sacred.</p>
               <p>No more sacred, however, in the estimation of Heaven, than
the person of Abraham Lincoln. As we have said, the assassin in this
case is more than a regicide; his crime greater if possible than
though he had slain a king. It seems to me that no one who stands at
the head of a nation as ruler, can be more truly the Lord's anointed,
so far as government is concerned, than the President of the United
States.</p>
               <p>This responsible position is not the accident of birth, it
is not the inheritance of family, it is <hi rend="italic">the gift of
the people</hi>. Whoever fills this high office as the choice of the
nation is <hi rend="italic">sacred</hi> to us, because almost alone
among the nations, God has given us this right of election. This high
privilege has been secured to us by suffering, sacrifice and blood. It
cost the patriotism of '76--which was not a parlor, or shoulder-strap
patriotism merely, but that practical devotion to country that pledged
life and fortune and sacred honor to the cause of freedom, and
sanctified the battle fields of the
<pb n="11"/>
                  <figure entity="hathaway11">
                     <figDesc>11th page of Warren
Hathaway's A Discourse Occasioned by the Death of Abraham
Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
Revolution with the best blood of our race. And no person can be more
sacred in view of cost and principle, sacrifice and freedom, than our
Chief Magistrate.</p>
               <p>We have often been told he was in danger. Still we could
not believe there was anything serious in the cowardly threats that
were uttered by the friends of the rebellion. Four years ago--we speak
it with shame, to save his life he fled through darkness to
Washington, and the plot of assassination was foiled. He has been
spared until the comparatively unknown man has acquired a world-wide
fame. Spared, until he has won the respect and love and confidence of
millions. Spared, during the darkness of the night, <hi rend="italic">he
has died in the morning</hi>. But in the dawn for which he looked and
longed and prayed: while its mellow tints were flushing the sky, the
murderous blow has fallen. The words of the assassin,--"<hi rend="italic">Sic semper tyrannis</hi>"--find no response in the heart
of suffering humanity. No tyrant ever had such a funeral, such <hi rend="italic">a mourning</hi> as the world decrees for LINCOLN. A
tyrant! He was the embodiment of American sentiment, of the
liberty-loving spirit of our age; he was the representative in
principle and action, of the people.</p>
               <p>The murderous blow that shattered the casket of his noble
soul was not aimed at him alone, but at us, at Americans, at the
loyal, liberty-loving masses, at all who desire the welfare of our
government, the stability of our nation. The words of the assassin
were the wolfish howl of anarchy, and his blow was struck at the
dearest interests of mankind. It was the attempted assassination of
the principle of Democracy, of the rights of the people. The murderer
aimed to shoot a truth, a principle, a law of God; between him and
that truth, that principle, that
<pb n="12"/>
                  <figure entity="hathaway12">
                     <figDesc>12th page of Warren
Hathaway's A Discourse Occasioned by the Death of Abraham
Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
law, stood Abraham Lincoln. The ball struck the President, he was
mortal, but principle, truth, righteousness are
invulnerable--immortal. He alas! was killed, but <hi rend="italic">not</hi> that at which the shot was aimed.</p>
               <lg type="stanza">
                  <l>Glory to God forever!</l>
                  <l>Beyond the despot's will</l>
                  <l>The soul of freedom liveth</l>
                  <l>Imperishable still.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg type="stanza">
                  <l>We will think of thee, O brother!</l>
                  <l>And thy sainted name shall be</l>
                  <l>In the blessing of the captive,</l>
                  <l>And the anthem of the free.</l>
               </lg>
               <p>Looking over the history of the world, I am often impressed
with the omnipotence of righteousness and truth. Nothing after all is
so secure as the principle of virtue. It is firmer than the mountains,
it is stronger than any fortress on the land, or iron-clad on the
deep. Virtue, in the bulrush ark, is more secure than vice in
Pharaoh's palace. And though truth has its martyrs, it is stronger at
the stake or on the scaffold, than falsehood in the moated castle, or
cannon-mounted citadel. And this effort to destroy virtue and national
righteousness at Washington, will impress us again, by showing the
immutability of justice and excellence.</p>
               <p>We have said the person of our President was
sacred. Re?lected by a popular majority of nearly five hundred
thousand, the people had said emphatically--"well done, good and
faithful servant." Again invested with the authority of his high
office, he was, if possible, doubly sacred to all--save the foul dogs
of a gigantic, cruel and fiendish rebellion! He and WM. H. SEWARD,
were perhaps, more than any other two, representative men. The people,
the Ameri-
<pb n="13"/>
                  <figure entity="hathaway13">
                     <figDesc>13th page of Warren
Hathaway's A Discourse Occasioned by the Death of Abraham
Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
can commonwealth, acknowledged their leadership rather I should say
regarded them as faithful servants. They were doing the behests of the
nation. Hence it is solemnly, impressively true, the President falls
for the people: for their rights and liberties, their government and
country.</p>
               <p>It is an event of awful magnitude. Its influence will be
wide-reaching and far-resounding, like the terrible judgments of
Heaven. It should lead the American people to humble devotion before
God. It should lead to honesty of purpose, candor of heart. It should
calm the turbulent waters of party strife, and lead to national
repentance. All should pause, review their course, and candidly
consider their duty to the nation and the world. Let the public weal,
let national prosperity, and virtue, and existence, be more sacred
than party. Let us make our political organizations the conservators
of truth and righteousness; not mere systematized opposition to the
government. Let partyism, be subject to a pure and lofty
patriotism.</p>
               <p>As Christians, let us not permit devotion to party to blind
our eyes so that we cannot see, to fetter our hands so that we cannot
strike for the right, to padlock our lips so that we cannot speak for
the truth. I would not make religion political, but I would make
politics religious. I would not carry party principles into
Christianity, but I would have all party platforms christianized. The
Jesuitical assumption, that we may do as politicians what we may not
do as Christians is infidelity in its worst form, and will lead to
individual and national perdition. When <hi rend="italic">wrong</hi> is
sanctioned in a political platform, when it becomes organic, it does
not cease to be iniquitous; and as Christians let us speak
trumpet-tongued against all
<pb n="14"/>
                  <figure entity="hathaway14">
                     <figDesc>14th page of Warren
Hathaway's A Discourse Occasioned by the Death of Abraham
Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
sin, whether individual or national, whether pertaining to a person or
a party.</p>
               <p>As Americans, let us cease from party warfare until the
government shall be safe and the integrity of the nation firmly
secured. 0, let us stand for our country, while traitors are
endeavoring to drag us down to ruin! Let us stand in the breach of the
wall of our nationality, as the hope of the world, while merciless
rebellion aims to bury beneath the ruins of our Republic--Liberty,
Equality, Fraternity.</p>
               <p>We cannot mourn over this saddest event of modern times
(unless we shed crocodile tears) without hating the <hi rend="italic">cause</hi> that bereaves the nation of its Chief. We
cannot reject the fruit without rejecting the tree. We cannot
pronounce the stream impure and bitter while we declare the fountain
sweet and good. When we sanction a cause we sanction its effect; and
every contrite mourner to-day, must abhor not only this foul crime,
but its origin. This leads me to notice--<hi rend="italic">Secondly</hi>: THE CAUSE OE THIS EVENT.</p>
               <p>It was not because of personal enmity the President was
assassinated. Not because he had been guilty of insulting or injuring
any man. Not because he had been overbearing, harsh, or in any manner
tyrannical. There was no kinder man in the nation. He had a smile and
a good word for all. He had tears to shed for the suffering, and time
amid the most arduous labors of office to write letters full of
sympathy and consolation to those who mourned the loss of friends and
children on the battle-field. While sternly, honestly discharging his
official duties, his great, tender heart bled for those who shared the
perils of war. His honesty of purpose and sincerity of life made him
unsuspicious, and though repeatedly warned, he could not believe he
was in any danger. 
<pb n="15"/>
                  <figure entity="hathaway15">
                     <figDesc>15th page of Warren
Hathaway's A Discourse Occasioned by the Death of Abraham
Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
Panoplied in kindness and love, he felt safe as though clad in triple
steel. Forbearance has been noticed as a peculiar trait of his
character, and seldom has this virtue shone forth more conspicuously
than it did in him. His executive clemency has sometimes offended his
friends. They have feared that his gentleness might interfere with the
true administration of justice. Repeatedly has he exercised his right
to extend mercy to those under sentence of death, or imprisonment: and
sometimes in such a manner as to show the utmost kindness of
heart. Abused, insulted, traduced, defied, as no other President has
been: when did he use his great power to gratify feeling s of anger,
when did he manifest the spirit of revenge? You cannot point to an
angry word, to any evidence of irritability, since his first
inauguration. You know how he had been abused in Richmond by the rebel
press and government. He went down there the other day, not with
vengeance in his heart; he did not go to sow that guilty city with
salt, and hang its traitors; but he went as a saviour and friend. The
active and passive virtues were strangely, beautifully blended in his
character. He will stand in the memory of the world among the most
forbearing, kindly and gentle, whose generosity towards the most
bitter foes is without a parallel among sucessful rulers and
conquerors.</p>
               <p>The London <title>Spectator</title>, in the number for
March 25th, thus speaks of Mr. Lincoln's character. "Finding himself
the object of southern abuse, so fierce and so foul that in any man
less passionless it would long ago have stirred up an implacable
animosity, mocked at for his official awkwardness, and denounced for
his steadfast policy by all the democratic section of the loyal
states, tried by years of failure before that policy achieved a single
great success, further tried by
<pb n="16"/>
                  <figure entity="hathaway16">
                     <figDesc>16th page of Warren
Hathaway's A Discourse Occasioned by the Death of Abraham
Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
a series of successes so rapid and so brilliant that they would have
puffed up a smaller mind and overset its balance, embarrassed by the
boastfulness of his people and of his subordinates, no less than by
his own inexperience in his relations with foreign states, beset by
fanatics of principle on one side who would pay no attention to his
obligations as a constitutional ruler, and by fanatics of caste on the
other, who were not only deaf to the claims of justice, but would hear
of no policy large enough for a revolutionary emergency, Mr. Lincoln
has persevered through all, without ever giving way to anger, or
despondency, or exultation, or popular arrogance, or sectarian
fanaticism, or caste prejudice, visibly growing in force of character,
in self-possession, and in magnanimity, till in his last short message
to congress on the 4th of March, we can detect no longer the rude
illiterate mould of a village lawyer's thought, but find it replaced
by a grasp of principle, a dignity of manner, and a solemnity of
purpose which would have been unworthy neither of Hampden nor of
Cromwell, while his gentleness and generosity of feeling towards his
foes are almost greater than we should expect from either of them."</p>
               <p>No, the <hi rend="italic">cause</hi> of this assassination
was not in him, was not in his assumption of illegal power. But he
died of a foul, infectious, loathsome disease. A disease that has
covered the land with graves and filled it with mourning. That has
cumbered the green shores of the SHENANDOAH, the JAMES, the
MISSISSIPPI, the TENNESSEE, and CUMBERLAND with the heroic dead. A
disease that infected our political atmosphere until virtue was almost
banished from the councils of the nation, and our great men were,
morally, in a dying condition.</p>
               <p>In other words, his murder is the result of a system
<pb n="17"/>
                  <figure entity="hathaway17">
                     <figDesc>17th page of Warren
Hathaway's A Discourse Occasioned by the Death of Abraham
Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
tolerated and heretofore defended by the American people. It is a
result of the same cause that murdered a Lovejoy because he dared to
speak for freedom, that brutally assaulted a Senator in his seat in
the Senate Chamber at Washington, that instigated this gigantic
rebellion, and that has carried it forward in a spirit of the utmost
cruelty. It is the culmination of that spirit that has made trinkets
of the bones of our dead heroes, and drinking cups of their skulls,
that has starved our soldiers taken in battle and doomed them to the
deep damnation of a stockade prison. "A tree is known by its fruits."
Freedom, is the tree of Heaven--it produces peace, contentment, joy
and love. Slavery, is a <hi rend="italic">bogus</hi> plant--forever
producing apples of discord, the ashy fruits of Sodom. It must be so
until man is emasculated and reduced from the human to the brute. It
<hi rend="italic">must</hi> be so for.</p>
               <lg type="stanza">
                  <l>God works for all. Ye cannot hem the hope of being free,</l>
                  <l>With parallels of latitude, with mountain range or sea.</l>
               </lg>
               <p>Freedom, from Nimrod to Napoleon, has been the pulse-beat
of the world, the rallying cry of every inspired ruler and
reformer. Jesus, glorious, divine-- was a Liberator, whose doctrine of
equality, unity and liberty must at last break every yoke and set
every captive free. Before the august tribunal of mankind, Slavery
will have charged upon it, among its many crimes, the guilt of this
felonious homicide. Why the assassin himself, says, by way of
justifying his premeditated crime--"I for one have ever considered
slavery as one of the greatest blessings that God ever bestowed upon a
favored nation." He has done its behests, he has obeyed its spirit.</p>
               <p>Again--we find a <hi rend="italic">secondary</hi> cause for
this sad event in the bitter language, the unjust, ungenerous
assertions of heated partizans. LINCOLN has been called a
<pb n="18"/>
                  <figure entity="hathaway18">
                     <figDesc>18th page of Warren
Hathaway's A Discourse Occasioned by the Death of Abraham
Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
tyrant, a usurper, a murderer. O friends, you have misjudged. He has
been true to his oath of office, true to the demands of the people. He
has been no more tyrannical than the loyal, heroic, sacrificing
millions of the nation. If he was a tyrant, there is some excuse for
J. W. Booth. Our fathers taught that "resistance to tyrants is
obedience to God," and the world has always been lenient to the crime
of tyrannicide.</p>
               <p>Men, responsible, influential men have said, <hi rend="italic">He ought to be shot</hi>. You have heard such disloyal,
inflammatory language. I need not say it is wrong, dangerous. It comes
from the spirit of rebellion, and has a tendency to destroy our
country, to overthrow its institutions. Such language educates the
vile, and tends to undermine that respect for law which is our only
security. If our President is guilty of usurpation, or any great
misuse of his office, let him be impeached--let him be tried before
the high court of the nation. But let us not condemn him to the knife,
or ball of the assassin, let us not revolt from his authority simply
because he was not the candidate of our political party.</p>
               <p>This crime is the legitimate fruit of rebellion. It strikes
the nation; it demands for its victim the choice of the people. This
is its spirit embodied in action, this is its crowning, and we <hi rend="italic">trust its dying effort</hi>. Those assassins, who last
Friday night filled Washington with alarm and the nation with sorrow,
were not alone in their great crime. They were backed by every
defender of treason, from Jeff. Davis, his cabinet and generals, to
the feeblest cur that has barked at the heels of loyalty and
patriotism. The rebellion aimed four years ago to destroy our
President and overthrow our nation, and alas! to-day we mourn the loss
of our Chief--but the <hi rend="italic">nation</hi>, thank God, is
vigorous; he dies
<pb n="19"/>
                  <figure entity="hathaway19">
                     <figDesc>19th page of Warren
Hathaway's A Discourse Occasioned by the Death of Abraham
Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
by the hands of traitors, but our threatened country lives--</p>
               <lg type="stanza">
                  <l>Round the cold form of death, smiles and roses are
blending--</l>
                  <l>And beauty immortal awakes from the tomb.</l>
               </lg>
               <p>The assassin is simply an earnest rebel; simply in this
murderous act, the hand on the body of confederate treason. If caught
he will be hung; but how then shall the chiefs of the rebellion, on
whom there is a torrent of blood, be pardoned and honored!!! O, MY
COUNTRY BE MERCIFUL AND JUST!</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Thirdly</hi>. THE VICTIM.</p>
               <p>During the last four years, many a princely, precious
sacrifice has been freely laid upon the altar of our country. We have
often been called to mourn, as the loved, the noble and the brave,
have fallen. We remember the early death of the gallant Ellsworth,
whose mangled form, as it passed through the land, seemed, "sent like
the twelve-divided concubine to inflame the tribes."</p>
               <p>We mourned when young WINTHROP fell, and LYON, and BAKER,
and the peerless MITCHEL; and the many noble patriots, brilliant
stars, that gave themselves for home and nation. Yet we never felt as
we do to-day, when the body of our President lies stark and stiff upon
the altar of our political hopes, the altar of our country.</p>
               <p>We shall not forget him. The nation will rear a monument
over his grave. But we ought not to forget the noble band, the mighty
army of heroes with whom he is now united in death. To-day we think of
the first one who fell--that noble patriot boy, LUTHER CRAWFORD
LADD. The city of Lowell has built a monument for him. That is right;
but there are thousands as worthy, whose names should not be
foregotten. It is sad for the dying soldier to think his grave will be
unmarked and forever unknown; that his lonely tomb
<pb n="20"/>
                  <figure entity="hathaway20">
                     <figDesc>20th page of Warren
Hathaway's A Discourse Occasioned by the Death of Abraham
Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
will never be wet with the tears of affection, or adorned by the hands
of love. On the battle field of Fair Oaks, dying apart by themselves,
were found four dead soldiers. A paper lay upon the breast of one and
a pencil by his side. On the paper written with a faltering hand were
their names, and these touching words: "Four dying soldiers. Be kind
enough to give us a decent burial." I repeat, let us not forget our
noble boys who have fallen on the field, or died in prison. We cannot
give them burial in the church yard at home; we cannot visit their
graves; but we can inscribe their names upon the enduring marble, and
thus preserve their memory. Every town should erect a monument for
those of their number who have falling, "IN THE SACRED CAUSE OF GOD
AND THEIR COUNTRY."</p>
               <p>Our fallen Chief was by nature and early education a
democrat. He belonged to the masses. He could not, without rejecting
himself, be an advocate of social exclusiveness, or of a privileged
class.</p>
               <p>He was slow to act, devoted to what he thought right, and
when his purposes were formed he was firm as the hills. Unambitious,
incorruptible, the crime for which he was slain was love of country
and freedom, regard for man, for the <hi rend="italic">rights</hi> of
all--white or black. We shall, as Americans, all glory in ABRAHAM
LINCOLN. He is booked for a star, and destined to be one of the
brightest that shines in the galaxy of the noble and the great. Like
the noblest statesman of England, he ascends to heaven bearing the
broken shackles of millions, and stands ready to be crowned the angel
of American Emancipation.</p>
               <p>He lies before us a <hi rend="italic">martyr</hi>. He fell
for principle. We cannot but notice the suggestive coincidence that he
was struck down on Good Friday: a day mem-
<pb n="21"/>
                  <figure entity="hathaway21">
                     <figDesc>21st page of Warren
Hathaway's A Discourse Occasioned by the Death of Abraham
Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
orable forever as the anniversary of the sublimest love and most
costly sacrifice. Day of all others that exhibits Divine mercy and
forbearance. Our President was betrayed on the night that saw a
suffering Saviour in the agonies of death for the salvation and
freedom of the world. His blood shall not be lost. In front of the
house where he died, a little boy was seen rubbing bits of white paper
on the steps and carefully placing them in his pocket. On being asked
why he did this, he repeated with childish simplicity: "Don't you see
those dark stains? It is the blood of the President, and I want to
save it." Yes, his blood shall be saved. It is precious. Like the
ashes of the martyrs those drops shall be the seeds of freedom.</p>
               <lg type="stanza">
                  <l>The Avon to the Severn runs,</l>
                  <l>The Severn to the sea,</l>
                  <l>And Wickliff's dust shall spread abroad</l>
                  <l>Wide as the waters be.</l>
               </lg>
               <p>The <hi rend="italic">cause</hi> and tragedy of his death,
shall extend his influence and secure his immortality. He fell the
victim of a doomed and devoted system, was struck down in the midst of
power and the exercise of mercy by a blind, staggering--</p>
               <lg type="stanza">
                  <l>Earth-born cyclops, fellest of the giant brood,</l>
                  <l>Son of
brutish force and darkness, who has drenched the earth
       with blood.</l>
               </lg>
               <p>The rebellion has committed a fatal error in his murder. It
has destroyed its mediator. He stood beneath the balance of justice,
in the attitude of mercy. He stood by the side of vengeance and held
back the glittering sword, ready to fall on those who have left us a
<hi rend="italic">fatherless</hi>, a <hi rend="italic">brotherless</hi>, a
<hi rend="italic">husbandless</hi> nation; and he in the confidence of a
victorious people could have bestowed mercy where now bolts of
vengeance will fall.</p>
               <pb n="22"/>
               <p>
                  <figure entity="hathaway22">
                     <figDesc>22nd page
of Warren Hathaway's A Discourse Occasioned by the Death of Abraham
Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <lg type="stanza">
                  <l>The Lord have mercy on the weak,</l>
                  <l>And calm their frenzied ire,</l>
                  <l>And save our brothers ere they shriek,</l>
                  <l>'We played with northern fire.'</l>
               </lg>
               <p>In conclusion--Let us notice--THE LESSONS OF THE HOUR.</p>
               <p>God, who doeth all things well, has permitted us to be
deeply bereaved, and if we receive this severe chastening in a spirit
of national penitence and humanity, it will at least be seen that it
was good for us to be afflicted. We may have needed this last great
sacrifice, to lead us to feel how sacred, how priceless, is the
freedom of a land; how dearly bought are the principles of national
integrity and virtue.</p>
               <p>We have, as a nation, been proud and oppressive retribution
has come, but while heretofore we have been a nation of mourning
individuals, weeping alone--now we are united in one sorrow, bowing
together in a great and <hi rend="italic">common</hi> grief. Then again,
we may have needed a national martyr to make the cause in which he
died forever sacred, to stimulate us to sustain with religious
devotion, <hi rend="italic">Union and freedom</hi>. Being dead, and
dying in the service of his country he shall yet speak his words shall
influence, his life shall guide, and from his grave amid the prairies
of the west, he shall plead with him who sleeps at MT. VERNON for
national virtue, for the widest liberty, for the principles of
govermental justice.</p>
               <p>Our joy has been turned into mourning that we might
properly finish the work which he so well began. We might have been
disposed to barter the precious blood of our patriot heroes, for the
tinsel of an empty peace--or the "pottage" of an iniquitous
compromise. We <hi rend="italic">might</hi> have been willing after
having our fair land ploughed with the burning share of war, and our
fields
<pb n="23"/>
                  <figure entity="hathaway23">
                     <figDesc>23rd page of Warren
Hathaway's A Discourse Occasioned by the Death of Abraham
Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
watered with blood, to permit the sowing again of those seeds of woe
that have resulted in a harvest of death. We may have needed this
further exhibition of the spirit of slavery, to teach us to detest it
with the hearty hatred which it deserves. It is now presented before
us in such dawning light, that no one will dare to stand as its
advocate. In this solemn hour let us desire not only that rebellion
should cease, but unite in the determination to remove its cause
forever from our land and nation. While we mourn as no people ever
mourned before, let us remember there is a God who has decreed that
individual and national prosperity shall depend upon
righteousness. Let us learn to put our trust in Him. His throne is
unshaken. His government eternal. No power can deprive us of our God,
or destroy the love and care of the Infinite.</p>
               <p>Let us be hopeful. "Our Country yet remains;" saved by its
baptism of blood, it is endeared to us as it never was before by
having our loved ones buried on a hundred battle-fields.</p>
               <p>Let us in the presence of God, in the presence of Death,
renew our vows of loyalty and piety. Let us pray for our government,
and hope for that peace which is the result of purity.</p>
               <p>There is ground for national hope, for believing that
before us there is a glorious future.</p>
               <lg type="stanza">
                  <l>With rudder foully broken,</l>
                  <l>With sails by traitors torn,</l>
                  <l>Our country on a midnight sea</l>
                  <l>Is writing for the morn.</l>
                  <l>But courage, O my mariners!</l>
                  <l>Ye shall not suffer wreck,</l>
                  <l>While up to God the freedman's prayers</l>
                  <l>Are rising from your deck</l>
               </lg>
               <pb n="24"/>
               <p>
                  <figure entity="hathaway24">
                     <figDesc>24th page
of Warren Hathaway's A Discourse Occasioned by the Death of Abraham
Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <lg type="stanza">
                  <l>Sail on! the morning cometh,</l>
                  <l>The port ye yet shall win;</l>
                  <l>And all the bells of God shall ring,</l>
                  <l>The good ship bravely in.</l>
               </lg>
               <p>But he has gone, who fondly looked and prayed for the dawn
of that happy morning. Beyond the tumult of battle, beyond the cares
and labors and honors of state, our departed President rests in the
peace of God. Beyond human praise or blame, we feel we can say nothing
better of him than that, <hi rend="italic">he was a good man</hi>. He
learned to love Jesus as he wept amid the graves of the brave boys who
fell at Gettysburg, and to love the Saviour is to secure a crown of
eternal life.</p>
               <p>As we survey our land with sadness and hope, as we look
upward with mingled tears and gratitude, let us remember our duty to
our country and our God,--serve both in such a manner that when done
with America, we may be prepared for Heaven.</p>
            </div2>
         </div1>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI.2>