<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader><fileDesc>
         <titleStmt n="God's Ways Unsearchable">
            <title>God's Ways Unsearchable</title>
            <author>Johnson, Herrick</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Compiled and edited by</resp>
               <name>Beck
Center</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent/>
         <publicationStmt><publisher>Lewis H. Beck Center</publisher><pubPlace>Emory University</pubPlace><address>
               <addrLine>Atlanta,
Georgia</addrLine>
            </address><availability>
               <p>1996 Emory
University. Permission is granted to download, transmit, or otherwise
reproduce, distribute or display the contributions to the work claimed
by Emory University for non-profit educational purposes, provided
this header is included in its entirety.  For inquiries about
commercial uses, contact the Director, 
Pitts Theology Library, Emory
University, Atlanta, Georgia 30322</p>
            </availability><date>1999</date></publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Lincoln
Sermons Project</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Johnson,
Herrick. "God's Ways Unsearchable." A Discourse, on the Death of
President Lincoln, Preached Before the Third Presbyterian
Congregation, in Mozart Hall, Pittsburgh, PA.  Sunday, April 23d,
1865. W. G. Johnston &amp; Co., Printers, Stationers and Blank Book
Makers, 57 Wood Street, Pittsburgh.</bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc><encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This text derives from the Special Collections 
of Pitts Theology Library, Emory University, and is produced in 
collaboration with the Lewis H. Beck Center a, the Emory 
Preservation Office, and Pitts Theology Library.</p>
            <p>TRANSCRIBER: Lewis H. Beck Center and Emory University 
Preservation Office.</p>
            <p>PRODUCER:  BookLab, Inc., 1606 Headway Circle, 
Suite 100, Austin, TX 78754</p>
            <p>CAPTURE DEVICE: XEROX DocuImage 620S flatbed scanner</p>
            <p>CAPTURE DETAILS: Scanner software: XEROX ScanTool 
version 4.2.3; no gamma correction; images are all bitonal.</p>
            <p>CHANGE HISTORY: Using the Adobe Photoshop Batch Processor, 
we interpolated  the original TIFF files to 8-bit grays, 
and altered the resolution to 144 dpi, producing screen 
images twice the original size.  We then saved them in 
JPEG format.  We produced GIF thumbnails from the JPEG files.</p>
            <p>RESOLUTION: 600 ppi</p>
            <p>COMPRESSION: Resolution 144 per inch with Constrain 
Properties to 72 per inch.</p>
            <p>SOURCE: Original documents.</p>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc><revisionDesc><change><name>Stewart Varner</name> transformed this document from p4 to p5 on <date when="2010-03-22">March 22, 2010</date></change><change xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><date>1999</date><label>Staff</label><name>Scott Ellis</name>SGML tags inserted in compliance
with TEI guidelines using TEILITE</change></revisionDesc></teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div1 xml:id="johnson.001" n="God's Ways Unsearchable" type="text">
            <head> 
               <bibl> 
                  <title>God's Ways
Unsearchable</title> 
                  <date>April 23, 1865</date> 
                  <pubPlace>Third
Presbyterian Congregation, in Mozart Hall, Pittsburgh, PA </pubPlace>
                  <author>Johnson, Herrick</author> 
                  
                     <pubPlace>Pittsburgh,
PA</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>W. G. Johnston &amp; Co.</publisher>
                     <date>1865</date>
                   
               <idno type="ark">http://pid.emory.edu/ark:/25593/15qgg</idno></bibl> 
            </head>
            <pb facs="johnson1.jpg"/>
            <p>"GOD'S WAYS UNSEARCHABLE."</p>
            <p>A DISCOURSE,</p>
            <p>ON THE DEATH OF PRESIDENT LINCOLN,</p>
            <p>PREACHED BEFORE THE</p>
            <p>Third Presbyterian Congregation,</p>
            <p>IN MOZART HALL, PITTSBURGH, PA.</p>
            <p>SUNDAY, APRIL 23rd, 1865.</p>
            <p>BY</p>
            <p>Rev. HERRICK JOHNSON, Pastor.</p>
            <p>PUBLISHED BY REQUEST.</p>
            <p>W. G. Johnston &amp; Co., Printers, Stationers and Blank Book
Makers, 57 Wood Street, Pittsburgh.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="johnson2.jpg"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="johnson3.jpg"/>
            <div2 xml:id="johnson.002" n="GOD'S WAYS UNSEARCHABLE." type="sermon">
               <head>"GOD'S WAYS UNSEARCHABLE."</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">O the depths of the riches, both of the
wisdom and knowledge of God! How unsearchable are his judgments and
his ways past finding out! For who hath known the mind of the Lord? or
who hath been his counsellor? or, who hath first given to him and it
shall be recompensed unto him again? For of him and through him and to
him are all things; to whom be glory forever. Amen.-ROM. XI:
33-36.,</hi>
                  </p>
               </epigraph>
               <p>IT was with these words, my people, that I had thought to
lead you in a jubilant song of triumph and of praise. I had already
selected them as the basis of a discourse commemorative of our recent
victories. But while I paused for official hand to write proclamation
of thanksgiving, summoning the people to their altars with offerings
of grateful joy, that hand grew cold and stiff in death. The spirit
that moved it, now praises God, I trust, in such golden speech as is
coined in the mint of heaven. But a bereaved and stricken nation has
no heart for gladness. The tumultuous acclaim over martial triumphs,
is hushed in the billows of a great grief. Shotted salutes for
victories give place to minute guns of woe. Our carol is changed to a
plaint. Our paeans of joy to wails of sorrow. Chords are struck in the
peoples hearts that vibrate only to mournful music. The nation is in
sackcloth. And to day we weep our tears over the bier that contains
all that was mortal of our beloved and honored Chief Magistrate,
ABRAHAM LINCOLN.</p>
               <p>Yet the words, whose consideration I had deemed appropriate
to a day of thanksgiving, strike me as alike consonant with the
changed circumstances in which we now come to our altars. The great
truth they embody is as fitted to stay our hearts in the shock of
disappointment, as to inspire our hearts in the gladness of achieved
success. Indeed, this last act of the bloody drama, whose changing
scenes we have witnessed for four years with such terrible interest,
gives completer illustration than any act that has gone before it, of
the truth that God's judgments are unsearchable and his ways past
finding out. And no other event in the whole history of the war has
given such startling emphasis to the question, Who hath known the mind
of the Lord? or, who hath been his counsellor? While better than by
our victories will it be, for us to be brought by this great woe to a
clearer recognition of God, and even out of our stony grief to say,
"Of him and through him and to him are all things: to whom be glory
forever. Amen."</p>
               <p>That God reigns, that in the government of human affairs he
has a plan, and that the accomplishment of that plan is by judgments
unsearchable and ways past finding out--ways not ours and of which we
have
<pb n="4" facs="johnson4.jpg"/>
had no thought or conception, until their revelation has struck men
dumb with astonishment and bewildering wonder--are truths emphasized
and corroborated with remarkable frequency and remarkable power ever
since the outbreak of our civil war.</p>
               <p>The war itself, in its
scope and significance, in its length and vastness and unlooked for
results, in its waste and desolation and havoc, in its high and grand
redemption; Is a thing of which we never dreamed. So opposed to human
expectation has it been--so unlike the prophecy both of friend and
foe--so contrary to the purpose both of loyal and disloyal hearts. Our
newly sworn President was right, when he said, in full recognition of
the dealings of an inscrutable Providence, "I shall not, attempt to
anticipate the future. Had any man gifted with pre-science, four years
ago uttered and written down in advance the events of this period, the
story would have appeared more marvelous than anything in the Arabian
Nights." More marvelous indeed. Fiction sinks into the utterest and
tamest common place before these wonders of fact.</p>
               <p>We of the North thought to lay the strong iron hand of the
Government down upon this petty revolt and crush it in ninety
days. God's way was to soak our soil with gore and redden our rivers
with blood, and thicken the very air with groans for four long years
before we should subdue it. They of the South thought to call the roll
of their slaves at Bunker Hill. God's way was that the roll of those
slaves should be called under the fields of a free flag, as soldiers
of the Army of the Union. And thus it has been all through these
trying years. We have thought our ways accordant with the will of God,
and they have proven to be athwart it. We have deemed ourselves wise
in forecasting the future, and events as they have transpired, have
written us fools for prophecy. We have sought to be counsellors of the
Lord, and he has been his own, bringing to pass his unsearchable
judgments amidst such amazing surprises, and by foiling schemes so
ripe for execution and when it seemed as if the very hour had struck
for their success, that the instinctive feeling of even irreligious
men has been, It is the Lord's doing, and it is marvelous in our
eyes.</p>
               <p>A bare enumeration of events that go to substantiate this
idea, is impossible in the brief hour allotted to this discourse. The
simplest refference to a few of the most signal and prominent must
suffice.</p>
               <p>The first mortifying failure of our arms at Bull Run may be
instanced as proof of our ignorance of the mind of the Lord.</p>
               <p>And right upon the heel of that national humiliation, the
people's cry was for a Leader. We were ready to make an idol of him
who should redeem us from that great shame, by marshaling our armed
hosts and leading them out to victory. The man came whom we thought
equal to the crisis, and we were almost run mad with hero-worship. The
country rang with his idolatrous praise. But God broke our idol to our
faces. And he has not allowed us to enthrone another since. The honors
of victory have been so divided and shared by those in civil and
military position, that the nation is in no danger of being swept away
by a passionate idolatry, or of bowing down to a hero as to a god
confessed. Even the lamented dead, notwithstanding his prominence and
personal worthiness and conspicuous agency and commanding influence,
was always made by an inscrutable Providence to appear in the eyes of
the people simply as
<pb n="5" facs="johnson5.jpg"/>
the <hi rend="italic">Lord's instrument</hi>. I deem it a thing of God,
that no man in the cabinet or in the field, has been thrust to such
unrivaled eminence and been permitted to bear off so many and such
peerless honors, as to leave us a nation of idolaters, with our trust
in an arm of flesh. To day, more truly than ever, we bow and believe,
as in the hush of silence, in awe of this new proof of the mysterious
ways of God, we listen to a voice from the opening heavens, saying,
"Be still, and know that I am God. I will be exalted among the
heathen, I will be exalted in the earth."</p>
               <p>Still further is it seen that the judgments of the most
High are unsearchable in this: that while in the beginning of the
strife we sent heralds and proclamations in advance of our armies,
announcing to traitors that the. institution which had given birth to
treason, and nursed the foul offspring until it grew strong enough to
attempt the life of the nation, was not to be interfered with, God's
purpose was to make this war the instrument of so upheaving that
institution, that of its foundations, <hi rend="italic">not one stone
should be left upon another</hi>. Fools and blind at first, we found
out the way of the Lord at last, and he, whose tongue shall never
speak God's truth to the nation again, made official recognition of
it, in words that should be engraven on our hearts forever. Solemnly,
reverently, as if moved by an impulse from on high, he said in his
late inaugural, "If God wills that this mighty scourge of war continue
until all the wealth piled by the bondman's two hundred and fifty
years of unrequited toil shall be sunk, and until every drop of blood
drawn with the lash shall be paid by another drawn with the sword, as
was said three thousand years ago, so still it must be said, that the
judgments of the Lord are true and righteous altogether."</p>
               <p>Little dreamed that Child of Providence, and man of the
people, as he stood there on the platform erected over the steps of
the last entrance of the Capitol, his forehead kissed by the sun-light
that came streaming down through the rifted clouds from heaven, and
that rested there on that bronzed and care-worn brow, as if it were a
smile from God--little dreamed he, interpreting the ways of the
Almighty in those memorable words, that his own blood was a part of
the price to be paid for the bondman's years of suffering and
unrequited toil. But God so willed it. And for this more than for all
else, an awe-struck people, through their blinding tears, look up and
say, "How unsearchable are thy judgments, and thy ways past finding
out."</p>
               <p>Ah, here indeed, God's thought was not our thought. If, at
this particular juncture in our affairs, we had been asked, who of the
honored and trusted leaders could least be spared, we should all have
answered ABRAHAM LINCOLN. Yet this was not the way of the Lord. In His
sight, he could best be spared. Linked as he was with every national
interest, conspicuous as he appeared in all that concerned the welfare
of the Republic, kept as he had been through perils seen and unseen,
essential as he seemed to the completion of the work he had so
modestly, and yet so grandly begun and prosecuted, the Chief of the
Nation, the trusted leader of a regenerated and disenthralled people,
the proved pilot who had brought the Ship of State through storms,
whose howling fierceness and tempestuous wrath blanched every cheek,
the God-fearing and God-honoring man,-wedded to liberty by a devotion
that made him prefer death to its surrender, touching the throbbing
pulses of the people's hearts to regulate his own, so true to
<pb n="6" facs="johnson6.jpg"/>
truth, so free from malice, so calm amidst the troubled sea of passion
that roared and surged around him, so cautious and conscientious in
reaching decision, yet so immovable when once resolved, so like a
child in guilelessness yet so stanch in moral frame, as if his nature
were ribbed and muscled with eternal truth, leaning on the hearts of
his countrymen with only less confidence than he leaned on the right
arm of God, one of "the wisest, virtuousest, discreetest, best" of all
earth's rulers--who would have prophesied that he would be moving
through the commonwealths of the country to-day, speaking only from
his shroud? Who of us thought on the morning of April 14th, as we
grasped the cup of thanksgiving, that it would so soon be dashed from
us, and this wine of bitterness pressed to our lips? It was God's
thought, my hearers. If we had been his counsellors we should have
known it all. But He is a God that hideth himself, and his judgments
are unsearchable. Canst thou by searching find out God? Canst thou
find out the Almighty unto perfection? And His ways are as inscrutable
as his being is. This last, the most inscrutable of all. The saddest
that ever concerned our nation. The bitterest, fearfullest stroke of
all the war. Over it, brave, strong men have sobbed almost to
heart-break. On account of it, little children have hushed their
gleeful laugh and cried in the street. Because of it, the poor
freedmen have gathered the shreds of crape and muslin swept from the
doors of the rich, and sewed them together and stretched them across
the doors and windows of their own rude homes, to symbolize their
humble but sincere sorrow. An old gray-haired negress, held her little
grand-child above the heads of the crowd thronging to take a last look
of the fallen form of the martyr-President, saying, in deep emotion,
"she wanted that little child to see the man that made her free."
Hardly had there been such lamentation in the land, had the first-born
in every house been slain.</p>
               <p>O, we seem to see him now, that high pure soul, who could
say he "never willingly planted a thorn in any man's bosom," as he
stood before the nation when about to take his first official oath,
pleading with the South to pause ere they plunged the country into an
abyss of blood and horror. "In your hands, my dissatisfied fellow
countrymen," said he, "and not in mine, is the momentous issue of
civil war. The Government will not assail you. You can have no
conflict without being yourselves the aggressors. You have no oath
registered in heaven to destroy the government, while I shall have the
most solemn one to 'preserve, protect and defend' it. I am loth to
close. We are not enemies, but friends. We must not be enemies. Though
passion may have strained, it must not break our bonds of
affection. The mystic chords of memory, stretching from every
battle-field and patriot grave to every-living heart and hearth-stone
all over this broad land, will yet quell the chorus of the Union, when
again touched, as surely they will be, by the better angels of our
nature." It was thus he closed the most affecting appeal. ever made to
a disaffected party against the madness and crime of treason. But,
alas! the better angels of the hearts to whom he made appeal had left
them, and fell spirits of evil struck the chords.</p>
               <p>He stood there again, the loved and trusted President, to
take his second oath. The rude shock had come. The country had gone
down into the dark abyss, but was emerging now on the other
side. Still, however, the path onward was rugged and bloody and full
of peril. Have four
<pb n="7" facs="johnson7.jpg"/>
years of war, with such hate and passion, and scorn and calumny, and
cruel, bitter defamation as have been born of them, tainted that high,
pure soul, or put a thought of malice in it? Let the closing words of
his last inaugural answer. "With malice toward none, with charity for
all, with firmness in the right, as God gives us to see the right, let
us strive on to finish the work we are in, to bind up the nation's
wounds, to care for him who shall have borne the battle and for his
widow and orphans: to do all which may achieve a just and a lasting
peace among ourselves and with all nations." There speaks the same
gentle, loving, merciful heart, that so affectionately and touchingly
pleaded ere full armed treason plunged the nation into the horrors of
this fratricidal strife. Vindictive wrath and hate have done their
worst, but they have waked no echo in his bosom. <hi rend="italic">Abraham Lincoln has firmer hold of truth and God and the
people's hearts. That is all.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A few weeks later and the Ruler, who, of all the men that
ever lived, made war with a Christian spirit, was seeking, under the
inspiration of decisive victory, with paternal and generous
magnanimity, his heart full of charities and pardons, to effect
conciliation. The nation knew that that manliest and gentlest of
spirits was opposed to all avoidable severity, and the advocate of
largest overtures of mercy to the criminal assailants. At the very
threshold of the gate of peace he was about to open, he was brutally
and cowardly assassinated. With forgiveness in his heart for them, and
a plea for their pardon on his lips, they shot him dead and <hi rend="italic">murdered mercy</hi>. There is nothing in all the records
of regicides or annals of crime that transcends this, save the scene
at Golgotha, where, from the bloody cross on which his murderers had
nailed him, and amidst their jeers and scoffs, the lips of the dying
Son of God moved with the prayer, "Father forgive them: they know not
what they do."</p>
               <p>It was most foul and atrocious deed. To name it is to
expose its malignity and horror. And yet,--and yet, my hearers, though
his charities and nobilities and virtues, all "plead like angels,
trumpet-tongued, against the deep damnation of his taking off," it was
best that he should die. Best, because God's way, not ours. Best, not
for the assassin. "It <hi rend="italic">must needs be</hi> that offences
come. <hi rend="italic">But wo to that man by whom the offence
cometh.</hi>" The name of J. Wilkes Booth is indissolubly and forever
linked with that of him of whom Jesus said, "It had been good for that
man if he had not been born." Best, not for the South. The gloved hand
of justice and power is naked now, and it is of iron. But best for the
great cause of God. It was God's way, not ours. <hi rend="italic">He</hi> was not taken by surprise. He is not
disappointed. A thousand swift messengers of His could have sped from
the four winds of heaven, from earth and air and sea and sky, to foil
the foul plot, though it were laid with all the craft and subtlety of
hell, if He had so willed. If He controls armies and organizes victory
for them, may he not control men! If He winged the arrow, shot from a
bow at a venture, which smote the king of Israel between the Joints of
the harness, has he nothing to do with the fatal ball of the fire-arm
in the hand of a ruffianly assassin! If it was His providence that
called our beloved Chief Magistrate to the kingdom for such a time as
this, was it not His providence that bade the faithful servant "come
up higher," when his work was done? We wonder, indeed, that the
thunderbolts of God were still, when that arm was
<pb n="8" facs="johnson8.jpg"/>
raised to do the cruel, deadly deed of causeless murder; but that
infinitely wise and holy purposes will be answered by it, it is not
permitted us to doubt. For of him and through and to him are all
things.</p>
               <p>Gathered about the fallen form of our lamented President,
we fortify our hearts with this sublimest truth, and re-dedicate
ourselves to the work in which he died a martyr. Beneath the laurel
and the willow the bowed heart of the nation pays its tribute of
unutterable sorrow to the memory of its loved and lost leader. Like
Moses, he had brought us through the wilderness. Like Moses, in the
midst of all our perils and trials, "he endured as seeing him who is
invisible." Like Moses, he did not escape the murmurings of the
people. May God forgive us; if our complaints laid one added burden on
his poor, patient, loving heart. He was permitted at last to climb
Pisgah's height, and to ravish his sight with the golden vision of
union and peace. That deep, sad, sorrowful eye of his was lighted up
with the dawn of a morning he had prayed and longed for all our dark
night, the darkest through which nation ever passed to day. Upon the
summit of the mount he stood and looked, and he was not--for God took
him.</p>
               <p>There are no broken lives in God's plan. ABRAHAM LINCOLN'S
had rounded into perfect completeness, and he was called home. Sacred
be the commonwealth that entombs him. The gentle flowers of the
prairie make room for his grave. And not another in all the earth
shall ever bedewed with the tears of a people's prouder or fonder
affection. Rear cenotaphs to his memory, O, mourning but redeemed
nation! Let wreaths of faceless laurel be woven for his burial
place. Yet, know that his deeds shall be his noblest monument; and
believe that God has given him "truer crown than any wreath that man
can weave him."</p>
               <p>And now, what to the living? This, first and most manifestly: <hi rend="italic">Our trust is not to lie in an arm of flesh, but in the
living God</hi>. "Cease ye from man whose breath is in his nostrils;
for wherein is he to be accounted of?" When Massillon stood in that
crowded cathedral by the coffin of a King, and saw lying there the
cold and shrouded form of him whose will millions had obeyed and
feared, he lifted his hand to heaven and said,--"God only is great."
On Friday, April 14, ABRAHAM LINCOLN, in all the investitures of power,
was the peer or superior of any King on earth. But in a night, shorn
of every vestige of authority, he passed a naked human soul, to the
bar of God. His commanding career, the increasing marvel of the world,
was ended by a pistol shot. The impersonated malice, and hate of
treason's fell spirit, changed the commander-in-chief of a half
million armed men, and the civil ruler of thirty millions of people,
to a lump of lifeless clay. "God only is great." And God is not
dead. Truth and God never die. With Him the nations are as a drop of a
bucket--He taketh up the isles as a very little thing. He bringeth the
princes to nothing: He maketh the judges of the earth as vanity. He
putteth down one and setteth up another. But there are no changes on
<hi rend="italic">that</hi> throne. <hi rend="italic">He</hi> lives and
rules who has kept us thus far, and whose right arm of power no one
felt need of, more than the lamented dead. We have lost our
President--but the President's God is our God still. "Trust him, ye
people," is one of the voices out of the midst of the cloud.</p>
               <pb n="9" facs="johnson9.jpg"/>
               <p>This, secondly, is to be said concerning the event that has
draped the land with symbols of sorrow: <hi rend="italic">It has given
another signal vindication of Republican institutions--of government
by the people</hi>. Liberty takes on new courage from this hour
forth. She has received a new baptism of blood, and <hi rend="italic">lives</hi>: and assurance deepens in men's hearts that she
is placed beyond the manacle and the sword of her foes, now and
forever.</p>
               <p>No doubt the assassins thought to make such record that
dark night of death and blood as should lead to national
dismemberment. They looked for division in consequence of the anarchy
they hoped to effect. Ah, the murderous blow struck away all our past
differences and welded us into compactest unity. Over the dead body of
the slaughtered Chief, a united people took renewed oath of
consecration to finish the work which he died in doing. Four hours
after his spirit took its flight, the official oath was administered
to his lawful successor, and the Government moved on without jostle or
pause. Great financial revulsions, and the overthrow of public credit
would have been the almost inevitable effect of such an occurrence in
any nations of the Old World. But even this most sensitive fiber of
our system suffered no derangement whatever from the shock. Revolution
would follow swift in the wake of such assassination in France. Here,
the wheels of government are not stopped for a moment. Neither the
permanency of our institutions nor the regular administration of our
laws is in the slightest degree affected. It is impossible to estimate
the weight this fact will carry with it, among despotisms. Out of this
last and saddest trial the Republic has come, more wedded to its
cause, more true to its fundamental idea, more united in its purpose,
to root out every fiber and vestige of rebellion, than ever. Who shall
doubt that the fruit of its past shall pale before the glorious
yielding of its future, when <hi rend="italic">such martyr-blood has
moistened its soil.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Another voice out of the midst of the cloud is this: <hi rend="italic">that the spirit of this rebellion is revealed before all
the world as most malignant and atrocious</hi>. Perhaps this last
exhibition was needed, in the providence of God, to keep the plotters
of treason from playing the role of martyrs. It puts an eternal stigma
upon their cause and sends it down to posterity loaded with infamy.</p>
               <p>The plot of assassination may not be traced to the leaders
of the rebellion. I trust it will not be. Possibly they did not know
of this foul conspiracy. But it was born of their spirit. It had its
inspiration in their madness. It was the culmination of their savage
and God-defying rage. And it is as indissolubly linked and welded to
their cause, as if they themselves were the proven and principal
actors. Ah, if they did not do the deed, they gave the doers some
bloody instructions. Proposals for Mr. Lincoln's assassination were
coolly and openly made in the South, and circulated without word of
remonstrance through leading journals, even before his first
inauguration. This was in the midst of wholesale perjury, through
repudiation of their official oaths. And crime has since been linked
to crime. They have starved and murdered our prisoners. They have
sought to fire the largest metropolis of the nation, full of helpless
women and children. Thy have waged their deadly strife by acts wholly
outside
<pb n="10" facs="johnson10.jpg"/>
the pale of civilized warfare. Truly they had been guilty of crimson
horrors enough, to make this last not so utterly beyond their agency
and connivance.</p>
               <p>And what was their treason itself? Was it anything less
than that of which this crime is the personification? Was not that a
blow at the Nation's heart? And did it not mean <hi rend="italic">death</hi> to the Nation, as truly as the blow that struck
down its head and chief? Perhaps there was danger of our forgetting
this, and of failing to regard this great wrong of treason with our
righteous abhorrence. Perhaps we were growing too oblivious of the
fact that association in crime involves individual guilt. Such
countenance do masses give to great iniquities. So common is it to
lessen our estimation of the heinousness of damning deeds, where great
communities and organized though rebellious governments are the
doers. But that danger, I believe, is past. Henceforth, forever, by
this last accursed plot, born of the spirit of slavery, itself the
child of hell, God in his providence has made this rebellion so odious
and abominable in men's eyes, that loyalty to this free government
will be a thing they dare not trifle with. When this blow fell,
planned in the interests of treason, it struck both ways. It slew our
President, indeed, but the backward stroke branded the brows of the
leaders of this dark conspiracy with the brand of Cain. Fugitives and
vagabonds shall they be in the earth, though they escape the
halter. The voice of the blood of the martyred President, and the
voice of the blood of thousands more, as truly martyrs as he, will cry
unto them from the ground; and though their hoarded gold buy them the
privileges of a dwelling place on some spot of earth, they will go
down with sorrow to the grave, their punishment greater than they can
bear.</p>
               <p>There comes another voice out of the midst of the
cloud--<hi rend="italic">justice</hi>! There <hi rend="italic">is</hi>
such a thing. God is just. Justice is the habitation of his
throne--yea, its foundation. His government rests upon it. His law
rests upon it. There can be no government, human or divine, if justice
be ignored. Men's moral convictions are on its side. Within their
bosoms is implanted of God the love of it. They do not always know
justice. And when they do know it they do not always conform to
it. They are taken in some swoop of passion, or are over-attracted by
the magnet of the affections, or they get in some bog of sickly
sentimentality, and are biased and blinded. But justice is, naturally,
to the conscience, as light is to the eye, or truth to the intellect,
or sentiment to the heart. Thus constituted we must be true to it, or
false to our own nature and so false to God. It is as much our duty to
do justly, as to love mercy and to walk humbly.</p>
               <p>This quality has relation to law! If law is mere advice,
justice is a farce. If law is command, sustained by penalty for its
violation, then justice is vindicated as a reality. In human
government this is so. In God's government. If in either, penalty is
laid aside, without meeting the claims of law and vindicating justice,
sooner or later, there will be anarchy and chaos. Calvary's cross and
Calvary's victim, that divinest proof of love and forgiveness God ever
gave the world, was possible, only as inexorable justice there poised
her scales. The innocent Sufferer would never have prayed "Father
forgive them," if his sufferings and death were not even then making
it <hi rend="italic">just</hi> for God to forgive.</p>
               <pb n="11" facs="johnson11.jpg"/>
               <p>Guilt, therefore, must be expiated. Crime must be atoned
for. Offenders against law, must suffer the penalties of law. To the
extent that we fail of exacting this up to the utmost requirements of
the public safety and the general good, to that extent we harm justice
and open upon ourselves the flood-gates of lawlessness. "The soul that
sinneth, it shall die," is not an arbitrary edict of naked power, but
the enunciation of a principle proceeding from the very nature and
being of God.</p>
               <p>Perhaps we were in danger of ignoring this fundamental
quality. I think we were. In our joy at the prospect of peace, and on
account of the difficulties that surrounded the whole question of the
settlement of the protracted strife, we were being led to feel and act
as if secession was not a great crime. Under the inspiration of
victory, we were tempted by undue leniency to hide the infamy and the
ruin of the rebel leaders, and to palliate the criminality of their
course. It may be that we were on the point of taking back a nest of
vipers into our bosom to nurse them there until they gathered
envenomed power sufficient to strike at our heart again. We all know
the breast of our smitten chief did never shut its gates of mercy on
them. That humanest heart of his was full of charities. And though I
believe he would sooner have died than purposely betrayed justice,
perhaps his was too kindly a nature for the stern work of righteous
retribution, that God has especially commissioned governments to
execute upon evil doers. So God took him away from war's tumults and
from retribution's ungrateful office,--home.</p>
               <p>But his taking off, by wicked instrument was a startling
and terrible revelation of rebel malignity. And the sharp report of
that deadly pistol shot has flashed the word justice through the
Nation's heart. O, does it not seem that God would thus write on our
national records, in the blood of a martyred President, that treason
is the highest and the blackest of crimes, and that its punishment
must be adequate and inevitable.</p>
               <p>Surely this is one of the interpretations to be put upon
the event, we mourn to-day. But let it be <hi rend="italic">justice</hi>, not <hi rend="italic">vengeance</hi>. <hi rend="italic">"Vengeance is mine, I will repay</hi>," saith the
Lord. Personally, we have no right to cherish other than the spirit of
forgiveness, and from our heart of hearts to pray for them. And in our
governmental capacity, as a power ordained of God, we are to bear the
sword with the solemn investitures that befit such high
ordainment. Blind passion, illegal violence, reckless dealing out of
retribution, will only defeat the ends of justice, and lift the
conspirators in the eyes of mankind, from the ignominious doom of
traitors, into the welcome elevation of heroic martyrs.</p>
               <p>No. Let the grave of ABRAHAM LINCOLN be unpolluted by the
blood of Americans slaughtered for revenge. But, if the culprits shall
at last be brought under the police arm of national power, with all
the solemnities high judicial process, let them be proceeded against;
and adjudged solemnities of treason, as they will be, solemnly,
holily, before the nation, and the world, and God, let us express our
righteous abhorrence of their crime by meting out its righteous
penalty. Thus shall we show that national and unity and life are held
so precious, that no man or men shall selfishly put them in peril and
go free from punishment. Thus shall we show that loyalty to this
government of freemen is a sacred and paramount obligation, to be
thrown off only less easily than loyalty to God. To whom and through
whom and to whom are all things; to whom be glory forever. Amen.</p>
            </div2>
         </div1>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>