<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader><fileDesc>
         <titleStmt n="Death of President Lincoln">
            <title>Death of President Lincoln</title>
            <author>Lowe, Rev. Charles</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Compiled and edited by</resp>
               <name>Beck
Center</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent/>
         <publicationStmt><publisher>Lewis H. Beck Center</publisher><pubPlace>Emory University</pubPlace><address>
               <addrLine>Atlanta,
Georgia</addrLine>
            </address><availability>
               <p>1996 Emory
University. Permission is granted to download, transmit, or otherwise
reproduce, distribute or display the contributions to the work claimed
by Emory University for non-profit educational purposes, provided
this header is included in its entirety.  For inquiries about
commercial uses, contact the Director, 
Pitts Theology Library, Emory
University, Atlanta, Georgia 30322</p>
            </availability><date>1999</date></publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Lincoln
Sermons Project</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Lowe,
Rev. Charles. Death of President Lincoln: A Sermon Delivered in the
Unitarian Church in Archdale Street, Charleston, S. C. Sunday, April
23, 1865. Boston: American Unitarian Association. 1865.</bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc><encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This text derives from the Special Collections 
of Pitts Theology Library, Emory University, and is produced in 
collaboration with the Lewis H. Beck Center a, the Emory 
Preservation Office, and Pitts Theology Library.</p>
            <p>TRANSCRIBER: Lewis H. Beck Center and Emory University 
Preservation Office.</p>
            <p>PRODUCER:  BookLab, Inc., 1606 Headway Circle, 
Suite 100, Austin, TX 78754</p>
            <p>CAPTURE DEVICE: XEROX DocuImage 620S flatbed scanner</p>
            <p>CAPTURE DETAILS: Scanner software: XEROX ScanTool 
version 4.2.3; no gamma correction; images are all bitonal.</p>
            <p>CHANGE HISTORY: Using the Adobe Photoshop Batch Processor, 
we interpolated  the original TIFF files to 8-bit grays, 
and altered the resolution to 144 dpi, producing screen 
images twice the original size.  We then saved them in 
JPEG format.  We produced GIF thumbnails from the JPEG files.</p>
            <p>RESOLUTION: 600 ppi</p>
            <p>COMPRESSION: Resolution 144 per inch with Constrain 
Properties to 72 per inch.</p>
            <p>SOURCE: Original documents.</p>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc><revisionDesc><change><name>Stewart Varner</name> transformed this document from p4 to p5 on <date when="2010-03-22">March 22, 2010</date></change><change xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><date>1999</date><label>Staff</label><name>Scott Ellis</name>SGML tags inserted in compliance
with TEI guidelines using TEILITE</change></revisionDesc></teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div1 xml:id="lowe.001" n="Death of President Lincoln" type="text">
            <head> 
               <bibl> 
                  <title>Death of
President Lincoln</title> 
                  <date>Sunday, April 23, 1865</date>
                  <pubPlace>Unitarian Church in Archdale Street, Charleston,
S. C.</pubPlace> 
                  <author>Lowe, Rev. Charles</author> 
                  
                     <pubPlace>Boston</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>American Unitarian
Association</publisher>
                     <date>1865</date>
                   
               <idno type="ark">http://pid.emory.edu/ark:/25593/15qkw</idno></bibl> 
            </head>
            <p>
               <figure><graphic url=""/>
                  <figDesc>1st page of Rev. Charles Lowe's
Death of President Lincoln.</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <p>Death of President Lincoln:</p>
            <p>A</p>
            <p>S E R M O N</p>
            <p>DELIVERED IN THE</p>
            <p>UNITARIAN CHURCH IN ARCHDALE STREET,</p>
            <p>CHARLESTON, S. C.,</p>
            <p>SUNDAY, APRIL 23, 1865.</p>
            <p>BY REV. CHARLES LOWE,</p>
            <p>OF MASSACHUSETTS.</p>
            <p>Published by Request of the Congregation.</p>
            <p>BOSTON:</p>
            <p>AMERICAN UNITARIAN ASSOCIATION.</p>
            <p>1865.</p>
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>
               <figure><graphic url=""/>
                  <figDesc>2nd page of
Rev. Charles Lowe's Death of President Lincoln.</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <p>BOSTON:</p>
            <p>PRINTED BY JOHN WILSON AND SON,</p>
            <p>15, WATER
STREET.</p>
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>
               <figure><graphic url=""/>
                  <figDesc>3rd page of
Rev. Charles Lowe's Death of President Lincoln.</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <div2 xml:id="lowe.002" n="SERMON" type="sermon">
               <head>SERMON.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <p>"And it shall be, when they say unto thee, Wherefore
sighest thou? that thou shalt answer, For the tidings; because it
cometh: and every heart shall melt, and all hands shall be feeble, and
every spirit shall faint, and all knees shall be weak as
water."--EZEK. xxi. 7.</p>
               </epigraph>
               <p>THERE is but one topic upon which I can have the heart to speak
to-day, or you the hearts to attend. We have moved about together,
these last three days, bowed down with a common grief; and we seek
this sanctuary that we may together find comfort and guidance in view
of the awful trial which has fallen upon us.</p>
               <p>I find no language in which to express my sense of the
appalling magnitude of the calamity which was told in the tidings
which have shrouded the land with gloom.</p>
               <p>It is little to say, that the Chief Magistrate of the
nation is no more; for, momentous as such an event would be regarded
under any circumstances, there is that, in the present condition of
national affairs, which makes the loss of the nation's leader and head
such a calamity as our hearts can feel, but our tongues cannot
express. I think that at no period of our history could the loss have
<pb n="4"/>
                  <figure><graphic url=""/>
                     <figDesc>4th page of Rev. Charles
Lowe's Death of President Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
seemed more deplorable. True, we have passed through more perilous and
difficult times than these. President Lincoln has himself guided us
through intricacies and dangers compared with which those of the
present seem trifling. But that very fact makes us lament him more
than we should have done at any time before; for every such proof of
his wisdom and worth only secured for him a new measure of our
confidence, till through all the land there was not a loyal heart that
did not gratefully own his sway, and lean on him for direction in view
of difficulties, which, though not the same in kind as those we have
passed, are yet such as require steadiness of nerve and purity of
principle and wisdom of counsel (such as we knew were his), else all
that we have gained may yet be wrecked.</p>
               <p>It is as though the noble Ship of State, safely guided
through storm and night, had come at last, with colors flying and with
crew rejoicing, to the very entrance of the port, soon, safe within
the haven, to find peace and rest. And yet she is first to be piloted
over the bar; and when, just as she is headed in, he on whose clear
eye and firm hand they had relied for this service, as for every thing
before, is smitten down, who can picture the consternation which takes
the place of the rejoicing and the hope?</p>
               <p>My friends, you who have dwelt here, shut out from
intercourse with the North, and receiving only infrequent and usually
distorted statements in regard to current events, can faintly
understand
<pb n="5"/>
                  <figure><graphic url=""/>
                     <figDesc>5th page of Rev. Charles
Lowe's Death of President Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
the sentiment, in regard to Mr. Lincoln, which has gradually taken
possession of the entire population of the Northern and Western
States. He began with a very moderate degree of public confidence and
regard. A large proportion of the most intelligent men in the loyal
states had, at the time of his election, and for a considerable period
afterward, a painful sense of distrust as to his fitness for the
position to which he was called. Ill-wishers to the Union did every
thing to increase this feeling of distrust,--distrust, I say, <hi rend="italic">in his ability</hi>,--that was all. For, from the
beginning to the end, the foulest calumny and the bitterest hate,
though they have tried with fiendish endeavor, have never found one
word to utter against his purity of character and his nobleness of
heart.</p>
               <p>This distrust was slow to yield. Good things were done; but
they were all attributed, on account of this preconceived opinion of
his ability, to the excellence of his advisers, while the evils and
mistakes were all laid to him.</p>
               <p>No man ever worked his way to favor against a harder
current of prejudice. Had he been laboring for popularity, it might
perhaps have been sooner won. He might sooner have made it appear,
that, when great rocks loomed up in our tempestuous course on which we
were nearly wrecked, it was no chance, nor yet the wisdom of his
advisers, but, under God, his steady hand and stout heart alone that
took us safely by. But he thought not of himself or fame, but of his
country; and thus it was only gradually, as, one by one, his
decisions, his
<pb n="6"/>
                  <figure><graphic url=""/>
                     <figDesc>6th page of Rev. Charles
Lowe's Death of President Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
acts, his words, smoothly adjusting perplexities by which we knew the
highest statesmanship was baffled, grandly and unexpectedly disposing
of difficulties that we had dreaded to encounter,--it was only, I say,
as these acts and measures directed our minds to him, that we learned
how, under that unpretending brow, reigned qualities that made him at
length undisputed Lord of our affections and our respect; till now, in
all the territory which has owned his authority, he stands
unmistakably by the side of Washington, in the hearts of his
countrymen.</p>
               <p>And, O brethren! I the time will come when this shall be
the sentiment, not of one section only, but of all the land. Oh that
those people of the South, who plotted his death, could only
understand, as they will by and by, that in all the earth they have
had no truer friend! Through trials, such as we cannot realize, he has
held steadfast their interests, even while resisting their
assaults. No injuries they have ever inflicted on him or his
Government have ever destroyed the kindness which he has felt for
them. He has never been provoked to utter one word of malice or
revenge, though man was never so provoked before. He was magnanimous
(ordinary men would have said) to a fault,--only that his magnanimity
was so coupled with firmness that it commanded respect; and the Nation
gloried in it, and imitated it themselves. Oh! at this hour, when this
last and greatest act of iniquity has inflamed the land creating a
horror of indignation such as even the firing on Sumter did not
<pb n="7"/>
                  <figure><graphic url=""/>
                     <figDesc>7th page of Rev. Charles
Lowe's Death of President Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
rouse, who is left to set the example of forbearance he would have
shown? Blind followers of the rebellion (of whose will that assassin
was only the implement), do they know what a blow they have inflicted
on themselves? Noble, Christian man! his very last recorded words were
of kindness to a conquered army and their chief, and of hope for a
speedy peace. And if, after that fatal wound had been received, he
could have roused for one moment to consciousness, and his lips had
had power to speak, who can doubt that his language would have been,
forgetting all personal wrong, "Father, forgive them; for they know
not what they do!"</p>
               <p>But all this reminds me that this is not the time for
eulogy, however grateful to our feelings this would be; and those same
lips, if they could speak to-day, would say, "Do not pause to pay
honors to me; but turn to take up the work which I have dropped, and
see to it that my death shall be, not a detriment, but a service, to
the State."</p>
               <p>I turn, therefore, from words of mourning, to speak of the
duties and the prospects which lie before us as they are made more
clear by this event. I shall speak plainly, and perhaps may say things
unpleasant to some of you, though loyal men; but I shall speak in
kindness, and with respect. Nay, I remember, with respect also, many
of those who once sat here, honored and loved; who, exiles now, and
following the fortunes of the cause they have chosen, would receive
with denunciation what I say. God forbid that I should utter any thing
that should seem to taunt them, or any thing in the
<pb n="8"/>
                  <figure><graphic url=""/>
                     <figDesc>8th page of Rev. Charles
Lowe's Death of President Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
spirit of revenge! I do not feel it. I feel no ill-will or spirit of
condemnation toward any person, simply because he is on the opposite
side. I know the power of education, and of prejudice, and of
example. I know the terrible contagion of opinion and purpose, when
once an earnest sentiment takes possession of a community; and, when I
think how every thing of social influence has combined to lead them as
they have gone, I dare not boast to myself, that, if I had been
similarly placed, I might not have been similarly misled.</p>
               <p>Conscious of this freedom from the spirit of exultation or
of animosity let me speak on a few points in regard to your present
duties and position.</p>
               <p>1. The one point which is the centre and basis of all the
rest, as regards this community, is <hi rend="italic">the necessity
for</hi> and <hi rend="italic">the absence of a real and uncompromising
loyalty</hi>.</p>
               <p>When I speak of the absence of such loyalty, let me not be
misunderstood. I do not mean that it is utterly wanting. On the
contrary, there are some (and among them this society has a proud
list), who, "faithful found among the faithless," have proved their
fidelity amid such trials, and under such sacrifices, that it puts to
the blush the ordinary loyalty of us of the North who have never been
tempted to serve. But I need not say to you that the number of such
loyal citizens is small; and that, even among those who have remained
within the Union lines, there is an amount of hatred to the Union
which is very feebly disguised. 
<pb n="9"/>
                  <figure><graphic url=""/>
                     <figDesc>9th page of Rev. Charles
Lowe's Death of President Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
Many who, for the sake of the immunities which it affords, have taken
the oath of allegiance, curse the Government which they have sworn to
obey; and no one would be credulous enough to suppose, that the oath
would be valid with them any longer than they were kept to it by their
interests or their fears.</p>
               <p>"But," it will be said, "must not
some allowances be made to the infirmities of human nature? Is it not
too much to expect, that the hopes and the endeavors of four such
years (however misguided they may have been), branded into the heart
and the convictions by so many experiences,--is it not too much to
expect, that they shall at once be rooted out, and leave no angry
sore? Can a man of spirit bear the consciousness of forced submission,
and show no trace of wounded pride? There must be," it is argued,
"allowance for all this, and concession to such an inevitable state of
feeling."</p>
               <p>In reply to such an argument, I desire to set forth as
clearly as I can the precise point which is to be observed, and an
important distinction which both sides are to keep constantly in
mind.</p>
               <p>All that may be said in plea for the necessity for
concession to the natural feelings of disappointment and alienation, I
would recognize to the full. In all matters pertaining to the
re-adjustment of things, it is right for the successful party to
regard with tenderness and respect the opinions and habits of those
for whom the turn of events has given them the power to
legislate. Even where their own views of what is right are most con-
<pb n="10"/>
                  <figure><graphic url=""/>
                     <figDesc>10th page of Rev. Charles
Lowe's Death of President Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
firmed, it may often be both Christian and wise to yield and wait
until time shall so soften the feelings and weaken the power of old
associations, that the changes may be wrought by common consent and
co-operation; whereas, if insisted on now, they would only embitter
and annoy. In all this spirit of mutual concession and consideration,
I trust and believe the North will go at least half-way; and that the
wise and generous spirit of President Lincoln may still direct the
national policy, and reign in the people's hearts. But there is a
distinction which, on the other hand, the South must understand. There
is one thing which is absolutely essential to the first beginning of
peace; and that is <hi rend="italic">unqualified submission and
unreserved and unhesitating allegiance, with a determined purpose
heartily to abide by it</hi> (for this mere sham of profession amounts
to nothing), <hi rend="italic">to the Constitution and Government of the
United States</hi>. It will be said, this very thing is the hardest of
all, most galling to the sensibilities, and most needing time for the
gradual subsiding of sectional pride. To be sure it is hard; and it is
useless to try to smooth it by any words which it would be easy to
utter, but which would only increase the feeling they might seek to
allay. But, hard as it may be, it must be met, and must be
accepted. The North cannot excuse them from it if it would, nor can it
help much to ease it. With all its pain, it is as absolutely essential
to the first birth of the new peace as to the woman is agony of labor
when a child is born.</p>
               <p>Christ said to his disciples when he sent
them
<pb n="11"/>
                  <figure><graphic url=""/>
                     <figDesc>11th page of Rev. Charles
Lowe's Death of President Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
forth, "Into whatsoever house ye enter, first say, Peace be to this
house. <hi rend="italic">And if the Son of Peace be there</hi>, your
peace shall rest upon it: if not it shall turn to you again." He
teaches that even to those who go out from his very presence, and
filled with his spirit of love, peace cannot be compelled until the
answering conditions are found. No one who had mingled much with the
people of this city previous to the news of the assassination, and
caught the sentiment of those (outside the loyal few in this
community), and measured thus the sentiment of the region round, could
have helped the conviction, that "the Son of Peace" was not there. No
one but would have dreaded lest, if, through the intense longing for
peace, a settlement should be attempted on such a foundation, we
should soon be reminded of the prophet's words, where he says,--</p>
               <p>"They have seduced my people, saying, Peace, and there was
no peace; and one built up a wall, and, lo, others daubed it with
untempered mortar. Say unto them which daub it with untempered mortar,
that it shall fall: there shall be an overflowing shower; and ye, O
great hailstones! shall fall, and a stormy wind shall rend it."</p>
               <p>I have purposely predicated what I said respecting this
unfavorable condition of Southern sentiment as applying to the <hi rend="italic">time preceding</hi> the news of Mr. Lincoln's death. That
event has materially changed the aspect of affairs. Perhaps it was
that it roused a fear of the consequences,--in the increased
stringency and austerity of the policy that
<pb n="12"/>
                  <figure><graphic url=""/>
                     <figDesc>12th page of Rev. Charles
Lowe's Death of President Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
would be pursued; perhaps it was that the horror at the deed gave a
thrill of indignation that was in sympathy with the Union side: but it
matters not what the motive may have been,--that event has done more
to hasten the true conditions of peace, than would have been done by
months of ordinary endeavor. The day on which the dreadful news
arrived will be for this city a memorable day. It was the nineteenth
of April,--the anniversary of the battle of Lexington and Concord, in
1775; and of the shedding of blood in the streets of Baltimore, in
1861. That morning, I sat in a feeling of disappointment at something
that had just occurred to illustrate the lack of cordial loyalty in
the South; and, as I recalled the date, I wondered if, this year, it
would be marked by any event. Even as I pondered, the boat was
steaming up the harbor with the intelligence that was to burst over
the city with a cloud that should mantle all in gloom.</p>
               <p>Who shall picture the despondency of that day? as one said
to another in your streets, "Ruin! ruin! all hope of reconciliation is
gone!" Ah! but in these things God is greater than our fears, and out
of this awful cloud came presently a gleam of light. No sooner was the
first shock over, than it began to be felt that now the hour for
decision had come. That very day, in this church,--which hereafter
will be proud in claiming the honor of being the first to take a
stand,--resolutions were passed (the first since the occupation of
this city), promising fidelity and service to the Union. The
<pb n="13"/>
                  <figure><graphic url=""/>
                     <figDesc>13th page of Rev. Charles
Lowe's Death of President Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
day, like those of which it was the anniversary, was a day of gloom;
but in its results it will be glorious, like them. On the dark 19th of
April, in 1775, liberty was born. In 1861, resistance to treason was
secured, and the continuance of the Union assured; in 1865, disunion
was buried in the grave of Abraham Lincoln.</p>
               <p>Who can say, when we consider this effect of the tidings of
that day,--who can say but that God's wisdom saw that he whose life
seemed to us necessary to our service, could serve us better by his
death?</p>
               <p>But, even now, all is not done; and I must speak to you,
who stand in the fore-front of Southern loyalty, in regard to the
great duties and responsibilities which now rest upon you.</p>
               <p>The mass of the Southern people are not even yet brought to
the point which is the necessary preliminary of peace. There is still
a holding-back,--not in most cases persistent and violent, but such as
is natural enough from the difficulty that grows out of the conflict
of feeling which it is not necessary to describe. Now, if once a
strong and influential movement is inaugurated in the right direction,
it may soon create a current of popular feeling, on which the
hesitating may be borne along to safety and peace; just as, by the
same power, four years ago, they were carried, through the contagion
of sympathy and enthusiasm, into danger and wrong.</p>
               <p>Rarely have men been placed in circumstances more
responsible and more enviable for power of
<pb n="14"/>
                  <figure><graphic url=""/>
                     <figDesc>14th page of Rev. Charles
Lowe's Death of President Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
usefulness than you, loyal citizens of Charleston, are to-day. You
are, on one hand, aglow with love of the Union, strengthened by years
of longing and suffering; and yet, on the other, you have a hold upon
your fellow-citizens, such as can only be acquired by years of
intercourse and sympathy, and community of interests. It is for you at
this hour to lead back your State.</p>
               <p>I am aware, there are certain imagined difficulties which
suggest themselves to your minds, in regard to which a few words may
be said; e.g.:--</p>
               <p>1. I have heard many urge this, that there are now no
recognized leaders, --that the accustomed guides of public sentiment
either have passed away, or still continue in sympathy with the cause
of rebellion, and there are none to take their place. Friends, let all
history teach you, <hi rend="italic">that emergencies make men, if they
do not find them</hi>. There may be <hi rend="italic">among you</hi>
those whose powers have never been called out, and perhaps are not
suspected by the community or by themselves, who are to be the great
men of your future, and perhaps equal to your great men of the
past. At any rate, for leadership in this particular thing, a true
heart, an honest conviction, an earnest sentiment, a sound judgment,
and a character to command respect, are worth more than any political
experience and reputation, or any powers of debate.</p>
               <p>May God touch you, and such as you, with a sense of the
opportunity, and then leaders will not lack!</p>
               <p>2. Another cause
of discouragement is the sup-
<pb n="15"/>
                  <figure><graphic url=""/>
                     <figDesc>15th page of Rev. Charles
Lowe's Death of President Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
posed difficulty, if not hopelessness, of ever restoring the kindly
feelings on the part of those who have been so long and so bitterly
estranged. Many believe that these feelings can never be
restored. Look, they say, at the facts. The war, regarded from a
military point of view, is nearly over; and yet you find a degree of
rancor and bitterness and animosity, which is as great as when the war
began. What hope is there, they say, of that harmony of feeling that
will ever make the people of both sections brothers again? This
difficulty deserves to be especially considered; for it has been the
occasion for despondency with many, North as well as South. In answer
to it, I might refer to history, and show how true sympathy between
hostile sections has more than once succeeded to the bitterest civil
feuds. But I would rather answer it by reference to the nature of
things. From the necessity of the case, <hi rend="italic">intercourse</hi>, both civil and commercial, <hi rend="italic">must be restored</hi>. In these days of railroads and
telegraphs, when distance is annihilated, <hi rend="italic">contact
between the two sections is inevitable;</hi> and it is equally
inevitable, that personal relationships of business and interest must
be formed. Before such influences, old animosities must melt. Then,
again, by the very intensity of the conflict, we have been made at
least to respect each other's bravery as never before; and this
feeling of respect is such a bond that you find now the quickest signs
of friendliness are among the bitterest antagonists. It did not take
long to form friendships between the soldiers of Grant and Lee. Then,
as we sail
<pb n="16"/>
                  <figure><graphic url=""/>
                     <figDesc>16th page of Rev. Charles
Lowe's Death of President Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
out into the future, there are to be new experiences in which we are
to share,--trials in which we are to stand side by side,--glories
which shall belong to both. The country is to be ours <hi rend="italic">together</hi>; its emblems, our common pride; its history,
our common possession.</p>
               <p>Of this approaching union we find the first harbinger in
the event which we commemorate to-day. Six months ago, an observer
would have said, that if there was one point in which was embodied as
it were, the spirit of our dissensions, it was the hate on the one
side, and the affection on the other, toward him who presided over our
national affairs; and yet the first thing in which the sympathies of
our once-more-to-be-united people have joined is in the common sorrow
which seems to prevail, South as well as North, over the grave of
Abraham Lincoln.</p>
               <p>But what if the indication of such unanimity of feeling be,
as yet, slight and uncertain? Let this not lead us to despond. Go out
with me into your gardens, and look at one of your fig-trees, now
loaded with its early fruit. All the spring, you have been watching
it, and giving it your constant care. You saw the bud when the first
warm days developed it, and you rejoiced when the blight did not
prevent it from bursting into bloom. You saw it swell into fruit; and
you dug about the tree, and secured it from drought, and the fruit has
expanded, and fills you with promise as it increases day by day; and
yet, even a few weeks hence, when it has attained its size, and is
nearly ready to be plucked,
<pb n="17"/>
                  <figure><graphic url=""/>
                     <figDesc>17th page of Rev. Charles
Lowe's Death of President Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
if one should taste it he would find it harsh and puckery, and would
throw it from him in disgust. What if we should say, "Ah! that is for
your pains. You have waited all these weeks; and rains have watered,
and suns have shone, and you have digged; and now, when, by all
calculation, the fruit should at least show signs of ripeness, if it
is ever to be good, it has no more the flavor of a fig than had that
first blossom in the spring." You would answer, "Wait, my friend, but
a single day, till one more sun shall have quickened and mellowed it,
and till that subtle chemistry shall have acted on its juices and
softened its pulp, and I will pluck it, and you will declare, as you
bite its luscious sides, that its taste is worthy of the gods." Well,
so it is with the fruit of a great contest for principle and right
like this, in which our hearts are bound. Four long years it has been
watered by a nation's blood and tears. It has been shone on by the
generous favor of a people's heart; it has been digged about and
tilled by a costly service of toil and care. You say, that now, when
it ought to be nearly ripe, there are still no signs of sweetness in
it, but only bitterness and rancor. I tell you, that it is no more a
miracle to expect that all the mutual hate and sourness of spirit that
now divides our hostile sections, and all those hindrances which now
seem so strong, shall, when the hour comes, melt and mellow into the
realization of a true peace and Union, such as the most sanguine can
predict, than it is that the hard juices of your fig shall, in one
day, after months of sourness,
<pb n="18"/>
                  <figure><graphic url=""/>
                     <figDesc>18th page of Rev. Charles
Lowe's Death of President Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
change into the richness and sweetness that is one of the marvels of
the year.</p>
               <p>But I have detained you too long. I have omitted to speak
of other questions, which, though difficult and trying, are of vital
importance, and must be met. I have omitted to speak of them, because
this one matter of loyalty is so at the basis of every thing, that,
for the hour, it supersedes all the rest.</p>
               <p>Pardon me if, because I am addressing a Southern audience,
I have dwelt chiefly upon the duties of the South. It is not that I do
not recognize the same necessity for the conquering of prejudice, for
the spirit of reconciliation, for the willingness to forget the past,
and to work together for the future, on the part of the North as well;
and whichever side has been most grievously wronged, has now the most
favored lot, for it has the most to forgive.</p>
               <p>And now, one word more in conclusion respecting him whom we
meet to deplore. He stands before us, and will so stand in history, as
the Moses of this Israel of ours. The medium and the willing
instrument of God, he has led us through the wanderings of the
wilderness for four long years. "Meek," but, like his great prototype,
not with the meekness of imbecility, but of reliance on a power that
was not his own; yearning, like him, for the deliverance of the people
he was appointed to lead; standing firm in his purpose when they, in
moments of discouragement, sighed after the flesh-pots they had left
behind,--
<pb n="19"/>
                  <figure><graphic url=""/>
                     <figDesc>19th page of Rev. Charles
Lowe's Death of President Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
the parallel became complete when, at last, after the final act of the
struggle was consummated, and after, in the rebel capital (the goal of
his efforts), he was able to declare the rebellion substantially at an
end, and the wanderings over; "with his eye not dim, nor his natural
force abated," he was called to die. It was like Moses upon Mount
Nebo, where he was permitted to see, but not himself to enter, the
Promised Land.</p>
               <p>But to the people it is given to enter in, rejoicing after
their weary wanderings, and without one lost tribe. The promised land
of peace and Union, and freedom for all, and prosperity restored. Be
not cast down. The fig-tree shall blossom again, and fruit shall be in
the vines; the labor of the olive shall revive, and the fields shall
yield their meat; and, all together, we will "rejoice in the Lord, and
will joy in the God of our salvation."</p>
               <pb n="20"/>
               <p>
                  <figure><graphic url=""/>
                     <figDesc>20th page of
Rev. Charles Lowe's Death of President Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <p>PROCEEDINGS</p>
               <p>OF A</p>
               <p>MEETING HELD IN THE UNITARIAN CHURCH IN</p>
               <p>CHARLESTON, S.C., APRIL 19, 1865.</p>
               <p>THE following account of a meeting held in the Unitarian Church, in
Charleston, is taken from the "Charleston Courier," of April 20:--</p>
               <p>In response to a call through the paper of the 19th inst.,
inviting all Unitarians in the city to meet at the Unitarian Church,
in Archdale Street, at five o'clock, P.M., a respectable number of
both sexes were in attendance; when, by motion of Dr. A. G. MACKEY,
Dr. JAMES MOULTRIE was called to the chair, and Mr. DAVID BARROW
requested to act as secretary.</p>
               <p>Rev. CALVIN STEBBINS opened the meeting with a most
eloquent and impressive prayer; after which, Mr. Barrow rose, and
said, that, before proceeding to the discharge of the duties of
secretary, he would state the object of the meeting, by saying, that,
"during the past week, we had a very large and interesting visitation
from our Northern friends; and among them, two reverend gentlemen of
our own household of faith, who had come among us as strangers, having
been sent as missionaries by the Unitarian Society of Boston, to look
for a field
<pb n="21"/>
                  <figure><graphic url=""/>
                     <figDesc>21st page of Rev. Charles
Lowe's Death of President Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
wherein to plant the standard of true faith, around which all of us
could rally, and have once more our own pure and unadulterated
Unitarian faith inculcated. They are young, strong, and zealous in the
work assigned them; earnest in the wish and hope to be useful; true to
the faith of their adoption. Let us receive them as brothers in our
own faith and church; let us welcome them in all kindness; let us
unite with them, heart and hand, in all the good work they and we can
find to do in the broad field before us. Here they are: the
Rev. Mr. Charles Lowe, of Boston, and the Rev. Calvin Stebbins, of
Cambridge,--receive them as brothers in the faith."</p>
               <p>Here the Rev. Mr. CHARLES LOWE, of Boston [Somerville],
rose, and said:--</p>
               <p>"Mr. Chairman,--The welcome which has been asked for us by
my respected friend has already been accorded to us. We came as
strangers, and have already experienced at the hands of the few who
represent this society, that generous hospitality and that courtesy
for which this city, and especially this church, has long been
known. Would that the few who greet us were the many who once filled
these pews!</p>
               <p>"We have come, as has been explained, in order to extend to
the Unitarians of this city, on behalf of the American Unitarian
Association, such aid as they may need, and as we can give. The
purpose of this meeting was to deliberate upon the course it may be
proper to adopt; but the intelligence which has reached us within a
few hours must have unfitted us for every thing but the utterance of
our grief. Under the shadow of such an event as this, it is fitting
that all business, even the most sacred, should be put aside; and I
have ventured to embody, in the form of resolutions, some expression of
<pb n="22"/>
                  <figure><graphic url=""/>
                     <figDesc>22nd page of Rev. Charles
Lowe's Death of President Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
feeling, which, with your 1eave, I will offer to the meeting. I
propose these resolutions with no desire to control the action of the
meeting, but simply because, feeling as I do, I can do <hi rend="italic">nothing</hi> else:--</p>
               <p>"<hi rend="italic">Whereas,</hi> this meeting of Unitarians
was called for the purpose of consulting in regard to the
re-establishment of worship for those who belong to our liberal faith;
and whereas, since the call was issued, our hearts have been
overwhelmed by the intelligence of the appalling calamity that has
come upon us and the nation, in the death, by the hand of an assassin,
of our beloved and trusted Chief Magistrate, the President of the
United States; therefore,--</p>
               <p>"<hi rend="italic">Resolved</hi>, That before this great
dispensation we bow in awe, but with undiminished faith in the
providence of God.</p>
               <p>"<hi rend="italic">Resolved</hi>, That, full of the solemnity
with which this event has oppressed us all, we here dedicate ourselves
anew to unswerving fidelity to the interests of the Union; that we
feel a deeper sense of the madness of those who, after all hope of
succeeding must have passed, would still continue efforts that could
only lead to further shedding of blood, and a postponement of
peace.</p>
               <p>"<hi rend="italic">Resolved</hi>, That we will do all in our
power to hasten the reestablishment of peace, on the one only basis of
a hearty allegiance to the Constitution and the authorities of the
United States. And we raise our prayers to Almighty God to help us in
these our endeavors.</p>
               <p>"<hi rend="italic">Resolved</hi>, That, in deference to this
event, the business which brought us together be postponed, and that
this meeting do now adjourn."</p>
               <p>Dr. A. G. MACKEY seconded the resolutions with the following
remarks:--</p>
               <p>"I rise to second these resolutions, Mr. Chairman, with a
profound emotion of grief. The magnitude of the calamity that has
befallen the nation, and the suddenness of the blow with which we have
been stricken, fall upon us with an appalling force which paralyzes
the heart as well as the tongue. We are hardly yet able to feel our
<pb n="23"/>
                  <figure><graphic url=""/>
                     <figDesc>23rd page of Rev. Charles
Lowe's Death of President Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
grief; we dare not venture to give utterance to it. For the first time
since the organization of our government, the Chief Magistrate of the
United States has been basely slain by the weapon of a cowardly and
traitorous assassin. It has always been the boast of Americans, that,
unlike the monarchs of Europe, their President needed no protecting
guard of soldiers to defend him from the attack of the traitor or the
rebel. The guards of an American President were found in the honor and
the affection of the people, and in the freedom and equality of our
political institutions. But the bitter and shameful disgrace has come
at last upon us in these already too troublous days; and secession,
developing itself, and culminating in this murderous act of one or
perhaps more of its disciples, has shown that treason may be as
rampant in a republic as in a despotism.</p>
               <p>"Abraham Lincoln, the man of the age, whose skill and
energy and wisdom had triumphantly conducted this war, as his clemency
and generosity and kindliness of heart were inaugurating a peace on
terms which treason had no right to claim, and which magnanimity alone
could offer, has fallen,--the true friend of the South has perished by
the polluted hand of a degenerate son of the South. But, sir, I
pause. Indignation for the great crime that has been committed, and
the great wrong that has been done, tempts me to the utterance of
language unfitting to this sacred place, where nothing but Christian
love and mercy should find an echo.</p>
               <p>"But this is no time, and we are in no mood, for
business. The children who assemble around the grave of their departed
father give themselves only to grief. Let us imitate their examples;
and here, on this day, whose sun had burst upon us with genial rays of
joy and hope,
<pb n="24"/>
                  <figure><graphic url=""/>
                     <figDesc>24th page of Rev. Charles
Lowe's Death of President Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
but which is about to set in gloom and despair, let us divest
ourselves of all thought of other avocations, and retire to our homes
to bewail the good, the wise, the brave man, who has fallen a martyr
to his duty and his patriotism, and humbly to beseech our heavenly
Father to withdraw from our beloved land the evil which now hangs over
it like a dark, funeral pall."</p>
               <p>The meeting was then adjourned, to meet at the church at
five o'clock on Friday afternoon.</p>
            </div2>
         </div1>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>