<TEI.2>
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt n="Discourse Delivered on the Day of the Funeral of President Lincoln.">
            <title>  Discourse
Delivered on the Day of the Funeral of President Lincoln.  </title>
            <author>McClintock, John</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Compiled and edited
by</resp>
               <name>Beck Center</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent/>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Lewis H. Beck
Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Emory University</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Atlanta, Georgia</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>1996 Emory University. Permission is granted to
download, transmit, or otherwise reproduce, distribute or display the
contributions to the work claimed by Emory University for non-profit
educational purposes, provided  this header is included in its
entirety.  For inquiries about commercial uses, contact the Director, 
Pitts Theology Library, Emory University, Atlanta, Georgia
30322</p>
            </availability>
            <date>1999</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Lincoln Sermons Project</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>McClintock, John. Discourse Delivered on the Day of
the Funeral of President Lincoln, Wednesday, April 19, 1865, in
St. Paul's Church, New York. Reported by J. T. Butts.  New York: Press
of J. M. Bradstreet &amp; Son.  1865.  </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This text derives from the Special Collections 
of Pitts Theology Library, Emory University, and is produced in 
collaboration with the Lewis H. Beck Center a, the Emory 
Preservation Office, and Pitts Theology Library.</p>
            <p>TRANSCRIBER: Lewis H. Beck Center and Emory University 
Preservation Office.</p>
            <p>PRODUCER:  BookLab, Inc., 1606 Headway Circle, 
Suite 100, Austin, TX 78754</p>
            <p>CAPTURE DEVICE: XEROX DocuImage 620S flatbed scanner</p>
            <p>CAPTURE DETAILS: Scanner software: XEROX ScanTool 
version 4.2.3; no gamma correction; images are all bitonal.</p>
            <p>CHANGE HISTORY: Using the Adobe Photoshop Batch Processor, 
we interpolated  the original TIFF files to 8-bit grays, 
and altered the resolution to 144 dpi, producing screen 
images twice the original size.  We then saved them in 
JPEG format.  We produced GIF thumbnails from the JPEG files.</p>
            <p>RESOLUTION: 600 ppi</p>
            <p>COMPRESSION: Resolution 144 per inch with Constrain 
Properties to 72 per inch.</p>
            <p>SOURCE: Original documents.</p>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>1999</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Scott Ellis</name>
               <resp>Staff</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <item>SGML tags inserted in compliance
with TEI guidelines using TEILITE</item>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div1 id="mcclintock.001" n="Discourse Delivered on the Day of the Funeral of President Lincoln." type="text">
            <head pn="1"> 
               <bibl> 
                  <title>Discourse
Delivered on the Day of the Funeral of President Lincoln.</title>
                  <date>Wednesday, April 19, 1865</date> 
                  <pubPlace>St. Paul's Church,
New York</pubPlace> 
                  <author>McClintock, John</author> 
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Press of J. M. Bradstreet
&amp; Son</publisher>
                     <date>1865</date>
                  </imprint> 
               </bibl> 
            </head>
            <p pn="1">
               <figure entity="mcclintock1">
                  <figDesc>1st page of John McClintock's
Discourse Delivered on the Day of the Funeral of President
Lincoln.</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <p pn="1">DISCOURSE</p>
            <p pn="1">DELIVERED ON THE DAY OF THE FUNERAL</p>
            <p pn="1">OF</p>
            <p pn="1">PRESIDENT LINCOLN,</p>
            <p pn="1">WEDNESDAY, APRIL 19, 1865,</p>
            <p pn="1">In St. Paul's Church, New York,</p>
            <p pn="1">BY</p>
            <p pn="1">JOHN McCLINTOCK, DD. LLD.</p>
            <p pn="1">REPORTED BY J.T. BUTTS.</p>
            <p pn="1">NEW YORK:</p>
            <p pn="1">PRESS OF J.M. BRADSTREET &amp; SON.</p>
            <p pn="1">1865.</p>
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p pn="2">
               <figure entity="mcclintock2">
                  <figDesc>2nd page
of John McClintock's Discourse Delivered on the Day of the Funeral of
President Lincoln.</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <p pn="2">Entered according to Act of Congress, in the year 1865,</p>
            <p pn="2">BY
BOWLES COLGATE,</p>
            <p pn="2">In the Clerk's Office of the District Court of
the United States for the Southern District of New York; in behalf of
the Young Men's Christian Association of St. Paul's M.E. Church.</p>
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p pn="3">
               <figure entity="mcclintock3">
                  <figDesc>3rd page
of John McClintock's Discourse Delivered on the Day of the Funeral of
President Lincoln.</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <p pn="3">NEW YORK, <hi rend="italic">April</hi> 20,1865.</p>
            <p pn="3">THE REV. JOHN McCLINTOCK, D.D.,</p>
            <p pn="3">
               <hi rend="italic">Dear Sir:</hi>
            </p>
            <p pn="3">Having listened to your Discourse yesterday, upon the sad
event of the death of our late President, and fully sympathizing with
the sentiments of the discourse, we, the Committee, in behalf of the
Young Men's Christian Association of St. Paul's M. E. Church,
respectfully solicit a copy for the press, believing that its
circulation in a permanent form will subserve the interest of justice
and freedom.</p>
            <p pn="3">We are, truly yours,</p>
            <p pn="3">BOWLES COLGATE, CHAIRMAN. 
                               <lb/>A. E. M. PURDY. 
                               <lb/>E. FRANK. HYDE. 
                               <lb/>L. BOLTON BANGS.</p>
            <pb n="4"/>
<!-- blank page -->
<!--            <p>
               <figure entity="mcclintock4">
                  <figDesc>4th page
of John McClintock's Discourse Delivered on the Day of the Funeral of
President Lincoln.</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p> -->
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p pn="5">
               <figure entity="mcclintock5">
                  <figDesc>5th page
of John McClintock's Discourse Delivered on the Day of the Funeral of
President Lincoln.</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <p pn="5">NEW YORK, <hi rend="italic">April</hi> 21, 1865.</p>
            <p pn="5">
               <hi rend="italic">Gentlemen</hi>:</p>
            <p pn="5">The Discourse was delivered <hi rend="italic">extempore</hi>. As I am just about to leave town, it is
impossible for me to write it out; but one of the reporters for the
daily press, Mr. BUTTS, has sent me his notes, which, though not taken
with a view to publication, are yet tolerably ample. I have hastily
revised them, and herewith submit them to you.</p>
            <p pn="5">Very truly,</p>
            <p pn="5">J. McCLINTOCK.</p>
            <pb n="6"/>
<!-- blank page -->
<!--            <p>
               <figure entity="mcclintock6">
                  <figDesc>6th page
of John McClintock's Discourse Delivered on the Day of the Funeral of
President Lincoln.</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p> -->
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p pn="7">
               <figure entity="mcclintock7">
                  <figDesc>7th page
of John McClintock's Discourse Delivered on the Day of the Funeral of
President Lincoln.</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <div2 id="mcclintock.002" n="DISCOURSE" type="sermon">
               <head pn="7">DISCOURSE.</head>
               <epigraph pn="7">
                  <p pn="7">HEB. Xiii. 7.--Remember them which have the rule over
you, . . . whose faith follow.</p>
               </epigraph>
               <p pn="7">IT is the LORD; His will be done. The blow has stunned the
nation. Had we no trust in Him who conquers even the last enemy, the
"victory of the grave" which calls us together to-day would fill us
with despair. And even with all the light which the word of God
affords, and with all the strength which our faith in God gives us, we
can still only say, "His way is in the sea, and His path in the deep
waters." We shall know hereafter what He doeth; but we know not
now.</p>
               <p pn="7">"<hi rend="italic">Remember</hi>," says our text, and "<hi rend="italic">follow</hi>."</p>
               <pb n="8"/>
               <p pn="8">
                  <figure entity="mcclintock8">
                     <figDesc>8th page of
John McClintock's Discourse Delivered on the Day of the Funeral of
President Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <p pn="8">There is little fear of our forgetting--there is little
fear of the world forgetting the name of ABRAHAM LINCOLN. It was the
remark of Heine, the German poet and satirist, that "men preserve the
memory of their destroyers better than that of their benefactors; the
warrior's name outlasts the philanthropist's." There is some truth in
this, taking the world's history as it has been. But it is one of the
best signs of the times that men's hearts are more than ever attracted
by moral greatness, and that all laurels are not stained with
blood. The day is dawning, even though its rising sun be dimmed by
clouds, and struggles up amid gloom, and tears, and blood, in which
the glory of the reformer shall outshine that of the conqueror--in
which the</p>
               <lg type="stanza">
                  <l>Saints of humanity, strong, yet tender,</l>
                  <l>Making the present hopeful with their
life,</l>
               </lg>
               <p pn="8">shall be held the true heroes in men's thoughts, as they are the
true heroes in the progress of humanity, and before the eye of
God. And to this heroic class belongs the name of Abraham Lincoln, who
fell, if ever man did, fighting the battles of humanity.</p>
               <pb n="9"/>
               <p pn="9">
                  <figure entity="mcclintock9">
                     <figDesc>9th page of
John McClintock's Discourse Delivered on the Day of the Funeral of
President Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <p pn="9">A voice came to us ten days ago from beyond the sea. Here
is what it says of Abraham Lincoln: "When the heats of party passion
and international jealousy have abated, when detraction has spent its
malice, and the scandalous gossip of the day goes the way of all lies,
the place of Abraham Lincoln in the grateful affection of his
countrymen and in the respect of mankind, will be second only, if it
be second, to that of Washington himself." When Robert Cairnes penned
those prophetic words, how little did he dream that in a few weeks his
prediction should become history! "When the heats of party passion are
abated!" A work of long and weary time, no doubt. Yet it has been done
in a day. The fame of Abraham Lincoln has not had to wait for the
revolving years to set it right. The bullet of the assassin has done
the work of an age. To-day that name stands as high before this whole
people, of all parties, of all sects, of all classes, as it would have
stood in a half a century, had the blow of the assassin never
fallen. Party spirit, for the time at least, is dead. Who thinks of
party now? There are doubtless, in this congregation, many men who
voted against Abra-
<pb n="10"/>
                  <figure entity="mcclintock10">
                     <figDesc>10th page of John
McClintock's Discourse Delivered on the Day of the Funeral of
President Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
ham Lincoln; is there one of them who does not mourn him to-day? When
you heard that Abraham Lincoln was dead--you, who a year ago, perhaps,
made his name an object of abuse and calumny; you, whose lips were
accustomed to speak of that brave, noble, loving man as a usurper,
perhaps, or at least as a foolish imbecile, and an unfit tenant of the
highest place in all the world--I ask you, when you heard on Saturday
morning that Lincoln was dead, did not your heart throb as never
before; did not your throat become husky and the damp gather in your
eyes, in spite of you, as you spoke of it? Party spirit for the moment
is indeed forgotten. Do not forget the lesson; and when your party
journals begin, as they will begin very soon, to assail Andrew
Johnson, as they have in the past assailed Abraham Lincoln, do not be
led away; let not opposition be sullied with calumny or embittered by
hate.</p>
               <p pn="10">The streets of the city of New York, and of every city in
the Union, from Portland to San Francisco, are clad in mourning. I
have been struck, in going through the poorer streets of this city, to
find the emblems of sorrow more general, if possible, on the abodes of
the humble and the
<pb n="11"/>
                  <figure entity="mcclintock11">
                     <figDesc>11th page of John
McClintock's Discourse Delivered on the Day of the Funeral of
President Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
lowly, than on the stately dwellings of the rich in the grand
avenues. All over this land, and over all the civilized world, I dare
say, there shall be grief and mourning in the hearts and homes of
those who are called the "common people:--of whom was Abraham
Lincoln. The "ruling classes" abroad will grieve also, but for a very
different reason. The Tories and aristocrats of England have watched,
with fear and wrath, the later progress of the Republic towards
triumph; and they will feel the tremor of a new fear when they learn
that this good and generous man--so tender, so merciful, so forgiving,
so full of all peaceful thoughts, that revenge or cruelty could find
no place in his heart; this noble, steadfast man of the people, at
whose feet all their taunts and gibes had fallen harmless, whose
simple dignity of nature achieved for him that serene indifference,
that high superiority to abuse and calumny which have been claimed as
the peculiar attributes of what are called high birth and
breeding--has passed away from earth. For they were just learning that
he loved peace next to justice, and, in the vague terror of their
conscious guilt, as abettors of the slaveholders' rebellion, they
<pb n="12"/>
                  <figure entity="mcclintock12">
                     <figDesc>12th page of John
McClintock's Discourse Delivered on the Day of the Funeral of
President Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
looked to the gentle ruler, whom they had so vilely traduced, to avert
the war which their consciences told them ought to come.</p>
               <p pn="12">But while, for this reason, there will be real grief among
the ruling classes, there shall be sorrow of another sort among all
the liberal hearts, among all who have hoped and struggled for the
future equality of the race, and who, these four weary years, have
been watching the issues of our great war for freedom, with an
intensity of feeling only next to our own. As for the working classes,
everywhere through the British islands, and on the continent of
Europe, the name of Abraham Lincoln had come to be, for them, the
synonyme of hope for their cause; for</p>
               <lg type="stanza">
                  <l>Love had he found in huts, where poor men
lie,</l>
               </lg>
               <p pn="12">not only in every slave cabin in the South, where he is canonized
already, but in many a shepherd's lodge of Switzerland--in many a
woodman's cabin of the Black Forest--in many a miner's hut of the
Hartz Mountains--in many a cottage in Italy, for there, as well as
here, the poor had learned to look upon him as the anointed of God for
the redemption of the liberties of mankind. It is
<pb n="13"/>
                  <figure entity="mcclintock13">
                     <figDesc>13th page of John
McClintock's Discourse Delivered on the Day of the Funeral of
President Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
but lately that Garibaldi named one of his grandchildren Lincoln,
little dreaming how soon that name was to be enrolled among the
immortals. Oh! how his great heart will throb, how the tears will roll
like bullets down his seamed and furrowed face, when to him shall come
the sad message, "Lincoln is dead!"</p>
               <p pn="13">And now let us ask why all this sorrow? Whence this
universal love? Certainly it was not intellectual grandeur that so
drew all hearts toward Lincoln. And yet I do not sympathize with much
that has been said in disparagement of his intellect, although mere
mental gifts, of the highest order, might well have been eclipsed, in
the popular estimation, by the sublimity of that moral power which
overshadowed all his other qualities. But it is stupid to talk of him
as a man of mean intellect. He had a giant's work to do, and he has
done it nobly. Called upon to steer the ship of state through the
mightiest and most rapid tide of events that ever swept over a nation,
he guided her safely, and was within sight of the harbor, when he was
struck down at the helm. Even in his speeches and writings, where
defects of form reveal the want of
<pb n="14"/>
                  <figure entity="mcclintock14">
                     <figDesc>14th page of John
McClintock's Discourse Delivered on the Day of the Funeral of
President Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
early culture and give room for the carping of petty critics who can
see no farther than the form, I do not fear to say that the calm
criticism of history will find marks of the highest power of mind. Do
you remember his little speech over the graves of our martyrs at
Gettysburg? I remember the thrill with which I read it, across the
sea. It is Greek-like in its simple majesty of thought, and even in
the exquisite felicity of some of its phrases. Nor could that have
been a mean intellect which enabled this simple son of the people,
standing among men who piqued themselves upon their refinement and
culture, among men of large acquirements and polished speech, to hold
on his own way among them, to take or reject their advice, to hear all
plans and all arguments, and after all to be the real ruler of the
nation and of the times. With such gifts as God gave him, he was
enabled to pierce to the very core of a matter, while others, with
their fine rhetoric, could only talk around it.</p>
               <p pn="14">Yet it was not for the intellect, but for the moral
qualities of the man that we loved him. It is a wise order of
Providence that it is so that men are drawn. We never love cold
intellect. We may
<pb n="15"/>
                  <figure entity="mcclintock15">
                     <figDesc>15th page of John
McClintock's Discourse Delivered on the Day of the Funeral of
President Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
admire it; we may wonder at it; sometimes we may even worship it, but
we never love it. The hearts of men leap out only after the image of
God in man, and the image of God in man is love. Oh! what a large and
loving heart was stilled last Friday! How fine, how tender, how
all-embracing was his love of that old man! Those of you who have
never seen him, and never have known the inexpressible charm of his
simple manner, can never understand how much there was in him to
love. Men of all classes were alike won by his personal
magnetism. Those who have traduced him most, and those who have been
most carried away by the blind fury of partisan hate, and have gone to
Washington to see him, have always come away disarmed. Whenever they
had talk with the President, whenever those tender eyes opened gently
upon them, (they had the habit of opening gently,) and they looked
through those portals of his soul and saw the infinite wealth of
tenderness that was there, they yielded to the spell. Illustrations of
the tenderness of his nature abound. A colonel in the army was telling
a friend the other day, of a time in 1862, when he had command of
<pb n="16"/>
                  <figure entity="mcclintock16">
                     <figDesc>16th page of John
McClintock's Discourse Delivered on the Day of the Funeral of
President Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
one of the posts, and the President visited the place for a few
days. This officer had never met the President, and had no very
exalted opinion of him, "but at the end of those ten days," said he,
"I found that I was in love with him, and I could not help it." He
related an incident that took place one evening while sitting alone
with the President. Mr. Lincoln was reading Shakspeare, when suddenly
turning his eyes upon the officer, he said: "Colonel, do you ever find
yourself talking with a dead friend as if he was present and still
living?" " Yes," said the colonel, "I know the feeling, for it has
occurred to me often." "I am glad I asked you the question," said
Mr. Lincoln, closing his book and leaning his head upon his hand, "I
did not know that it was common, but ever since my little boy died, I
find myself talking with him every day."</p>
               <p pn="16">The entire absence of vindictiveness, either personal or
political, was one of the ripe fruits of Lincoln's native
tenderness. Did you ever hear of his saying a hard thing of his
opponents? After all the vile calumnies heaped upon him at home and
abroad, did you ever know him to utter a
<pb n="17"/>
                  <figure entity="mcclintock17">
                     <figDesc>17th page of John
McClintock's Discourse Delivered on the Day of the Funeral of
President Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
single word showing personal hate, or even personal feeling? It is a
marvellous record. Test our public men by this standard, and you will
see how loftily he towers above them in moral dignity. He lived as he
died: the last of his public utterances closed with the words, "With
malice towards none, with charity for all." This phrase will fall
hereafter into that small number of phrases, not Scripture, but which
men often cite, unwittingly, as though they were.</p>
               <p pn="17">Another striking element of his moral nature was his
profound faith--a faith not like that of the man who now stands at the
head of the French people, a blind fatalistic confidence in his own
destiny, or in the destiny of the system with which he is
identified. Nor yet merely an uncalculating faith in the wisdom,
virtue or steadfastness of the American people. Abraham Lincoln had
this, indeed; but it was not all: he had a profound religious faith:
not simply a general recognition of the law of order in the universe,
but a profound faith in a Personal God. He once remarked to me, at a
sudden turn in conversation, "Ah, Providence is stronger than you or
I," and he said it in such a 
<pb n="18"/>
                  <figure entity="mcclintock18">
                     <figDesc>18th page of John
McClintock's Discourse Delivered on the Day of the Funeral of
President Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
tone as to reveal a habit of thought. It was out of the abundance of
the heart that the mouth spoke. We were discussing at the time the
relations of this country with Europe, and the effects of his
Proclamation of Emancipation. "When I issued that Proclamation," said
he, "I was in great doubt about it myself. I did not think that the
people had been quite educated up to it, and I feared its effect upon
the Border States, yet I think it was right; I knew it would help our
cause in Europe, and I trusted in God and did it." I believe that no
president since George Washington ever brought in so eminent a degree
to his official work a deep religious faith. Of his personal religious
experience I cannot speak of my own knowledge, but we have more than
one cheering testimony about it. I have been assured that ever after
the battle of Gettysburgh he was daily in the habit of supplicating in
prayer the throne of divine grace, as a believer in Jesus Christ, and
that from that time he classed himself with believers. Oh! what
prayers those must have been in the dark days of '63, and how
wondrously has God answered them.</p>
               <pb n="19"/>
               <p pn="19">
                  <figure entity="mcclintock19">
                     <figDesc>19th page
of John McClintock's Discourse Delivered on the Day of the Funeral of
President Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <p pn="19">I shall not speak of the patriotism of Abraham Lincoln, though
it is one of the points of which I had intended to speak, but you know
all about it. You know what a tremendous duty fell to him, and how he
did it all the way through; seduced by no blandishment, frightened by
no threats from the steady pursuit of his one duty--to restore the
integrity of the government. How far he succeeded is known to you
all. The "forts and places" which he said he would retake are all ours
to-day, and the main army of the rebellion is scattered and gone!</p>
               <p pn="19">The manners of Abraham Lincoln have been a matter of a
great deal of comment, and of snobbish comment too. If unaffected
simplicity, the most entire ease, and the power to put one's visitor
at ease, and to do it unconsciously; if these are the ultimate results
and the final tests of refinement, as they unquestionably are, then
was he the peer of any nobleman in manners. When you shall learn to be
as easy, as gentle, as truly unaffected, as free from all thought of
yourself, as Abraham Lincoln was, then indeed will you have finished
manners. What if there were a few accidental remnants of his
<pb n="20"/>
                  <figure entity="mcclintock20">
                     <figDesc>20th page of John
McClintock's Discourse Delivered on the Day of the Funeral of
President Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
former habits? Of all people in the world, we are the very last that
should think of these.</p>
               <p pn="20">Just now, across the sea, men are grieving over the death
of a plain man of the people, like Abraham Lincoln, a man of the same
kind of manners, a man bred to the plough, and whose early years were
given to trade--Richard Cobden. And not merely in naturalness of
manners, but also in moral elevation, in guileless sincerity, in
delicate regard for the feelings even of enemies, in true devotion to
the good of their fellow-men, especially to the cause of the poor and
oppressed, and in earnest religious faith, were these men
twin-brothers. Even in outward look there was a marked resemblance;
the same tenderness of eye, the same pathetic sadness of general
expression, and the same lurking smile of humor.</p>
               <p pn="20">In two weeks after the fall of Sumter, I heard the news of
it in Paris. Cobden arrived in town, from Algiers, I think, just
then. Early the next morning I went to him, and said, "Are you enough
interested in the American question to have a few words?"
"Interested!" said he, "interested!" and the tears started to his
eyes. "My God! 
<pb n="21"/>
                  <figure entity="mcclintock21">
                     <figDesc>21st page of John
McClintock's Discourse Delivered on the Day of the Funeral of
President Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
sir, I do not sleep at night!" We then talked over all the probable
phases of this great question and its tremendous issues. Never, until
I came home and sat down alone with Abraham Lincoln, as I had sat down
with Richard Cobden, did I know how much alike these two men were. How
prophetic is it of the near coming of the time when all the sophisms
of power by which a few have held, and are still striving to hold, the
mass of mankind in their iron grasp to make them the tools of their
ambition and their avarice, shall be swept away forever, that, all
over the earth, in palaces as well as in hovels, there is mourning
over Richard Cobden and Abraham Lincoln; men that worked with their
hands and yet raised themselves higher than nobles; precursors of that
triumphant Christian civilization that is yet to gladden the hearts of
all mankind with the reign of universal brotherhood. In seven years
Cobden bowed the neck of the proudest aristocracy in the world. In
five years Lincoln destroyed and buried the most cruel, the most
dangerous aristocracy that ever sought to establish itself in a
civilized nation. The two representa-
<pb n="22"/>
                  <figure entity="mcclintock22">
                     <figDesc>22nd page of John
McClintock's Discourse Delivered on the Day of the Funeral of
President Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
tive men of the spirit of the age have passed away from earth
together.</p>
               <p pn="22">We had no fear about Abraham Lincoln, except the fear that
he would be too forgiving. Oh! what an epitaph--that the only fear men
had was that he would be too tender, that he had too much love; in a
word, that he was too Christ-like! And how Christ-like was he in
dying! His last official words in substance were, "Father, forgive
them, they know not what they do." And on Good Friday he fell a martyr
to the cause of humanity. I do not think there was adequate ground for
the fear that he would ever have sacrificed substantial justice upon
the altar of his personal tenderness; or, that he had not the strength
and the resolution to punish the authors of the rebellion; yet, after
all, in coming ages, it shall no be the least of his titles to the
veneration and love of mankind, that his compeers found no fault with
him, except that he had <hi rend="italic">too much</hi> love.</p>
               <p pn="22">Last Friday, we are told, President Lincoln asked General
Grant if he had heard from General Sherman? General Grant replied that
he had not; but that he was hourly in expectation
<pb n="23"/>
                  <figure entity="mcclintock23">
                     <figDesc>23rd page of John
McClintock's Discourse Delivered on the Day of the Funeral of
President Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
of receiving dispatches announcing the surrender of Johnston. "Well,"
said the President, "you will hear very soon now, and the news will be
important." "Why do you think so?" said the General. "Because," said
Mr. Lincoln, "I had a dream last night, and ever since the war began I
have invariably had the same dream before any important event has
occurred." He then instanced Bull Run, Antietam, Gettysburgh, &amp;c., and
said that before each of those events he had had the same
dream. Turning to Secretary Welles, he said: "It is in your line, too,
Mr. Welles. I dreamed that I saw a ship sailing very rapidly by, and I
am sure that it portends some important national event." Dear friends,
the life of Abraham Lincoln is closed. After a very, very stormy
voyage, the ship has reached her harbor at last. And how, after all
these tempests, these fierce blasts, these rising floods, how did the
ship sail in? Shattered and sinking, with sails all torn and rent? No,
dear friends, God ordered it otherwise. Not a mark of the storm was on
the noble vessel; the hull was sound, the spars were strong, the sails
were spread, with the broad flag flying again as it
<pb n="24"/>
                  <figure entity="mcclintock24">
                     <figDesc>24th page of John
McClintock's Discourse Delivered on the Day of the Funeral of
President Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
never waved before, and with pennants of red, white and blue streaming
gloriously and triumphantly over all, the ship sailed into port, and
the angels of God said their glad "All hail!" So now say I--and I
venture to speak in your behalf, as well as in my own--Abraham
Lincoln, Patriot, Philanthropist, Christian, Martyr, Hail! and
Farewell!</p>
               <p pn="24">And now, what are to be the results of this tragedy to the
country and to mankind? It is God that rules, and already we see that,
even in this terrible crime, He has made the wrath of man to praise
Him. One thing is clear: even now the American people are united as
they were never united before. Four years ago (or it will be four
years within a week), in 1861, I stood in Exeter Hall, in the City of
London, with an audience of nearly four thousand people. The London
<title>Times</title> of the day before had said "the great Republic is
gone." I made these words the text of a little speech to these four
thousand Englishmen. I ventured to say to them, what in my heart I
believed to be true, that whatever might be the result of civil war
elsewhere, and however a single battle might turn in the United
States, the Government of the
<pb n="25"/>
                  <figure entity="mcclintock25">
                     <figDesc>25th page of John
McClintock's Discourse Delivered on the Day of the Funeral of
President Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
United States was impregnable; that the great Republic would come
forth out of the trial stronger than ever; that however the first
battle might go, we should win the last, and the Rebellion would be
crushed. It is but right to say that these remarks met with
sympathy. The four thousand people that sat before me showed every
sign of feeling; they rose from their seats, they clapped their hands,
they stamped their feet, they shouted.  The four years have passed,
and the Republic is not gone, thank God, but stands out in grander
proportions, is established upon a firmer foundation than ever
before. In the four days that have passed since the shot that laid
Abraham Lincoln low, the work of fifty years in the consolidation of
the Republic has been done. The morning of the same day that saw one
President die, saw another quietly inaugurated and as quietly
performing his functions. True, there were a few men in Wall street
who seemed to look upon it as the harbinger of a golden harvest; men
who, if allowed by any chance to pass the gates of the Celestial City,
would go with their eyes bent downward studying some plan to pluck up
the golden pavement. Naturally
<pb n="26"/>
                  <figure entity="mcclintock26">
                     <figDesc>26th page of John
McClintock's Discourse Delivered on the Day of the Funeral of
President Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
enough, these men mistook the mighty import of passing events, and
bought gold for a rise. On Monday gold was ten per cent. lower than on
Saturday.</p>
               <p pn="26">Another lesson we have learned is this: that in our
government no one man is essential. The Harpers have just published a
book by Louis Napoleon Bonaparte on the Life of Julius Caesar. Its
object is to teach the world that it must be governed by its great
men; that they make epochs and not merely mark them. How suddenly that
book has been refuted, and what a blow has been given to this gospel
of Napoleon, by the assassination of Lincoln and its issues. Here is
one greater than Caesar struck down as Caesar was, and yet the pillars
of the Republic are unshaken. What a pitiful anachronism does the
Imperial plea for C&#x00E6;sarism appear, in presence of the dead Lincoln,
and the mourning, yet living and triumphant Republic!</p>
               <p pn="26">Let us now gather one or two practical lessons for
ourselves and our children. Hatred of assassination is one of these
lessons, if, indeed, we needed to learn it. The work that Brutus did
to Caesar was just as bad a work as that of Booth to Lincoln. It was
centuries before humanity recovered from
<pb n="27"/>
                  <figure entity="mcclintock27">
                     <figDesc>27th page of John
McClintock's Discourse Delivered on the Day of the Funeral of
President Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
the poisoned wound it received from the stroke of the dagger that
pierced the breast of Caesar. Teach your children, moreover, not only
to hate assassination, but treason as well; for treason breeds
assassins, as it breeds all other forms of crime and wrong. You cannot
be too severe upon it in your thoughts or in your talk; you are severe
upon the robber and the assassin; shall you be lenient toward the
treason which has begotten both robbery and assassination?</p>
               <p pn="27">Remember, too, that as treason is the parent of
assassination, so slavery has been the parent of treason. Is it
necessary for me to exhort you to teach your children to hate slavery
too? In this one thing I ask you to join with me this day. Let us bow
ourselves before Almighty God, and vow that so far as in us lies, none
of us will ever agree to any pacification of this land, until slavery
be utterly extirpated. Watch your editors, then; watch your clergy;
watch your generals and soldiers, your admirals and sailors; watch
even Andrew Johnson, though of that I apprehend there will be no
need. Watch them all, if need be, and see to it that this sprout of
hell never shoots up again in the American soil.</p>
               <pb n="28"/>
               <p pn="28">
                  <figure entity="mcclintock28">
                     <figDesc>28th page
of John McClintock's Discourse Delivered on the Day of the Funeral of
President Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <p pn="28">One more lesson, and not the least. If anything I have
said, or anything that you read or hear in these sad days, breeds
within you a single revengeful feeling, even towards the leaders of
this rebellion, then think of Abraham Lincoln, and pray God to make
you merciful. Think of the prayer of Christ, which the President said,
after his Saviour, "Father, forgive them, they know not what they do."
Let there be no place for revenge in our souls; justice we may and
must demand, but revenge, never. "Vengeance is mine, I will repay,
saith the Lord." I counsel you also to discountenance all disorder,
all attempts by private persons to avenge the public wrong, or even to
punish sympathizers with treason. I have been sorry to hear from the
lips of generous young men, under the pangs of the President's
assassination, sentiments of bitterness and indignation, amounting
almost to fierceness. It is natural, no doubt, but what is natural is
not always right. Indulge this spirit, and you may hear next that this
man's house or that man's should be mobbed. Mobs are alien to our
northern soil; they belong to another atmosphere than that of free
schools and free men. The
<pb n="29"/>
                  <figure entity="mcclintock29">
                     <figDesc>29th page of John
McClintock's Discourse Delivered on the Day of the Funeral of
President Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
region of slavery was their natural home; let us have none of
them. And soon, when the last shackles shall have fallen, and
throughout our land, from sea to sea, there shall be no master and no
slave, the blessed Peace shall come, for which we have looked, and
prayed, and fought so long, when the Republic shall be established
upon the eternal foundations of Freedom and Justice, to stand, we
trust, by the blessing of God, down to the last syllable of recorded
Time.</p>
               <pb n="30"/>
               <p pn="30">
                  <figure entity="mcclintock30">
                     <figDesc>30th page
of John McClintock's Discourse Delivered on the Day of the Funeral of
President Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <p pn="30">THE SECOND INAUGURAL.</p>
               <p pn="30">"FELLOW COUNTRYMEN:</p>
               <p pn="30">At this second appearing to take the oath of the
Presidential office, there is less occasion for an extended address
than there was at the first. Then a statement somewhat in detail of a
course to be pursued seemed very fitting and proper. Now, at the
expiration of four years, during which public declarations have been
constantly called forth on every point and phase of the great contest
which still absorbs the attention and engrosses the energies of the
nation, little that is new could be presented.</p>
               <p pn="30">The progress of our arms, upon which all else chiefly
depends, is as well known to the public as to myself, and it is, I
trust, reasonably satisfactory and encouraging to all. With high hopes
for the future, no prediction in regard to it is ventured.</p>
               <p pn="30">On the occasion corresponding to this four years ago, all
thoughts were anxiously directed to an impending civil war. All
dreaded it; all sought to avoid it. While the inaugural address was
being delivered from this place, devoted altogether to
<pb n="31"/>
                  <figure entity="mcclintock31">
                     <figDesc>31st page of John
McClintock's Discourse Delivered on the Day of the Funeral of
President Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
saving the Union without war, insurgent agents were in the city
seeking to destroy it without war--seeking to dissolve the Union and
divide the effects by negotiation. Both parties deprecated war, but
one of them would make war rather than let the nation survive, and the
other would accept war rather than let it perish, and the war came.</p>
               <p pn="31">One-eighth of the whole population were colored slaves, not
distributed generally over the Union, but localized in the Southern
part of it. These slaves constituted a peculiar and powerful
interest. All knew that this interest was somehow the cause of the
war. To strengthen, perpetuate and extend this interest, was the
object for which the insurgents would rend the Union even by war,
while the government claimed no right to do more than to restrict the
territorial enlargement of it.</p>
               <p pn="31">Neither party expected for the war the magnitude or the
duration which it has already attained. Neither anticipated that the
cause of the conflict might cease with, or even before the conflict
itself should cease. Each looked for an easier triumph, and a result
less fundamental and astounding.</p>
               <p pn="31">Both read the same Bible and pray to the same
<pb n="32"/>
                  <figure entity="mcclintock32">
                     <figDesc>32nd page of John
McClintock's Discourse Delivered on the Day of the Funeral of
President Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
God, and each invokes His aid against the other. It may seem strange
than any men should dare to ask a just God's assistance in wringing
their bread from the sweat of other men's faces, but let us judge not,
that we be not judged. The prayers of both could not be answered. That
of neither has been answered fully. The Almighty has his own
purposes. "Woe unto the world because of offences, for it must needs
be that offences come; but woe to that man by whom the offence
cometh." If we shall suppose that American slavery is one of these
offences, which in the providence of God must needs come, but which
having continued through His appointed time, He now wills to remove,
and that he gives to both North and South this terrible war as the woe
due to those by whom the offence came, shall we discern therein any
departure from those divine attributes which the believers in a living
God always ascribe to Him?  Fondly do we hope, fervently do we pray,
that this mighty scourge of war may soon pass away. Yet, if God wills
that it continue until all the wealth piled by the bondman's two
hundred and fifty years of unrequited toil shall be sunk,
<pb n="33"/>
                  <figure entity="mcclintock33">
                     <figDesc>33rd page of John
McClintock's Discourse Delivered on the Day of the Funeral of
President Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
and until every drop of blood drawn with the lash shall be paid with
another drawn with the sword, as was said three thousand years ago;
so, still it must be said, "The judgments of the Lord are true and
righteous altogether."</p>
               <p pn="33">With malice toward none, with charity for all, with
firmness in the right, as God gives us to see the right, let us strive
on to finish the work we are in, to bind up the nation's wounds, to
care for him who shall have borne the battle, and for his widow and
his orphans, to do all which may achieve and cherish a just and
lasting peace among ourselves and with all nations."</p>
               <pb n="34"/>
               <p pn="34">
                  <figure entity="mcclintock34">
                     <figDesc>34th page
of John McClintock's Discourse Delivered on the Day of the Funeral of
President Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <p pn="34">THE SPEECH AT GETTYSBURG.</p>
               <p pn="34">"Fourscore and seven years ago our fathers brought forth
upon this continent a new nation, conceived in liberty, and dedicated
to the proposition that all men are created equal. Now we are engaged
in a great civil war, testing whether that nation, or any nation so
conceived and so dedicated can long endure. We are met on a great
battle-field of that war. We have come to dedicate a portion of that
field as a final resting-place for those who here gave their lives
that that nation might live. It is altogether fitting and proper that
we should do this. But in a larger sense we cannot dedicate, we cannot
consecrate, we cannot hallow this ground. The brave men, living and
dead, who struggled here, have consecrated it far above our power to
add or detract. The world will little note, nor long remember, what we
say here, but it can never forget what they did here. It is for us,
the living, rather to be dedicated here to the unfinished work which
they who fought here have thus far so nobly advanced. It is rather for
us to be here dedicated to the great task remaining before us, that
from these
<pb n="35"/>
                  <figure entity="mcclintock35">
                     <figDesc>35th page of John
McClintock's Discourse Delivered on the Day of the Funeral of
President Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
honored dead we take increased devotion to that cause for which they
gave the last full measure of devotion; that we here highly resolve
that these dead shall not have died in vain; that this nation, under
God, shall have a new birth of freedom, and that government of the
people, by the people, and for the people, shall not perish from the
earth."</p>
            </div2>
         </div1>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI.2>