<TEI.2>
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt n="A Discourse Delivered on the Occasion of the Funeral Obsequies of President Lincoln">
            <title>A Discourse
Delivered on the Occasion of the Funeral Obsequies of President
Lincoln</title>
            <author>Reed, Rev. S.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Compiled and edited by</resp>
               <name>Beck
Center</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent/>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Lewis H. Beck Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Emory University</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Atlanta,
Georgia</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>1996 Emory
University. Permission is granted to download, transmit, or otherwise
reproduce, distribute or display the contributions to the work claimed
by Emory University for non-profit educational purposes, provided
this header is included in its entirety.  For inquiries about
commercial uses, contact , contact the Director,  Pitts Theology
Library, Emory University, Atlanta, Georgia 30322</p>
            </availability>
            <date>1999</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Lincoln
Sermons Project</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Reed,
Rev. S. A Discourse Delivered on the Occasion of the Funeral Obsequies
of President Lincoln, April 19, 1865. Boston: Press of Geo. C. Rand
&#x0026; Avery, 3 Cornhill. 1865</bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This text derives from the Special
Collections  of Pitts Theology Library, Emory University, and is
produced in  collaboration with the Lewis H. Beck Center a, the Emory
Preservation Office, and Pitts Theology Library.</p>
            <p>TRANSCRIBER: Lewis H. Beck Center and Emory University 
Preservation Office.</p>
            <p>PRODUCER:  BookLab, Inc., 1606 Headway Circle, 
Suite 100, Austin, TX 78754</p>
            <p>CAPTURE DEVICE: XEROX DocuImage 620S flatbed scanner</p>
            <p>CAPTURE DETAILS: Scanner software: XEROX ScanTool 
version 4.2.3; no gamma correction; images are all bitonal.</p>
            <p>CHANGE HISTORY: Using the Adobe Photoshop Batch Processor, 
we interpolated  the original TIFF files to 8-bit grays, 
and altered the resolution to 144 dpi, producing screen 
images twice the original size.  We then saved them in 
JPEG format.  We produced GIF thumbnails from the JPEG files.</p>
            <p>RESOLUTION: 600 ppi</p>
            <p>COMPRESSION: Resolution 144 per inch with Constrain 
Properties to 72 per inch.</p>
            <p>SOURCE: Original documents.</p>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>1999</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Scott Ellis</name>
               <resp>Staff</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <item>SGML tags inserted in compliance
with TEI guidelines using TEILITE</item>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div1 id="reed.001" n="A Discourse Delivered on the Occasion of the Funeral Obsequies of President Lincoln" type="text">
            <head> 
               <bibl> 
                  <title>A Discourse
Delivered on the Occasion of the Funeral Obsequies of President
Lincoln</title> 
                  <date>April 19, 1865</date> 
                  <pubPlace>M. E. Church,
Edgartown, Mass.</pubPlace> 
                  <author>Reed, Rev. S.</author> 
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Boston</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Press of Geo. C. Rand &#x0026;
Avery</publisher>
                     <date>1865</date>
                  </imprint> 
               </bibl> 
            </head>
            <p>
               <figure entity="reed1">
                  <figDesc>1st page of Rev. S. Reed's A
Discourse Delivered on the Occasion of the Funeral Obsequies of
President Lincoln.</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <p>A</p>
            <p>Discourse</p>
            <p>DELIVERED ON THE OCCASION OF</p>
            <p>THE FUNERAL OBSEQUIES</p>
            <p>OF</p>
            <p>PRESIDENT LINCOLN,</p>
            <p>APRIL 19, 1865.</p>
            <p>By REV. S. REED,</p>
            <p>Pastor M. E. CHURCH, EDGARTOWN, MASS.</p>
            <p>BOSTON:</p>
            <p>PRESS OF Geo. C. RAND &#x0026; AVERY, 3 CORNHILL.</p>
            <p>1865.</p>
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>
               <figure entity="reed2">
                  <figDesc>2nd page of
Rev. S. Reed's A Discourse Delivered on the Occasion of the Funeral
Obsequies of President Lincoln.</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>
               <figure entity="reed3">
                  <figDesc>3rd page of
Rev. S. Reed's A Discourse Delivered on the Occasion of the Funeral
Obsequies of President Lincoln.</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <p>CORRESPONDENCE.</p>
            <p>EDGARTOWN, April 19, 1865.</p>
            <p>REV. S. REED.</p>
            <p>SIR,-At a
meeting of the Committee appointed by the citizens of Edgartown to
make arrangements for the appropriate observance of the funeral
obsequies of President Lincoln, it was unanimously resolved that a
copy of the very excellent and appropriate discourse this day
delivered by you be respectfully requested for publication.</p>
            <p>Appreciating the kindness which induced you to consent, upon so
brief a notice, to the request of the Committee, that you would speak
to the people burdened with sadness and sitting under the shadow of
the terrible affliction which has converted this entire nation into a
house of mourning,</p>
            <p>I am, sir,</p>
            <p>With the highest respect,</p>
            <p>Yours truly,</p>
            <p>RICHARD L. PEASE,</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italic">Chairman.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>MR. R. L. PEASE, and GENTLEMEN OF THE COMMITTEE:</p>
            <p>If the publication of the discourse which it was my sad duty to
deliver to you to-day will, in your judgment, promote the happiness of
any one in our now sorrow-stricken nation, I cheerfully comply with
your request. I am aware, however, as you doubtless are, of its many
imperfections, arising in part from. the brief time in which it was
prepared. Hoping you will receive it, as I most certainly give it, as
a sincere tribute of affection to the memory of our beloved and
lamented President,</p>
            <p>I am</p>
            <p>Yours
truly,</p>
            <p>S. REED.</p>
            <p>EDGARTOWN, April 19, 1865.</p>
            <pb n="4"/>
<!-- blank page -->
<!--            <p>
               <figure entity="reed4">
                  <figDesc>4th page of
Rev. S. Reed's A Discourse Delivered on the Occasion of the Funeral
Obsequies of President Lincoln.</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p> -->
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>
               <figure entity="reed5">
                  <figDesc>5th page of
Rev. S. Reed's A Discourse Delivered on the Occasion of the Funeral
Obsequies of President Lincoln.</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <div2 id="reed.002" n="DISCOURSE" type="sermon">
               <head>DISCOURSE.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <p>Shall not the Judge of all
the earth do right?" -GEN. xviii. 25.</p>
               </epigraph>
               <p>ABRAHAM had long been an anxious spectator of the awful degradation
of the cities of the plain; and, when the decree of the Almighty was
communicated to him, that the sword of vengeance should be unsheathed,
he saw its justice and he -murmured not. But when he thought of the
few probable righteous in the cities, and could see no way for them to
escape the impending ruin, his great heart melted with sympathy, and
he began to question the wisdom and goodness of' the divine
proceeding. But his questionings were as blind as they were ill-timed;
for, as yet, God had communicated to him only a part of his plan, and
had not told him that if a sufficient number of righteous persons were
not found to move divine forbearance, yet what few there were should
be led forth by his holy angels to a city of refuge. Abraham misjudged
the character of the wonderful providence which he was told was about
to take place, because he judged before the designs of God in that
providence were fully unfolded.</p>
               <p>From all the information he then had, it was apparent to him that
the righteous must perish with the wicked; and the justice of such a
providence he distrusted. 
<pb n="6"/>
                  <figure entity="reed6">
                     <figDesc>6th page of Rev. S. Reed's A
Discourse Delivered on the Occasion of the Funeral Obsequies of
President Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
This distrust arose from his ignorance of the divine plan; and so do
men often fall into doubt and disbelief when they attempt to inspect
and pass judgment upon the doings of the Almighty. They behold but
parts of his ways; they see but one link in the great chain of his
providence,-the one right before their eyes; and., failing to see the
good and benevolent results which that chain unites to God, they
conclude, in their ignorance, that the ways of the Lord are not
equal.</p>
               <p>In examining the providence of God, we should be careful not to
form Our conclusions from those parts of it which are visible to our
own eyes, at the present time, and immediately around us. We should
search for the most probable effect that such and such parts are
designed to have upon men at large. We should study God's designs, not
only in the external and superficial changes that affect society, but
we should trace those designs down deep into the human mind and
character, and we should follow them outward and onward to the
boundaries of his moral government.</p>
               <p>There are events in human life which reveal the wickedness of man
and the holiness of God in such apparent proximity as to fill the mind
with the most profound and solemn questionings; events which force the
soul to the resources of eternal Truth. Such are the events
transpiring around us at the present time and in their light we come
to inquire--</p>
               <p>WHAT ARE THE LIMITATIONS OF DIVINE PROVIDENCE IN HUMAN CONDUCT?</p>
               <p>1. Man is a moral agent therefore free. God created him free,
therefore the creation is "right;" and here we see providence. But his
being man implies the possibility that he may sin. Should God make it
im-
<pb n="7"/>
                  <figure entity="reed7">
                     <figDesc>7th page of Rev. S. Reed's A
Discourse Delivered on the Occasion of the Funeral Obsequies of
President Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
possible for him to sin, he would make him something else than man.</p>
               <p>"Why," it is often asked, "does not God prevent such and such acts
of wickedness?" I answer that he could, doubtless, prevent all acts of
wickedness; but he would then prevent the power of obedience also, for
the possibility of virtue in a probationer implies the possibility of
vice. If, therefore, it is wise and good in God to grant to men a term
of probation, it is wise and good in him to grant to them the
possibilities of virtue and vice; and the power to commit great acts
of wickedness is but the power to perform great acts of virtue.</p>
               <p>2. We see the providence of God in the restraints which he throws
around men everywhere to deter them from the commission of sin; and,
on the other hand, in the inducements which he everywhere affords to
men to the performance of virtue. These restraints and incentives are
always of the same holy character, and they are presented with a force
as great as can possibly consist with men's freedom. If the power of
right motives were increased upon men, their power of resistance must
be correspondingly increased; hence nothing would be gained to
virtue.</p>
               <p>3. We trace the providence of God, also, in working continually
against the results of sin, yet all the while in perfect accordance
with man's freedom.</p>
               <p>In all the history of the race we see God bounding and
counteracting sin so that it shall not become universal.</p>
               <p>Though he cannot prevent men from wrong-doing without making them
something else than men, yet he does overrule the results of their
wrong-doing; he does press their wickedness into his own service, and
"make their wrath to praise him;" he does bring light out of darkness
and good out of evil. Whatever may
<pb n="8"/>
                  <figure entity="reed8">
                     <figDesc>8th page of Rev. S. Reed's A
Discourse Delivered on the Occasion of the Funeral Obsequies of
President Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
be the malignity of the vicious, however deep the turpitude of their
crimes, God will not suffer consequences to flow therefrom which he
cannot control.</p>
               <p>From this stand-point we come to-day to look upon our bereavement;
and, though we meet under a cloud of unwonted gloom, which has been
caused by a fellow-being, yet we will remember that the "Judge of all
the earth doeth right."</p>
               <p>An act has been performed by an American citizen which strikes
horror to the hearts of millions; an act the results of which reach
farther than the shores of a continent, which will shock the entire
civilized world; an act which will pass into human history as the most
unparalleled in atrocity since its great archetype was performed at
Mount Calvary.</p>
               <p>A brutal assassin, thirsting for the most precious of human blood
steals to the presence of the unsuspecting Magistrate of this nation,
and, with plans laid with fiendish precision, delights in a deadly aim
which pierces the hearts of all Christendom. By that assassin's hand
our beloved President now sleeps in death; and now a nation has met,
as never a nation met before, to mourn his loss. The lamentation is as
wide as our land. The weeds of woe which hang around this temple
to-day, and which are so consonant with the feelings of our hearts,
stretch away from the Atlantic to the Pacific shores, and from the
northern lakes to the southern gulf. There is not a city, or town, or
hamlet, or family, where loyalty and humanity dwell, but is in
mourning at this hour. As one great family the American people now sit
in silent grief, bereaved and desolate, a common affliction binding
all hearts in one universal brotherhood of sorrow; every heart
feeling, "all thy waves and thy billows are gone over me." 0 God,
<pb n="9"/>
                  <figure entity="reed9">
                     <figDesc>9th page of Rev. S. Reed's A
Discourse Delivered on the Occasion of the Funeral Obsequies of
President Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
what an hour of gloom is this! What sadness we feel! So sudden so
mysterious, so aggravating, such crushing sadness! We look through our
tears to thee, 0 God, and we try to discern thee. Oh, may we behold
thee! may we even seen thy hand, and our mourning shall be hushed, and
we will know that the Judge of all the earth will do right!</p>
               <p>And, my hearers, let us prayerfully inquire to-day, <hi rend="italic">Can we behold a Providence here? What part has the Lord
performed in our bereavement, and what part has he not
performed?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is true God gave to the assassin, or the assassins, <hi rend="italic">freedom</hi>. He made them men, and endowed them with
those high powers which in their perversion, have wrought such
ruin. But with the gift of freedom comes the fact of
accountability. The murderers of our President are <hi rend="italic">guilty</hi>, and the law of the righteous Judge connects
their guilt with its punishment. They can be punished, because, <hi rend="italic">being free, they committed the crime</hi>. And here we see
providence in that those bloody fiends are <hi rend="italic">bound to
the Judgment</hi>. The eternal law binds them there, and He says
"Vengeance is mine, I will repay." No power in the universe can
dissolve the relation between crime and its punishment. Great is the
anxiety in the American nation to-day that the guilty ones may be
arrested, in order that they may be brought to justice. Let not our
anxiety at this point be mistaken. Should they be arrested and
punished, the punishment would have respect only to human laws, and be
designed only to protect human society; it could not meet the claims
of God's violated law; nor could it come up at all to the measure of
their guilt. Whether or not those men elude the vigilance of civil
officers, and the penalties of human laws, thank heaven,
<pb n="10"/>
                  <figure entity="reed10">
                     <figDesc>10th page of
Rev. S. Reed's A Discourse Delivered on the Occasion of the Funeral
Obsequies of President Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
there is a Providence "<hi rend="italic">that shall by no means clear
the guilty</hi>."</p>
               <p>We see God's providence, also, in the restraints which were thrown
around the assassins to prevent the commission of their deed. They had
been restrained by fear of detection, by the vigilance of the people,
if not by their own consciences. They had been foiled in their plans
again and again, since the first dark plot was formed for the
President's murder four years ago; and even now they were unable to
carry out the awful plot to its completion.</p>
               <p>But further than this, in the act which bereaved our nation of its
head, <hi rend="italic">Providence had nothing to do</hi>. Tell us not
it was the hand of the Lord that took Abraham Lincoln from us. His
hand was stretched out to restrain, not to put forward the assassins;
to preserve, not to kill, the President. There was no providence in
his murder, any more than in any other wicked act that man ever
did. "It was an enemy that did this," an enemy that both planned and
executed the deed. It was not the hand of Providence that did this
stupendous wrong; it was the great, black hand of the Devil, and there
shall the wrong rest.</p>
               <p>And this distinction between the spirit of evil, which prompts men
to wicked deeds, and the spirit of the Lord, which only prompts them
to good, will save us from distrust and despair.</p>
               <p>And this leads us again to inquire--</p>
               <p>WHAT IS THAT SPIRIT WHICH IS THE SOLE PRODUCING CAUSE OF OUR
BEREAVEMENT THIS DAY?</p>
               <p>Mr. Lincoln falls not as a usurper, to indemnify injured
rights. Kings and emperors have been assassinated;
<pb n="11"/>
                  <figure entity="reed11">
                     <figDesc>11th page of
Rev. S. Reed's A Discourse Delivered on the Occasion of the Funeral
Obsequies of President Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
but it was by those whose rights to dominion  had been violated or who
expected to ascend the throne when it should be vacated. But our
President was no usurper. He was elected to the chief magistracy by
the free choice of a free people. There was not a human being on this
footstool whose rights had been injured by his occupancy of the
national chair.</p>
               <p>Mr. Lincoln falls not by the hand of the midnight robber who
thirsted for his gold. It was no ordinary spirit of covetousness,
though that spirit has tasted the blood of untold millions, that
thirsted for his. It was a spirit feller and fiercer far than that.</p>
               <p>Mr. Lincoln falls not for any abuse of power placed in his hands,
nor for the practice of any personal vices that made him odious to the
people. Other rulers have practised, and have forced upon their
people, such intolerable vices, that assassination, always a crime,
became their excuse and their relief. But Mr. Lincoln had no vices
that afflicted the people; neither was there the least approach to any
thing like the spirit of tyranny manifested through all his public
career. In the administration of the duties of his high office, as in
the more, private walks of life, he was ever the same man of kindness
and of genuine sympathy with his fellow-men. Coming from the ranks of
the people, his heart was in closest union with the people. Their
welfare was his welfare; their joy, his joy; their sorrow, his
sorrow. His hand grasped with like cordiality the hand of the
statesman, the mechanic, or the day laborer; and all classes of honest
people received a welcome to his presence, and a blessing from his
lips.</p>
               <p>No: it was the spirit, which has drenched our land in blood, the
spirit that has raised the greatest rebellion
<pb n="12"/>
                  <figure entity="reed12">
                     <figDesc>12th page of
Rev. S. Reed's A Discourse Delivered on the Occasion of the Funeral
Obsequies of President Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
Booth the murderer is but one among the tens of thousands of his kin;
and, viewed in reference to the spirit that produced him, he is a most
insignificant particle, like a flake of black cinder thrown from the
molten bowels of a volcano.</p>
               <p>Booth was but the tool of the confederacy; the plot was the plot of
the rebels; and when he leaped upon the stage, and shouted "<hi rend="italic">Sic semper tyrannis</hi>!" he but shouted the rebels'
watchword.</p>
               <p>That plot embraced, doubtless, not only the President, but the
Vice-President, the Cabinet, and the Lieut. General. The spirit that
planned it is older than the Rebellion, as the father is older than
the child. It has lived a century and more in this country, and has
fattened and thrived upon the richest heritage, and under the best
human government, ever given to men.</p>
               <p>The genius of that spirit is the genius of barbarism; it is the
soul of tyranny, the breath of indolence, and the life of lust. See
this dark spirit of hell! At first it only demanded sufferance while
it might die; but, instead of dying, it began to grow, and to assume
gigantic, strength, making demand after demand, receiving concession
after concession, until it overrides the Constitution, paralyzes the
Government, and debases the sacred ermine of justice in the State and
Federal courts. It grasps the Bible, and first it blots and blurs all
its parts which speak of human freedom and the equality of men; next
it enjoins silence upon the pulpit; then commands it to proclaim the
divinity of this horrid thing. It presses the majesty of theology into
its service, tears churches in twain, and makes doctors of divinity
advocate it on their knees. It then seizes the reins of national
government, unfurling its black banner over this entire land of
freedom. Because rebuked
<pb n="13"/>
                  <figure entity="reed13">
                     <figDesc>13th page of
Rev. S. Reed's A Discourse Delivered on the Occasion of the Funeral
Obsequies of President Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
and checked at this point, it then plots treason; steals the property
of the Government, bribes her officers, butchers her citizens, knocks
down her best senators, hangs her ministers and lays its bloody hand
on her flag to rend it in pieces. Thus this dark thing lifts itself up
in the light of our Christian civilization; and, with eyes gloating
over the downfall of freedom and religion, and with heart swelled with
the glut of human innocence it shouts, <hi rend="italic">Though a
million of freeman die, yet slavery shall live!</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And so has this spirit sought to lay the foundation of its black
monarchy in our midst, resting on the hearts and pressing out the
sighs and tears, of millions of human beings. This is the spirit,
which, for four dark years, has been hanging its weeds of woe in all
our homes; which has been drinking the blood of our brothers,
husbands, and sons; which has starved them in barbarous prisons; and
has laughed at their dying groans. This is the spirit that has
murdered our noble President. Abraham Lincoln falls the victim of'
slavery, THE MARTYR OF LIBERTY.</p>
               <p>We will now inquire--</p>
               <p>WHAT ARE THE RESULTS WHICH WE MAY HOPE DIVINE PROVIDENCE WILL
CONNECT WITH THIS SAD EVENT?</p>
               <p>For He who is all-wise, whose eyes are everywhere, beholding the
evil and the good, saw that the assassin would do the deed. Because he
is good and wise, we must believe that he is ready to connect with the
deed results that shall be glorious to humanity. Such is his
prerogative, and such his pleasure; and many of the most blessed
dispensations of mercy to our world have been brought forth from its
deepest crimes. Great and
<pb n="14"/>
                  <figure entity="reed14">
                     <figDesc>14th page of
Rev. S. Reed's A Discourse Delivered on the Occasion of the Funeral
Obsequies of President Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
glorious were the results which God brought out of the wicked sale of
Joseph by his brethren ; greater, more glorious, the results he
brought out of the sale of Jesus by Judas, the great prototype of
Booth; and great shall be the results which God will draw from this
deed of monstrous birth, if we are willing to receive them. And,</p>
               <p>1. We may believe that he would lead the American people to a more
profound recognition of himself. We have "forgotten God," - so said
President Lincoln in his immortal inaugural. Men are prone to creature
worship: so has it ever been. The great men of the past, who, under
God, have been the benefactors and deliverers of the people, were then
exalted and deified by the people, while the giver of their blessings
was forgotten. Had Mr. Lincoln lived longer, who can say but we should
have ascribed to him the glory that was not his? We might have lost
sight of the omnipotent arm that had wrought our victories for us. As
a people, we might have sinned in glorifying the creature; and our
danger of this was very great. We loved our Lincoln and we almost
thought he was our strength and our deliverer; but God had said, "I am
a jealous God, and my glory will I not give to another." Mr.Lincoln
saw this danger of ours, and he warned us against it. More than any
other president since John Adams did he ascribe all the glory of our
national prosperity to the Divine Being, and earnestly did he call
upon us to seek the favor of the Almighty in order to
success. Mr. Lincoln recognized the divine arm, during all our
struggles, mysteriously directing events so as to preserve our nation;
and he was not the man to arrogate to himself the glory that belonged
to God.</p>
               <p>And we are this day reminded that we can lean on
<pb n="15"/>
                  <figure entity="reed15">
                     <figDesc>15th page of
Rev. S. Reed's A Discourse Delivered on the Occasion of the Funeral
Obsequies of President Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
no human arm. The greatest and the best of human rulers are as the
"flower of the field;" in a moment they are cut down, and are hidden
from our view. But, if in our hearts there is a profound regard for
the righteousness of God, we shall be preserved, even though our
rulers fall before our eyes.</p>
               <p>2. From this event there shall spring forth a holier, stronger bond
of union to this nation. Reaching, as it does, to the very depths of
the human soul; stirring all its most holy sympathies; rousing all its
sense of justice, honor, right,--this event will be more mighty on the
hearts of oncoming generations than laws or armies.</p>
               <p>The influence of the grave of a patriot, a statesman, a deliverer,
is mysterious and powerful over the human mind The graves of some
kings and conquerers do more for their people than the reign of some
living monarchs. England could not spare the grave of Wellington, and
for what would America part with the grave of Washington?</p>
               <p>See that young prince, heir to the proudest throne on the globe, as
he visits our Republic a few years since. Apparently uninterested, he
passes through our crowded cities, and over our broad States, till he
comes to Mount Vernon. There he pauses, and, with head uncovered, in
profound meditation, as if communing with some mighty spirit from the
past, he stands silently gazing into the tomb of Washington. A sigh
escapes from his bosom tears fill his eyes; humbled and satisfied, he
turns from the sacred place and says, "I have seen enough of America
now; let me go home."</p>
               <p>But he had not seen all nor felt all. He had seen only the grave of
a great patriot. There is a grave opened in our land to-day that shall
have a mightier power, that shall shape vaster destinies. It is the
grave
<pb n="16"/>
                  <figure entity="reed16">
                     <figDesc>16th page of
Rev. S. Reed's A Discourse Delivered on the Occasion of the Funeral
Obsequies of President Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
of a great martyr as well as patriot. WASHINGTON came down to his
grave calmly, serenely, as the full- glowing sun sinks out of sight at
evening, leaving in all hearts a feeling of sadness that he had
departed, yet of joy that he had departed so gloriously. LINCOLN comes
down to his grave like the sun in his mid-day splendor, arrested by
some mighty power and plunged instantly into midnight darkness.</p>
               <p>But this martyr's death shall tell to future generations the value
of freedom. The future patriot, historian, Christian, when he reads
the history of the administration now closed; when he shall have
visited the homes now desolated, and listened to the recital of sorrow
that can never be written; when he shall have visited a hundred
battle-fields, and seen the soil strewed with the bones of noble
freemen, and shall then come to the grave of Lincoln, and read there
the lesson we are reading to-day, will have learned something of the
price we have paid for liberty.</p>
               <p>But the tree of liberty is firmly planted upon our soil now. Its
roots strike into half a million of free-men's graves; its centre-root
strikes to the bottom of our President's grave; and there is no
despot's hand can uproot that tree. It is well watered now,-watered by
the blood of America's best; and it will grow well.  The meanest of
America's sons who has freely bled in this struggle for liberty has
shed better blood than any monarch on the globe has to shed.</p>
               <p>3.  But this result, also, we think God will connect with this
event, -A HIGHER APPRECIATION OF JUSTICE.</p>
               <p>When the Lord gave promise to Abraham that he should become a great
nation, he said, "For I know him that be will command his children,
and his household after him, to do justice and judgment, that the Lord
<pb n="17"/>
                  <figure entity="reed17">
                     <figDesc>17th page of
Rev. S. Reed's A Discourse Delivered on the Occasion of the Funeral
Obsequies of President Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
may bring upon Abraham that which he hath spoken of him."</p>
               <p>Justice is that quality which underlies all right government, which
secures it from the encroachments of evil, which guards the persons
and rights of all the individual subjects of government. Indeed, it is
the very foundation-stone on which the order and peace of society
rest.</p>
               <p>If, on the one hand, rulers disregard justice, the perpetuity of
government and the safety of the people are endangered: if; on the
other hand, the people have a low sense of the sacredness of justice,
it will be impossible for rulers to enforce it; and the laws which are
made for the bad will be ineffective, and the vicious will go
unpunished.</p>
               <p>A time of national disorder and prostration occurred in Israel once
and God assigned the cause and said, "No man careth for justice, -nor
any pleadeth for the truth."</p>
               <p>It is well known, that, for many years, our wisest and best
statesmen have discovered among both officers and people, a declension
of the sense of justice; and they have experienced great anxiety on
account of it.</p>
               <p>The indications of decline were unmistakable. There was apparent a
very general neglect to enforce law upon transgressors, who became,
consequently, bold and numerous, while many pleaded openly in favor of
letting criminals go unpunished. German infidelity, which would
abolish all penalties, and allow each man to avenge his own personal
injuries, if he were strong enough to do so found surprising growth
here; so that spontaneous efforts to release the guilty from the hands
of justice were quite as frequent as like efforts to bring them to
justice. In some States, capital punishment had
<pb n="18"/>
                  <figure entity="reed18">
                     <figDesc>18th page of
Rev. S. Reed's A Discourse Delivered on the Occasion of the Funeral
Obsequies of President Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
been abolished and there too the pardoning power had been exercised to
an alarming degree; so that crime had increased, and Government gave
less pledge of security to person and property.</p>
               <p>How far this low sense of justice among us had been produced by
slavery, which openly sets all justice at defiance, I stop not now to
inquire; but, certain it is, that, from a disregard of personal rights
and private life, the life of the nation came to be disregarded, and
organized treason was the result. And, strange to say, treason, which
in all civilized countries is considered as the highest civil crime,
and is punishable everywhere by death, found so many in this nation to
palliate it that it was exceedingly difficult, and it has been
difficult up to the present time, to brand it with its own native
guilt.</p>
               <p>Now, it is one thing to guard and defend a man from the hands of an
assassin; it is quite another thing to bring the assassin to justice
and punish him. One man may be eminently qualified for the one work,
another man for the other. It is one thing to defend. a nation from
the assaults of traitors; it is quite another thing to lift up the
down-trodden law and bring those traitors to justice.</p>
               <p>When our Heaven-favored nation was assaulted, and eight millions of
her subjects, armed from her own armories, rose in hellish purpose to
slay her, and unknown thousands through all our midst stood ready to
her burial, Abraham Lincoln was called to her defence. Nobly did he
take his stand between the foe and his unarmed victim. Never did the
war of human elements rage fiercer around a human ruler than around
him. The mad legions of the foe surged up to the capital; they
surrounded it; they began to close in;
<pb n="19"/>
                  <figure entity="reed19">
                     <figDesc>19th page of
Rev. S. Reed's A Discourse Delivered on the Occasion of the Funeral
Obsequies of President Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
enemies were in the city, and traitors in the Government-offices;
senators trembled; secretaries turned pale; ministers said it was all
over; and the enemy shouted, "On to the capital!"</p>
               <p>But there stood the great man in the majesty of his mighty manhood,
calm and undaunted, while great men quaked around him. With his eye
upon the foe, and his arm outstretched to wave the flag of liberty
over the nation committed to his charge, there he stood to command
both the armies of the country and the admiration of the world. For
that place, God had given him the qualifications, - firmness that
saved him from faltering; leniency to attract and fix the wavering;
buoyancy of spirit; and faith in the right which saved him from
despairing. With a breadth of comprehension and a power of execution
which but few men of our age possess, he surveyed the real work to be
done and at the same time estimated the agencies necessary to
accomplish it. To the preservation of this Republic and its
emancipation from the chains of slavery for all future time, he was
called; nor did he leave his post either to hurl back the shafts of
malignity that fell harmless at his feet from foreign thrones or to
join in the shouts of victories he had won at home. During the long
dark years of his first term of administration he stood, till the
enemy, crushed beneath the gathering forces of the nation, began to
retire; and, as they fell back, and the din of war subsided, and the
smoke began to roll away, there was revealed to the gaze of the
nations that colossal embodiment of LIBERTY still waving the flag
which is dearer to humanity than any that ever floated on the breeze
of heaven. And now, as that flag floated proudly from his hand,
floated over the national capital, over the fallen rebel capital, over
every
<pb n="20"/>
                  <figure entity="reed20">
                     <figDesc>20th page of
Rev. S. Reed's A Discourse Delivered on the Occasion of the Funeral
Obsequies of President Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
State of the old Union, we hear the voice of our Lincoln shouting "THE
NATION IS FREE AND SLAVERY IS DEAD!" It is the voice of Lincoln ; but
it is the voice of Freedom too, and she is shouting her eternal rights
in the ear of old despotism. That voice dies not when it touches the
shores of this continent. It rolls on; the waves of ocean bear it; the
winds of heaven waft it; the lightnings of God flash it to every
despot's throne on the globe. It is the voice that announces their
doom; and, from the time of Abraham Lincoln's administration onward,
tyrants and traitors will tremble.</p>
               <p>But Mr. Lincoln had done his work. During the long night in which
the assault upon the nation had been made, he had defended her, and
had put the assailants to flight. Now when the morning dawns, he,
satisfied with his work and rejoicing in the prospect of a long and
cloudless day of national prosperity, retires to his rest.</p>
               <p>Other work is to be done now; and what is it? Last Friday night,
and Saturday and Sunday and Monday, a scene of excitement prevailed in
Washington: it continues to the present hour. The assassins of our
President have fled; the officers of justice are in pursuit; the
murderers shall be caught if possible. If taken, (which may Heaven
grant!) what shall be done with them? Do I hear any one around me
today pleading for their pardon and release? Not one. The law says
they shall be hung; and there is not a Christian or a philanthropist
on earth but would say from the depth of his heart "The law is good:
let them hang!"</p>
               <p>But what shall we do with those other assassins who planned the
death of the nation as well as of the President who put the dagger to
the nation's breast, whose deadly aim was for the nation's life? What
shall we
<pb n="21"/>
                  <figure entity="reed21">
                     <figDesc>21st page of
Rev. S. Reed's A Discourse Delivered on the Occasion of the Funeral
Obsequies of President Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
do with those men, guilty as Booth, who deliberately planned the
slaughter of tens of thousands; who urged their rebel hordes on to
execute their plan; who, like savages starved and murdered our
soldiers till the land is filled with mourning? Are those men who
planned this Rebellion and led it on less guilty than Booth? Not one
whit! What shall we do with them? is the question that now rises
spontaneously in every patriot's mind. The question as yet is
unanswered, and it begins to assume an importance in the minds of
all. Grave issues are likely to arise from it,--issues that will touch
the foundations of government and shape future destinies.</p>
               <p>But hark! While the nation is uttering its wail of sorrow there
comes another voice. We turn and look. No sooner does our President
expire than we see advancing to take his place one of determined mien
and quick of step. In his voice there is a certain sound, and a
flashing light in his eye.</p>
               <p>Who is this that cometh from Tennessee, with dyed garments from the
fields of blood? We hear him answer, "I am Johnson, and I now speak
with authority." But wherefore art thou red in thine apparel, and thy
appearance like him that treadeth in the wine fat? He answers, "
Because I have trodden the winepress alone, and of the people there
was none with me; I come from the scenes of secession and murder; I
have witnessed the deep, damning guilt of treason -therefore will I
tread down our enemies in my fury, and I will sprinkle their blood
upon my garments, for the day of vengeance is in my heart, and the
year of the redeemed is come."</p>
               <p>In the very presence of the lifeless form of our beloved Lincoln,
Mr. Johnson says, " I pity the deluded masses
<pb n="22"/>
                  <figure entity="reed22">
                     <figDesc>22nd page of
Rev. S. Reed's A Discourse Delivered on the Occasion of the Funeral
Obsequies of President Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
of the Southern people; <hi rend="italic">but upon the leaders, the
responsible men of this Rebellion, I would the penalty of the
law</hi>."</p>
               <p>To that declaration there comes from the hearts of all loyal
Americans a hearty AMEN; AMEN comes from the desolated homes and
hearts through all our land; AMEN comes from the graves where sleep
our noble soldiers.</p>
               <p>In the name of our outraged, weeping nation, we say, Welcome,
Johnson! In the name of Heaven's injured innocence, in the name of
Liberty, so long in chains now rising in her beauty, we say to
President Johnson, Welcome to the chair of National Government; and
may the law of eternal justice ever encircle that chair!</p>
               <pb n="23"/>
               <p>
                  <figure entity="reed23">
                     <figDesc>23rd page of
Rev. S. Reed's A Discourse Delivered on the Occasion of the Funeral
Obsequies of President Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <p>ORDER OF EXERCISES.</p>
               <p>VOLUNTARY.</p>
               <p>A.H. WENZELL, ORGANIST.</p>
               <p>HYMN.</p>
               <lg type="stanza">
                  <l>There's rest in the grave:</l>
                  <l>Life's toils are
past,</l>
                  <l>Night cometh at last.</l>
                  <l>How calmly I rest</l>
                  <l>In
the sleep of the blest,</l>
                  <l>Nor hear Life's storm rave</l>
                  <l>O'er
my green grassy grave!</l>
               </lg>
               <p>INVOCATION.</p>
               <p>REV. JOHN E. WOOD.</p>
               <p>DIRGE.</p>
               <lg type="stanza">
                  <l>Unveil thy bosom, faithful tomb,</l>
                  <l>Take this
new treasure to thy trust;</l>
                  <l>And give these sacred relics
room</l>
                  <l>To slumber in the silent dust.</l>
               </lg>
               <p>SELECTIONS FROM SCRIPTURES.</p>
               <p>REV. HARTFORD P. LEONARD.</p>
               <p>PRAYER.</p>
               <p>REV. JOHN E. WOOD.</p>
               <p>HYMN.</p>
               <lg type="stanza">
                  <l>Calmly now in peace thou'rt  sleeping</l>
                  <l>In thy grave so low;</l>
                  <l>While sad Eve her tears is weeping,</l>
                  <l>Emblem of our woe;</l>
                  <l>And the night-wind, without failing,</l>
                  <l>Sadly o'er thee now is wailing</l>
               </lg>
               <pb n="24"/>
               <p>
                  <figure entity="reed24">
                     <figDesc>24th page of
Rev. S. Reed's A Discourse Delivered on the Occasion of the Funeral
Obsequies of President Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <p>ADDRESS.</p>
               <p>REV. SETH REED.</p>
               <p>PRAYER.</p>
               <p>HYMN.</p>
               <lg type="stanza">
                  <l>No change of time shall ever shock</l>
                  <l>My trust, O Lord, in thee;</l>
                  <l>For thou hast always been my
rock,</l>
                  <l>A sure defence to me.</l>
               </lg>
               <p>BENEDICTION.</p>
               <p>Committee
of Arrangements.</p>
               <p>Richard L. Pease.                                Hartford
P. Leonard.                            Grafton N. Collins.  <lb/>John
Vinson.                                         James B. Huxford.
John E. Wood.  <lb/>James L. Barrows.
Shubael H. Norton.                                 Jeremiah Pease.<lb/>
Ralph Cleavland.                                  J.D. Usher.
George Coffin.  <lb/>Seth Reed.
Joseph Athearn.                                      James M. Cooms,
Jr.</p>
            </div2>
         </div1>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI.2>