<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader><fileDesc>
         <titleStmt n="A Sermon Preached Before the Congregational Church and Society in Green's Farms, Conn., on the Day of the National Fast, Occasioned by the Death of Abraham Lincoln, President of the United States, June 1st, 1865.">
            <title>  A Sermon Preached Before the Congregational Church and
Society in Green's Farms, Conn., on the Day of the National Fast,
Occasioned by the Death of Abraham Lincoln, President of the United
States, June 1st, 1865.</title>
            <author>Relyea, Rev. B. J. </author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Compiled and edited by</resp>
               <name>Beck
Center</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent/>
         <publicationStmt><publisher>Lewis H. Beck Center</publisher><pubPlace>Emory
University</pubPlace><address>
               <addrLine>Atlanta,
Georgia</addrLine>
            </address><availability>
               <p>1996 Emory
University. Permission is granted to download, transmit, or otherwise
reproduce, distribute or display the contributions to the work claimed
by Emory University for non-profit educational purposes, provided
this header is included in its entirety.  For inquiries about
commercial uses, contact the Director, 
Pitts Theology Library, Emory
University, Atlanta, Georgia 30322</p>
            </availability><date>1999</date></publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Lincoln Sermons Project</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Relyea, Rev. B. J. The Nation's Mourning. A Sermon Preached
Before the Congregational Church and Society in Green's Farms, Conn.,
on the Day of the National Fast, Occasioned by the Death of Abraham
Lincoln, President of the United States, June 1st, 1865.  The
Congregational Church and Society in Green's Farms, Conn. June 1st,
1865. </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc><encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This text derives from the Special Collections 
of Pitts Theology Library, Emory University, and is produced in 
collaboration with the Lewis H. Beck Center a, the Emory 
Preservation Office, and Pitts Theology Library.</p>
            <p>TRANSCRIBER: Lewis H. Beck Center and Emory University 
Preservation Office.</p>
            <p>PRODUCER:  BookLab, Inc., 1606 Headway Circle, 
Suite 100, Austin, TX 78754</p>
            <p>CAPTURE DEVICE: XEROX DocuImage 620S flatbed scanner</p>
            <p>CAPTURE DETAILS: Scanner software: XEROX ScanTool 
version 4.2.3; no gamma correction; images are all bitonal.</p>
            <p>CHANGE HISTORY: Using the Adobe Photoshop Batch Processor, 
we interpolated  the original TIFF files to 8-bit grays, 
and altered the resolution to 144 dpi, producing screen 
images twice the original size.  We then saved them in 
JPEG format.  We produced GIF thumbnails from the JPEG files.</p>
            <p>RESOLUTION: 600 ppi</p>
            <p>COMPRESSION: Resolution 144 per inch with Constrain 
Properties to 72 per inch.</p>
            <p>SOURCE: Original documents.</p>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc><revisionDesc><change><name>Stewart Varner</name> transformed this document from p4 to p5 on <date when="2010-03-22">March 22, 2010</date></change><change xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><date>1999</date><label>Staff</label><name>Scott Ellis</name>SGML tags
inserted in compliance with TEI guidelines using TEILITE</change></revisionDesc></teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div1 xml:id="relyea.001" n="A Sermon Preached Before the Congregational Church and Society in Green's Farms, Conn., on the Day of the National Fast, Occasioned by the Death of Abraham Lincoln, President of the United States, June 1st, 1865." type="text">
            <head>
               <bibl>
                  <title> The Nation's Mourning. A Sermon Preached Before the
Congregational Church and Society in Green's Farms, Conn., on the Day
of the National Fast, Occasioned by the Death of Abraham Lincoln,
President of the United States, June 1st, 1865.</title> 
                  <date>June
1st, 1865</date> 
                  <pubPlace>The Congregational Church and Society in
Green's Farms, Conn.</pubPlace> 
                  <author>Rev. B. J. Relyea</author>
                  
                     <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Jno. P. Prall, Printer by
Steam, No. 9 Spruce-Street</publisher>
                     <date>1865</date>
                  
               <idno type="ark">http://pid.emory.edu/ark:/25593/15qv0</idno></bibl>
            </head>
            <pb facs="relyea1.jpg"/>
            <p>THE NATION'S MOURNING.</p>
            <p>A</p>
            <p>SERMON,</p>
            <p>PREACHED BEFORE THE</p>
            <p>CONGREGATIONAL CHURCH AND SOCIETY IN GREEN''S FARMS, CONN., ON THE
DAY OF THE NATIONAL FAST,</p>
            <p>OCCASIONED BY THE DEATH</p>
            <p>OF</p>
            <p>ABRAHAM LINCOLN</p>
            <p>PRESIDENT of the UNITED STATES,</p>
            <p>JUNE 1st 1865,</p>
            <p>By REV. B. J. RELYEA,</p>
            <p>PASTOR.</p>
            <p>New York:</p>
            <p>JNO. P. PRALL, PRINTER BY STEAM, No. 9
SPRUCE-STREET.</p>
            <p>1865.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="relyea2.jpg"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="relyea3.jpg"/>
            <p>CORRESPONDENCE.</p>
            <p>GREEN's FARMS, June 5th 1865.</p>
            <p>Rev. Mr. RELYEA,
<lb/>
Dear Sir-: In accordance with the general and often repeated wish
of your congregation, on Fast Day, we would respectfully request the
publication of your sermon, delivered on that occasion. We believe it
to be timely, instructive, well fitted to be useful, and well worthy
of permanent preservation.  <lb/>Yours affectionately, <lb/>E. B. ADAMS.<lb/>
JOHN S. HYDE.  <lb/>E. J. TAYLOR.  <lb/>S. B. SHERWOOD.  <lb/>JARVIS
JENNINGS.  <lb/>H. B. WAKEMAN.  <lb/>J. B. ELWOOD.  <lb/>T. B. WAKEMAN.<lb/>
DANIEL BURR.  <lb/>F. SUMNER.</p>
            <p>REPLY.</p>
            <p>GREEN's FARMS, June 7th 1865.  <lb/>DEACON E. B. ADAMS AND OTHERS,--
<lb/>
               <hi rend="italic">Gentlemen</hi>:
<lb/>
Your note of the 5th inst. has been handed to me. The sermon to
which you refer, was written hastily in the ordinary course of
preparation for the pulpit, without the remotest thought of its being
published. My individual preference would lead me to decline giving it
to the public in the form you suggest; but I find it difficult to
refuse compliance with the request of a people from whom so many
tokens of kindness have been received. I therefore place it at your
disposal, and you are at liberty to make such use of it as you may
think proper. In doing so, I have, the satisfaction of feeling fully
assured that it contains no sentiments but such as are held in common
by the members of this society, who though in some respects they may
differ in political sentiments, yet have had enough of good sense to
maintain harmony among, themselves, and enough of patriotism not to
shrink from their full share of the burdens and sacrifices necessary
to preserve unimpaired the authority of our national government. 
<lb/>
Very sincerely, and with much esteem, yours,  <lb/>B. J. RELYEA.</p>
            <pb n="4"/>
<!-- blank page -->
<!--            <p>
               <figure entity="relyea4">
                  <figDesc>4th page of
Rev. B. J. Relyea's The Nation's Mourning.</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p> -->
            <pb n="5" facs="relyea5.jpg"/>
            <div2 xml:id="relyea.002" n="SERMON" type="sermon">
               <head>SERMON.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <p>"And all Judah and Jerusalem mourned for Josiah."  <lb/>II
CHRON: XXXV. 24.</p>
               </epigraph>
               <p>In every great bereavement, whether individual or national, the
benefit to be derived results not from the first abolition of painful
and sorrowful feeling, but from the subduing influence of after
reflection. In the first moments of grief our minds are filled with a
tumult of emotions which renders us for the time incapable of fully
comprehending the meaning of the event--of measuring the interests
affected by it, or of learning the lessons which it teaches. It is
only when time and nature have come to the aid of reason, and given
calmness to our minds, that we are able to indulge in such meditations
as shall suitably impress the heart and influence the life.</p>
               <p>It is eminently appropriate, therefore, that such a day as this
should have been set apart in view of that event which has filled the
nation's heart with sorrow; and it is well that it should have been
deferred to this distance of time. The first bewilderment of the
sudden and stunning blow-the tumult of excited and conflicting
emotions which struggled in the national mind-the roll of muffled
drums-the tolling of bells-the solemn tramp of civic and military
processions, with all the pomp and pageantry of a nation's woe, have
passed away. And
<pb n="6" facs="relyea6.jpg"/>
we shall be able perhaps more calmly to view the bereavement and to
consider the lessons which it teaches.</p>
               <p>The most striking and showy demonstrations of grief are not always
indicative of deepest and most lasting sorrow. I have learned
seriously to doubt the depth and sincerity of the man's real,
self-denying patriotism, who finds it necessary to be always giving
some marked proof or protestation of his loyalty. I put such an one
down as having either a soft head or an unsound heart. So in the case
of national bereavement. It is not the most ostentatious display of
grief that is always most genuine. Great depth of feeling is not apt
to be over demonstrative. Deep waters flow with a comparatively calm
and quiet surface. Shallow streams are always most boisterous. When a
man is found babbling of his own. great sorrow, and lamenting the want
of it in others, generally you do not greatly err in esteeming him to
be one of those shallow streams--a man whose feelings, lie very much
on the surface, and not likely to be greatly benefitted by the
affliction.</p>
               <p>Neither is it true that the first outburst of uncontrollable
feeling, however real, is always followed by that permanent
improvement of character without which affliction fails to accomplish
its end. You have sometimes witnessed instances of individual or
family bereavement, in which the first tumult of emotion seemed for
the time ungovernable; yet in the course of a few months, or even
weeks, the whole current of their thoughts and of their lives was as
vain and frivolous as if no such affliction had befallen them. You
have witnessed other instances of affliction borne with comparative
serenity, and with little outward demonstration, which has,
nevertheless, left its mellowing and subduing influence upon the whole
after life. Thus in national bereavement. While a solemn and be-
<pb n="7" facs="relyea7.jpg"/>
coming respect for the nation's dead, and a suitable regard for the
forms and manifestations of sadness are always eminently fit and
proper, it is well to remember that true sorrow does not consist in
the trappings and decorations of mourning, but in a heart contrite and
bowed down with grief. The benefits of affliction are not derived from
transient feeling, however violent, but from calm reflection, and the
abiding, deep-toned impression left upon the mind.</p>
               <p>It is evident, from the following history, that the general
mourning of the Jewish nation, on the occasion referred to in the
text, partook very much of this ostentatious and evanescent
character-that it was not accompanied by repentance of heart, nor
followed by any lasting improvement in their way of life.</p>
               <p>On the death of Josiah there was indeed occasion for great
lamentation and mourning. More than people at the time were aware
of. He was a man of extraordinary virtue and piety. He shone as a star
of the purest lustre in a corrupt and degenerate age. Soon after he
had ascended the throne he set about the reformation of manners and
religion. He destroyed idolatry throughout the land. He brake down
their idols and their altars, and defiled them with dead men's
bones. He repaired the Temple and reinstated the pure worship of
God. He mourned and wept because of the sins of the people. He caused
the nation to assemble and renew their vows and their covenant with
God.</p>
               <p>Because of all this God was pleased to make known to him, through
Huldah the prophetess, that he would defer his anger, and postpone for
his sake the wrath which had been determined upon that people until
Josiah should have been gathered to his fathers. So that Josiah, as
their king, really stood be-
<pb n="8" facs="relyea8.jpg"/>
tween the nation and their coming destruction when he was suddenly cut
down-slain in battle. They brought him to Jerusalem, where he died,
and was buried and all Judah and Jerusalem mourned for Josiah," and
made great lamentation over him.</p>
               <p>But their great mourning was of a transient and evanescent
character, followed by no good results. Scarcely had he been laid in
his sepulchre, and the funeral obsequies ceased, before the reforms
which he bad instituted disappeared. The people relapsed into their
idolatry and wickedness, growing worse and worse. In the language of
the inspired writer, "They mocked the messengers of God, and despised
his words, and misused his prophets, until the wrath of the Lord arose
against his people till there was no remedy." In a little more than
twenty years, notwithstanding their great mourning for this good king,
Josiah, their sins had reached a point which could be endured no
longer. By one sweep of destruction their land was made desolate, and
the remnant of the people who escaped the sword were borne away into
captivity. Thus we see there was, indeed, great occasion for mourning,
and all Judah and Jerusalem did mourn, but their mourning was not such
as tended to any permanently good results.</p>
               <p>With a view, then, to a more abiding impression, and a more lasting
improvement of this afflictive dispensation of Providence, let us
proceed to notice the occasion which we as a nation this day have to
mourn, and some of the lessons which this bereavement should teach
us.</p>
               <p>1st. There is occasion for mourning because it is the executive
head of the nation-the representative of the law and of the authority
of the Government, who has fallen. The inquiry might arise, perhaps,
in the minds of some who have
<pb n="9" facs="relyea9.jpg"/>
not duly considered the subject, What was Abraham Lincoln more than
others, that a whole nation should mourn his death ? I answer, simply
in himself, in his own person as a citizen of our common country, he
was no more than thousands of others, but in his official capacity he
was more than others, and more than others to every inhabitant of the
land. Why is the American flag more to us than any other similar
product of the loom? Not because of the richness of its texture or the
costliness of the fabric of which it is made but because throughout
the world it is the chosen emblem of the nation's sovereignty and
independence, and at home it is the representative of the nation's
authority. To vindicate its honor, and to maintain its supremacy,
whether at home or abroad, every patriot is ready, if need to be, to
lay down his life and his fortune. So with him who for the time was
chosen to rule over us as our chief magistrate, he represented the
majesty of the law and the authority of the nation. In the providence
of God, and by the will of the nation, expressed in strict accordance
with all the forms of constitutional law, he was called out from the
multitude of his equals, constituted the head of the Government, and
clothed with the nation's authority and power. He was the embodiment
of the nation's majesty, for its government and for its
protection. Since human governments began on earth, if there ever was
a man lawfully and rightfully constituted a ruler over men, he was
rightfully and lawfully the chief ruler in this land. The highest were
justly amenable to his executive authority; the lowest had a claim
upon him for protection; and all had a right to demand of him that the
integrity of the Government and the authority of law be maintained. In
his official capacity, he stood in a different relation to every one
of us from that which he occupied before, and in a different
<pb n="10" facs="relyea10.jpg"/>
relation from that of any other man for the time. By the nation's act
he was taken out from the general relation of a simple citizen of a
common country and placed in a personal relation to every one of us as
our ruler. All the reverence and obedience which by laws, human and
divine, are due to human rulers any where, were due to him, not merely
as Abraham Lincoln but as the representative of the nation's
authority. All the loyalty and allegiance which are due to human
governments any where were due to this government, as embodied and
represented in his official person.</p>
               <p>Human government is not a thing in the abstract. If it exists as a
reality, it must exist as represented in living men, placed in a
position to wield its power and give it efficiency. The idea of law or
government unrepresented in men, not embodied in particular persons
charged with the exercise of the functions of such government, is a
mere theory. Allegiance or loyalty to a mere abstract theory is an
impossibility. If a man, therefore, will be loyal, he must be loyal to
the government as represented in the persons of those who are its
regularly constituted rulers. When, therefore, we did homage to him in
life, it was not merely to him as Abraham Lincoln, but to him as the
nation's representative. When we honor him in death, it is not as a
citizen of the State of Illinois, nor as a citizen of the United
States of America, but as the President of the United States-the man
who wielded the power, and embodied in his person the majesty and the
authority of a great and free people. There is not an inhabitant of
this broad land that ought not, nor is there a loyal and right-minded
one that does not, feel in his death an individual affliction, a
personal bereavement. God in his afflictive providence .has come near
to every one of us. He has laid his hand on a
<pb n="11" facs="relyea11.jpg"/>
point which touches each member of the nation, and we ought to feel
it. He has spoken in tones that should vibrate in every heart.</p>
               <p>In the eye of divine law there is something sacred in the person of
a ruler, not merely in the office but in the person of him to whom the
office inheres. He is the minister of God, ordained of him; a revenger
to execute wrath upon him that doth evil; and in the death of such an
one there is a marked and special providence to every individual of
the nation. Nor is the obligation to regard it to be evaded by the
consideration that the office and the prerogative is readily
transmitted to another equally competent and worthy. You might as well
say a man is excused from mourning on account of the death of his
wife, or is under no obligation to consider the chastisement of God
upon his house in such death, because it is possible for him to obtain
another wife equally good. What I insist upon is, that this is a
national bereavement. In permitting this blow to fall upon the head of
the nation, God has caused his judgment to rest upon the nation, and
upon. every individual of it. And it becomes all of us to mourn, and
to humble ourselves before him in penitent sorrow.</p>
               <p>I dwell upon this the more because in our heated party
controversies we have not always suitably regarded the sacredness of
the persons of those who actually rule over us, nor the divine
sanctions which to them personally commands our loyalty, reverence,
and obedience. This is one of our sins as a nation, and one of the
principal causes of all those calamities which have befallen us. It
is, I believe, one of the lessons which God, by his fierce judgments,
is burning into the nation's conscience. Happy will it be for us if we
so mourn as that the influence of this lesson shall be permanently
felt in the nation's life.</p>
               <pb n="12" facs="relyea12.jpg"/>
               <p>2d. In this afflictive dispensation there is great occasion for
mourning on account of the personal character of him who is thus
suddenly stricken from the head of our national affairs. When the head
of a family is removed by death, it is, and ought to be, regarded as a
divine chastisement to that family --An occasion for mourning,
repentance and humiliation before God; and it adds greatly to the
sense of bereavement if he was a wise, provident and good father. So
when the head of a nation is smitten down, it ought to be felt to be a
divine judgment, a national affliction. Especially is it an occasion
for mourning if he of whom the nation be bereaved be a man possessed
of those qualities of mind and heart which adapt him to the office,
and to the situation of the country. It is no part of my present
purpose to pronounce a penegyric on the character of him whom the
nation has just honored with such extraordinary and unexampled
obsequies, and such tokens of respect. Nothing in his life or history
is known to me which is not equally well known to every one of you. I
need not, therefore, recount his deeds. At this period of time, as we
look back upon his finished career, it will not be denied that he
possessed many of the qualifications of a wise and good ruler.</p>
               <p>His intellectual abilities, certainly, were not of that showy and
brilliant order which is apt to captivate the imaginations of men. He
was not learned, perhaps, in all the intricacies of diplomacy nor in
all the refinements of State craft. It will not be doubted, however,
but that he possessed in a good degree that wisdom which goes by the
more homely and less imposing name of good practical common sense,
which, accompanied as it was in him, with honesty of heart and
singleness of purpose, is certainly of infinitely more importance for
all the just ends
<pb n="13" facs="relyea13.jpg"/>
of government. If it is any proof of ability for a man to accomplish
what one-half of the civilized world for four years strenuously
affirmed never could be done-if this is any proof of ability, then
certainly he has given us some proof of ability. I would not detract
anything from the honor and the well-earned fame of those men who have
bravely fought on the field of battle, yet surely much of the credit
of calling forth and directing the resources of the nation in such
manner as to bring this war to a successful and triumphant conclusion
is due to him.</p>
               <p>I am not anxious to place myself in that class of persons who are
always wise after the event, and who are always ready to say, " I knew
it would be so." In those times of repeated defeat and disaster on the
field of battle, and of confusion and disaffection at home-in those
days of darkness and national despondency, I confess to have shared
the doubt whether he possessed the nerve and the mental stamina which
would enable him to master the situation and control the elements with
which he had to deal. He was yet, in this respect, an untried man, and
the question could only be determined by the event. But looking back
now upon the period of this great conflict, it must be confessed, that
surrounded with difficulties as great as those which ever beset the
ruler of any country, he has shown himself equal to the work which was
given him to do.</p>
               <p>I have no occasion now to discuss the principles and complicated
questions involved in the controversies of political parties which led
to the terrible conflict which has desolated so large a portion of our
land, and carried mourning and grief into so many homes. And I might
as well take this occasion to say, that in my ministry here I have
refrained from all political controversy. This I have done designedly
and intention-
<pb n="14" facs="relyea14.jpg"/>
ally, not from fear or favor, but from honest principle; from a regard
to the harmony, the peace, and the religious welfare of this society,
from a thorough conviction that it was altogether outside of my
province, and that no possible good could result from any other
course. And I feel bound frankly to tell you, that if any insist upon
having that kind of work done here, the sooner they get some one else
to do it the better it will be for you and for me. I have now
certainly no occasion to discuss the principles involved in the
controversies of the past. I think I can understand how men may differ
in regard to them and be honest, loyal, Christian men
notwithstanding.</p>
               <p>It will not be doubted, however, but that he whom now we mourn did
represent the opinions of the majority of the nation. If any think
that he was wrong in his opinions, still a man is not to be harshly
judged or hastily condemned for holding sentiments which are
entertained by a majority of the people of a great and free
Republic. The basis of all free government being that the will of the
majority shall rule, and he having been placed in a position to
represent and give efficiency to that will of the majority, it must be
confessed that up to the moment of his death he had borne the country
through its trials with as few mistakes as we had any right to expect
from any one whose wisdom was not more than human.</p>
               <p>But one who is called to rule over a nation, especially in such
times, has need of other qualifications than those of intellectual
ability, and he was not deficient in them. It was the qualities of the
heart rather than of the head which gave him that hold of the nation's
mind which it must be acknowledged he really did possess.</p>
               <p>In the judgment of mankind-in the sentiments of the civilized
world, he stands to-day acquitted of any of that sor-
<pb n="15" facs="relyea15.jpg"/>
did and personal ambition which seeks individual aggrandizement and
dominion at the expense of national liberties. However jealous men may
have been of that almost absolute power which the necessities of the
war placed into his hands we have all lived to feel that in the whole
exercise of it he was guided by an integrity of heart, an honesty of
purpose, and a ingleness of aim, which have placed him above
suspicion; and withal there was a frankness of manner which rendered
him incapable of duplicity--there was a genial temper and an
imperturbable good nature which never forsook him in the most
vexatious and trying circumstances; and a kindness of heart to which
the oppressed and the wronged never pleaded in vain. Amid all this sea
of human blood--amid all this turbulence of human passion, and all
this anguish, which has wrung the nation's heart, on his escutcheon
there is not left one stain of blood-thirstiness--there is not left
the taint of one deed of dishonor, of wanton cruelty, or of
revenge. As I look back upon the past, as I view that conflict of
opinions which, without an entire change in the moral character of the
nation, rendered a conflict of arms inevitable--as I trace the
progress of the fearful strife, fraught with so many dangers to the
country's future, affording just the opportunity which a Caesar or a
Napoleon would have coveted to build an empire on the ruins of the
Republic--as I consider all this, I cannot but find occasion for
devout gratitude to Almighty God that he gave us such a man for such a
time. Now when such a ruler is suddenly stricken down, every
right-minded person, whatever may be his political sentiments, cannot
but feel that it is a national calamity, a divine chastisement, an
occasion for sorrow, mourning, and repentance to a whole people. I
cannot resist the conviction that one of the lessons which God is
teaching us by all
<pb n="16" facs="relyea16.jpg"/>
these terrible dealings is, that we be less bitter in our party
spirit-that we be less harsh in our judgments of those who are called
to rule over us, and less severe in our condemnation of those who are
charged with such great and solemn responsibilities.</p>
               <p>3d. The manner of his death is no small addition to this national
bereavement, as a cause for mourning and sorrow. That such a man in
such a position should be stricken down by a foul blow of murder--that
he should fall by the cowardly stroke of an assassin--that our own
country should produce a company of hardened wretches, capable of so
infamous a conspiracy, cannot but fill the mind with horror as well as
grief. When we remember too that the blow was aimed not at him
personally, but at the nation's life, it not only aggravates the
crime, but overwhelms the heart with mingled anguish and detestation,
of the deed. It was not at ABRAHAM LINCOLN that the stroke was aimed,
but at the authority and life of the nation, as represented in him.</p>
               <p>There is a sense, in which his name will justly go down to
posterity as a martyr to his country. According to the whole theory
and foundation of all free government, the will of the majority,
constitutionally expressed, is the will of the nation for all
governmental purposes. No fact in human history is more clearly
established than this, that he represented the will of the majority of
this nation in its sovereign capacity. The will of the majority, in
strict conformity with the provisions of law, was not only expressed
in his first election to office, but the principles of his
administration and his acts were endorsed and ratified by an increased
majority in his re-election. If a majority is not to rule, then tell
me who is? He was called by the sovereign voice of the people to give
efficiency to the
<pb n="17" facs="relyea17.jpg"/>
nation's will in the exercise of its high prerogative of
government. He was honestly discharging that duty. Because he was
honestly and faithfully executing the nation's will he was stricken
down. The quarrel was not with him personally, but with the principle
which he represented and which the sovereign voice of the nation
decreed. The blow was aimed at the nation's life, and he, as its
representative, fell the martyred victim.</p>
               <p>In the absence of positive proof it is not for me to charge
complicity with the deed upon the leaders of the rebellion. Still it
is but in keeping with the attempt to destroy the unoffending
inhabitants of populous cities by fire and imported pestilence. It is
but in keeping with the cool, deliberate starving of thousands of
disarmed prisoners of war. It was the culminating point of a most
determined and relentless war upon the nation's authority. If it had
been within its power, the spirit which assassinated him would have
plunged the dagger into the nation's heart and poured out the nation's
lifeblood. That we should have fallen upon times when such a crime was
possible in this free nation--when such a war could be waged against a
nation's life, cannot but fill every loyal and well-disposed mind with
profound gloom and mourning.</p>
               <p>Surely one of the lessons which God is grinding into the nation's
conscience, is the solemn responsibility of the American people, to
the government which is over them, and the respect which is due to it
from them. The whole management of our political affairs has been made
so much a matter of trickery and trade; so much a matter of duplicity
and deception, that the people have lost in a great measure that
reverential awe which the forms and enactments of just government
should always inspire, and the salutary restraints which they
<pb n="18" facs="relyea18.jpg"/>
should always impose. The whole idea of government has been lowered
and degraded. The people have been educated to feel less respect for
the majesty of laws and rulers than our fathers were wont to feel.</p>
               <p>There is a solemn law of Jehovah, enacted in the interests of
Eternal righteousness, and for the welfare of every nation under
heaven, which reads on this wise: "Thou shalt not speak evil of the
ruler of thy people." Here is at least one law of God which few
American citizens comparatively seem to feel themselves bound to obey,
except when the ruler happens to be of their party.</p>
               <p>It is but a few years ago, and within the recollection of all, when
many of those who now claim to be, par excellence, the loyal of the
land, did not hesitate, in the pulpit and out of it, to preach
resistance to the law and defiance to the powers that be. If it is
treasonable and dangerous now, it was treasonable and dangerous
then. The truth is, that by our political huckstering, and by our
persistent habit of denouncing all our rulers indiscriminately as
tyrants and knaves, we have brought our government and our rulers into
contempt in the eyes of the people. And there is but one step between
this state of mind and overt acts of treason. It requires but a slight
occasion to call them forth. In this respect we have sown the wind and
most fearfully have we been reaping the whirlwind as the
consequence. There never was a truer word uttered by any ruler than
that which was spoken by our present chief magistrate, when he said,
"the American mind must be educated to feel that treason--resistance
to government--is the greatest of crimes." Want of respect for the
majesty of law and for the representatives of government, is one of
the great sins of this nation. I speak not of one party, but of all
parties. It is one of the great sins of this
<pb n="19" facs="relyea19.jpg"/>
nation--a sin which must sooner or later bring its own punishment with
it in the anarchy and confusion which it will inevitably work in the
bosom of society. My mind is deeply impressed with the conviction,
that one of the lessons which God, by his judgments, is grinding into
the conscience of this nation, is a solemn reverence for constituted
authority, as the representative and the delegated minister of his own
divine prerogative of executing justice on earth.</p>
               <p>4th. The event which calls us together to-day is an occasion for
sorrow and mourning in view of the present circumstances of the
country, and the difficulties which still lie in the way of the
nation's future. I take it as no small praise to him who has fallen,
and no slight proof of his honesty and integrity of heart, that the
very people who had just been in armed rebellion against the
Government, as they were compelled to yield to rightful authority,
felt that his death to them was a great calamity. The moment forcible
resistance ceased, and they were brought powerless before the
vindicated majesty of the law, there was no man living to whose tender
mercies they would sooner have committed what remained of life and
fortune than to his. And the foreign enemies of our country, who for
four years have been vilifying and denouncing him and his
administration, are now, in his uprightness of character, his kindness
of heart, his unswerving truthfulness, his unimpeachable sincerity,
and his conciliatory spirit, able to discern those qualifications
which would eminently have fitted him to bring about a reconciliation,
and a restoration of social order. The loss of such a man at such a
time cannot but be felt by every right-minded person to be a national
calamity. The permitting of him to be thus suddenly taken away is one
of those mysterious dispensations of Providence to which it becomes us
to bow in submission but with penitent and sorrowful hearts.</p>
               <pb n="20" facs="relyea20.jpg"/>
               <p>Then, too, in regard to that race who by the events of the war are
now released from bondage. Whatever view men may take of the complex
questions involved in the controversies which preceded the rebellion,
taking the situation as it now is, no man in his sober mind can think
that it would be either just to them or conducive to the future peace
and welfare of the country, that slavery should be reinstated. If it
is not to be reinstated, then here are four millions of poor, helpless
and dependent creatures, who have a claim upon us that the shield of
the nation and the protection of the law shall be thrown around
them. In the present state of affairs; the national government is
necessarily charged with this solemn responsibility, a responsibility
from which it cannot escape without proving recreant to all moral
obligations. To whom then, I ask, in all this land would that race, or
the nation at large, sooner have had that high and sacred trust
committed, than to him whose large heart and kind disposition ever
made him the friend of the oppressed.</p>
               <p>From all these considerations, the event which calls us together
to-day is an occasion for sorrow and mourning to the nation. Humanly
speaking, the only thought which can reconcile us to it is, that in
the eye of Infinite Wisdom, perhaps, the demands of justice and the
future welfare of the Republic requires a stern work of retribution to
be performed upon the guilty leaders of the rebellion, for which, by
his conciliatory spirit, by his generous heart, and by his sympathetic
nature, he was unfitted.</p>
               <p>At least God is teaching us to cease to put our trust in man, but
to commit all our interests, and the nation's destiny, into the hands
of that just and merciful Being who ordains his own counsels, and who
executes by whatever agencies it pleases him, his own eternal
purposes.</p>
            </div2>
         </div1>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>