<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader><fileDesc>
         <titleStmt n="A Discourse on the Death of Abraham Lincoln">
            <title>A Discourse on the Death of Abraham Lincoln</title>
            <author>Robbins, Frank L.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Compiled and edited by</resp>
               <name>Beck
Center</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent/>
         <publicationStmt><publisher>Lewis H. Beck Center</publisher><pubPlace>Emory University</pubPlace><address>
               <addrLine>Atlanta,
Georgia</addrLine>
            </address><availability>
               <p>1996 Emory
University. Permission is  granted to download, transmit, or otherwise
reproduce,  distribute or display the contributions to the work
claimed by Emory University for non-profit educational  purposes,
provided this header is included in its entirety.   For inquiries
about commercial uses, contact the Director,  Pitts Theology Library,
Emory University, Atlanta, Georgia 30322</p>
            </availability><date>1999</date></publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Lincoln
Sermons Project</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Robbins,
Frank L. A Discourse on the Death of Abraham Lincoln, Delivered in the
Greenhill Presbyterian Church, on Sunday Evening, April 23, 1865.
Philadelphia: Henry B. Ashmead, Book and Job Printer, Nos. 1102 and
1104 Sansom Street.  1865. </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc><encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This text derives from the Special
Collections  of Pitts Theology Library, Emory University, and is
produced in  collaboration with the Lewis H. Beck Center a, the Emory
Preservation Office, and Pitts Theology Library.</p>
            <p>TRANSCRIBER: Lewis H. Beck Center and Emory University 
Preservation Office.</p>
            <p>PRODUCER:  BookLab, Inc., 1606 Headway Circle, 
Suite 100, Austin, TX 78754</p>
            <p>CAPTURE DEVICE: XEROX DocuImage 620S flatbed scanner</p>
            <p>CAPTURE DETAILS: Scanner software: XEROX ScanTool 
version 4.2.3; no gamma correction; images are all bitonal.</p>
            <p>CHANGE HISTORY: Using the Adobe Photoshop Batch Processor, 
we interpolated  the original TIFF files to 8-bit grays, 
and altered the resolution to 144 dpi, producing screen 
images twice the original size.  We then saved them in 
JPEG format.  We produced GIF thumbnails from the JPEG files.</p>
            <p>RESOLUTION: 600 ppi</p>
            <p>COMPRESSION: Resolution 144 per inch with Constrain 
Properties to 72 per inch.</p>
            <p>SOURCE: Original documents.</p>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc><revisionDesc><change><name>Stewart Varner</name> transformed this document from p4 to p5 on <date when="2010-03-22">March 22, 2010</date></change><change xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><date>1999</date><label>Staff</label><name>Scott Ellis</name>SGML tags inserted in compliance
with TEI guidelines using TEILITE</change></revisionDesc></teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div1 xml:id="robbins.001" n="A Discourse on the Death of Abraham Lincoln" type="text">
            <head> 
               <bibl> 
                  <title>A Discourse on
the Death of Abraham Lincoln</title> 
                  <date>April 23, 1865</date>
                  <pubPlace>Greenhill Presbyterian Church</pubPlace> 
                  <author>Robbins,
Frank L.</author> 
                  
                     <pubPlace>Philadelphia</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Henry B. Ashmead, Book and Job Printer</publisher>
                     <date>1865</date>
                   
               <idno type="ark">http://pid.emory.edu/ark:/25593/15qx8</idno></bibl> 
            </head>
            <pb facs="robbins1.jpg"/>
            <p>A DISCOURSE</p>
            <p>ON THE</p>
            <p>DEATH OF ABRAHAM LINCOLN,</p>
            <p>DELIVERED IN THE</p>
            <p>Greenhill Presbyterian Church,</p>
            <p>ON SUNDAY EVENING, APRIL 23, 1865.</p>
            <p>BY THE REV. FRANK L. ROBBINS, PASTOR OF THE CHURCH.</p>
            <p>PHILADELPHIA:</p>
            <p>HENRY B. ASHMEAD, BOOK AND JOB PRINTER, Nos. 1102 AND
1104 SANSOM STREET.</p>
            <p>1865.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="robbins2.jpg"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="robbins3.jpg"/>
            <p>PUBLISHED BY REQUEST OF THE CONGREGATION, FOR PRIVATE
DISTRIBUTION</p>
            <pb n="4"/>
<!-- blank page -->
<!--            <p>
               <figure entity="robbins4">
                  <figDesc>4th page of
Frank L. Robbins' A Discourse on the Death of Abraham
Lincoln.</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p> -->
            <pb n="5" facs="robbins5.jpg"/>
            <div2 xml:id="robbins.002" n="A DISCOURSE" type="sermon">
               <head>A DISCOURSE</head>
               <p>WHAT a contrast! How strange and startling the vicissitudes of
human life!</p>
               <p>A few weeks since, President Lincoln, for the second time, stood on
the steps of the Capitol at Washington, to be re-invested with power
and dominion over this vast empire.</p>
               <p>He had been tried and was found faithful. He had been re-elected by
overwhelming majorities, and on the fourth of March last he received
and took the oath of office, amidst the homage of millions of
rejoicing citizens. Under the brightest auspices he entered upon his
second term of office. The clouds of war were rolling away. The golden
rays of the sun of peace were beginning to be seen and felt. Men
comforted and congratulated themselves, and each other, saying, The
era of wild war is passing; the reign of peace and prosperity is at
hand. Everywhere, victories upon victories were being piled up, and
rebellion was going down before the resistless march of our armies.</p>
               <pb n="6" facs="robbins6.jpg"/>
               <p>Soon came the news, stirring in its very depths the the mighty
heart of the nation, and causing the Republic to rock, and heave, and
sway, by reason of its profound emotions of joy and gratitude--"
Richmond is taken!" Babylon is fallen, is fallen, that great city, for
the hour of her judgment is come, and her princes and they who were
made rich by reason of their merchandise of "slaves and souls of men,"
stand afar off weeping and wailing for fear of her torment, saying,
Alas! alas that strong city, for in one hour is she deserted and made
desolate!</p>
               <p>Then came the news--swift succeeding--"Lee has surrendered!"--the
power that so long defied the Union armies is shivered at
last-rebellion is crushed--the Union is saved--authority and law,
justice and freedom are triumphant!</p>
               <p>We were wild with excitement--delirious with joy. Probably the sun
never shone upon a more intensely jubilant, self-confident people. <hi rend="italic">Now</hi>, we said, is it proven that our Government will
stand like the everlasting mountains. <hi rend="italic">Now</hi>, is it
demonstrated that our Republic, though rocked on the earthquake of
internal treason, or assailed by external combinations of hostile
power, cannot be subverted or overthrown, for the might of Omnipotence
is in the just principles upon which it is based. Now, let Despotism
tremble on its iron throne, for there is contagion in the example of
Freedom, contending for existence, offering its best blood in
sacrifice, and at
<pb n="7" facs="robbins7.jpg"/>
length emerging from the long and bloody struggle, triumphant over the
old spirit of caste, the spirit of slavery, fell and fiendish, the
spirit of oppression and wrong, and rising in a cloudless sky,
glorious and resistless as the sun in its path of fiery splendor.</p>
               <p>But alas, alas! while these grand anticipations for the future of
our Republic remain to us--while, indeed, under that mysterious
Providence which rules our human affairs, the hearts of millions have
been drawn together, and the nation has been made mightier in its
power to hate the spirit of treason, and to hate <hi rend="italic">Slavery</hi>, its accursed mother; while millions have
been led to swear by the Eternal, never to consent to any
re-adjustment until every vestige of this inhumanity is swept away
forever, under the influence of this unutterable sorrow-how changed is
the mood and the posture of this nation! Let there be no more ringing
of bells--no processions and illuminations in honor of victories--no
mirth and feasting, and revelry and hilarity. All over the land for
these past eight days there has rested the cloud of gloom, and the
thick clouds of the nation's infinite grief, and our thrilling wail of
sorrow has been increasingly ascending to Him--God over all immortal,
eternal, invisible, and blessed forever--"in whose hands our breath
is, and whose are all our ways."</p>
               <p>"Our feasts have been turned into mourning, and all our songs into
lamentation; sackcloth was brought upon all loins and baldness upon
every head; our sun has gone
<pb n="8" facs="robbins8.jpg"/>
down at noon; we are made to mourn as for an only son, and the end
thereof as a bitter day."</p>
               <p>Humanity has lost a lover. Freedom has lost a mighty champion. The
poor slave has lost his true friend and deliverer-but, thank God, not
his deliverance. ABRAHAM LINCOLN did his work well, and when he gave
to the wings of the wind the immortal proclamation of emancipation, he
spake words which can never be recalled, and proclaimed a fiat of
destiny which can never be annulled; he sent forth an influence which
shall work on and on through the agencies of war and of statesmanship,
nor cease, until not a slave in all our vast domain can be found.</p>
               <p>Who, now that America's pure patriot and just ruler has hallowed
the act of emancipation by his most precious blood, securing thus the
permanence of his work, and the immortality of his fame, will dare to
say aught in opposition to emancipation, or in extenuation of slavery
and treason--one and the same--which murdered him? And not alone in
this land and among contiguous peoples, will the influence of this
calamity be felt, but in far off lands, wherever men are oppressed and
sigh for freedom; wherever men work or wait in hope, looking for a
political regeneration; wherever men--and there be many such among the
nations of the old Continent  --have been anxiously looking upon our
struggle and have felt for us true sympathy; there will be felt
unfeigned emotions of sorrow, and inexpressible ab-
<pb n="9" facs="robbins9.jpg"/>
horrence of the crime which has smitten down the man the
philanthropist, the emancipationist, the patriot, the incorruptible
ruler, whom they with us had learned to love and reverence as the man
raised up by God to achieve the redemption of the liberties of
mankind.</p>
               <p>To-day, this night, we have all that remains of our murdered
President among us, and it seems befitting to consecrate this evening
hour to meditation upon the character and virtues and services of the
man gone from us to God, and his reward. Indeed, until the last
funeral rites have been performed, and these remains are entombed in
the church-yard at Springfield, there to await the resurrection
morning, other feelings and other thoughts will be excluded from the
heart of this great nation, and the people will continue to give
themselves up to tears and suffocating emotions.</p>
               <p>Perhaps I can say nothing that has not already been well said; but
it is a relief to our oppressed and wounded feelings to meet together
and tell each other how much we loved ABRAHAM LINCOLN; just as
affectionate children incline to come together and talk over the
goodness and virtues of a beloved father, after his decease, speaking
with loving charity of his traits, and recalling with fondness remote
and almost forgotten, or of recent and familiar incidents in his
life.</p>
               <p>It is remarkable to notice how <hi rend="italic">personal</hi> is the
feeling we have, and how grievously the late President is mourned, as
if indeed he were the real father of all the
<pb n="10" facs="robbins10.jpg"/>
people. Never was a man carried to his grave amid such universal and
profound grief. Why is this so? Is it because the best and most
capacious intellect has passed away? O no! And yet Mr. LINCOLN was a
man of marked intellectual traits and vigor; not narrow, certainly, if
not capacious and colossal in power of brain. Is it because we fear a
revolution? In other countries the assassination of the monarch would
be the signal for a revolution. But our system of government is such,
that upon the removal of the Chief Magistrate there is no revolution,
no friction, no jar; the scheme of government and the order of society
move on, undisturbed.</p>
               <p>Indeed, our Government never was so firm, our institutions never
were so rooted and grounded in the hearts of the people as since the
murder of Mr. Lincoln; for under the good providence of God, it seems
that this last baptism of blood and tears is destined to inspire the
hearts and nerve the arms of our citizens, and concentrate and
consolidate and intensify their love and devotion for the
republic. Indeed, the blood of ABRAHAM LINCOLN seems destined to be
the cement which is to fasten in its place the keystone of the arch of
the restored, and henceforth indissoluble Union.</p>
               <p>Why, then, was this man so tenderly loved? and why is there such
touching, pathetic, universal grief over his death?</p>
               <p>The people loved him because he was a man of blame
<pb n="11" facs="robbins11.jpg"/>
less life; of an elevated, transparent, firm character, and of an
affectionate, benign disposition. I will not weaken commendation by
giving utterance to indiscriminate praise of Mr. LINCOLN. If he was
the perfect and matchless man he is described to be in many of the
eulogiums which have been pronounced since his death; if he was so
immeasurably removed in high superiority, and by transcendent
abilities above other men, the nation might have been proud of him,
but never would common men--the millions--have felt that familiarity
of friendship which was so generally felt, or loved him with so filial
a love as they did.</p>
               <p>Mr. LINCOLN was not highly prominent for intellectual abilities. He
had not the grand imperial mind of a Webster, nor the subtle,
metaphysical, intense intellect of a Calhoun, nor the splendid and
ready powers and eloquence of a Fox or a Chatham; and yet his
intellectual abilities were adequate to every occasion; indeed, they
were such as seem to have admirably fitted him for the work which he
has so ably accomplished.</p>
               <p>Where others with higher range and more profound faculties might
have failed, doubtless would have failed, he has succeeded, guided by
his matchless sagacity, and prudence, and common sense, and native
shrewdness.</p>
               <p>His thoughts were his own; they were fresh and original, and were
clothed with a quaintness, a directness, a simplicity of style
peculiar to himself.</p>
               <p>The American mind is quick, rapid, eager, impatient of
<pb n="12" facs="robbins12.jpg"/>
slow and elaborate methods and processes; hence whatever emanated from
Mr. Lincoln's lips or pen was sure to engross general attention, for
it went directly to the root of the matter. Everybody understood him;
and often the most agreeable surprise has been expressed, when others
have darkened "counsel by words without knowledge," as a subject has
opened, and a practical solution of a perplexing question has been
suggested in a few paragraphs put in his clear, concise, forcible
manner.</p>
               <p>But Mr. LINCOLN'S greatness was not the greatness of intellect, nor
of genius, nor of eloquence, nor of place and power. Like the
illustrious Washington, he had no pre-eminent quality. <hi rend="italic">Like Washington, he was great by reason of the moral
heroism of his transcendent character</hi>.</p>
               <p>His affections were pure and ardent, and in his heart there was no
guile. His temperament was emotional; his disposition was sweet and
gentle as a woman's; his sensibilities were quick and acute; his
impulses were warm and generous. He understood and felt in his in most
soul the worth of human nature, and the inalienable rights of man. He
felt for the poor and the oppressed, and his ear was ever open to the
voice of their pleadings. <hi rend="italic">As the great Emancipator of
a down-trodden race, he will go into history, and his name will be
cherished and his memory fragrant through the revolving
centuries</hi>. For these qualities men loved him. They were proud
that he was eminently a man of the people, and sprung from them. 
<pb n="13" facs="robbins13.jpg"/>
He knew them and they knew him. They read his character; they knew his
heart; they understood him.</p>
               <p>It may be that his work was done. Perhaps his death was not
untimely. Possibly, had he survived, his disposition would have
inclined him to a too lenient policy toward the leaders of this
atrocious rebellion. It remains to be seen what their course will
be. I trust and pray God that their hearts may be touched by the
influence of this last baptism of blood and sorrow, and that with deep
penitence they will throw themselves upon the clemency of the
Government.</p>
               <p>But if it shall be otherwise--if they stubbornly, sullenly persist
in cherishing and manifesting the spirit of treason, making their
motto to read, "Bound, but not broken, then let the severities of
immutable justice be meted out to them: let them die the death. So let
it be, and may God have mercy upon their guilty souls.</p>
               <p>Ah! my friends, these are solemn words. But the unspeakably vast
interests of this Republic and of mankind may summon this Government
to their fulfillment. It may be that a man of sterner mood than the
late President is required in the high p1ace which has been so ably
filled for over four years.</p>
               <p>In any event the Republic will survive, and the new President will
receive the prayers and sympathies and support of the people, while
they will not forget to bow down and thank God for the faithful
services, the wisdom, the unostentatious goodness, and the Christian
heroism of ABRAHAM LINCOLN.</p>
               <pb n="14" facs="robbins14.jpg"/>
               <p>The deceased President, let me further add, was immeasurably above
the use of those methods and arts to which men of inferior minds
resort, to advertise themselves. He appeared to be all unconscious of
himself. He never aimed <hi rend="italic">to seem</hi> to be, <hi rend="italic">but to be</hi> what he seemed. From centre to
circumference his character was honest, luminous, truthful. He spake
just what he believed, and believed just what he spake.</p>
               <p>Was he a Christian man? I think he was. He said, "I do love Jesus."
I believe what he said. We have it on unquestioned authority, that the
first hour of the morning he was accustomed to devote to prayer and
the reading of his Bible. I have myself been profoundly impressed,
hearing him give utterances to the most devout sentiments in
connection with the issue of this war, that he was a man of prayer and
religious faith.</p>
               <p>All his State papers breathed the very spirit of religious
reverence and trust, especially the later ones. After he had
promulgated the proclamation of emancipation, he said to an eminent
clergyman of New York, "I did not think the people had been educated
up to it; yet I thought it was <hi rend="italic">right</hi> to issue it,
and I did it." Here is an instance of his reliance on God, indicating
the spirit of true religion. His moral courage was such as seldom
appears save in conjunction with deep religious faith, and the
consciousness of soul integrity. From the commencement to the close of
his official career the ma-
<pb n="15" facs="robbins15.jpg"/>
lignant spirit of treason sought his life, and he knew it;
nevertheless he marched right forward in the path of duty, not
counting his life dear unto himself. He had the faith in God, the
reverent spirit, the firmness and consistency of moral principle, the
purity of heart and character, the sweet and loving disposition, the
Christ-like quality of forbearance toward his enemies, which, in our
view, are only to be found in the character of a man of God; and
perhaps there is no better thing I can wish for each of my audience
than that when you come to stand before God's judgment, it may be as
well with you as it is with him, and that your record may be as clean,
and your destiny as high for eternity as was his.</p>
               <p>In deliberation Mr. LINCOLN was not hasty, nor premature; but when
once he had taken his stand, he was the last man to swerve from the
course marked out for himself.</p>
               <p>Tender and benignant as was his disposition, his conduct was marked
by unwavering fidelity to truth, justice, and right. If he deliberated
well, and looked with clear-eyed sagacity down to the bottom before he
ventured, there was no after hesitation, no quibbling, no fear of
consequences. He paid no lip service, no half allegiance. What he
believed he believed with all his heart, and what he did he did from
conscientiousness. He was thus ever true to principle, and ever true
to himself, and I am constrained to believe, ever strove to realize in
his conduct and character, and official acts,
<pb n="16" facs="robbins16.jpg"/>
religious rectitude; and to exhibit, in conjunction with his living,
gushing sympathy for men, inflexible devotion to truth, justice, and
right.</p>
               <p>Such were the character and virtues and services of ABRAHAM
LINCOLN.</p>
               <p>In after times the American people will cherish his memory as a
precious legacy, nor will they suffer any detraction from the merit of
his character or his services. His name and fame will be identified
with all that is great and glorious in the cause and principles for
which the people have made such immense sacrifices in this great
struggle, and to which he fell a martyr. May his illumined spirit find
eternal repose above the skies!</p>
               <p>My friends, I have ceased to think and feel as I did. At first I
was inexpressibly shocked, appalled, depressed. I said, is this so? Is
the Chief Magistrate of this nation murdered? They have been trying
for four years to do the deed. Is it accomplished at last? Is he dead?
Are those dreamy eyes closed in death? Has that warm heart, that
genial smile, that honest brain passed away forever?</p>
               <p>I could not think at first of anything but the deed. In vain I
strove, as we all did, for words to express my abhorrence of it. I
could only think of ABRAHAM LINCOLN as a murdered man. But now I think
of the glorious spirit--of the immortal part--which malignity and
murder could not touch,--as garnered and glorious, and eternally safe
with God. He rises now before me in
<pb n="17" facs="robbins17.jpg"/>
vision, bright and beautiful as the star of the morning. Immortality
has now put its impress upon his goodness and worth. My faith
contemplates now only the image from which death can efface nothing
more. Henceforth I shall think of him as numbered with the immortals,
sharing their communion and their joys.</p>
               <p>And now what shall we say of the spirit which slew him? He was no
tyrant. He did no wrong for which he was worthy of death. In his great
heart there was pity even for traitors. He was their best friend;
and</p>
               <lg type="stanza">
                  <l>"He hath borne his faculties so meek, hath been</l>
                  <l>So
clear in his great office, that his virtues</l>
                  <l>Will plead like
angels, trumpet-tongued, against</l>
                  <l>The deep damnation of his
taking off."</l>
               </lg>
               <p>As for the spirit which slew him, let us hate it, and pray God for
more strength and more power and more intensity and more capacity to
hate it. I tell you, my friends, it is the very spirit of hell. It is
the very spirit that long defeated public justice, debauched the
conscience, ruled in the halls of legislation, and sat on the bench of
the highest court in this land, perverting justice and judgment. It is
the very spirit which organized this rebellion, and which has
suggested and sanctioned its atrocious wrongs. It is the dark spirit,
invested with the guilt of immeasurable crimes, the spirit of
Slavery. May, then, this spirit be cast down to everlasting
death. Standing together, heart speaking to heart, hand grasping hand,
let us--and with us may the loyal millions-
<pb n="18" facs="robbins18.jpg"/>
swear to avenge the martyrdom of ABRAHAM LINCOLN, by consenting to no
terms of pacification, until the work, so gloriously begun and carried
forward by him, is completed; until treason is forever silenced, and
slavery is forever dead, and the Republic, regenerated and redeemed,
emerges from its long eclipse of darkness, "fair as the sun, clear as
the moon, and terrible as an army with banners."</p>
               <p>As for the miscreant that did the deed of murder, the brand of
Cain's infamy is upon his brow--the eye of Omniscience is upon him. He
may possibly elude detection, and baffle man's justice,--which is
extremely doubtful--but God's vengeance will follow him wherever over
the earth be wanders. There is no place of hiding, no nook or corner
or crevice in the universe where he can escape the presence of
Omnipotent Justice. "There is no darkness, neither shadow of death,
where he may hide himself." FOR EVER has he doomed himself to endure
the burning consciousness that he is a murderer. Ten thousand years
hence must he feel and know himself to be a guilty spirit the murderer
of the innocent and just man.</p>
               <p>What a doom and destiny is his! In my soul I pity this man of
blood, and I pray God that he may be overtaken by a sense of his
guilt, surrender himself to justice, and apply to the infinite Saviour
for pardon, ere his soul pass into eternity.</p>
               <p>Meantime the Republic lives, and will live forever. The
assassinating spirit that slew the man who, under God,
<pb n="19" facs="robbins19.jpg"/>
presided over the destinies of the nation, was, and is, powerless to
harm the life of the nation.</p>
               <p>So far from producing terror; so far from causing divided counsels
or inaugurating a reign of anarchy; the deed of blood and murder has
welded the people into an inflexible purpose, and into a tremendous
power, bent upon accomplishing retributive justice. It has inclined
the nation to think and determine, less upon clemency and more upon
justice. There will be no concessions now to the master spirits of
rebellion. They have made their self-destruction sure.</p>
               <p>Meanwhile this Republic lives, and will live forever. Our grand
chief is slain, but our grand cause is triumphant. Men may die, but
principles are immortal. Though treason had struck down every member
of the cabinet, not a stone would have been misplaced or loosened in
the arch of our nationality.</p>
               <p>Slavery has staked all and lost.</p>
               <p>Liberty has won for itself an immortal existence. Now let
Republicanism, purer, better, stronger, holier, through sacrifices and
martyrdoms, lift up her head among the family of nations.</p>
               <p>Though our most eminent statesmen pass hence, and the delegated
head of the Government meet with sudden and violent death, the
Government itself cannot be overthrown; for the foundations upon which
it stands are Liberty, Justice, and Equality; and never were the
friends of these so numerous, so determined, so devoted as now.</p>
               <pb n="20" facs="robbins20.jpg"/>
               <p>Thank God, there is no hatred malignant enough, and no power strong
enough to quench the nation's life, or arrest its advancing
destiny. Now let the influence of Freedom go forth and encompass the
earth. Now let the star of our destiny rise on the world's horizon,
bright and beautiful, climbing higher and higher, until it attracts
the admiring gaze of distant nations, and becomes the world's star of
hope. May God speed the day; and to Him be all the praise. Amen and
amen!</p>
               <p>And now shall I err, my friends, if I summon you--in view of all
that God is doing for us--in his most holy name, to put away sin; to
put your trust in the infinite Redeemer and devote your lives to his
service; to do justice, walk in the light, and live for immortality?
God has given us a fair land, and a noble Government. His hand is
holding us up in this great struggle, and crowning our cause with
victory. Here then and now, let us gratefully consecrate ourselves to
his service. May none of us hesitate or falter in our allegiance to
Heaven. May every heart throb with gratitude for Divine blessings. May
every life be holy, and every lover of his country be a lover of God
and a follower of Jesus. Here and now, let us offer prayers for our
country, invoking the blessing of our covenant-keeping God, with whom
are the hidings of power, and the consolations of grace.</p>
               <p>May our country be Immanuel's possession,--a delightsome land,
exalted, as in privileges so in right-
<pb n="21" facs="robbins21.jpg"/>
eousness. May our rulers be men of God, and our people be virtuous and
good. God bless and save the Republic!</p>
            </div2>
         </div1>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>