<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader><fileDesc>
         <titleStmt n="A Discourse Occasioned by the Death of Abraham Lincoln">
            <title>A Discourse Occasioned by the Death of Abraham Lincoln</title>
            <author>Stone, Andrew L.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Compiled and edited by</resp>
               <name>Beck Center</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent/>
         <publicationStmt><publisher>Lewis H. Beck Center</publisher><pubPlace>Emory University</pubPlace><address>
               <addrLine>Atlanta,
Georgia</addrLine>
            </address><availability>
               <p>1996 Emory
University. Permission is  granted to download, transmit, or otherwise
reproduce,  distribute or display the contributions to the work
claimed by Emory University for non-profit educational  purposes,
provided this header is included in its entirety.   For inquiries
about commercial uses, contact the Director,  Pitts Theology Library,
Emory University, Atlanta, Georgia 30322</p>
            </availability><date>1999</date></publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Lincoln
Sermons Project</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Stone, Andrew
L. A Discourse Occasioned by the Death of Abraham Lincoln, President
of the United States of America, Who as Assassinated in Washington,
Friday, April 14th, 1865.  Preached in the Park Street Church, Boston,
on the Next Lord's Day.  300 Copies Printed for J. K. Wiggin, Boston:
1865.</bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc><encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This text derives from the Special Collections  of
Pitts Theology Library, Emory University, and is produced in
collaboration with the Lewis H. Beck Center a, the Emory  Preservation
Office, and Pitts Theology Library.</p>
            <p>TRANSCRIBER: Lewis H. Beck Center and Emory University 
Preservation Office.</p>
            <p>PRODUCER:  BookLab, Inc., 1606 Headway Circle, 
Suite 100, Austin, TX 78754</p>
            <p>CAPTURE DEVICE: XEROX DocuImage 620S flatbed scanner</p>
            <p>CAPTURE DETAILS: Scanner software: XEROX ScanTool 
version 4.2.3; no gamma correction; images are all bitonal.</p>
            <p>CHANGE HISTORY: Using the Adobe Photoshop Batch Processor, 
we interpolated  the original TIFF files to 8-bit grays, 
and altered the resolution to 144 dpi, producing screen 
images twice the original size.  We then saved them in 
JPEG format.  We produced GIF thumbnails from the JPEG files.</p>
            <p>RESOLUTION: 600 ppi</p>
            <p>COMPRESSION: Resolution 144 per inch with Constrain 
Properties to 72 per inch.</p>
            <p>SOURCE: Original documents.</p>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc><revisionDesc><change><name>Stewart Varner</name> transformed this document from p4 to p5 on <date when="2010-03-22">March 22, 2010</date></change><change xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><date>1999</date><label>Staff</label><name>Scott
Ellis</name>SGML tags inserted in
compliance with TEI guidelines using TEILITE</change></revisionDesc></teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div1 xml:id="stone.001" n="A Discourse Occasioned by the Death of Abraham Lincoln" type="text">
            <head>
               <bibl> 
                  <title>A Discourse Occasioned by the Death of Abraham
Lincoln</title> 
                  <date>[N/A]</date> 
                  <pubPlace>Park Street Church,
Boston</pubPlace> 
                  <author>Stone, Andrew L.</author> 
                  
                     <pubPlace>Boston</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>J. K. Wiggin</publisher>
                     <date>1865</date>
                   
               <idno type="ark">http://pid.emory.edu/ark:/25593/15r5b</idno></bibl> 
            </head>
            <p>
               <figure><graphic url=""/>
                  <figDesc>1st page of Andrew L. Stone's A
Discourse Occasioned by the Death of Abraham
Lincoln.</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <p>A DISCOURSE</p>
            <p>OCCASIONED BY THE DEATH OF</p>
            <p>Abraham Lincoln,</p>
            <p>PRESIDENT OF THE</p>
            <p>UNITED STATES OF AMERICA,</p>
            <p>WHO WAS ASSASSINATED IN WASHINGTON,</p>
            <p>FRIDAY, APRIL 14TH, 1865.</p>
            <p>Preached in the Park Street Church, Boston,</p>
            <p>ON THE NEXT LORD'S DAY,</p>
            <p>BY ANDREW L. STONE, D.D.</p>
            <p>300 COPIES PRINTED FOR</p>
            <p>F. K. WIGGIN, BOSTON:</p>
            <p>1865.</p>
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>
               <figure><graphic url=""/>
                  <figDesc>2nd page of
Andrew L. Stone's A Discourse Occasioned by the Death of Abraham
Lincoln.</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>
               <figure><graphic url=""/>
                  <figDesc>3rd page of Andrew L. Stone's A Discourse Occasioned by the Death of Abraham Lincoln.</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>

            <div2 xml:id="stone.002" n="[Discourse]" type="sermon">
               <head>[Discourse]</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <p>LAMENTATIONS V: 15,16.</p>
                  <p>THE JOY OF OUR HEART IS CEASED; OUR DANCE IS TURNED INTO
MOURNING.</p>
                  <p>THE CROWN IS FALLEN FROM OUR HEAD.</p>
               </epigraph>
               <p>WHEN, three days ago, the morning of the day appointed for fasting,
humiliation, and prayer, rose upon a people jubilant with the joy of
victory, many felt that both the designation of the day and the
accustomed manner of its observance should be changed; that, instead
of fasting, there should be feasting, instead of humiliation and
supplication, thanksgiving and praise.</p>
               <p>But some of us remembered, and we called it to mind, that the chief
intent of the day, as our fathers kept it, was prospective. It did not
look backward with penitential review, so much as it looked forward
with forecasting deprecation to possible evils. The day was appointed
in the spring season, when the great venture of the harvest was at
hazard, and all the uncertainties of elemental blight and blessing
hung poised in the scales of Providence. If there were confession,
forsaking of sin,--as was always true,--it was as a
<pb n="4"/>
                  <figure><graphic url=""/>
                     <figDesc>4th page of Andrew
L. Stone's A Discourse Occasioned by the Death of Abraham
Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
preparation of heart for availing prayer, that "the early and the
latter rain" might fall, each in its time; the hand of the reaper bind
and gather its sheaves with joy, and the autumn granaries be
full. Then should follow the commemorative festival, looking to the
past, and celebrating the throned goodness that had provided abundance
for the wants of man and beast. It was this ideal of the day recently
observed, that held so many Christian pulpits and Christian people so
closely to its first design.</p>
               <p>We ought to have felt, more deeply than we did, that the future
might bring up, into that bright morning sky, dark clouds big with
storm and tempest, and have stretched our hands up with a mightier
reach of supplication toward the sovereign hand holding the balances
weighted with coming events.</p>
               <p>The thought was on our hearts and on our lips that there might be
perils brooding for our country, shadows gathering over the path of
its future. But who could have looked forward to so dark a shadow as
this which has fallen! who could have painted this sable cloud on that
smiling sky!</p>
               <p>There was talk, with some, of reversing our associations with this
month of the Spring, and our religious observances wedded to its
annual return, and making it henceforth our month of most tuneful
rejoicing,--the coronal of the year. But not now! We cannot change
thee, oh, weeping April! oh, month of tears! Pour down all thy warm
showers : from our eyes the rain falls faster yet! Evermore, from
henceforth, at thy return, thou and the sorrowing nation shall weep
together.</p>
               <pb n="5"/>
               <p>
                  <figure><graphic url=""/>
                     <figDesc>5th page of
Andrew L. Stone's A Discourse Occasioned by the Death of Abraham
Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <p>How sudden the changes of the April sky,--sunshine! shower! And
beneath, on our faces and in our hearts, how faithfully copied! What
glad days they were that followed those two memorable sabbaths,
freighted with such a gospel of victory and peace! What a deep and
tender joy rested upon all our homes and temples! Richmond was
taken. The sword of Lee was broken. Loyal and honest hands were on
their way to run up the old flag above the battered and ruined walls
of Sumter. Every eye was sunny with gratulant greetings to every
other. How sudden the darkness! Night comes in nature with twilight
herald running before. Our night came without precursor, --"in a
moment, in the twinkling of an eye," as though noon and midnight had
met.</p>
               <p>There were beds the night before last, I suppose, restless with
dreams; but with all the sleepers there was no dream so black as that
awful fact that went pulsing and tolling through the night, and lies
now like an incubus which memory cannot chase away, upon the
shuddering national heart.</p>
               <p>We have lost great and good men before. They have been taken from
the high places of honor and of trust with their robes of office
on. They have been taken from the scenes of retirement whither a
nation's homage followed them, bearing in its offerings before their
feet. Washington died leaving that one peerless title behind
him,--"The Father of his Country." Harrison and Taylor died, sinking
wearily down from that chair toward whose great vacancy our dim eyes
look to-day. Our two great Massachusetts statesmen and orators passed
<pb n="6"/>
                  <figure><graphic url=""/>
                     <figDesc>6th page of Andrew
L. Stone's A Discourse Occasioned by the Death of Abraham
Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
away leaving us to feel that the world was less rich and grand since
they were gone. But these were all led gently from our presence, by a
messenger hand, whose power and whose right none of us could
question. The Divine Will, by itself, and alone, made up and executed
the summons.</p>
               <p>But our dear President was snatched from us by the hand of
violence. This was the bitter element in the cup. He might have
lived. He was not sick. He was not old.  "His eye was not dim, nor his
natural force abated. "All wantonly and wickedly his precious blood
was shed; unchilled by age, untainted with disease. He had reached no
natural bound of life. It was not a treasure expended, but stolen by
forceful robbery. It is not simply bereavement,--but bereavement by
such awful fraud, that tries us most sorely.</p>
               <p>And yet none the less--but how it strains upon our submission-none
the less is it the solemn, sovereign providence of the reigning
God. Truly "clouds and darkness are round about him." In this visit to
us "He maketh darkness his pavilion," and our hand cannot draw back
the heavy folds. He is trying, by a hard test, our faith, our
confidence, our resignation. Oh that our struggling lips could say
clearly, if not calmly, "It is the Lord, let Him do what seemeth Him
good." We must say that, before we can have any comfort, before our
prayers can find acceptance, and before the divine hand will take from
our suppliant hand the loose-lying reins of state. God help us to say
out of the depths of this great grief, without a doubt, without any
reserve, with our yearning affections still clinging around that 
<pb n="7"/>
                  <figure><graphic url=""/>
                     <figDesc>7th page of Andrew
L. Stone's A Discourse Occasioned by the Death of Abraham
Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
pale, dead form, lying in the chamber of the White House, "Thy will be
done!"</p>
               <p>How dear he was to the people! That thought comes first after the
loss. He was of them. He was not lifted above them, either in pride of
place, or pride of intellect, or the kingly style of his greatness. He
walked on our levels still. All his simple, plain, homely talk, kept
him near us. He spoke our vernacular, the language of the fireside and
common life, and not the dialect of courts. He did not leave us, and
wrap himself in official stateliness, when he went up the hill of the
capitol. His kindly face and voice, his cheerful, humorous, fireside
English, his form and attitudes, and all his personal habits, made him
seem of kin to each of us. A familiar, friendly, neighborly air hung
about him everywhere. He put on nothing. He was always his own, true,
hearty, republican self. The people loved him. That thin, swarthy
face, that tall, angular form, drew after them, more than all beauty
and grandeur in the land, the blessings of their hearts. And he loved
them. He was thoughtful for the comfort of the aged, the poor, the
hearts which war had made desolate. The humblest could go to him,
finding an open door and an open heart. It seems to me that we have
never held any other President so tenderly in our affections. And one
reason is, we have never found any other so accessible to our thoughts
and sympathies, and never one so much of our own mould and
substance.</p>
               <p>How we confided in him! He was a man to build trust upon. His
honesty was a pillared rock. The pleasant air, with which, against
whatever importunity,
<pb n="8"/>
                  <figure><graphic url=""/>
                     <figDesc>8th page of Andrew
L. Stone's A Discourse Occasioned by the Death of Abraham
Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
he kept his purposes, covered and mantled the sternest
conscientiousness. The careless step with which he walked toward his
objects in the country's welfare, neither wealth nor favor could make
to swerve. All was simple, easy, and natural, but firm-fibred as oak,
true as steel. The most faithful discharge of his great duty,--the
highest good of the nation,--to this fixed, unrevolving star his soul
was steady as the needle to the pole. He had a sharp insight that cut
through all the rind of sophistries to the core of difficult
questions, leaving such light on the stroke that other minds could
follow. He was a man of parables, and translated the dark and vexed
problems of political science into pleasant similitudes, transparent
to the dullest eye. Where a diplomatic answer would have been
dignified obscurity, he told a story through which flashed the honest
light of clear intelligence. He was in this way a wonderful teacher of
the nation. His brief, pithy, humorous narratives have made crooked
things straight, through a thousand tortuous walks of State
policy. This quaint, ever-ready humor was the soft cushion upon which
the great burdens of his public cares impinged, covering and shielding
his nerves from laceration. It saved him half the wear and tear of his
official work. It kept his friends, and conciliated those who differed
from him. He could convince with a smile, refute with a jest, turn the
flank of heavy reasoning with this agile lightness of wit and conquer
kind feeling, if not persuasion,--generally both.</p>
               <p>His goodness was his greatness. His honest heart helped his
straight-forward mind. He saw truth and duty more clearly by this
inward illumination. His
<pb n="9"/>
                  <figure><graphic url=""/>
                     <figDesc>9th page of Andrew
L. Stone's A Discourse Occasioned by the Death of Abraham
Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
reach of genuine desire carried out his reach of intellect, and became
genius. He was more sagacious than his advisers, partly because he was
more single-hearted. He sought so earnestly the best means to the
noblest end, that he was sure of an intellectual triumph in their
discovery. He kept the moral sky clear, and it reflected light upon
the mental. A pure patriot, who walked with honor, faith, and truth,
though walking amid the defilements and corruptions of political life,
and so kept his garments unstained. But this is no time, in the
freshness of our affliction, for his eulogy. It is too soon to write
that. We must wait till the clouds have risen from all the paths he
trod,--till the smoke of conflict and the haze of prejudice are swept
away by the sun-bright air of our newly-risen day. By and by the
future will lead us up to calm heights that will give us perfect
vision over all these fluctuating levels. We are too near Abraham
Lincoln yet, fully to survey and respect his great nature and his
great work. Not till the wave on whose crest he rode has receded with
him a little, shall we be able to discover on the back-ground of these
eventful times the true proportions of his greatness. Every coming day
will add to his fame; and coming generations will testify that no
purer, no nobler, no more fruitful life has been given to our nation
and American history.</p>
               <p>"We trusted it had been he," whom God had appointed to lead us
through both the Red Sea and the desert beyond, to the Canaan of our
future. But the dastard hand of treason struck,--struck as cowards
always strike, from behind,--struck, with the confession of weakness
and desperate inferiority which the assassin
<pb n="10"/>
                  <figure><graphic url=""/>
                     <figDesc>10th page of Andrew
L. Stone's A Discourse Occasioned by the Death of Abraham
Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
and his cause always make in the very act that gluts their hate, and
the good, the great, the gentle, the kind, the large-hearted, the
beloved President is no more! Whatever else may be dark about this
mystery of crime, we cannot mistake the spirit that steeped itself in
that sacred blood. It is the same spirit that has been deaf for
generations to the groans and sighs of the bondman; the same that
struck with parricidal hand at the breast of the country's life; the
same that opened the murderous thunders of war in Charleston harbor,
and has kept them resonant over the land through four wasteful, tragic
years; the same that sent hired incendiaries to fire the mansions in
our Northern cities, where women and babes as well as men slept in
unsuspecting security; the same that laid in wait for the President
elect, with murderous intent, when he first left his Western home for
the Capitol; the same that advertised for bids upon his head, through
the consenting press of the South; the same that administered keepers'
discipline in Libby Prison and Castle Thunder, for a step or gesture
amiss, with bullet and bayonet; that made grim Famine jailer at Belle
Isle and Andersonville, over tens of thousands, to whom death only
brought release. This black, consummate crime is only the ripe fruit
of that system of barbarism which has struck its roots so deep, and
had such stalwart growth in this continent. That barbarism has
cheapened human life in hearts where it has had its hour; made
shedding of blood like the pouring out of water; the cries of
famishing men as whisperings of the idle wind; the striking down of
senatorial dignity in its own place of privilege and unsuspecting
safety, a deed of chivalrous gallantry; and
<pb n="11"/>
                  <figure><graphic url=""/>
                     <figDesc>11th page of Andrew
L. Stone's A Discourse Occasioned by the Death of Abraham
Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
now the cold-blooded murder of one who has led in the great marches of
liberty to a whole race, and is hailed as deliverer and saviour by
four millions of souls whose fetters have fallen at his word, and has
disappointed thus the scheme to build a kingdom of darkness and of
iron upon the necks of those millions, an act of fruitless though
sweet revenge. It has delivered many a blow before, that has wrung and
pierced the individual heart; but it has found here at last its
opportunity, Nero-like, to gather in one the hearts and hopes of all
loyal people, and pierce them through with a single thrust. Will any
one say that I go too far in attributing this stroke of a single hand
to the whole system which it so fitly represents? The evidence found
in the papers of the assassin, the time at first arranged for the
execution of the plot, the hesitation of an accomplice <hi rend="italic">at that time</hi>, until WORD SHOULD COME FROM RICHMOND,
and the mysterious threats and prophecies of Richmond papers of <hi rend="italic">that date</hi>, of some great shock to the Union, and the
world even, then just impending, which would be the deliverance of the
confederacy, all go to show that the secret of this conspiracy, and
its dark purpose, were in the hearts of the rebel chiefs in the rebel
capital.</p>
               <p>But what has it gained for itself by such triumphant guilt? Any
reversal of its own infamy; a more clement judgment in history; the
blossoming of fresh hope for its own dark designs; a change of
sentiment and will with the loyal people; the blotting out of the
great victories of the fortnight past; aught but a crimson hand whose
stain strikes all through the soul, and the curse of earth and heaven?
It has bought its revenge dear.</p>
               <pb n="12"/>
               <p>
                  <figure><graphic url=""/>
                     <figDesc>12th page of
Andrew L. Stone's A Discourse Occasioned by the Death of Abraham
Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <p>And what, we may ask, is the extent of this revenge? or, rather, in
what aspects may we view it, that shall help us bear our loss, and
show us the divine hand mingling in it?</p>
               <p>That deadly aim took the life of Abraham Lincoln. But it could not
touch his past. That is forever safe. It could not blot out one of
those pregnant years through which his hand was on the helm of the
ship of state, as she drove reeling over the great waves of the
storm. It could not make good the threat, that he should never live to
take his seat in the Presidential chair. It could not bereave the
country of one counsel of wisdom, one firm resolve upon which she has
leaned so steadily in her darkest hours. It could not put out the
light of that shining example of truthfulness and dutifulness which
has been to us all, in this night of gloom, a star of cheer and of
guidance. It could not undo the policy which has gathered and
marshalled invincible armies, and conquered peace by the sword,
without one compromise of righful, unfettered authority. It could not
silence that voice that spoke out on the most illustrious New Year's
morning of all our history, and said to Four Millions of slaves, "BE
FREE"--and the winds of heaven bore it out,--"Be Free!"--and the sea
repeated it, on all our shores, "Be Free"-and the eagle of liberty,
looking down on his own broad continent, screamed it, "Be Free!"--and
the bending heavens with saluting angels sent it back to all our dusky
homes, " Be Free!"--and the echo rose in unnumbered voices of lonely
lips, toned with wondrous gratitude, " Free, Free, Free!" That word
has been spoken. In that word the murdered
<pb n="13"/>
                  <figure><graphic url=""/>
                     <figDesc>13th page of Andrew
L. Stone's A Discourse Occasioned by the Death of Abraham
Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
President "though dead still speaketh." That voice can never be
silenced, though those pale lips shall never part again. The work that
has been done, and so well done, by this faithful worker, cannot be
undone. No power beneath the sun can roll back this nation to where
she stood four years ago. Those grand acts of the drama that have
moved across the stage will never retrace their steps. This final act
of victory and certainty cannot be exchanged for that first act of
surprise, confusion and fear. Our risen morning cannot sink down
behind the orient, and hide again in the darkness of the past. The
night of doubt and defeat, the night of slavery, the night of defiant
rebellion, those deep shadows of the past, have fled; and the new day
no man can sweep from the brightening firmament. All this has been
gained, for us and humanity, under that leadership whose stricken hand
has dropped the sceptre now. The sceptre has fallen, but this work
remains. The past is secure. No murderer's hand has power to blot
it.</p>
               <p>In our hearts, too, our slain leader <hi rend="italic">still
lives</hi>. He lives more vitally than ever. Many hearts that were
cool to him will have opened now, and taken him in. All prejudice will
forgive him and accept him.  He is no more an object of criticism; he
is beyond the reach of hate. Hate itself will die out, and in its
place will come a concession of his many virtues and peerless
excellences. He is dead. All pens that write of him will write
forbearingly, if not tenderly and admiringly. And those of us who
loved and honored him before will take his name and image into some
more interior cham-
<pb n="14"/>
                  <figure><graphic url=""/>
                     <figDesc>14th page of Andrew
L. Stone's A Discourse Occasioned by the Death of Abraham
Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
ber of our hearts, within some more sacred shrine, and guard them
there. It was not Abraham Lincoln, it was our cause, the cause of
liberty, the cause of humanity, the cause of government, the cause of
the Union, that was doomed to the death by that felon hand. The victim
stood on that perilous height, as the representative of this whole
great scheme of human progress. He is its martyr. He died for that. He
was slain because of his faithfulness to that scheme. Our hands led
him up, once and again, to that eminence, and set him there as a
target for the deadly malice of the conspirators. He fell because we
laid upon him such trust, and because he discharged it all too
well. We can but love him the more for this. Our noble, murdered
witness, with his good confession, his home and his throne, are
henceforth in our heart of hearts. The assassin's steel, the deadly
aim, cannot reach him here. We will teach our posterity to honor
him. Our children, and our children's children shall hear us speak his
name as our fathers spoke to us the name of Washington, and shall grow
up revering and guarding the hallowed memory of this second <hi rend="italic">Father of his country;</hi> whom History will write, also,
<hi rend="italic">the Father of a race.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>His future, too, is <hi rend="italic">safe</hi>. There is no question
now, in any mind, whether any eclipse can come upon his fame. Would he
have guided the vessel as wisely, through the intricate channels of
reconstruction, as over the tempestuous sea of civil strife? Could he
have gained such wide assent and cheerful support to his measures, in
the new exigencies of ruling, as in those through which he has safely
brought us? Might not some, who have been
<pb n="15"/>
                  <figure><graphic url=""/>
                     <figDesc>15th page of Andrew
L. Stone's A Discourse Occasioned by the Death of Abraham
Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
his friends, have turned against him possibly, as the new questions of
the hour, and of coming hours, came into sharp debate? Already there
were fears that he would not prove stern enough for the stern work of
retributive justice, and that his great, kind heart, rather than his
bond to law, and to the destinies of the future, would have guided him
in his treatment of the chiefs of the rebellion. But all fears, all
questions, all doubts looking toward any qualification of his
well-earned renown, are vanished now. He can show no weakness in the
future, to reflect upon his strength in the past, commit no folly to
reproach his old sagacity, make no blunder that shall leave him shorn
of influence, and mingle large qualification with the praise of
history. He is safe from all these possibilities of errors, frailties,
and failures. History must take his portrait as he is, standing at the
very highest eminence of a just and stainless life. Not one laurel
which he has won, and which he wears, is ever, by any reversal of
coming days, to be stolen from his wealth of power.</p>
               <p>He was permitted, too, to see the great triumph toward which his
hopes looked and his counsels helped. Thank God for that. He knew the
rebellion doomed, the war ended, and the nation saved. That one
supreme moment when his feet trod the streets of the conquered rebel
capital paid him for all. He did not die like the old prophets
"without the sight." He gazed with mortal eyes upon the glorious
consummation, for which, with such grandeur of constancy and
diligence, through four years whose weight would have crushed a weaker
man, and would have crushed him but that he leaned on
<pb n="16"/>
                  <figure><graphic url=""/>
                     <figDesc>16th page of Andrew
L. Stone's A Discourse Occasioned by the Death of Abraham
Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
Heaven, he had been toiling. If the assassin had struck before the
rebel banner fell at Richmond, and the sword of Lee was yielded to the
hand of Grant, if the sun of the President had gone down before the
sun of our rescued nationality had fairly risen, that would have been
a darker and more trying providence. But that sun was up. Those
patriot eyes saw its morning radiance, and reflected it back. He might
almost have said, like aged Simeon, perhaps he did so say in the
silence of some secret and thankful prayer, "Lord, now lettest thou
thy servant depart in peace, for mine eyes have seen thy
salvation!"</p>
               <p>It will not be too bold to say, that his work was done when it
paused; for God, who gives each man his task, so judged and so
appointed. His mission was accomplished. That for which God raised him
up he had performed. All that was committed to him to do he finished,
and finished well. That which comes after is assigned to other
heads. God is not limited in the number or in the variety of his
agents. Nothing is put in peril now by this falling of a trusted
leader which God cannot as well provide for, and make even more
victoriously secure.</p>
               <p>Least of all are we to fear, that the great cause of progress in
this land must needs be turned back, or even halt. That cause may be
served and forwarded by men; but it is not dependent upon their living
or dying. It is not invested in any vulnerable, human life. It is not
something material which bludgeon or steel may strike to the
earth. Its citadel is not within frail human flesh, or within the
truest and noblest human heart. It is a
<pb n="17"/>
                  <figure><graphic url=""/>
                     <figDesc>17th page of Andrew
L. Stone's A Discourse Occasioned by the Death of Abraham
Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
kingdom of truth,--a life of ideas, invisible, invulnerable,--on all
the air,--in the faith and testimony of millions of confessors,--in
God's imperishable word,--linked with his invincible providence,-in
living seed of thoughts and principles which righteous blood shed by
the hand of violence only quickens to a more instant germination, and
ripens to an earlier and broader harvest. That cause is God's
cause. It is hid in his heart. It is carried on his eternal
purpose. It is too high and safe for human desperation to strike.</p>
               <p>Let none of us in his great grief despair or despond over his
country. Recall to-day that word which has become in these stern times
our national motto, "In God we trust!" He did not lead Israel through
the Red Sea to forsake them in the wilderness. He will not forsake us
on the shore from which we have looked down on our foes overwhelmed
and broken. He has led us hitherto. He can lead us on. His counsels
have not changed. His power is not baffled. He can appoint us a
leader. Moses was not permitted to go over Jordan; but there arose a
new captain of the Lord's host, and the sword of Joshua instead of the
rod of Moses waved in the van of advance. David was not permitted to
build a temple for the Lord his God, because he had been a man of war,
and had shed much blood; but he prepared the way, accumulated the
means, conquered the peace, and Solomon reared the magnificent, sacred
pile. Through our tears let us look up and confide in that Supreme
Leader.</p>
               <p>He has mingled mercy even with this great tragedy. Part of the
bloody conspiracy was foiled. The Secretary
<pb n="18"/>
                  <figure><graphic url=""/>
                     <figDesc>18th page of Andrew
L. Stone's A Discourse Occasioned by the Death of Abraham
Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
of State, and those smitten in his defence, we may hope will
survive. The arm that conquered in the field, doomed in the foul plot
with those who were stricken, the arm of our hero, Grant, is nerved
still with life and strength. God keep it so nerved. God shield the
head of Grant. How wide the murderous scheme, and how many names were
written on the assassins' roll, none of us can tell, but every great
and precious life we can commend to his vigilant keeping who has
numbered the hairs of our head, and without whom not a sparrow falls
to the ground.</p>
               <p>What if the new unexpected responsibility settling upon the legal
successor of the slain President should fill him with another heart,
call him up to the height of a great consecration, gird him with noble
and faithful purposes, so that the memory of one hour of shame shall
be remembered no more against him, in the splendor of a long and just
renown? That issue is more than possible. This, too, may be given as
the answer of Christian intercession.</p>
               <p>And oh, we have that stricken household to bathe with a nation's
sympathy; to beseech God's tenderest consolations for them; to lift
them, and lay them for strength and comfort on the heart of Jesus.</p>
               <p>Of what infinite worth to them now, and to us also, those words of
tender confession which came a few months ago from the President's
lips: "Yes, now I can say that I do from my heart love the Lord Jesus
Christ."</p>
               <p>We feel, many of us, that we could have wished, for him whom we
mourn, a different scene for the last hour of his health and
consciousness on earth, that he could
<pb n="19"/>
                  <figure><graphic url=""/>
                     <figDesc>19th page of Andrew
L. Stone's A Discourse Occasioned by the Death of Abraham
Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
have met the fatal missive on some stage of official duty, or in the
retirement of home, or in the circle of religious worship, rather than
within those festal walls. Yes, it would have been better.</p>
               <p>But they were scarcely festal walls to him. They were a sort of
refuge often, for one who had no retirement of home, from the
incessant calls and wearying importunities of aspirants for place and
office.</p>
               <p>And it has seemed to be rather one of the penalties than pleasures
of political rank and illustrious position, that they must yield
themselves to the popular welcomes and fellowship in such festive
gatherings. And the plea that prevailed with the President to visit
the theatre on this particular night was that of his own kind heart,
unwilling, in the necessary absence of their idolized general, that
the waiting enthusiasm of the people should be altogether denied an
object for its expression; his last thought not for himself, but for
the gratification of those whom he loved and served.</p>
               <p>And so he has passed from the midst of us. Our joy-bells have
changed their merry peals for solemn tolling. Our festive banners
droop at half-mast. Our purposed jubilant processions must become
funeral marches to this new grave. "The joy of our hearts is
ceased. Our dance is turned into mourning. The crown is fallen from
our head."</p>
               <p>We touch, in this event, one of the great pivotal points in our
history and destiny, on which turn issues more momentous than we can
now discern. But our future is with God, and not at the mercy of human
scheming and human crime.</p>
               <pb n="20"/>
               <p>
                  <figure><graphic url=""/>
                     <figDesc>20th page of
Andrew L. Stone's A Discourse Occasioned by the Death of Abraham
Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <p>We shall not have much time for tears even over so great a
sorrow. Our work is stern and pressing. One thing is beyond
contradiction. Yielding rebellion has lost its most lenient
judge,-returning rebels their best friend. His successor has always
entertained towards these parricides a sharper and more incisive
purpose. They will meet in him a face set like a flint, a hand of
iron. They have not gained much by the exchange.</p>
               <p>We shall none of us be any the more inclined to spare the last
remaining weakness of the old system, from this new exhibition of its
fell spirit, or to apologize for that temper in the midst of us that
can make this day of broken-hearted mourning, a day of glad tidings to
itself.  It is not wise just now for such minds to speak out their
brutal gladness. Our hearts are too sore to bear it. They had better
hide it, if they feel it, so deep that neither by look nor lip shall
it get expression. We shall not be very patient with it. The law
officers have found out that there is such a crime as being
accessories to murder after the fact, and the spirit of Andrew Johnson
is the downright kindred spirit of the Andrew Jackson of other days,
and treason, North and South, will have a short shrift and a sharp
doom. Perhaps we needed, all of us, to see more clearly the wickedness
against which we have had to contend, and to be girded anew for its
utter extermination. Let us crush it quickly, and forever.</p>
               <p>And so, bereft of this one helper in whom we have felt strong, let
us turn to God with a new spirit of dependence on his Almighty arm,
and make our tears of
<pb n="21"/>
                  <figure><graphic url=""/>
                     <figDesc>21th page of Andrew
L. Stone's A Discourse Occasioned by the Death of Abraham
Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
mourning the waters of a new baptismal consecration to the service of
our country and humanity, the supremacy of law, and the safety, honor,
and perpetuity of this Union, for which we have paid so great a
price.</p>
            </div2>
         </div1>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>