<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader><fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A Commemorative Discourse on the Death of Abraham Lincoln</title>
            <author>Sweetser, Seth</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Compiled and edited by</resp>
               <name>Beck
Center</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent/>
         <publicationStmt><publisher>Lewis H. Beck Center</publisher><pubPlace>Emory University</pubPlace><address>
               <addrLine>Atlanta,
Georgia</addrLine>
            </address><availability>
               <p>1996 Emory
University. Permission is granted to download, transmit, or otherwise
reproduce, distribute or display the contributions to the work claimed
by Emory University for non-profit educational purposes, provided
this header is included in its entirety.  For inquiries about
commercial uses, contact the Director, 
Pitts Theology Library, Emory
University, Atlanta, Georgia 30322</p>
            </availability><date>1999</date></publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Lincoln
Sermons Project</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Sweetser,
Seth. A Commemorative Discourse on the Death of Abraham
Lincoln. Worcester, Massachusetts.  MDCCCLXV.</bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc><encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This text derives from the Special Collections 
of Pitts Theology Library, Emory University, and is produced in 
collaboration with the Lewis H. Beck Center a, the Emory 
Preservation Office, and Pitts Theology Library.</p>
            <p>TRANSCRIBER: Lewis H. Beck Center and Emory University 
Preservation Office.</p>
            <p>PRODUCER:  BookLab, Inc., 1606 Headway Circle, 
Suite 100, Austin, TX 78754</p>
            <p>CAPTURE DEVICE: XEROX DocuImage 620S flatbed scanner</p>
            <p>CAPTURE DETAILS: Scanner software: XEROX ScanTool 
version 4.2.3; no gamma correction; images are all bitonal.</p>
            <p>CHANGE HISTORY: Using the Adobe Photoshop Batch Processor, 
we interpolated  the original TIFF files to 8-bit grays, 
and altered the resolution to 144 dpi, producing screen 
images twice the original size.  We then saved them in 
JPEG format.  We produced GIF thumbnails from the JPEG files.</p>
            <p>RESOLUTION: 600 ppi</p>
            <p>COMPRESSION: Resolution 144 per inch with Constrain 
Properties to 72 per inch.</p>
            <p>SOURCE: Original documents.</p>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc><revisionDesc><change><name>Stewart Varner</name> transformed this document from p4 to p5 on <date when="2010-03-22">March 22, 2010</date></change><change xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><date>1999</date><label>Staff</label><name>Scott Ellis</name>SGML tags inserted in compliance
with TEI guidelines using TEILITE</change></revisionDesc></teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div1 xml:id="sweetser.001" n="A Commemorative Discourse on the Death of Abraham Lincoln" type="text">
            <head> 
               <bibl> 
                  <title>A Commemorative
Discourse on the Death of Abraham Lincoln</title>
                  <date>[unknown]</date> 
                  <pubPlace>Central Church</pubPlace>
                  <author>Sweetser, Seth</author> 
                  
                     <pubPlace>Boston</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Press of John Wilson and Son</publisher>
                     <date>1865</date>
                   
               <idno type="ark">http://pid.emory.edu/ark:/25593/15r7m</idno></bibl> 
            </head>
            <pb facs="sweetser1.jpg"/>
            <p>A</p>
            <p>COMMEMORATIVE  DISCOURSE</p>
            <p>On the Death</p>
            <p>of</p>
            <p>ABRAHAM LINCOLN.</p>
            <p>BY SETH SWEETSER,</p>
            <p>PASTOR OF THE CENTRAL CHURCH</p>
            <p>Worcester, Massachusetts.</p>
            <p>MCDCCCLXV.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="sweetser2.jpg"/>
            <p>Abraham Lincoln,</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italic">Sixteenth President of the United States,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>DIED ON THE 15TH OF APRIL, A.D. 1865,</p>
            <p>AGED 56.</p>
            <p>"That magnanimity that neither feareth greatness of alteration, nor
the views of conspirators, nor the power of enemy, is more than
heroical."</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="sweetser3.jpg"/>
            <p>WORCESTER,
MAY 8, 1865.</p>
            <p>DEAR SIR,</p>
            <p>The Congregation of the Central Church in
this city greatly desire to preserve and perpetuate your Discourse in
commemoration of the Death of our revered President, ABRAHAM
LINCOLN. They have, therefore, this day commissioned us, the
undersigned, to request of you a copy for the press. In preferring
this request, as we now do, we desire to express, for ourselves and
for the Congregation, our conviction that the Discourse is eminently
entitled to a place among the permanent memorials of our great
national bereavement. Trusting that you will grant this request,</p>
            <p>We remain, with great respect,</p>
            <p>Your friends,</p>
            <p>CHAS. E. STEVENS.<lb/>
THOMAS H. GAGE.<lb/>
P. EMORY ALDRICH.<lb/>
C. M. MILES.<lb/>
G. HENRY WHITCOMB.  <lb/>The REV. SETH SWEETSER, D. D.</p>
            <p>WORCESTER,
MAY 10, 1865.</p>
            <p>GENTLEMEN,</p>
            <p>In compliance with your request, I send you the manuscript of my
Discourse preached on Sunday, the 23d of April last.</p>
            <p>With acknowledgments of your continued regard,</p>
            <p>Your friend and Pastor,</p>
            <p>S.
SWEETSER.</p>
            <p>Messrs. CHARLES E.  STEVENS, THOMAS H. GAGE,  P. EMORY ALDRICH,</p>
            <p>C. M. MILES, G. HENRY WHITCOMB.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="sweetser4.jpg"/>
            <p>AND THE KING SAID UNTO HIS SERVANTS, KNOW YE NOT THAT
THERE IS A PRINCE AND A GREAT MAN FALLEN THIS DAY IN ISRAEL?</p>
            <p>2
SAMUEL, III. 38.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="sweetser5.jpg"/>
            <div2 xml:id="sweetser.002" n="DISCOURSE." type="sermon">
               <head>DISCOURSE.</head>
               <p>TO keep in memory, and to review with gratitude and honor, the
lives of men conspicuous for great services, has the sanction of the
universal judgment of mankind. In so doing, the goodness which would
be ephemeral is embalmed; the examples worthy of perpetual imitation
are kept as ever-burning lights in the darkness of the world. It is
thus History adorns her temple with noble statues, and fills her
archives with the choicest wisdom of the ages. It is thus that
prophets and kings, benefactors and holy men, being dead, speak on
from generation to generation, and the righteous are in everlasting
remembrance.</p>
               <p>A prince and a great man has fallen, and a grateful people will
establish his memorial: they will enrol his name with the illustrious
benefactors of the world, and treasure his deeds amongst the worthiest
traditions that are handed down to after-times. The
<pb n="6" facs="sweetser6.jpg"/>
thrill of horror which shot through the nation on the morning of the
FIFTEENTH OF APRIL, though somewhat abated in its force, still
vibrates in the hearts of afflicted millions, and has left an
impression which a lifetime will not obliterate. In the stroke which
deprived the country of its Chief Magistrate, malice has done its
utmost. The malignant spirit of treason and conspiracy culminated in a
crime hitherto unknown in our annals. The records of despotic
governments have often been stained with like atrocities; for
despotism is itself a violence and a felony against human nature; and
the atmosphere of tyranny breeds the malicious passions which revel in
murders. This awful instance of insane depravity is but another crime,
born of the same mother whose hideous offspring have filled the
land. Treason, rebellion, and war, the unnamed and unnumbered
inhumanities which have transcended all the supposed horrors of war,
are not the growth of free institutions, but of that disregard of
human rights which claimed slavery as essential to the highest social
condition. The same spirit, which, for its own ends, assailed the life
of the Republic, has now struck by the hand of the assassin the chief
and the leader of the nation. The magnitude of the crime excites us
with feelings of the utmost horror: the bereavement afflicts us with
the deepest grief. A nation mourns as nations have seldom had occasion
to mourn: a whole people
<pb n="7" facs="sweetser7.jpg"/>
weeps as they only weep who have loved. How deep and strong the love,
no one knew until it was told in the wailing and lamentation which
sounded through the land, from one end of it to the other. And yet, as
the violence of sorrow subsides, we find the sharpness of the
affliction modified by rare satisfactions. God has added an exalted
name to the roll of the honored dead in our country's history, and
enlarged our annals with a new chapter crowded with great events, and
deeds of lasting renown. The man who has fixed our attention and
inspired all our hopes more than any other, and into whose hands the
destiny of the future seemed to be given, has in a moment passed
away. Who will say that his lifework was left incomplete? Who will say
that he had not done for himself, for his country, and for mankind,
all that was given him to do? He had reached a height of power, a
security of public confidence, a depth and universality of affection,
seldom gained by rulers. He had seen the dawn of an era towards which,
with a single eye and an intense gaze, he had been looking, for which,
with almost superhuman persistency and courage, he had been
struggling. He ascended the mount where he could see the fair fields
and the smiling vineyards of the promised land. But, like the great
leader of Israel, he was not permitted to come to the possession. His
vigor was not diminished. His natural strength was
<pb n="8" facs="sweetser8.jpg"/>
not abated. His sun never declined. His day knew no evening. He
departed at the noontide hour, in the zenith and full blaze of his
glory. The beautiful language in which the Senate of the United States
communicated to John Adams the death of Washington, may with propriety
be applied here: "The scene is closed, and we are no longer anxious
lest misfortune should sully his glory: he has travelled to the end of
his journey, and carried with him an increasing weight of honor: he
has deposited it safely where misfortune cannot tarnish it, where
malice cannot blast it."</p>
               <p>An accomplished life is a great thing. There is, indeed, a charm in
a life rounded out with its full term of years, and closing with the
serene light of a quiet evening. But life is estimated by its purposes
and their fulfilment. And when a man's day has been crowded with great
events, and God has given him the post and the honor of directing the
currents of destiny to beneficent ends, and that has been done, what
higher idea can we have of life? It is true, our hopes are
disappointed. We walk and are sad, as were the unenlightened disciples
on their way to Emmaus. We trusted that it had been he which should
have redeemed Israel. May not the revelations of the future satisfy us
as the disciples were satisfied? May we not find yet, that all our
loftiest and most cherished expectations are realized? 
<pb n="9" facs="sweetser9.jpg"/>
It is not unnatural for us to be filled with dread when the swift
revolution of the great wheel suddenly takes out of our sight the
objects on  which our eyes have dwelt with fondest desire. We never
see much at a time. The chain which binds in fixed succession all
events, exhibits to us but a few links. We see neither the beginning
nor the end. The chain is not broken because we lose sight of the
connection. The great procession goes on under the eye of the Lord of
the whole earth. All down the centuries of time, and on through coming
generations, not a break occurs. Steadily onward, not by a blind
necessity, but under the control of an omnipotent will, goes forward
the march of events with unerring certainty, till all is
finished. And, as at the beginning, so in the end, the Creator will
look upon his work; and, behold, it is very good. And, when the
problem which now perplexes us shall have been worked out in all its
parts, the whole troubled scene will present to the comprehension of
the human mind an orderly and beneficent arrangement, fully justifying
the ways of God.</p>
               <p>The elevation of Mr. Lincoln to the chief magistracy was a pregnant
event. It opened a new era. It was the first distinct and effective
utterance of the reviving life of the nation. Whatever were the
judgments of the hour,--and they were various,--whatever its hope or
its fears, the result has demonstrated that 
<pb n="10" facs="sweetser10.jpg"/>
it was the hinge on which the destiny of the country was turning. The
malice with which the change was met has been one and the same in
quality and tone until now. The menace of the beginning has shaped and
charged all the violence and outrage which have filled the intervening
period with the darkest atrocities, and which have at length reached
the limit of our conception of crime against the State. Such a series
of years, like all revolutionary epochs, cannot but be crowded with
momentous events. The chief actors are invested with extraordinary
responsibilities, with the high privilege of controlling the mighty
issues at stake, and determining the welfare to be secured in the
struggle.</p>
               <p>Such were the circumstances and such the position in which the
President was called to discharge the duties of his office. That he
had a singular fitness for it is now the universal judgment,
notwithstanding many suspected or perceived
deficiencies. Indiscriminate eulogy and indiscriminate censure are
alike distasteful and unjust; but we should be ungrateful to God not
to acknowledge his goodness in appointing and qualifying such a man
for the burdens and perils of this service. His honesty of purpose
amid abounding dishonesty was a lustrous virtue. His
self-forgetfulness, at a period when selfish ambition had shamed
patriotism into obscurity, was a rare jewel. His childlike simplicity,
which exposed him to many
<pb n="11" facs="sweetser11.jpg"/>
a jeer, was a fresh illumination in the surrounding darkness of
intrigue and policy. His very ignorance of state-craft and artifice
was as charming as the frankness and ingenuousness of youth in the
crowd of hardened and deceitful men of the world. His acknowledgment
of God was a gleam of hope in the days of unreasoning trust in
material prosperity. With such qualities of heart he could not be a
patriot, without being a sincere one; he could not bend his energies
to subserve the interests of his country, without a firm hand and a
single eye. Many doubted, many feared: some were utterly faithless and
hopeless. And for such feelings, it may be, there were grounds not
altogether unreasonable; for he was a new man, girding himself to a
new enterprise. He had yet to demonstrate his capacity, and to show,
in the hardest conflict of the most tempestuous times, his competency
and quality. The faint outlines and foreshadowings which in the outset
inspired hope have been deeply drawn and filled in to the admiration
of his countrymen, and so as to secure, we doubt not, the approving
judgment of a dispassionate posterity.</p>
               <p>Napoleon was fond of calling himself the child of Destiny. Abraham
Lincoln was the child of Providence. An undevout philosophy might say
that he was the pupil of events, sagaciously detecting the clew, and
then implicitly following the thread. We
<pb n="12" facs="sweetser12.jpg"/>
had rather say, that he sat a learner under the teachings of God, in
his providence and his word, and waited patiently to learn God's will
and the path of duty; and, when that will was known, and the path
opened, no man was more prompt to do the, one or enter the
other. This, if I mistake not, was one of the distinctive features of
his character. For he was not a man, as I apprehend, of remarkable
intuitions, of comprehensiveness of view, and penetrating forecast. He
did not stand amongst statesmen where Lord Bacon stood amongst
philosophers, detecting great principles in their germs, and jotting
down the synopsis of the world's thought ages beforehand. He did not
stand in public affairs where Newton stood in the realm of nature,
seizing, with an almost prophetic insight, the great laws which
determine the vast cycles of celestial movements in their absolute
harmony. In the combined qualities of the statesman and general, he
can hardly rise to the eminence of William the Silent, whom he so much
resembled, in the life-work he performed as a national deliverer, in
the nobleness of his character, in the piety of his sentiments, in the
tenderness of his heart, and, more than all, in the cruel death he
suffered. He seems not to have been gifted with that keenness of sight
which outruns observation, and with a glance detects and follows out
the certain connection between present causes and future
consequences. His mind was
<pb n="13" facs="sweetser13.jpg"/>
of another order, not perhaps of a lower order; for all true greatness
is not of one quality. He was prone to watch the currents as they were
passing; to eye the development as God opened it in his providence; to
trust the hand which guided events, and wait till it beckoned him
onward; to learn his lesson day by day, and to be satisfied, as
Cromwell was, to do in the day the duty of the day. Such a course
exposed him to the charge of hesitation and wavering. He sometimes
seemed to be the victim of ignorance and indecision. He was not rapid
enough for an impatient people. He was not rash enough for
enthusiastic partisans. But this very hesitation, this holding back
till the way opened and the duty was ascertained, was his insurance
against fatal errors. It would be presumptuous to say that he
committed no faults. It would be unjust not to say, that, in view of
the fearful complexity of affairs, the untried scenes of his action,
the lack of precedents, and his own inexperience of the burdens of
government, his mistakes were as few and as venial as could reasonably
be expected from a short-sighted mortal. That he was ever betrayed by
malice, blinded by passion, or instigated to doubtful measures by
self-seeking or personal ambition, his enemies would scarcely be
willing to affirm.</p>
               <p>In the letter addressed to Congress by the convention which framed
the constitution of the United
<pb n="14" facs="sweetser14.jpg"/>
States, submitting the constitution to the consideration of that body,
and bearing the signature of Washington, are these words: "In all our
deliberations ... we kept steadily in our view that which appears to
us the greatest interest of every true American,--the consolidation of
our Union, in which is involved our prosperity, felicity, safety,
perhaps our national existence."</p>
               <p>One could hardly select more appropriate language in which to
describe the avowed aim of the administration which has so suddenly
terminated. It is the leading idea in the entire series of the
President's efforts. Whether or not he was too exclusively devoted to
this purpose, and whether or not he was wise in all the measures he
adopted in attaining it, it was, beyond any question, his great
aim. He looked upon the Union with an ardor and sincerity of
affection, with a self-denying patriotism, and with a single-hearted
devotion, which would not have dishonored the chief heroes of the
Revolution. To the consolidation and perpetuity of the Union, and the
resulting welfare, he made every thing subservient. He did not at once
see all that was necessary. And this is one of the brightest features
in his career, that, as the elements essential to unity and prosperity
were evolved from the confused and conflicting mass of judgments,
opinions, and political dicta, he fearlessly accepted them, and firmly
applied them. Upon the
<pb n="15" facs="sweetser15.jpg"/>
all-important question of emancipation, he seemed at first to be
unsettled,--not from a deficiency of kind and humane feelings,--but
from the lack of a clear discernment as to right and duty under the
constitution. But he was a willing learner. He was a sure learner. He
studied. He observed. He pondered. He weighed the great question as a
ruler, with the solemn responsibilities of the high trust upon him; as
a man, with all the moving instincts of a loving and tender heart: and
as a ruler, sure of his duty, he spoke the disinthralling edict, when
multitudes still doubted: as a man he rejoiced in the glorious
prospect of a race emancipated from a bondage more cruel than the
grave, and elevated to the privileges of manhood and the opportunity
of respect and honor. This progressive enlargement of view was
characteristic of him. He rose with the tide of events. He was never
before his day; perhaps it is just to say he was never behind it. He
kept well up with the line of time; and, when the emergency came, he
was ready. No man, in the opening of the conflict, understood it. No
mind conceived of the magnitude and strength of the occasion. The
rapid developments of the war have kept all thoughts upon the
stretch. Whoever was hampered by precedents, and confined to the old
measures of things, was necessarily left far in the rear of the
advancing column. Under a pressure so resistless, and exposed, almost
of necessity, to be pushed onward,
<pb n="16" facs="sweetser16.jpg"/>
it indicates no ordinary firmness and discipline to have been able to
advance, step by step, under the guiding force of internal conviction
and intelligent determinations. Such I believe to be the measure of
praise due to Mr. Lincoln. If any man was exposed to the utmost rush
of the current, he was. If any man was liable to be forced out of
course by the whirls and eddies of the boisterous stream, he was. Amid
the tumultuous feelings of the hour, and under the disparaging
influence of nearness to the chief events, we may be unable to discern
the full credit he deserves, in so manfully persisting in duty, and so
gloriously leading the country through the fierce ordeal of civil
war. When history shall be written calmly and impartially, the strong
features will come out in bold relief. Then the wisdom, the firmness,
the humanity, the faith, of our lamented President will furnish the
portrait of a ruler which will not lose lustre in the presence of
Aurelius, Alfred, Orange, or even of Washington. If the statue of
George Washington fills, by unanimous consent, the first niche in the
Pantheon of illustrious worthies, will not that of Abraham Lincoln
fill the second?</p>
               <p>It would be enough for the largest desire, and for fame, to have
administered well the affairs of the nation under the ordinary reign
of peace and prosperity. But to have achieved success amid
dismembering revolutionary struggles, and the convulsive
<pb n="17" facs="sweetser17.jpg"/>
agitations of a ruthless and gigantic rebellion, pressed with all the
ferocity of unscrupulous war, is the highest renown. The world will
admire the measure of wisdom which marked his decisions in council,
when the profoundest minds were held in suspense, or divided in
judgment. We take an enthusiastic pleasure in the heroism which
gallantly pursues the path of speedy victory, and is always elate with
triumph. But there is a deeper tone of gratification in witnessing
such persistent endurance as we have seen in our leader, which did not
falter under defeat, or grow faint in the hour of disaster, or despond
when trusted agents proved inefficient, and selfish loyalty threatened
to withdraw its support. With the accumulated obstacles which beset so
vast an enterprise, with the varying fortunes attending it, amidst the
willing doubts and disparaging coldness of foreign powers, under all
the intense provocations with which a merciless cruelty in the enemies
of the Government provoked him, to have maintained a firm and steady
course, uniformly considerate, undeviatingly humane, unfalteringly
energetic, and rising ever and always to higher views and more
distinct results, and pressing onward with increasing and resistless
strength to the hour when victory crowned the whole with its cheering
light, is an achievement to be ranked with the most illustrious deeds
of the brightest names in the world's record.</p>
               <p>But this is drawing faintly, and only in outline, the 
<pb n="18" facs="sweetser18.jpg"/>
character and the renown which future history will portray in fulness
of detail, and with a depth and harmony of coloring demanded by so
extraordinary a subject. 
It should not be presumed, that the process by which the higher
character to which I have alluded was attained, depended merely on a
clearer intellectual understanding, or was carried forward by the
ordinary steps of experimental and instructive effort. Mr. Lincoln was
pre-eminently a practical man. His upward progress, from an humble and
unprivileged early position, had been accomplished by a settled
determination to comprehend what he assumed to know, and to understand
what he attempted to master. He had no mind for abstractions and
theories; but, studying in order to gain the power to do, and at once
applying the principles he settled, his life was a perpetual
augmentation of strength, and an enlargement of capacity to discharge
incumbent duty. Nevertheless, in the manifest elevation of feeling and
thought which he exhibited in his public career, other elements were
developed. Very evidently, there was all along an education and an
exaltation of the sentiments of the heart. There was more in his
thoughtfulness than was demanded by the solution of a
perplexity. There was a higher restraint in the caution of his
utterances than is due to prudence in affairs. A deeper feeling moved
him than the instincts of
<pb n="19" facs="sweetser19.jpg"/>
a humane and generous disposition. He gained a richer endowment than a
simple-hearted, ingenuous, kindness. No one can have watched his
course as a man and a ruler without detecting in him an increasing
religious seriousness; a tone and simplicity of faith in God and his
providence; an evident seeking after a knowledge of the will and
counsel of the Most High. All this was added to a frankness and
ingenuousness and rare kindliness of nature, a sort of "inflexible
gentleness," which spread a veil over rougher features; and this
unaffected piety gave a tone to his measures and to his utterances
everywhere perceptible. This religious conscientiousness inspired him
with courage to attempt, and decision in executing, the requirements
of duty. Will any one say that he did not find something of a
practical force controlling him, in the law of love, from the
teachings and example of Christ? Will any one say, that, when his mind
turned to the exercise of mercy, he had no inward promptings, gathered
from the voice of mercy to which he himself listened in the promises
of the Redeemer? His late addresses indicate a depth of serious
feeling which has now a significance, unrealized till death added its
emphasis. Can any man read the solemn utterances of the FOURTH OF
MARCH last, without the conviction that they are the profound
reflections of a heart which looked into the ways of God with
trembling reverence, rather than the conventional
<pb n="20" facs="sweetser20.jpg"/>
language proper to an established ceremony of State? "If we suppose
American slavery is one of those offences which, in the providence of
God, must needs come, but which, having continued through his
appointed time, he now wills to remove; and that he gives to both
North and South this terrible war as the woe due to those by whom the
offence came,--shall we discern therein any departure from those
divine attributes which the believers in a living God always ascribe
to him? Fondly do we hope, fervently do we pray, that this mighty
scourge of war may soon pass away. Yet, if God wills that it continue
till all the wealth piled by the bondman's two hundred and fifty years
of unrequited toil shall be sunk, and until every drop of blood drawn
by the lash shall be paid by another drawn by the sword, as was said
three thousand years ago, so still it must be said, 'The judgments of
the Lord are true and righteous altogether." These words are spoken
with the solemnity of the old prophets who declared the judgments of
God. Was the President the friend of the slave for mere purposes of
state necessity? Was he earnest to carry on the work of emancipation
as a war policy only? Was he moved in his generous act only by tender,
sympathy for sufferers? His words come out with the clear tone of a
heart subdued to a sense of guilt under the law of God, trembling with
the consciousness of the terrors of divine justice, and humbly
<pb n="21" facs="sweetser21.jpg"/>
resigned to the work of that justice in its fearful
threatenings. Without a sincere and exalting faith, such an elevation
of sentiment could hardly be possible. If, when the responsibility was
at first laid upon him, he was unprepared; if, when the question first
demanded his attention, he did not see the solution,--must we not
admit, that he rose to the full level of the emergency, and with all
the strength of his understanding, and with the undeviating firmness
of a heart certain of duty and of God's approbation, gave himself to
the resolved and settled purpose of establishing freedom throughout
the land in all the borders of it? And this will be the consummate
flower in the chaplet of his renown. To him God has given the honor of
writing the decree which spoke liberty to the captive, and opened the
prison-doors to them that were bound. A redeemed race have lifted up
their humble voices to honor his name. In their simple prayers they
have invoked benedictions upon him. Their tears have flowed over his
bier with a fulness and spontaneousness known only to grateful and
broken hearts; and, if it were possible for all other voices to be
dumb, there is one people, whose future life will always be devoted to
the bestowment of honor upon the name of him who was God's hand in
lifting the yoke and breaking the chain of their long oppression.</p>
               <p>An administration has closed with results such as
<pb n="22" facs="sweetser22.jpg"/>
the most sanguine would have held to be Utopian, if they had been
predicted at its commencement. It is sufficient for one man to have
made such progress; to have led so far in the onward march of a mighty
nation; to have done so much to have trained a people for the coming
blessings of liberty, union, and republican government. Our honored,
revered, and now lamented President has ceased from earth. His last
hour found him at a height of power more than kingly, and in the
enjoyment of an affection which kings might envy. From the obscurity
of his origin to the dignity of his ultimate position, the range is
immense. This may be the sport of fortune, the eddies and currents of
life burying one in oblivion, and lifting another to a casual but
envied distinction. But here we behold greatness achieved without the
aid of accident, and glory won in the straight and luminous path of
single-hearted patriotism and single-eyed fidelity. Events have a
power to bear men onward and upward to unexpected posts of honor. But
he is the hero, whose inward energies rise with the tide, and expand
with the swelling current; and who becomes strong in the violence of
commotion, so as ever to be not only master of himself, but also
master of events, by knowing their interpretation, receiving the
lesson, and with a clear eye and firm hand holding all things steady
in the course of destiny. Such a life is an unfolding and a growth of
its own
<pb n="23" facs="sweetser23.jpg"/>
germ, the shooting upward of its stem, the out-spreading of its
branches, by the stimulation and nutrition which its own vitality
gathers in from the soil in which it is set. Such a life pre-eminently
was that which has just now reached the fulness of its maturity. The
period of its activity which has been so turbulent and distracted has
been a period of discipline and development. Every month was marked by
progress, in character and comprehension. Every year added its
increment and expansion. Without a stain from surrounding corruption,
he gained in purity as he rose in power. Never losing the genuine
simplicity of his nature, the more exalted he was in the estimation of
men, the more humble was he, and the more reverent his spirit in the
sight of God. His intellect, as well as his heart, acquired vigor and
force under the perpetual exertion of his powers; so that his highest
efficiency and his most illustrious worth crowned together his
meridian glory. He left the burdens of office and the conflict of life
with a name unsullied by any unworthy deed; with a record of success
as full as ambition itself could covet; with a reputation as
substantial as it was widely spread; and with the universal consent,
that in character and action he had proved equal to the demand of his
high stewardship, and established a fame as ample as the affection he
had inspired. He whom God raised up, and has allowed to do so much,
cannot be said to have
<pb n="24" facs="sweetser24.jpg"/>
lived in vain. Can he be said to have died too soon? We will embalm
his memory in our hearts. We will record his worth and write his name
with the heroes and the nobles of our republic. We will transmit his
deeds as an inheritance to our children. We will elevate his life to
the gaze of the nations. We will present his career as an example to
all men, of integrity, firmness, fidelity to duty, and kindliness of
heart; and his public character to all rulers as a pattern of wisdom
and moderation, and an illustration of the solemn sense of
responsibility which becometh those who are put in authority of
God. By the will of God he has fallen on sleep. He rests from his
labors. He has passed away. But we remain. The country remains. The
Government remains. There are lessons to be learned; there are duties
to be done, and a future to be provided for. Let us remember, that to
confide in our rulers is, as ever, and now pre-eminently, our
imperative duty; to stand by and sustain the Government of our
country, our high concern. The life of the nation is continuous; and
that life is not yet delivered from peril. We have only reached the
banks of the Jordan. Under another leader, we are to be conducted into
the promised land. We are to give to him our allegiance, and with an
earnest co-operation encourage and strengthen his heart. He will need
all the support of our prayers, and the guiding hand of God. Do we
need any other argu-
<pb n="25" facs="sweetser25.jpg"/>
ment to fix this fact upon our consciences than the scenes which have
closed around us with a record so full of God's deliverance? Can we
hesitate to trust and go forward, to gird ourselves to the conflict in
faith and cheerful hope? We miss the great lesson, if we are not
firmer, truer, and more faithful henceforth. One of the conspicuous
and impressive features of our national struggle has been the distinct
manifestations of God's interposition. Events are God's teachers; "the
logic of events" is the line of God's argument. And have not the
events of providence been the sharp points in the controversy which
have pierced out torpid hearts to the quick? Was not the actual insult
upon the flag necessary to arouse us to a consciousness of existing
treason? Was not defeat necessary to reduce the inflation of our
pride, and humble us to a sense of our weakness? Were not the rivers
of blood which have flowed, and the agony of thousands of hearts, the
testimony required to convince us of the deep guilt of the nation,
which God was about to wipe out? The judgments of God are a great
deep: who can fathom them? "If it was necessary, in order to stimulate
a too sensual race to he severe duties before them, that savage
barbarities should be added to the horrors of war, and that thousands
of lives should be wasted by the slow cruelties starvation, may there
not have been a necessity in he last act of fatal wickedness to nerve
the people to
<pb n="26" facs="sweetser26.jpg"/>
a yet deeper trial of fidelity in duty? If, to quicken the pulsations
of a paralyzed patriotism, it was necessary that blood should be drawn
on the NINETEENTH OF APRIL, 1861, may it not have been necessary, in
like manner, in order to fuse all hearts into one great purpose, that
on the NINETEENTH OF APRIL, 1865, the whole prostrate nation should
with weeping and bitter lamentation follow to the grave the man of all
men most deeply beloved, the ruler of all rulers most affectionately
confided in? Shall we say, that the hand of the assassin, which struck
at so noble a life, did it for any fault of his? or shall we say, that
God permitted for a greater good to us, to our country, to posterity,
that the sword, with a sharper edge than ever, should cut to the very
core of our hearts? Let us remember the words of Holy Writ which he
himself repeated in view of the deserved chastisements of the
Almighty: "The judgments of the Lord are true and righteous
altogether." Justice and mercy, though unlike, are harmonious. They
are both the attributes of God, who is love. They both subserve the
great ends of benevolence. It is as necessary to be just, as to be
merciful. It is justice in God that makes him terrible. It is justice
in God that renders him worthy to be trusted. Justice and love unite
in the highest manifestation of God. Justice smote the afflicted
Saviour upon the cross. The majesty of law, outraged by sin, demanded
the sacrifice. Love moved the dying lips
<pb n="27" facs="sweetser27.jpg"/>
of the Son of God in that prayer which will sound through all
time,--an anthem of sweetest tone: "FATHER, FORGIVE THEM, FOR THEY
KNOW NOT WHAT THEY DO." And yet God punishes. God sits upon the
judgment-seat. Therefore the whole earth stands in awe of him. Is it
needful for us to separate justice and mercy? Without justice and
judgment, the majesty of law cannot be vindicated. Without justice
upon offenders, the peace of the community cannot be secured. Without
condign punishment upon evildoers, the wicked will triumph. It is the
teaching of God's oracles, that the ruler beareth not the sword in
vain. He is set to execute vengeance, not in his own name, but as the
instrument appointed of God for this very thing. The land has been
suffering judgments through the wickedness of the wicked that were in
it. Treason and rebellion and barbarity have done their worst. The
spirit which sustained, unabashed, the horrors of oppression from
generation to generation, has yielded the whirlwind of its
seed-time. A cry is going up from the nation, that justice may be
done; that felons and traitors, and the instigators of savage cruelty,
may have the recompense of their deeds. It is right that justice
should have its course upon desperate and incorrigible criminals.  If
this is the duty to which God calls, shall we bold back? If the work
of justice be more dreadful than the work of mercy, yet it must be
done. The work of justice is
<pb n="28" facs="sweetser28.jpg"/>
stern, the deeds of justice are fearful; but the spirit of justice is
not revengeful. It is easy for human nature to pass over the narrow
line which separates between justice and vengeance. It is easy to
supplant the spirit of justice, by the burning passion of unholy
indignation. Let not God's great goodness be thus returned. Let no
malignant passion pollute the stream of our gratitude, or mingle in
the tide of our sorrow. Let not our hope of mercy be so perilled. Let
not the spirit of our lamented chief be so soon forgotten. Let us do
our duty in a calm spirit of inflexible integrity, without discarding
the heavenly instincts of charity. Let us pray that Government may be
sustained in its duty, in its whole, severe duty, true to the demands
of justice, without abjuring the sentiments of humanity; that
punishment may be righteously meted out to whomsoever deserves it,
according to the spirit of the law and the demands of right; so that
salutary fear may seize upon the hearts of evil-doers, and that
traitors and conspirators may no more infest the land. It is necessary
that Government should vindicate its authority and enforce law; and so
secure to itself respect, and command the confidence of the people. It
is equally important that we should be purged of all hateful and
vindictive passion, and that we should address ourselves to the
pressing and momentous duties of the hour in the fear of the Lord.</p>
               <p>We have had a high and noble example. That
<pb n="29" facs="sweetser29.jpg"/>
benignant spirit which has passed away from earth was ever gentle and
yet firm, ever simple and yet wise, ever humble but yet prompt, ever
moderate but always true. We can do him no greater honor than to
remember and follow the words with which he closed his last address to
the American people:--</p>
               <p>"WITH MALICE TOWARDS NONE, WITH CHARITY FOR ALL, WITH FIRMNESS IN
THE RIGHT AS GOD GIVES US TO SEE THE RIGHT, LET US STRIVE ON TO FINISH
THE WORK WE ARE IN; TO BIND UP THE NATION'S WOUNDS; TO CARE FOR HIM
WHO SHALL HAVE BORNE THE BATTLE, AND FOR HIS WIDOW AND HIS
ORPHANS,--TO DO ALL WHICH MAY ACHIEVE AND CHERISH A JUST AND LASTING
PEACE AMONG OURSELVES AND WITH ALL NATIONS."</p>
               <pb n="30" facs="sweetser30.jpg"/>
               <p>BOSTON:</p>
               <p>PRESS OF JOHN WILSON AND SON,</p>
               <p>15, WATER STREET.</p>
            </div2>
         </div1>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>