<TEI.2>
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt n="Discourse on the Death of Abraham Lincoln">
            <title>Discourse on the Death of Abraham Lincoln</title>
            <author>Tousey, Thomas</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Compiled and edited by</resp>
               <name>Beck
Center</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent/>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Lewis H. Beck Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Emory University</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Atlanta,
Georgia</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>1996 Emory
University. Permission is granted to download, transmit, or otherwise
reproduce, distribute or display the contributions to the work claimed
by Emory University for non-profit educational purposes, provided
this header is included in its entirety.  For inquiries about
commercial uses, contact the Director, 
Pitts Theology Library, Emory
University, Atlanta, Georgia 30322</p>
            </availability>
            <date>1999</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Lincoln
Sermons Project</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Tousey,
Thomas. Discourse on the Death of Abraham Lincoln, Preached at the
Presbyterian Church, Palmyra, N. Y., April 19th, 1865.  Rochester,
N.Y. C. D. Tracy &amp; Co., Printers, Evening Express
Office. 1865.</bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This text derives from the Special Collections 
of Pitts Theology Library, Emory University, and is produced in 
collaboration with the Lewis H. Beck Center a, the Emory 
Preservation Office, and Pitts Theology Library.</p>
            <p>TRANSCRIBER: Lewis H. Beck Center and Emory University 
Preservation Office.</p>
            <p>PRODUCER:  BookLab, Inc., 1606 Headway Circle, 
Suite 100, Austin, TX 78754</p>
            <p>CAPTURE DEVICE: XEROX DocuImage 620S flatbed scanner</p>
            <p>CAPTURE DETAILS: Scanner software: XEROX ScanTool 
version 4.2.3; no gamma correction; images are all bitonal.</p>
            <p>CHANGE HISTORY: Using the Adobe Photoshop Batch Processor, 
we interpolated  the original TIFF files to 8-bit grays, 
and altered the resolution to 144 dpi, producing screen 
images twice the original size.  We then saved them in 
JPEG format.  We produced GIF thumbnails from the JPEG files.</p>
            <p>RESOLUTION: 600 ppi</p>
            <p>COMPRESSION: Resolution 144 per inch with Constrain 
Properties to 72 per inch.</p>
            <p>SOURCE: Original documents.</p>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>1999</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Scott Ellis</name>
               <resp>Staff</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <item>SGML tags inserted in compliance
with TEI guidelines using TEILITE</item>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div1 id="tousey.001" n="Discourse on the Death of Abraham Lincoln" type="text">
            <head pn="1"> 
               <bibl> 
                  <title>Discourse on
the Death of Abraham Lincoln</title> 
                  <date>April 19th, 1865</date>
                  <pubPlace>Presbyterian Church, Palmyra, N. Y.</pubPlace>
                  <author>Tousey, Thomas</author> 
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Rochester,
N.Y.</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>C. D. Tracy &amp; Co., Printers, Evening
Express Office</publisher>
                     <date>1865</date>
                  </imprint> 
               </bibl> 
            </head>
            <p pn="1">
               <figure entity="tousey1">
                  <figDesc>1st page of Thomas Tousey's
Discourse on the Death of Abraham Lincoln.</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <p pn="1">Discourse</p>
            <p pn="1">ON THE DEATH OF</p>
            <p pn="1">Abraham Lincoln</p>
            <p pn="1">Preached at the Presbyterian Church, Palmyra, N. Y.</p>
            <p pn="1">April
19th, 1865, by</p>
            <p pn="1">REV. THOMAS TOUSEY,</p>
            <p pn="1">PASTOR OF M.E. CHURCH.</p>
            <p pn="1">PUBLISHED BY REQUEST.</p>
            <p pn="1">ROCHESTER, N. Y.</p>
            <p pn="1">C. D. TRACY &amp; CO., PRINTERS, EVENING EXPRESS OFFICE.</p>
            <p pn="1">1865.</p>
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p pn="2">
               <figure entity="tousey2">
                  <figDesc>2nd page of
Thomas Tousey's Discourse on the Death of Abraham
Lincoln.</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p pn="3">
               <figure entity="tousey3">
                  <figDesc>3rd page of
Thomas Tousey's Discourse on the Death of Abraham
Lincoln.</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <div2 id="tousey.002" n="DISCOURSE." type="sermon">
               <head pn="3">DISCOURSE.</head>
               <epigraph pn="3">
                  <p pn="3">THE JOY OF OUR HEART IS CEASED-OUR DANCE IS TURNED INTO
MOURNING. THE, CROWN IS FALLEN FROM OUR HEAD. WOE UNTO US THAT WE HAVE
SINNED! FOR THIS OUR HEART IS FAINT FOR THESE THINGS OUR EYES ARE
DIM.<hi rend="italic">-Lamentations 5: 15-17.</hi>
                  </p>
               </epigraph>
               <p pn="3">The Bible is a wonderful book. It is God's book and man's book. God
made it and man made it. Just as Christ is verily God and verily man,
so every word is verily divine and verily human. It came not to us
ready written with an angel's plume, but with reeds from the Jordan,
inspired of God, committed to the parchment by man, and thus we have
not only the thoughts and mind of God, and those grand and wonderful
ideas that span eternity, but the emotions, experiences, perplexities,
anxieties, doubts, and oppressive sorrows of men, beautifully blended
in majestic appeal, stern denunciation, overflowing tenderness, or
melodious woe.</p>
               <p pn="3">It appears to me that these words were inspired and given to us for
this very occasion-so appropriately do they describe our condition and
express what seems to me to be the emotions of every heart. "One would
think," says Dr. South, " that every letter was written with a tear
every word the sound of a breaking heart; that the author was
compacted of sorrows, disciplined to grief-one who never breathed but
in sighs, nor spoke but in a groan. 
<pb n="4"/>
                  <figure entity="tousey4">
                     <figDesc>4th page of Thomas
Tousey's Discourse on the Death of Abraham Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
Nor can we too much admire the full and graceful flow of that pathetic
eloquence in which the author pours forth the effusions of a <hi rend="italic">patriotic</hi> heart, and piously weeps over the disasters
of his beloved country. Misery has no expression which the author of
the Lamentations has not employed." Those who tell us that they <hi rend="italic">burn</hi> for their country's welfare, may well look at
the prophecies and history of this extraordinary man-look at his
lamentations-take him through his life to his death, and learn from
him what <hi rend="italic">true Patriotism</hi> means. The man who
watched, prayed and lived for the welfare of his country-who chose to
share her adversities, her sorrows, her wants her afflictions, and
disgrace-when he might have been a companion of princes, and have sat
at the table of kings; who only ceased to live for his country when he
ceased to breathe-was a patriot, in comparison with whom. almost all
others are obscured."</p>
               <p pn="4">The great design of this sacred poem was to teach the suffering
Jews the proper medium between obdurate insensibility and rebellious
despondency under their calamities; to lead them to consider <hi rend="italic">God</hi> as the righteous author, and <hi rend="italic">sin</hi> as the deserving cause of their suffering-to call
them to the exercise of submission, repentance, faith and prayer; to
show them the way of finding support under every trial and benefit
from it; to inspire them with abhorrence of those crimes which had
involved them in such complicated miseries, and with hopes of ultimate
deliverance through the mercy of God.</p>
               <p pn="4">A like object seems befitting a minister of God at such a time as
this. It is no part of his duty to flatter the pride or quiet the
consciences of godless men. Nor is he at
<pb n="5"/>
                  <figure entity="tousey5">
                     <figDesc>5th page of Thomas
Tousey's Discourse on the Death of Abraham Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
liberty to be silent when God commands him to speak. There are times
and circumstances when silence even is <hi rend="italic">treason</hi>. The professed minister of Jesus who
neglects, from any. motive to speak, as the oracles of God speak, is
false to his trust, a traitor to his profession, deserving the
execration of men, and sure to meet the just judgments of the
Almighty.</p>
               <p pn="5">God has two modes of revealing his will to men-one by a written,
the other by an unwritten revelation. The former we call his Word the
latter his Providence. Our text to day is taken from both these
volumes, and if we speak as the Word of God and as the Providence of
God speak, what think you must be the character of the discourse? We
have only to look around us to see the theme which Providence has
selected for us. The tears and sighs of the loyal men, women and
children of a great nation--the banners mourning at half mast--the
churches decked with the weeds of unaffected sorrow--even the private
dwellings clad in the habiliments of mourning and woe--the melancholy
countenances of all classes in society-these are our text to day.</p>
               <p pn="5">But yesterday we were <hi rend="italic">electrified</hi> with
joy. The proud, defiant, strongly fortified city, where treason walked
and swaggered in her boasted strength and security-the capital of the
so-called Southern Confederacy-had yielded to the pressure of the
armies of freedom, and <hi rend="italic">loyal</hi> feet had pressed and
purified the, soil which had been polluted by traitors. The flying foe
were pursued by the nation's chosen general and his brave subordinates
and soldiers, day after day, with untiring tenacity and perseverance,
until the great rebel
<pb n="6"/>
                  <figure entity="tousey6">
                     <figDesc>6th page of Thomas
Tousey's Discourse on the Death of Abraham Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
chieftain struck his colors and surrendered to the indomitable
GRANT.</p>
               <p pn="6">As the cheering news sped on the wings of lightning, in the still
hour of night, a slumbering nation sprung to its feet in such
transports of joy as is seldom the lot of mortals to experience. The
booming cannon, the pealing bells, the exultant and almost frantic
shouts of millions of glad voices were a faint expression of the
gladness that thrilled every loyal heart and beamed from every loyal
eye. Mothers pressed their children to their bosoms with a new and
strange rapture-children danced and sang for joy--fathers wept,
shouted and praised God-old men were inspired with the elasticity of
boyhood's days--young men and maidens were wild with the prevailing
excitement. Bonfires were kindled-cities and villages, hamlets and
private dwellings were illuminated-the glorious Old Flag floated from
millions of spars, church--steeples and dwellings, and the breezes of
heaven seemed to kiss it with unwonted fervor. A day like that was
never known in this land before. None, save here and there a son of
treason or a daughter of rebellion (the Lord pity them), thought the
demonstrations extravagant or wished them less. Each felt that they
were but faint expressions of the joy and gratitude <hi rend="italic">demanded</hi> of a disinthralled and regenerated nation
The night--the long dark night had passed away. The glorious morning
had dawned. The sun in full-orbed glory sprung to the mid-heaven, and
his beams flashed light into every darkened cell. <hi rend="italic">Treason was dead</hi>, and her demon sister, <hi rend="italic">Slavery</hi>, had ceased to breathe. For four long years
we had struggled, and fought, and bled, and watched, and
<pb n="7"/>
                  <figure entity="tousey7">
                     <figDesc>7th page of Thomas
Tousey's Discourse on the Death of Abraham Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
mourned, and waited, and prayed. Battles, and slaughter, and death,
and funerals, and woe, had become our everyday experiences. But now it
was all past. No more long, and dreary marches-no more deadly assaults
or terrible battles for our brave boys. In a little while we will
welcome them home again.</p>
               <lg type="stanza">
                  <l>"Oh these were hours when thrilling joy repaid</l>
                  <l>A long, long course of darkness, doubts and fears;</l>
                  <l>The heart-sick faintness of the hope delayed-</l>
                  <l>The waste, the woe, the bloodshed and the tears</l>
                  <l>That tracked with terror previous rolling years-</l>
                  <l>All was forgot in that blithe jubilee.</l>
                  <l>Her downcast eye even pale Affliction rears,</l>
                  <l>To sigh a thankful prayer amid the glee</l>
                  <l>That hailed the traitor's fall, and peace and liberty."</l>
               </lg>
               <p pn="7">Scarce bad the song of rejoicing died away ere we were again
startled from our slumbers by another message borne upon the flashing
wires. But oh, how different its character! How different the emotions
it excited! ABRAHAM LINCOLN <hi rend="italic">is dead! Fallen by the
hand of a foul assassin!</hi> Never was transition from excessive joy
to grief untold, so sudden. Never before did the heart of the nation
struggle with such throes of agony. <hi rend="italic">Agony</hi>, that
is the word-agony unexpressed and inexpressible-agony unrelieved and
unrelievable by any earthly power. Men were paralyzed. Grief, horror,
indignation, despair, seemed depicted on every countenance. They held
high carnival in every breast. Business was almost involuntarily
suspended. The relish for trade was gone. Even young children wept as
though their hearts would break, and tears flowed freely from eyes
unused to weep. Mourning, lamentation and woe, spread a funeral pall
over a stricken nation. The
<pb n="8"/>
                  <figure entity="tousey8">
                     <figDesc>8th page of Thomas
Tousey's Discourse on the Death of Abraham Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
people wandered with aimless tread along the streets, They knew not
what to do, or what to say, or where to <hi rend="italic">go</hi>. Shocked, stunned, overwhelmed, they seemed like
sheep without a shepherd. "The shepherd was smitten and the flock was
scattered." Truly <hi rend="italic">"the joy of our heart is ceased; our
dance is turned into mourning. The crown is fallen from our head. Woe
unto us that we have sinned! For this our heart is faint-for these
things our eyes are dim."</hi>
               </p>
               <p pn="8">Nor are these evidences of almost frantic grief unwarranted. We had
learned to love and trust ABRAHAM LINCOLN as we have loved and trusted
no man since the days of GEORGE WASHINGTON. Called from comparative
obscurity by the suffrages of a free people, he assumed the duties of
Chief Magistrate at a time of unprecedented peril to our nation. Foul
treason stalked defiantly through the nation's capital. That "mystery
of iniquity" had been working until it had culminated in a bold and
determined attempt to overthrow our government and destroy our
glorious Union. With plans long studied and well matured-with an unity
of purpose, zeal and devotion, worthy a better cause, the leaders and
abettors of treason counted on a short struggle or no struggle at all,
and an easy triumph. All was confusion, worse confounded. Men high in
authority had joined in the conspiracy.</p>
               <p pn="8">I need not trace the history of those dark and tumultuous days. It
is written with fearful distinctness on our memory. We have hardly yet
recovered from the horror and amazement, which almost froze the vital
current of the nation, and settled in sullen gloom and despair upon
every countenance. ABRAHAM LINCOLN appeared upon the scene
<pb n="9"/>
                  <figure entity="tousey9">
                     <figDesc>9th page of Thomas
Tousey's Discourse on the Death of Abraham Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
and the first words that fell from his lips on taking leave of his
friends in Springfield were "fitly spoken," and like apples of gold in
pictures of silver: "A duty devolves upon me, which is, perhaps,
greater than that which has devolved upon any other man since the days
of WASHINGTON. He never would have succeeded but for the aid of Divine
Providence, upon which he at all times relied. I feel that I cannot
succeed without the same Divine aid which sustained him; and in the
same Almighty Being I place my reliance for support. I hope you, my
friends, will all pray, that I may receive that Divine assistance,
without which I cannot succeed, but with which success is certain."</p>
               <p pn="9">Oh, how did such devout language recall the memory of those godly
men of old, who by faith and prayer,  " subdued kingdoms, wrought
righteousness, obtained promises, stopped the mouths of lions,
quenched the violence of fire, escaped the edge of the sword, out of
weakness were made strong waxed valiant in fight, turned to flight the
armies of the aliens." Courage inspired the heart of the nation. It
breathed easier. Through the darkness and storms along our dangerous
way-over mountains steep and rugged, and bare-under God, he has led us
in safety during the four years of unparalleled anxiety, through which
we have just passed.</p>
               <p pn="9">I have neither time, ability, nor heart to attempt a sketch of his
character, or to write his eulogy. I believe he was raised up for the
duties and responsibilities of his day by the same hand which is so
clearly visible in all the past of our history-that in answer to the
prayers and supplications 
<pb n="10"/>
                  <figure entity="tousey10">
                     <figDesc>10th page of Thomas
Tousey's Discourse on the Death of Abraham Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
of a prostrate people, he has been divinely guided in the discharge of
those duties. The careful prudence, the almost omniscient sagacity,
the firm decision, and the invincible integrity which have
characterized nearly his every official act, must have had a higher
source and a stronger support than merely human endowments could
give.</p>
               <p pn="10">But it is comparatively easy to recognize God's hand in events that
are past, and results that are known. It is in times like these, when
"He removeth the mountains and they know not when He overturneth them
in His anger--when He shaketh the earth out of her place and the
pillars thereof tremble--when He commandeth the sun, and it riseth not
and sealeth up the stars, "that we sigh and struggle in our
bewilderment; that "He goeth by us and we see Him not--He passeth on,
also, and we perceive Him not." We are prone to regard favors and
blessings as coming from God, while we forget that calamities and
judgments are from the same infinite source.</p>
               <p pn="10">The great comprehensive lesson taught throughout the Word of God,
written in flaming capitals on every event of Providence, and
reiterated by the million voices of past history, is, that "<hi rend="italic">the Lord God omnipotent reigneth</hi>."</p>
               <p pn="10">Far back in the annals of time, He distinctly announced His
determination to reduce men and nations to a practical acknowledgment
of His supremacy, and all along the track of ages past, He has erected
monuments, more enduring than brass or marble, and on them re-written
this determination. Still with many, even in Christian lands, this
doctrine is a mere "theoretic abstraction, a soulless idea, judged to
be necessary, perhaps, to complete the symmetry
<pb n="11"/>
                  <figure entity="tousey11">
                     <figDesc>11th page of Thomas
Tousey's Discourse on the Death of Abraham Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
of their ideal system, but of no practical utility in the
matter-of-fact occurrences of every day life. Their God is a God
without a sceptre, without an empire, without a moral law, and without
a judgment throne. If they allow Him personality, it is less the
personality of a distinct, conscious, intelligent, active Ruler and
Judge than the poetic personality that the bard gives to his own ideal
creations." To such the voice of God has no significance-the reality
of providential interpositions is doubted or denied, and those eternal
principles which underlie His throne and ensure the stability of the
universe are utterly ignored. But He reigns, nevertheless, and will
reign, despite the covert scepticism or undisguised rebellion of
men. Traitors will not subvert His government, the assassin will never
reach His throne. "Clouds and darkness are round about
Him. Righteousness and judgment are the habitation of His throne. A
fire burneth before Him and burneth up His enemies round about. His
lightnings enlightened the world-the earth saw and trembled. The hills
melted like wax at the presence of the Lord, at the presence of the
Lord of the whole earth. The heavens declare His righteousness and all
the people see His glory."</p>
               <p pn="11">The same great principles which have governed His administration in
ages past, govern Him still. They are changeless-eternal. It is not
difficult then to trace substantially the line of consequences which
must result from any given course pursued by any people. "Woe unto us,
that we have sinned", is the inspired rule which connects cause and
effect, and binds them together with the chains of God's
omnipotence. In case of continual sin and impeni-
<pb n="12"/>
                  <figure entity="tousey12">
                     <figDesc>12th page of Thomas
Tousey's Discourse on the Death of Abraham Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
tence, it is as vain to endeavor to escape the everlasting
consequences of our course as to dethrone the Eternal. "Human skill
cannot match infinite wisdom, and what sinful finite will measure arms
with the Almighty? Who can thunder with a voice like His? Who can
dodge the invisible sword that glitters in the hand of Divine justice?
What domain is so broad that He cannot sweep it with His illimitable
armies? What mountain barriers so lofty that He cannot scale them?
What fortress so impregnable that He cannot force an entrance? Did the
pride of Edom ever climb so high, that vengeance could not reach  to
pull it down? Did they hew their hiding places so deep in the mountain
cliffs that the band of retribution could not drag them out? Was the
seven-hilled city so mighty that it could not be desolated? And
Athens, and Corinth, and Thebes, and Troy, and Carthage, Damascus of
the plain Tyre by the sea, Tadmor of the desert, and Jerusalem among
the hills--were any of these able to resist the going forth of
retributive vengeance? And have we, with our exhaustless wealth, our
boundless resources, Our countless numbers, our boasted courage and
invincible strength, been able to escape the terrible scourge, which
has come to vindicate God's insulted majesty? Let the wasted wealth,
the desolated homes, the bleeding hearts, the bloody fields of carnage
and death, answer.</p>
               <p pn="12">For years past it has required no prophet's ken to discover
unmistakable indications of the gathering storm which has swept the
land with such wide wasting ruin. Any one who had any just conception
of God as a Ruler and Judge, who has declared that He "will be exalted
in the earth,"
<pb n="13"/>
                  <figure entity="tousey13">
                     <figDesc>13th page of Thomas
Tousey's Discourse on the Death of Abraham Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
could have discovered premonitions of coming and terrible
judgments. The countless evidences of political corruption, the
shameless disregard of the simplest morals by men high in official
station, and above all-in all and through all the startling fact of a
great and growing nation, consenting that her power and influence
should be employed to sustain, perpetuate, extend, legalize and even
<hi rend="italic">baptize</hi> and <hi rend="italic">christianize</hi> a
system of slavery, born in hell-nourished in the Southern
Confederacy-until it became too black for even devils to tolerate!
These, and such as these, were evidences clear as sunlight and
unmistakable as the oracles of heaven that a terrible retribution <hi rend="italic">would come</hi>. Treason, rebellion and civil war, are but
the legitimate outgrowth of such stupendous iniquity; for "out of the
serpent's root shall come forth a cockatrice, and his fruit shall be a
fiery, flying serpent."</p>
               <p pn="13">We had no excuse for thus denying and insulting God. From the first
He has watched over us with more than parental solicitude. He has
rocked us in the cradle of blessings and nursed us on the bosom of
piety. Amid the storm of elements, the howling wilderness, the savage
foe, what could have saved us from extinction but the hand of God? And
when for seven long years we tracked our way to liberty with bleeding
feet was not God our Friend? Did He not set the day-star of freedom on
the brow of the firmament to cheer our desolate spirits? And when we
were permitted to repose on the basis of a free constitution, enjoy
privileges bought with blood, and a prosperity which contrasted
strongly with the afflictions of our youth, was lit honorable in us to
forget we were children of Providence,
<pb n="14"/>
                  <figure entity="tousey14">
                     <figDesc>14th page of Thomas
Tousey's Discourse on the Death of Abraham Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
and that we turned against our foster-mother, true religion, and
talked and acted as though we no longer needed her aid? At various
stages of our history the angel of retribution passed over the
land. At different times the pestilence that walketh in darkness, and
the destruction that wasteth at noon-day, swept to an untimely grave
multitudes of young and old. Financial revulsions of alarming
magnitude suspended, business and paralyzed trade; and <hi rend="italic">twice</hi> before has the "Angel of Death spread his wings
on the blast," and buried the nation in mourning for loved and honored
Chief Magistrates. Surely there is no excuse for such blind
forgetfulness of God, and such glaring disregard of His righteous
law. His name is written and His hand is seen on every page of our
past history.</p>
               <p pn="14">Nor is it at all strange or any departure from God's ancient ways
that the punishment due for the accumulated guilt of three-quarters of
a century should be meted out to us in the untold horrors of the past
four years of bloody, fratricidal war. If His retributions on nations
were equally distributed along the years of their sin, they might pass
wholly unobserved, just as His electricity in the heavens, while
evenly. diffused, attracts no attention. It is only when He gathers it
up in His thunderbolts and hurls them from His Almighty hand, that men
tremble and stand in awe before. His appalling majesty and power. So
the terrible enormity, the deep and damning guilt of American slavery
could never have been fully realized, or the glaring crime adequately
atoned for, or the heart of the nation. sufficiently aroused to wipe
out the foul stain upon her
<pb n="15"/>
                  <figure entity="tousey15">
                     <figDesc>15th page of Thomas
Tousey's Discourse on the Death of Abraham Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
escutcheon, only by the blasting scourge of war. God saw this and
hence His red, right hand of vengeance was called forth to the
accomplishment of the work.</p>
               <p pn="15">President LINCOLN came to see this. His clear, penetrating mind-his
great and noble heart, were intent upon the study of the foundation
principles of God's administration, until he grasped the mighty truth,
and it opened with celestial clearness to his vision. The turning
point in the history of his administration-the pivot on which the
destiny of the nation hung suspended-the great crowning act of his
life, which will go down to future ages, as the brightest spot in
American history-was when he planted his feet on the eternal rock of
God's immutable justice, and <hi rend="italic">proclaimed Liberty
through all the land to all the inhabitants thereof!</hi> From that
day anew life has inspirited the nation. From that day the armies of
the Union have been, in the main, victorious. From that day the power
of treason, has waned, until scarcely a vestige remains to oppose the
cohorts of freedom.</p>
               <p pn="15">The last Inaugural of our lamented Chief Magistrate sounds
marvellously like the utterances of those holy men of old, who spake
as they were moved by the Holy Ghost. We seem, while reading it, to be
listening to the voice of Isaiah or Jeremiah as, they uttered the mind
of God to his ancient people:-"The Almighty has His own purposes. 'Woe
unto the world because of offences, for it must needs be that offences
come, but woe to that man by whom the offence, cometh.' We may suppose
that American slavery is one of these offences, which in the
Providence of God must needs come, but which, having continued through
<pb n="16"/>
                  <figure entity="tousey16">
                     <figDesc>16th page of Thomas
Tousey's Discourse on the Death of Abraham Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
His appointed time, He now wills to remove; and He gives to both North
and South this terrible war as the woe due to those by whom the
offence came. Shall we discern that there is any departure from those
Divine attributes which the believers in a living God always ascribe
to Him? Fondly do we hope--fervently do we pray--that this mighty
scourge of war may speedily pass away. Yet if God will that it
continue until all the wealth, piled by the bondman's two hundred and
fifty years of unrequited toil, shall be sunk, and until every drop of
blood drawn by the lash shall be paid with another drawn with the
sword; as was said three thousand years ago, so still it must be said
that the judgments of the Lord are true and righteous altogether.'
With malice toward none--with charity for all--with firmness for the
right, as God gives us to see the right-let us strive on to finish the
work we are in--to bind up the nation's wounds, and care for him who
shall have borne the battle, and for his widows and orphans-to do all
which may achieve and cherish a just and lasting peace among
ourselves-among all nations."</p>
               <p pn="16">These thoughts and words will live forever, for they are God's
thoughts and many of them His words. They ought to be written with the
point of a diamond on the heart of the American people. Encircled with
a halo of glory they should be inscribed among the stars of our
country's banner. They will be quoted with reverence when the men of
this generation are dead, and read with rapture by millions yet
unborn. From the hut of poverty--from the palace of wealth--from the
gloomy dungeon-from the hall of justice--by the oppressed and
down-trodden--by the free and
<pb n="17"/>
                  <figure entity="tousey17">
                     <figDesc>17th page of Thomas
Tousey's Discourse on the Death of Abraham Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
prosperous-wherever God is known and His law regarded, a voice of
gratitude and melody will be heard rising to heaven in thankfulness
that their author ever lived. <hi rend="italic">But he is dead!</hi> The
clear and penetrating intellect revolves and thinks in its earthly
sphere no more. The warm and noble heart that dictated them is
pulseless now. The hand that wrote them is palsied, and the lips that
uttered them are sealed with an everlasting frost. A nation weeps as
she has never wept before. Nay, the great throbbing heart of humanity,
world-wide, is pressed with a weight of sorrow, such as she has seldom
borne before.</p>
               <p pn="17">We have lost not only a wise, sagacious, God-fearing ruler, but a
<hi rend="italic">personal friend!</hi> ABRAHAM LINCOLN was the friend
of humanity--"the friend of God." He was your friend. He was my
friend. Color did not exclude from his presence or kindly
offices. Poverty was no bar even to intimacy with him. One of the
people, he did not suffer the dignities of official station to dim the
finer qualities of the man, the friend, the Christian. I doubt whether
the heart of any <hi rend="italic">loyal</hi> man in the land would
suffer greater anguish at the death of the dearest personal friend,
than it suffers to day.</p>
               <p pn="17">But in our grief that such a man is dead, we should not forget to
be grateful to God that such a man has lived. As God raised up Moses
to be the great leader and deliverer, of his people, Israel, so he
raised up ABRAHAM LINCOLN to guide our ship of state over the stormy
sea of political strife, and through the terrible breakers of
secession and civil war to the quiet and safe harbor of peace,
union. and liberty. Let us not forget that He gave us such a man, at
<pb n="18"/>
                  <figure entity="tousey18">
                     <figDesc>18th page of Thomas
Tousey's Discourse on the Death of Abraham Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
such a time, and that He preserved him alive until the death knell of
rebellion was sounded--, and the angel of peace, with her wings of
light, was hovering over a regenerated land.</p>
               <p pn="18">But who has done this deed? Not <hi rend="italic">Booth</hi>, wretch
and miscreant that he is-not he alone. He only gave expression to a
spirit deeper, darker-more nearly allied to hell than even murder or
assassination-the <hi rend="italic">spirit of slavery, secession, and
treason!</hi> The aggregations of every thing false, criminal,
malignant, devilish-as exemplified in the brief history of the
Southern Confederacy. A darker page than ever before disgraced the
annals of time must now be, added to the world's history. The
barbarism of the darkest ages and of the lowest and most degraded
savages appears almost humane in comparison. With a pen dipped in the
burning lake, and a scroll of infamy plucked from the centre of
Pandemonium should the dark record be written. Would that for
humanity's sake it could be blotted forever from the memory of men or
God. But there it stands, and will stand, black with inconceivable
infamy and covered with untold horrors. This cowardly assassination is
only one of a long catalogue of crimes instigated by this diabolical
spirit. ABRAHAM LINCOLN is only another martyr to the cause of
freedom, and another victim of this foul conspiracy against God and
humanity.</p>
               <p pn="18">What else could be expected from a class of fiends in human shape?
I will not call them men, who have for years past rioted in wealth,
wrought from the tears, groans, sighs, blood, and outraged virtue of
their fellow-man-who have been schooled in lowest vice, and educated
in blackest
<pb n="19"/>
                  <figure entity="tousey19">
                     <figDesc>19th page of Thomas
Tousey's Discourse on the Death of Abraham Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
crime from their infancy--whose heart is treason, and breath
pollution. Men who can deliberately, and with set purpose, murder by
the slow torture of starvation tens of thousands of innocent prisoners
who have fallen into their hands by the fortunes of war! Surely those
who look for any thing better from them have not deeply studied the
laws of cause and effect in morals, or calculated rightly the force of
evil in a heart depraved.</p>
               <p pn="19">And now, that the rebellion is substantially crushed--now that the
war is practically over--what shall be our treatment of the authors
and leaders of, the rebellion--the murderers of our noble President?
Shall a weak, dangerous and wicked leniency prevail? Shall they be
flattered, feted, lionized, and welcomed back to the privileges and
immunities of citizenship, like "erring brethren" who have only been
guilty of a little indiscretion under the heat of passion? Let the
earth, red with the blood of patriots, answer. Let the million broken
hearts all over the land answer. Let the voiceless graves of our brave
sons, husbands and fathers answer. Let the cold, silent form of our
murdered President answer. Let the spirits of those ancient worthies
who fought, and bled, and died to bequeath to us this glorious
heritage of freedom answer. Nay! let mercy, humanity, justice, GOD,
answer.</p>
               <p pn="19">If I mistake not, here is our chief peril now. It is not safe to
trust men guilty of murder and treason for devils are devils still in
hell or heaven. When God shall welcome Satan back to heaven, <hi rend="italic">then</hi> it may be safe; <hi rend="italic">but not till
then!</hi> When nature's laws can be broken and the offender escape
the penalty--when the eternal principles of mercy and
<pb n="20"/>
                  <figure entity="tousey20">
                     <figDesc>20th page of Thomas
Tousey's Discourse on the Death of Abraham Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
justice can be overthrown and no calamities result-when law and order
give place to anarchy and disorder, and no evil ensue--then it may be
safe to let leading traitors go unhung--but not till then.</p>
               <p pn="20">Generations past and generations to come, will hold us accountable
for a strict, a firm, and a righteous policy towards these engineers
of the darkest plot against human happiness that any age or any clime
has witnessed. A grand license will be taken out. by all the ring
-leaders of ruffianism and anarchy the world over, if they are allowed
to infer from our policy in this crisis, that the failure of' their
nefarious plans may involve but a few of their subordinates in ruin,
while the leaders get off safely in a sort of magnificent haze of
daring criminality. Interests too vast and far-reaching are pending;
principles too high and sacred are involved to admit of a policy so
certainly ruinous. It cannot, must not, shall not be. Our fathers from
behind admonish us with their anxious, paternal voices. Posterity
calls to us from the bosom of the future. The world turns hither with
its solicitous eyes. All, all conjure us, by all that is dear and
sacred in the past; by all that is hopeful and inspiring in the
future, and by all that is high and holy in principle, to act wisely,
firmly, justly, ill matters so momentous.</p>
               <p pn="20">When the startling news of this terrible calamity first fell upon
my ear, I said the American people will yet learn that <hi rend="italic">treason is a crime</hi>. I have seen no reason yet to
alter or amend that opinion. There was danger before. We were "losing
a just appreciation of the awful crimes of this rebellion." It seemed
doubtful whether Gen. GRANT or
<pb n="21"/>
                  <figure entity="tousey21">
                     <figDesc>21st page of Thomas
Tousey's Discourse on the Death of Abraham Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
Gen. LEE was to be the hero of our times. But this fresh and horrible
outbreak of the Satanic character of the rebellion has already aroused
anew the American heart and kindled afresh the slumbering fires of our
patriotism. "Our President is dead-but the Republic lives," and his
precious blood will cement the heart of the nation as it was never
cemented before. Our institutions are dearer to us for every drop of
patriot blood that has been shed in their defence. How shall then
their value be enhanced a million fold since they have cost the
nation's best and most precious heart's blood!</p>
               <p pn="21">The blood of the martyrs has ever been the seed of the church and
the blood of martyred freemen--of martyred LINCOLN--will generate a
host of earnest patriots that can not be trifled with. I have not the
faintest idea, nor is there, in my opinion, the slightest foundation
for the assumption that President LINCOLN would have favored the
lenient, self-destroying policy of pardoning and restoring to
citizenship leading traitors with their hands reeking in patriot
gore. His past course contradicts such an assumption. He was too wise
a statesman, too merciful and just a man, and too good a Christian, to
pursue such a suicidal policy. He would never have done it, and in
murdering him the rebellion has but heightened its guilt and
accelerated its doom. As certain as the ordinances of heaven, and as
swift as the lightnings of God, a just and righteous retribution shall
overtake them.</p>
               <p pn="21">Too well we know that "we can never secure indemnity for the past,
for our wasted treasure and blood more precious than gold;" but by the
help of God, we will "exact
<pb n="22"/>
                  <figure entity="tousey22">
                     <figDesc>22nd page of Thomas
Tousey's Discourse on the Death of Abraham Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
ample security for the future." Security for the future--that is
all. Nothing from malice, nothing from revenge. I have no personal
hate towards even a rebel. I would feed him and bind up his wounds,
and point him to the Lamb of God, who taketh away the sin of the
world, and if the blood of Jesus could cleanse his damning stains
away, I would welcome him to the realms of endless peace, if that were
my prerogative. But as a citizen, I could never trust him again, even
though the oath of allegiance were uttered by his perjured
lips. President LINCOLN had no personal ill-will towards traitors. His
large, loving heart was incapable of such passion, and for this the
crime of the rebellion was the greater, Traitors must know-the world
must know, that <hi rend="italic">treason</hi> is considered a <hi rend="italic">crime</hi> in America; and hereafter when men shall
contemplate the disruption of the Republic, they must see the frowning
gallows and a yawning hell before them of deter them from such
stupendous villiany.</p>
               <p pn="22">I am happy to believe that such a policy will be pursued; and as a
pledge of this, hear a few sentences from the last public speech of
ANDREW JOHNSON, who now occupies the post of trust and responsibility,
made vacant by the assassination of ABRAHAM LINCOLN. "When you ask me
what I would do with such traitors, my reply is, I would arrest
them. I would try them. I would convict them, and I would hang
them. As humble as I am and have been, I have pursued but one
undeviating course. All that I have, life, limb and property, have
been put at the disposal of the country in this great struggle. I have
been in camp, I have been in the field, I have been, everywhere where
this
<pb n="23"/>
                  <figure entity="tousey23">
                     <figDesc>23rd page of Thomas
Tousey's Discourse on the Death of Abraham Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
great rebellion is; I have pursued it till I believe I can now see,
its termination. Since the world began, there has never been a
rebellion of such gigantic proportions, so infamous in character, so
diabolical in motive, so entirely disregard- ful of the laws of
civilized warfare. It has introduced the most savage mode of warfare
ever practiced upon earth. My notion is, that treason must be made
odious, and the traitors must be punished and impoverished; their
social power broken; and they must be made to feel the penalty of
their crimes. I am in favor of leniency, but in my opinion, evil doers
should be punished. Treason is the highest crime known in the
catalogue of crimes, and for him that is guilty of it--for him that is
willing to lift his impious hand against the authority of the nation,
I would say death is too easy a punishment. I say this--the halter to
intelligent, influential traitors but to the honest boy, the deluded
man, who has been deceived into the rebel ranks, I would extend
leniency. I would say, 'return to your allegiance; renew your support
to the government, and became a good citizen; but the <hi rend="italic">leaders</hi> I would hang. We have put down the traitors
in arms; let us put them down in public judgment, and in the morals of
the world."</p>
               <p pn="23">Brave words---and true, and just, and right! God bless ANDREW
JOHNSON and preserve him to carry out to the fullest extent the policy
thus indicated!</p>
               <p pn="23">And now, my countrymen-under the impressive solemnities of this sad
hour-amid the tears and sighs of a stricken nation--around the open
grave of our murdered but glorified President--with the spirits of
Washington,
<pb n="24"/>
                  <figure entity="tousey24">
                     <figDesc>24th page of Thomas
Tousey's Discourse on the Death of Abraham Lincoln.</figDesc>
                  </figure>
ADAMS and JEFFERSON, and a host of other worthies of, Revolutionary
days looking down upon us, and the eye of the world intently
glazing--nay, with the Searcher of Hearts scanning our motives and
ascertaining the exact measure of our sincerity and loyalty, let us
encircle the holy altar of <hi rend="italic">Freedom</hi>, GOD, and our
<hi rend="italic">Country</hi>, and thereof consecrate anew "our lives,
our fortunes, and our sacred honor." God help us. Amen.</p>
            </div2>
         </div1>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI.2>