<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader><fileDesc>
         <titleStmt n="A Discourse in Memory of our Late President, Abraham Lincoln">
            <title>A Discourse in Memory of our Late President, Abraham Lincoln</title>
            <author>Tucker, J. T.</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Compiled and edited by</resp>
               <name>Beck Center</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent/>
         <publicationStmt><publisher>Lewis H. Beck Center</publisher><pubPlace>Emory University</pubPlace><address>
               <addrLine>Atlanta,
Georgia</addrLine>
            </address><availability>
               <p>1996 Emory
University. Permission is granted to download, transmit, or otherwise
reproduce, distribute or display the contributions to the work claimed
by Emory University for non-profit educational purposes, provided
this header is included in its entirety.  For inquiries about
commercial uses, contact the Director, 
Pitts Theology Library, Emory
University, Atlanta, Georgia 30322</p>
            </availability><date>1999</date></publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Lincoln
Sermons Project</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Tucker,
J. T. A Discourse in Memory of our Late President, Abraham Lincoln,
Delivered in the First Parish Church, Holliston, Mass., Thursday, June
1, 1865. Holliston: Plimpton &amp; Clark. 1865.</bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc><encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This text derives from the Special Collections 
of Pitts Theology Library, Emory University, and is produced in 
collaboration with the Lewis H. Beck Center a, the Emory 
Preservation Office, and Pitts Theology Library.</p>
            <p>TRANSCRIBER: Lewis H. Beck Center and Emory University 
Preservation Office.</p>
            <p>PRODUCER:  BookLab, Inc., 1606 Headway Circle, 
Suite 100, Austin, TX 78754</p>
            <p>CAPTURE DEVICE: XEROX DocuImage 620S flatbed scanner</p>
            <p>CAPTURE DETAILS: Scanner software: XEROX ScanTool 
version 4.2.3; no gamma correction; images are all bitonal.</p>
            <p>CHANGE HISTORY: Using the Adobe Photoshop Batch Processor, 
we interpolated  the original TIFF files to 8-bit grays, 
and altered the resolution to 144 dpi, producing screen 
images twice the original size.  We then saved them in 
JPEG format.  We produced GIF thumbnails from the JPEG files.</p>
            <p>RESOLUTION: 600 ppi</p>
            <p>COMPRESSION: Resolution 144 per inch with Constrain 
Properties to 72 per inch.</p>
            <p>SOURCE: Original documents.</p>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc><revisionDesc><change><name>Stewart Varner</name> transformed this document from p4 to p5 on <date when="2010-03-22">March 22, 2010</date></change><change xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><date>1999</date><label>Staff</label><name>Scott Ellis</name>SGML tags inserted in compliance
with TEI guidelines using TEILITE</change></revisionDesc></teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div1 xml:id="tucker.001" n="A Discourse in Memory of our Late President, Abraham Lincoln" type="text">
            <head> 
               <bibl> 
                  <title>A Discourse in
Memory of our Late President, Abraham Lincoln </title> 
                  <date>Thursday,
June 1, 1865</date> 
                  <pubPlace>First Parish Church, Holliston,
Mass.</pubPlace> 
                  <author>Tucker, J. T.</author> 
                  
                     <pubPlace>Holliston</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Plimpton &amp;
Clark</publisher>
                     <date>1865</date>
                   
               <idno type="ark">http://pid.emory.edu/ark:/25593/15rc5</idno></bibl> 
            </head>
            <pb facs="tucker1.jpg"/>
            <p>A</p>
            <p>DISCOURSE</p>
            <p>IN MEMORY OF OUR LATE PRESIDENT,</p>
            <p>ABRAHAM LINCOLN,</p>
            <p>DELIVERED IN THE</p>
            <p>FIRST PARISH CHURCH, HOLLISTON, MASS.,</p>
            <p>THURSDAY, JUNE 1, 1865,</p>
            <p>By J. T. TUCKER,</p>
            <p>PASTOR.</p>
            <p>HOLLISTON:</p>
            <p>PLIMPTON &amp; CLARK.</p>
            <p>1865.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tucker2.jpg"/>
            <p>NOTE.</p>
            <p>Fully satisfied as I am of the justness of the conclusions reached
in this discourse, my purpose in giving it to the public is not so
much to declare my own individual opinions, as thus to become the
medium of expressing the judgment, on our present affairs, of a large
number of intelligent and influential hearers, by whose request these
pages are sent to the press.</p>
            <p>	J.T. TUCKER.</p>
            <p>LAWNSIDE,</p>
            <p>Holliston,</p>
            <p>June 5th, 1865.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tucker3.jpg"/>
            <div2 xml:id="tucker.002" n="DISCOURSE." type="sermon">
               <head>DISCOURSE.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <p>LAMENTATIONS 4: 20.</p>
                  <p>"THE BREATH OF OUR NOSTRILS, THE ANOINTED OF THE LORD, WAS TAKEN IN
THEIR PITS, OF WHOM WE SAID, UNDER HIS SHADOW WE SHALL LIVE AMONG THE
HEATHEN."</p>
               </epigraph>
               <p>In these mournful strains, the Hebrew prophet and poet bewailed the
captivity of the last of the kings of Judah, taken captive by his
enemies and carried sightless and chained like a slave or a wild
beast, to Babylon. That fallen prince had brought this heavy judgment
upon his own head, by his abominable crimes. Yet, though he had proved
himself so utterly unworthy the lineage and crown of David, the
prophet chants his requiem as the selected chief magistrate of the
Jewish land, the Anointed of the Lord as the ruler of the people, set
up by Providence as the great rock under the shadow of which the
nation should dwell, in dignity and safety, among its neighbors. His
throne, his kingdom, his life had paid the penalty of his sins: but
the man of God drops a tear at his memory, as the son of Jesse wept
over Saul--the beauty of Israel slain upon its high places. If, then,
the Spirit of inspiration has sung such elegies over the great, bad
princes of the people, how justly may we repeat them, as to day we
mourn the loss and honor the name of our great, good President: "The
breath of our nostrils, the Anointed of the Lord, was taken in their
pits, of whom we said, under his shadow we shall live among the
nations."<ref target="#tucker.002.n01">*</ref></p>
               <p>We assemble at this hour, under a proclamation sent forth</p>
               <note xml:id="tucker.002.n01" n="*" place="foot" anchored="true">
                  <p>The words, <hi rend="italic">heathen</hi> and <hi rend="italic">nations</hi>, were used interchangeably by the early
Jews. All other nations, <hi rend="italic">ethnoi</hi>, to them were
heathen. V. LXX. <hi rend="italic">in loco</hi>.</p>
               </note>
               <pb n="4" facs="tucker4.jpg"/>
               <p>to all the loyal people of this Republic, by its present Executive,
summoning us to a memorial service for him, the late occupant of that
high station, so ruthlessly cut off in the midst of his days. In the
first gush of our sorrow and our indignation because of this atrocity,
we waited not for any official prompting to pour forth our grief in
tremulous, glowing words of mingled emotion, as the irrepressible
bidding of our hearts draped our homes and our sanctuaries in the
weeds of a national funeral. Let no one say that those manifestations
of regret, of anguish were premature, were superficial. Every day of
the interval since elapsed has only justified and strengthened
them. If space gained for reflection upon that awful deed of shame has
begun to disclose in what ways an overruling Providence can turn it to
good account in our future career, this does not go a hair's breadth
toward changing our feelings, then first spontaneously expressed,
concerning our common bereavement and its unutterably wicked cause. It
is well, that, after these weeks of meditation and observation, we are
drawn again, in this formal manner, to a reviewal of God's recent
dealing with us. The annals of our country furnish one close
historical parallel to the present occasion. When our first President
died, than whom scarcely any mortal man was ever more venerated and
beloved by millions, the Congress of the original States requested his
successor to recommend, by proclamation, "to the people of the United
States to assemble, on the twenty-second day of February next, in such
numbers and manner as may be convenient, publicly to testify their
grief for the death of General George Washington, by suitable
eulogies, orations, and discourses, or by public prayers." How that
day was solemnized, some among us still recollect. It is equally, and
I will venture to say, it is even more fitting, that this nation
to-day build up a monument of honest, truthful words commemorative of
our last great chief, which shall also help to keep his virtues, and
his noble quarrel with gigantic wrong, fresh and fragrant in the
memories of our children, and our children's children.</p>
               <pb n="5" facs="tucker5.jpg"/>
               <p>If the labor which we thus assume be difficult, it is not because
the subject in itself is either intricate or obscure. Within the whole
range of my historical reading, I know of no public character more
thoroughly transparent, more readily understood than that of our late
President. From the first advent of Mr. Lincoln on the political
stage, until the curtain dropped so suddenly, he carried his heart (so
to speak) pinned upon his sleeve, where every one could see it, just
as it was from day to day. He had no concealments. Every step which he
took in his political education became the public property almost as
soon as he became aware of it himself. There is a most unusual
simplicity about his life almost a child's life to the last, yet in
the manliest proportions. This makes it no easy thing to speak rightly
and intelligently of this mightier than kingly potentate, who wielded
more than the power of a Louis XIV, with the artless rectitude, the
child-like directness, of an Edward VI.</p>
               <p>And this was an anomaly in the nineteenth century. By reason of bad
examples and sophistical theorizings, the idea of state-craft has come
to be mainly localized in the last half of that suggestive
word. Statesmanship has degenerated into state-cunning, has become the
science of finesse, the art of looking one way and rowing another,
like the water-man whose face is always the reverse of his
progress. But Abraham Lincoln always looked and rowed in the same
direction. And men whose political school had taught them only the
game of hide and seek, could not comprehend his open, plain-spoken
policy. Surely, there was a change from the White House atmosphere of
eighteen hundred fifty-three and nine, to that of eighteen hundred
sixty-one and five. It was like getting out of the dim and cob-webbed
crypts of an Egyptian pyramid up to the pure air and free vision of
its glorious summit.</p>
               <p>The nation felt it, and loved and honored the man who had taken off
the stricture from their lungs, the bandage from their eyes. It is a
grand thing to look at--how heartily the
<pb n="6" facs="tucker6.jpg"/>
millions will rally around a leader who shows himself worthy of their
trust. They have been cheated so often and so bitterly, from the days
of Saul to the last Napoleon, that you would think they never would
venture again to confide over much in a new candidate for their
reliance. But they will, where they see their way. Modern history
gives no finer instance of this than the record of our last four
years. Mr. Lincoln had won the hearts of the loyal citizenship of this
Republic so absolutely, that he was the personal friend as well as the
lawful chief magistrate of his constituents. It was their willing
tribute, not to brilliancy of mind or profoundness of statesmanly
acquirements, but to genuine goodness. Two words might fitly grace his
monument--the Beloved and the Trusted. Were not this a royal
epitaph?</p>
               <p>The seed of this character was in a peculiarly fortunate
combination of constitutional qualities: it was as fortunately guarded
and nourished by the circumstances of his early life. That Western
home, so free from the dwarfing influences of artificial mannerisms,
from the cramping power of a false refinement, was just the place to
develop a muscular body, and as muscular and masculine a soul. He was
poor enough to be compelled to work hard, to plan closely, for a
position in life. But there were no overgrown lords of the soil or of
society to crowd the growing nature into deformity. The young man made
his way up into notice against such obstacles as are common and
largely unavoidable in a new country. A rough life it is, but a
wholesome one. It did not give him the finish of a university
training, nor did it corrupt his spirit with chicanery, duplicity,
selfish ambition or vicious tastes. Abraham Lincoln's first
twenty-five or thirty years were very much like George Washington's,
in their demand for self-reliance. And they fostered substantially the
same manly probity and purity.</p>
               <p>A few years include all that history will claim of Mr. Lincoln's
career. Within a decade his name begun to meet our eye in the public
journals, as a shrewd, popular, self educated
<pb n="7" facs="tucker7.jpg"/>
Illinois attorney, who was taking the field as a political antagonist
of slave-extension in our country. Since then, his life has been a
unit in its purpose, law and end. He entered the lists against the
institution of slavery because, from boyhood, he had believed it to be
morally and politically wrong: true, in this, to the traditions of his
ancestors, who, three generations before, were Pennsylvania
Quakers. Made a member of the national House of Representatives in
1847, he stood squarely with the friends of freedom through all the
various skirmishes and battles of those years of Southern pride and
power. But he was not a radical in his creed. While opposing
unflinchingly every extra-constitutional grant to Southern principles,
he evermore contended for the fulfilment of whatever legally could be
claimed by the slave-system. In his great campaign against Mr. Douglas
in 1858 for a seat in the U. S. Senate, which, though it gained him
not that honor, made him our President in 1860, he uniformly abjured
the right of interference with slavery in the existent slave-states,
and refused to counsel the popular resistance of the odious Fugitive
Slave-bill. Utter and uncompromising resistance by all constitutional
and peaceful measures to the enlargement of the area and powers of
slavery--was his one-planked platform, and this on moral as well as
economical grounds. He knew, as he knew his own personal identity,
that slavery was hostile, and would be fatal, if allowed to be, to the
national life. That was motive enough, for a true patriot like him, to
regard it as a public and common enemy.</p>
               <p>But Mr. Lincoln entered upon his presidential career with no
settled purpose of slavery-extermination. He could not as an honest
man. The millions of free citizens had not elected him for that
object, much as the mass of them might have desired this result. He
took his oath of office to hold the Republic safe and intact against
all foes. He was put in trust of this by the people of the land who
love it as their home; and his heart and head had taught him the
duties of a trustee, for one--for myriads of men. Had the Republic
<pb n="8" facs="tucker8.jpg"/>
been imperrilled by a foreign invader, he would have set its whole
strength in motion to repel the assault. Had Massachusetts attempted
rebellion and secession, or all the North combined in such unholy
treason, that oath which he had sworn would have fulfilled itself as
promptly and impartially upon New England rebellion as it did on
Southern secession. Mr. Lincoln was no respecter of persons or
sections. He had no idea, when he took his official seat at
Washington, that he was entering on a war-administration. He
understood something of Southern malice and treachery, and he was
willing to risk it. But he did mean to govern the country--all of
it--fairly, evenly, firmly, kindly, whatever might come. That was his
business as "the Anointed of the Lord." And he did it. </p>
               <p>Knowing, of course, that he was made President by Northern votes,
he knew just as well that the withdrawal of the Southern vote was
simply the result of that section's self-will, for which he was not
responsible. This, however, would have made no difference with the
status of those States under his administration, if they had behaved
even no better than we did under the Southern usurpation, for that is
its true name, of his immediate predecessor. Who believes that Abraham
Lincoln would have harmed a hair of their heads, if the slaveholders
had kept quiet within their constitutional and political strong-holds?
Can any body conjecture the struggles and the sufferings of that man
of more than womanly kindness, when the oath, which he had sworn
before the God who gave him the sword of government, compelled him to
unsheathe it, and year upon year to bathe it in the blood of
self-outlawed men and enemies, even to its dripping hilt. God only
knows what a work that man has been conscience-driven to execute, as
it had to be shaped consciously and experimentally in his own soul:
and this, against the pleadings of his own natural pity, against the
peaceful tendencies and sentiments of a progressive Christian
civilization, against every thing human and divine, save that most
humane and
<pb n="9" facs="tucker9.jpg"/>
sacred duty of preventing a gigantic conspiracy of treason and of
wickedness from doing the very thing for our Republic which it did
succeed, in an evil hour, in doing for its honored head. The President
prevented the assassination of the nation. He could not prevent his
own. The men, who were foiled by him in the first crime, accomplished
in the madness of their disappointment, the second.</p>
               <p>This tragic extinguishment of that good man's life puts the entire
cause which compassed it, in its true historic position, from which no
special pleading will avail to remove it, to the end of days. If any
one shall wish to know, in remotest centuries, what kind of a mutiny
this Southern outbreak was against all right reason and justice and
honor, he will find his indisputable answer in the murder at
Washington on Friday night, the 14th of April last. That was the
condensation and eruption of the smothered volcanic fire. Mr. Lincoln
had gradually been obliged to understand that the South would go all
lengths in fighting through its disunion-creed. He saw what they had
done in the deliberate atrocities of battle-fields and prisons. That
they would ever go to the extreme guilt of taking his own life, his
generous soul never fully could accredit, though he was aware of not a
few plottings of this sort against him. But, as he brought one force
after another to crush this armed revolt, and saw that still it lifted
its defiant front as proudly, he reached at length the point of a full
conviction, that the disloyal confederacy could never be subjugated
save by a deadly blow struck into its very heart--the
slave-system--for which it was fighting by its own plainest avowals,
and which was its vital-blood. Mr. Lincoln had no more intention of
issuing the Emancipation-proclamation in 1861, than he had of being
shot in 1865. But he was willing to set every slave free if the Union
could not be saved without it. That he had sworn to do, if done it
could be. When he had tried all else to effect it, he let slip the one
last thunderbolt. He did it, not because as a man he was anti-slavery
in sentiment, not because he was ready to use his
<pb n="10" facs="tucker10.jpg"/>
public power to break up what he knew was unutterably evil and
troublesome, that he might so gratify the compassion of' his own
nature or the wishes of partizans, or gain applause from spectators
abroad, or win a proud name in history. He signed his name to that
great charter of African freedom, as a necessary military measure to
destroy the Southern Confederacy. Had he done it for any other reason,
he would have gone outside of his presidential oath.  Had he not done
it for this, he would have stood condemned, at the bar of humanity,
for official delinquency. He saved the integrity of American liberty
and nationality by that heroic act. Again the pen has been mightier
than the sword. He sealed his testimony with his blood. But think you
that this blood will have stained the earth in vain? Did the martyrs'?
Look around you and answer.</p>
               <p>A man's real character cannot be studied apart from his public
deeds. It must be confessed that sometimes a wide discrepancy appears
between the private and the official aspects of an individual life. We
see very little of this in the late President. His personal
truthfulness and good nature interfused whatever he did. There used to
be some vague echo of a rumor floating in the air, that Mr. Lincoln
was a tyrant. No one could say it now without the risk of being very
justly classed as sympathising with the miserable stage-player, whose
attempt thus to dramatize his horrid crime was as futile as was his
subsequent effort to escape the justice of God. The man never breathed
who was farther from vindictive promptings than this victim of
political revenge. Almost the last thing which he did was to permit,
by telegraph, the flight from the country of a party of rebel
chiefs. Had he lived, Mr. Davis would never have had his mock dignity
smothered beneath the ridicule of a feminine arrest by a military
police. His flight to a foreign obscurity would never have been
hindered. How well nigh impossible it was to procure the presidential
consent to a death-sentence by court-martial, has become
proverbial. Says Mr. Speaker Colfax,
<pb n="11" facs="tucker11.jpg"/>
in his Chicago oration: "No man, in our era, clothed with such vast
power, has ever used it so mercifully. No ruler, holding the keys of
life and death, ever pardoned so many and so easily. When friends said
to him they wished he had more of Jackson's sternness, he would say,
'I am just as God made me, and can not change.' It may not be
generally known that his door-keepers had standing orders from him
that no matter how great might be the throng, if other Senators and
Representatives had to wait, or to be turned away without an audience,
he must see before the day closed every messenger who came to him with
a petition for the saving of life. One night in February I left all
other business to ask him to respite the son of a constituent, who was
sentenced to be shot at Davenport, for desertion. He heard the story
with his usual patience, though he was wearied out with incessant
calls, and anxious for rest, and then replied: 'Some of our Generals
complain that I impair discipline and subordination in the army, by my
pardons and respites, but it makes me rested, after a day's hard work,
if I can find some good excuse for saving a man's life, and I go to
bed happy, as I think how joyous the signing of my name will make him
and his family and his friends.' And with a happy smile beaming over
that care-furrowed face, he signed that name and saved that life."
Think you he could have authorized such a treatment of rebel prisoners
as was deliberately planned and sanctioned by the phlegmatic Jefferson
Davis and the chivalric General Lee? It is time that the Northern
people should cease to talk about the high and honorable spirit of
this latter author of our brave soldiers' inhuman privations at
Richmond, where his military word was always omnipotent. If tyranny
needs modern illustrations, let no one stop till he gets to the James
River. There was not a vestige of it in the heart of our noble
chief.</p>
               <p>Some doleful censor has compared Mr. Lincoln's indulgence in
story-telling and a genial laugh to Nero's fiddling, up in that little
grim tower, while Rome was burning. Verily, the
<pb n="12" facs="tucker12.jpg"/>
running of historical parallels is "a sharp razor working deceitfully"
in not a few hands. Our President's humor was as natural as his
pulse. It never could have welled up so sweetly and richly from a
despot's breast. It was not levity. It betokened no indifference to
his country's woes. It was often coupled with a seriousness too deep
for tears. But for this escape-valve for his overworked, wearied,
aching sensibilities and energies, he used to say that he should
die. Who can not see it? And besides--this was the normal working of
his mind. A confidential friend of his told me that Mr. Lincoln never
reached an intellectual judgment by slow processes of inductive
reasoning and argument. He took in a thought, and let it steep and
simmer in his brain, holding it there in solution while engaged with
men and affairs, in the usual round of work. Often, he would draw
around him a pleasant company and spend an evening, in seemingly a
complete abandon to the whim or pastime of the hour. But, the next
morning he was ready, with a clear head and a sound heart, to pen a
proclamation or issue an order charged with the weightiest
consequences. Thomas Carlyle has a remark somewhere, that a man who
cannot laugh sometimes, not merely with a muffled chuckle, as if
through a cotton-cushion, but from the very depths of his being, is
not capable of salvation. Without going the whole length of the
essayist, it is certain that our beloved President was all the better
and the happier, amidst those days of darkness, for this geniality of
his temperament. The people understood it and enjoyed the wit and the
wisdom which, like the oil on Aaron's beard, flowed down to the skirts
of the garments.</p>
               <p>The people understood more than this. They felt that there was, at
the head of the government, a thoroughly honest man. It was not that
kind of Poor Richard honesty which is only the best policy. It was an
honesty which feared God. What commended itself, at first, as a lofty
moral conscientiousness, had taken on, at length, the profounder depth
of a religious affection. What had long ap-
<pb n="13" facs="tucker13.jpg"/>
proved itself as doing justly and loving mercy, had manifestly
advanced to the loftier eminence of walking humbly with its God. There
was no cant nor pretension about this, but, a sedate, fixed,
impressive reality in it which everybody felt and reverenced. God had
given him a task to do, and the soul of an unusual Christian manhood
with which to do it. Unselfish as a person can be and not hate his own
flesh; self-sacrificing beyond living comparison, for the public good;
humble as a child, and as ingenuous; humane in all his instincts and
principles; careless of unpopularity when risked for the true and the
right; never tempted to angry outbreaks in word or act; forgiving his
enemies, yea and loving them tenderly in their worst excesses of wrath
and guilt; divine Providence seems to have created and trained him for
his appointed work; and when, like a good and faithful servant he had
finished it, God, who had kept him immortal till that work was done,
suffered him to fall in death by just the stroke which should brand
with eternal shame the rebellion which he had crushed; which should
hand him down to history with the splendor of his public glory made
yet more beautiful by the personal love and sympathy of the purest
souls that live, or shall live until the close of time.</p>
               <p>It is not for me, or any one, to say that President Lincoln
committed no errors of judgment in the course of his administration,
nor that he was faultless as a man. That were to be more than
human. Whatever were his executive mistakes he can afford to have
deducted from his credits. The wonder is, that, in the unexampled
embarrassments of his government, those mistakes were so few. Other
presidential terms, in no uncommon difficulties, have been hardly else
than one long blunder, if not crime. His was the herculean task of
creating a military and naval power out of a wholly commercial and
industrial nation, and to fit it with warlike resources equal to the
conquest of one half the republic which had been organizing for
rebellion during a quarter of a century; all this with no notice and
in the very presence of the
<pb n="14" facs="tucker14.jpg"/>
enemy actually besieging his capital. Did he, and his generals, and
his cabinet do some unwise things? Let writers and speakers criticize
these, who have no sight to see approvingly that the Washington, which
to-day is free from Southern usurpation and bondage, free in its
Congressional halls, its Supreme and local courts, its executive
mansion, its social life, was, four years ago, a very nest of treason
and outlawry; that the vast domain of the new territories is forever
barred against slavery; that the area of this huge rebellion has been
rescued from the same curse; that the project of secession and
Southern empire is wrecked; that we have conquered the hosts of the
oppressor, taken his fortresses and cities, broken up his government,
ruined all his unrighteous projects, captured the ringleaders of the
accursed crusade, whom we are holding for trial under the charge of
high treason. They, who find no pleasure in all this vindication of
justice, may still employ their valueless time in showing up the
President's weak points. We are far from saying that our almost
miraculous success is wholly due to his labors. First of all and ever,
we give praise unto God who has wrought these mighty works among
us. Next, we are content with Mr. Bancroft's words; "Those who come
after us will decide how much of the wonderful results of
Mr. Lincoln's career is due to his own good common sense, his shrewd
sagacity, readiness of wit, quick interpretation of the public mind,
his rare combination of fixedness and pliency, his steady tendency of
purpose; how much to the American people, who, as he walked with them
side by side, inspired him with their own wisdom and energy." History
is a safe depository for genuine goodness and greatness. And this
to-day is American history--that our republic "is cast into another
mould" from what it was when Mr. Lincoln delivered his first
inaugural, and that "the gigantic system of wrong, which had been the
work of more than two centuries, is dashed down, we hope,
forever."<ref target="#tucker.002.n02">*</ref>
What ruler, through the ages, has left a worthier record?</p>
               <note xml:id="tucker.002.n02" n="*" place="foot" anchored="true">
                  <p>Hon. George Bancroft's Oration in New York,
April, 1865.</p>
               </note>
               <pb n="15" facs="tucker15.jpg"/>
               <p>The topic is alluring, but it is time for its concluding
suggestions. Our annals are enriched with another rare model for
youthful study and imitation, second only to that of the Father of our
nation, in all the catalogue of our public men. For a long time we
have greatly needed such a model, to whom to point our youth as a
pattern of the staunch, honest, frank, unselfish qualities of the
American citizen of to-day's imperative want. We have it here; and of
none the less value because not haloed about with that aristocratic
radiance, which made Washington the admiration of thousands who cared
nothing for his virtues, but only for his gentle blood. Do not think
that I undervalue this, so far as it possesses any value. But, just
now, we need to put some tougher timber into our social and national
structure. Reconstruction is the lesson for the day; and while all
graceful adornment should be saved for use and beauty, the
under-pinning of our new life should not be made of plaster, nor its
towers and arches be a frescoed counterfeit of solid stone and
wood. Our nation wants a whole, immediate generation of honest, true,
intelligent, straight-forward Abraham Lincolns:--if the genuine metal
be within, who cares about the gilt glitter of the surface? If there
be anything to bear a polish, it will get it by and bye: but the less
you brush gold leaf the better. Was Cicero proud, not that he had
inherited but had made a renowned name? Honor to the old Roman. He was
so far forth, a New-England Puritan. Mr. Lincoln's self-made nobility
was of a loftier patent than that of any Norman lord who to-day grinds
the faces of England's poor. When his life shall have been worthily
written, let it become the textbook of our generous youth, who would
help to lift our national character and name to the loftiest point of
a manly and a Christian honor.</p>
               <p>Another view: Divine Providence is furnishing, through the progress
and end of this rebellion, a more palpable
<pb n="16" facs="tucker16.jpg"/>
illustration of the self-defeating doom of enormous iniquity, than
history records since the crucifixion of our Lord. Every success which
the South has won has been a defeat. Bull Run was the Bunker Hill of
this war, where all that the enemy gained only roused and combined a
thousand fold more vigorously the patriotic ardor of the
land. Periodically almost, some invasion or fierce grapple, like the
Pennsylvania raids or Virginia massacres, have seemed to be the only
means of holding us to our hard warfare until the prize was won. But
for the increasing hauteur of rebel good fortune, we should have
compromised the quarrel two years ago, and lost everything which
to-day, by dint of persevering against bitter disappointment, we
firmly grasp. Did our guardian God thus spur us on to make clean work
of extirpating the giant heresy of the South? We have been grievously
annoyed and hampered by foreign sympathy with our foes; have fretted
that intelligent men abroad would not or could not comprehend the
merits of our cause. And so it might have gone on, to the involving us
in foreign war, had not the great Ruler permitted this conspiracy of
oppression and sedition to explain itself to the universe by the
assassination of our President. That deed of blood has opened the eyes
of the world to the true nature of the adversary which we are
throttling. What did the rebel sympathizers abroad say when the
strange news thrilled with horror the heart of Europe? With one loud
cry, the organs of that sympathy said that the responsible heads of
the Southern Confederacy must disavow and reprobate the murder, on
pain of forfeiting the respect of every person there who was not
infamous. A British peer of that side predicted, from his place in
parliament, that the next steamer would assuredly bring over a
universal outburst of condemnation from the South of Booth's nefarious
act. The London Times demanded, with a well-set scowl of rebuke, that
the South should wash its hands of the crimson stain. Has it been
done? Not a beginning of it. Even Mr. Mason's weak disavowal,
compelled by
<pb n="17" facs="tucker17.jpg"/>
public decency, has found no echo from a rebel statesman or newspaper
or convention that I have beard of. The spirit of the rebellion
sanctions it, and of course can not eschew it. Mr. Davis even is not
capable of the hypocrisy which such a disclaimer would require. He
knows that such a falsehood would be a waste of words; that no one
would believe his assertions, who understands this subject. Did he,
does he know, that evidence is in the hands of our government which
will prove him to have been an accomplice, before the fact, in this
plot of damnable guilt? I believe that he knows precisely so much. I
do not wonder that his knees tremble like Belshazzar's, and that the
bitterness of a felon's death is beginning to drink up his spirit.</p>
               <p>What is thus putting its finishing blot on this Southern iniquity,
to our convictions, will speedily consign it to a like detestation the
world over. Into the pit which they digged have they themselves
fallen. And it is bottomless. Their sin has found them out. The wicked
is snared in his own devices. What a termination of self-confounded
wrong! We thought, on the 15th of April, that the last scene of this
revolt of barbarism against civilization, would live in memory as a
superlatively tragic tableau, electrifying posterity with a sense of
awful terror. But, as if Providence would take out of it even this
attraction of sublime guilt, would make this four years mutiny against
righteousness and mercy as ridiculous as it is criminal--lo! the
flitting across the stage of that oddly "questionable shape." Why
could not the arch traitor have died on the spot, like a man? Almighty
justice would not permit him to throw even so much false glory around
a cause so vile. He must go down the ages, laughed at for his cowardly
foolishness, as well as reprobated for his crimes. The Southern
Confederacy of secession, oppression, rebellion, has found its
definition, for all time, in the bloodiest of tragedies, and the most
grotesque of farces.</p>
               <p>Again: The Sovereign of us all is teaching us a lesson of the
sacredness of legitimate government, and the necessity of
<pb n="18" facs="tucker18.jpg"/>
executing its sanctions. The enormity of the assassination of our
President lies not, after all, in his personal qualities as a good
ruler, nor in the justness of the cause for which he fell a
victim. That blow took effect on the man elevated by constitutional
methods to the supreme magistracy of this nation, and thus made a
"minister of God" to execute justice and administer authority, as his
representative so far forth, in the land. Government thus set up is
literally a Divine ordinance. Its head is the Lord's anointed, as
really as was a David or a Solomon. This is substantially true,
irrespective of the personal qualities of the lawful incumbent of that
office. To strike at him with murderous weapons is to fight against
God in a most aggravated sense.</p>
               <p>And this defines the crime of high treason. It is a wholesale
attempt to destroy a nation's organic life. No crime can surpass it in
guilt. This Southern rebellion is that crime in. its superlative
degree. It has dragged to its door, as their responsible author, all
the woes and carnage, the sacrifice of life, and the promiscuous
devastation, which have followed this Moloch of war, through four long
years. And its leaders ought to die. There is no reason why the
assassin of the President should have expiated his act on the
scaffold, had not the arrest of God made a quicker end of him, which
does not equally, and more than equally, require that the beads of the
Confederate government, civil and military, should thus pay the
forfeit of their atrocious lawlessness. Our greatest weakness, in
government, has been our remissness in exacting the penalties of the
violation of law. Our legislation is good; our neglect to enforce it
is bad and suicidal. Our best friends abroad have remarked this habit
of our country with deep concern. Now, we must turn a new leaf and
justice to the enemies of man must be its heading. We can not afford
to let this conspiracy of traitors and assassins live. Their blood
must vindicate the majesty of law, in mercy to this nation and to the
world. We are in charge, at this time, of the safe-keeping of that
great barrier which is built
<pb n="19" facs="tucker19.jpg"/>
up of the penalties of the statute-book against the floods of outlawry
ever threatening the public security. And we must hold that barrier
firmly, sternly, in these days when "evil men and seducers are waxing
worse and worse."</p>
               <p>It is not surprising that a class of anti-capital punishment
philanthropists should already be pleading for the lives of these
ring-leaders of rebellion, these accomplices in assassination and
promiscuous plots of Northern ravage and slaughter. These persons are
at least consistent with themselves in what I deem to be a violent
departure from the truth. If that doctrine is to rule us, we may as
well know it now as at any other time. Nor is it surprising that
foreign presses, which have habitually traduced us, should now be
volunteering their advice and remonstrances concerning our disposal of
these rebel chiefs. As, however, we conquered our foe without their
help, it is to be hoped that our rulers will have the self respect to
decide this and all other matters, quite independently of such
officious and really impertinent interference. Surely we are better
qualified than they to adjudicate this question. They have blundered
enough about our affairs, to put their opinions at a ruinous
discount.</p>
               <p>This conclusion, with me, is the dictate of no personal feeling,
for I sincerely pity the misguided men who have thus snared themselves
in these meshes of iniquity. I devoutly pray that the Lord may have
mercy on their souls. Two months ago, I thought that possibly a decree
of exile forever from these shores might be a sufficient doom for
their treason. I recall that opinion. That may do for subordinates, or
a decree of perpetual disfranchisement here at home. But the authors
of this rebellion, its voluntary heads, its representatives before the
nations and the world--they must be made a solemn sacrifice to
outraged righteousness, justice, mercy and truth. Humanity demands it,
as God's own sentence against guilt like this.</p>
               <p>Finally: The vast difficulty of securing our present vantage, in
this conflict, should put the nation on its guard lest
<pb n="20" facs="tucker20.jpg"/>
it lose in peace what it has gained in war.<ref target="#tucker.002.n03">*</ref> We have broken up the
military power of the rebellion by hard fighting; but now we shall
have a more troublesome task--to hold the ground thus fairly won, in
an upright, unswerving loyalty to these nobly asserted principles of
free government. There is only one great interest which is in special
danger. All other issues can be easily enough adjusted. But this
chiefest of them all has a critical ordeal yet to pass. I do not allow
myself to suppose that any thing valuable will be sacrificed to the
prayers or threats or intrigues of the slave-party in these
States. But that every thing conceivable will be tried to save that
bad institution from a root and branch destruction, we clearly
foresee. Providentially the seceders have been left to push on in
their revolt to that final point where, deaf to all past offers of
pardon, they have forfeited every right and claim to the restoration
of any property which they have ever called their own. They may be
thankful for what is given them; they are entitled to nothing. With
the loyal Southeners, the government can find a way to be just without
leaving a root of that poison-tree which has nearly been the utter
death of the Republic. All this is plain. Still, it is just as plain
that Southern rights will soon begin to be talked about, meaning by
that, the rights of the South to go on with its old slave-code. No
lack of people or pens will there be to prove up the soundness of
these pretensions, or at least, to mystify the public into vacillation
and moral cowardice in asserting downright, simple equity on this
question. Persistent and great as these efforts will be, I do not
believe they will avail. But, "let him who thinketh he standeth take
heed lest he fall." Sleepless vigilance is yet to be the price of our
freshly and dearly bought freedom. Prepare yourselves, then, for a
vigorous controversy on this whole subject. The worst of causes, as
of</p>
               <note xml:id="tucker.002.n03" n="*" place="foot" anchored="true">
                  <p>This and the next paragraph are introduced from
the author's Fast Day sermon, April 13, 1865; which was requested for
publication, but the next day's tidings absorbed all other
interests.</p>
               </note>
               <pb n="21" facs="tucker21.jpg"/>
               <p>criminals, will never want apologists. We have suffered too much to
give an inch of ground here. If the administration needs instructions,
it should have them, in a voice of millions, to make no terms
legitimating slavery on American soil. The North should be a unit in
this demand. The South saw fit to stake their entire cause at this
point, making it the head and front of their offending. They have
failed. Let them abide the consequences of their own madness. They
have nobody to blame but themselves.</p>
               <p>Do not delude yourselves with the dream that the slave-system and
spirit is so paralyzed and broken up that it will now die out in a few
years, if left to itself. It will not, no more than idolatry died out
of Canaan, no more than witch-grass will die out of your garden. It has
got to be slain, by a sentence like that which bangs a
murderer--"until it is dead, dead, dead." And now is the time to do
it, in compassion to the land which it has strewn with slaughtered
heaps, and to the future which it must not curse with its evil
power.</p>
               <p>Respected hearers, I have detained you longer than my wont, with
these observations. But such a day comes only once in a life-time and
may well secure a patient listening to its instructions. We look
onward now, from our recent troubles and depressions, to a brightening
future. It will bring new duties, cares, perils. May God help and keep
us amidst them all! Hear ye his word to the people. "If ye walk in my
statutes, and keep my commandments and do them; Then I will give Peace
in the land, and ye shall lie down, and none shall make you
afraid."</p>
            </div2>
         </div1>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>