<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader><fileDesc>
         <titleStmt n="The Conflict of Truth">
            <title>The Conflict of Truth</title>
            <author>Reed, Villeroy Dibble</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Compiled and edited by</resp>
               <name>Beck
Center</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent/>
         <publicationStmt><publisher>Lewis H. Beck Center</publisher><pubPlace>Emory University</pubPlace><address>
               <addrLine>Atlanta,
Georgia</addrLine>
            </address><availability>
               <p>1996 Emory
University. Permission is granted to download, transmit, or otherwise
reproduce, distribute or display the contributions to the work claimed
by Emory University for non-profit educational purposes, provided
this header is included in its entirety.  For inquiries about
commercial uses, contact: the Director, Pitts Theology Library, Emory
University, Atlanta, Georgia 30322</p>
            </availability><date>1999</date></publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Lincoln
Sermons Project</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Reed,
Villeroy Dibble. The Conflict of Truth. A Sermon Preached In The First
Presbyterian Church, Camden, N. J., April 30,1865.  Camden,
N.J. Printed By S. Chew, At the Office of the "West Jersey Press."
1865.</bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc><encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This text is from the Special Collections of Pitts
Theology Library, Emory University, and produced in collaboration with
the Emory Preservation Office, Pitts Theology Library and the Beck
Center at Emory University.   </p>
            <p>TRANSCRIBER: Lewis H. Beck Center and Emory University 
Preservation Office.</p>
            <p>PRODUCER:  BookLab, Inc., 1606 Headway Circle, 
Suite 100, Austin, TX 78754</p>
            <p>CAPTURE DEVICE: XEROX DocuImage 620S flatbed scanner</p>
            <p>CAPTURE DETAILS: Scanner software: XEROX ScanTool 
version 4.2.3; no gamma correction; images are all bitonal.</p>
            <p>CHANGE HISTORY: Using the Adobe Photoshop Batch Processor, 
we interpolated  the original TIFF files to 8-bit grays, 
and altered the resolution to 144 dpi, producing screen 
images twice the original size.  We then saved them in 
JPEG format.  We produced GIF thumbnails from the JPEG files.</p>
            <p>RESOLUTION: 600 ppi</p>
            <p>COMPRESSION: Resolution 144 per inch with Constrain 
Properties to 72 per inch.</p>
            <p>SOURCE: Original documents.</p>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc><revisionDesc><change><name>Stewart Varner</name> transformed this document from p4 to p5 on <date when="2010-03-22">March 22, 2010</date></change><change xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><date>1999</date><label>Staff</label><name>Brandon
Scott</name>SGML tags inserted in
compliance with TEI guidelines using TEILITE</change></revisionDesc></teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div1 xml:id="vreed.001" n="The Conflict of Truth" type="text">
            <head>
               <bibl> 
                  <title>The Conflict of Truth</title> 
                  <date>April 30,
1865</date> 
                  <pubPlace>First Presbyterian Church, New Jersey</pubPlace>
                  <author>Reed, Villeroy Dibble</author> 
                  
                     <pubPlace>New
Jersey</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>S. Chew</publisher>
                     <date>1865</date>
                   
               <idno type="ark">http://pid.emory.edu/ark:/25593/15rff</idno></bibl> 
            </head>
            <pb facs="vreed1.jpg"/>
            <p>The Conflict of Truth.</p>
            <p>A SERMON</p>
            <p>PREACHED IN THE</p>
            <p>FIRST PRESBYTERIAN CHURCH,</p>
            <p>Camden, N.J.,</p>
            <p>APRIL 30, 1865,</p>
            <p>BY</p>
            <p>REV. V. D. REED, D. D.</p>
            <p>CAMDEN, N.J.:</p>
            <p>PRINTED BY S. CHEW, AT THE OFFICE OF THE "WEST
JERSEY PRESS."</p>
            <p>1865.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="vreed2.jpg"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="vreed3.jpg"/>
            <p>Camden, May 1st, 1865.</p>
            <p>REV. V.D. REED, D.D.</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italic">Rev. and Dear Sir</hi>:--The members of
your congregation, with many others of your fellow-citizens, listened
with great pleasure and profit to the sermons, which you delivered on
yesterday morning and evening.</p>
            <p>The desire has been expressed, with great unanimity, that
those discourses shall be published in pamphlet.</p>
            <p>The doctrines and principles of which they treat, are
eminently practical, appropriate, and satisfactory; and so fully in
accordance with the wants and demands of this eventful period of our
country's history, that greater publicity will but be productive of
greater good.</p>
            <p>We respectfully solicit, therefore, the manuscripts of said
discourses.</p>
            <p>Very Truly, Yours,</p>
            <p>
               <lb/>P.C. BRINCK,	G.W.N. CUSTIS,<lb/>
THOS. C. KNIGHT,	WM. FEW SMITH, <lb/>JNO. A. CALDWELL,	JOHN
AIKMAN,, <lb/>M. NEWKIRK,		T.M.K. LEE,,<lb/>
GEO. W. .CARPENTER,	B.F. ARCHER,<lb/>
J.D. REINBOTH,		ROBT. 	B. POTTS,<lb/>
S. CHEW,		J. V. SCHENCK, <lb/>JAMES
M. SCOVEL,	JAS.. H. STEVENS, <lb/>J.C. DE LA COUR,	MAURICE
BROWNING, <lb/>HENRY VANUXEN,		R. S. CURTIS,<lb/>
C. A. SPARKS,		WM. HART,<lb/>
B.H. BROWNING.		I.H. PORTER.</p>
            <p>CAMDEN, MAY 2D, 1865.</p>
            <p>GENTLEMEN:</p>
            <p>The discourses, you ask for publication, are so connected
that they can readily be made one. I have therefore combined the
two--leaving out considerable portions, which though deemed important
in the delivery, are not essential to the main design.</p>
            <p>The manuscript so abridged, is submitted to you, with the
earnest prayer, that if published, it may subserve the cause of truth
and good citizenship.</p>
            <p>Very respectfully yours,</p>
            <p>V. D. REED.</p>
            <p>To Messrs.	P.C. BRINCK,
	<lb/>G.W.N. CUSTIS,
	<lb/>THOS. C..KNIGHT, and others.</p>
            <pb n="4"/>
<!-- blank page -->
<!--            <p>
               <figure entity="vreed4">
                  <figDesc>4th page of
Villeroy Dibble Reed's The Conflict of Truth.</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p> -->
            <pb n="5" facs="vreed5.jpg"/>
            <div2 xml:id="vreed.002" n="The Conflict of Truth." type="sermon">
               <head>The Conflict of Truth.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <p>MATTHEW X: 34. "THINK NOT THAT I AM COME TO SEND
PEACE ON EARTH: I CAME NOT TO SEND PEACE, BUT A SWORD."</p>
               </epigraph>
               <p>Jesus Christ is called the Prince of peace. His advent to
our world was heralded, by a multitude of the heavenly host,
proclaiming, "On earth peace, good-will to men." Wherever the
principles of the gospel prevail, and exert their appropriate
influence, animosities, divisions, strifes, hatred, variance, wars
cease, and their opposites prevail, unity, brotherly kindness,
charity, peace, good will to all. How then could the Savior say that
he came to send, not peace, but a sword? To understand this subject
aright, it must be remembered that men are by nature in a state of
alienation from God! Satan, the prince of darkness, is god of this
world. He rules in the hearts of unbelieving men, leading them captive
at his will.</p>
               <p>The kingdom of Christ is in direct antagonism to his
rule. The setting up of that kingdom in the world,
<pb n="6" facs="vreed6.jpg"/>
therefore will necessarily elicit opposition, awaken deadly hatred and
intense animosity. All the powers of darkness will be arrayed in
opposition to it. The men of this world will oppose its extension,
frown upon the prevalence of its principles and the spread of its
power. And as Christians must adhere to their religion and faithfully
maintain the truth they will be brought into collision with the
unbelieving world. There will be serious conflicts of' opinion,
perhaps open assaults by the enemies of the truth, and cruel
persecution of those who adhere to the kingdom of Christ. The
doctrines of Christianity are entirely opposed to the opinions
generally held, about the Supreme Being, our relations to him and the
mode in which his favor can be secured. On the other hand the precepts
of the gospel are at war with the customs of society. The prevalence
of those precepts necessarily must produce new forms of social
life.</p>
               <p>Christianity strikes at the root of all iniquity. It aims
to correct evils in all departments of society, and all the relations
of life. Hence it is revolutionary in its character. Unregenerate men
do not like to retain God in their knowledge. They have no love for
moral rectitude or holiness; and while very religious oftentimes,
their religion is of a gross and debasing character. Every form of
superstition is embraced, while God in his true relations and claims
is rejected. The understanding is biased so that the truth is not
received. The conscience is perverted and its dictates are opposed to
godliness. The judgment is warped, and its decisions are
incorrect. The heart is in love with sin, and all the acts and
exercises of the soul are against the truth.</p>
               <p>Prejudice exerts great influence upon the mind, and
<pb n="7" facs="vreed7.jpg"/>
nothing is more powerful than religious prejudices. If their religion
has any hold upon them, men will contend with an earnestness and
tenacity which they show in nothing else.</p>
               <p>The followers of Christ dare not give up their principles,
for if their religion is anything to them it is everything. The
sacrifice of the truth or a perversion of the truth subjects them to
the displeasure of the God of truth. The loss of worldly advantages,
property, honors, emoluments, personal liberty, or even life itself,
involves only a temporal calamity, while the sacrifice of their
religious principles involves the loss of their souls. Poverty, shame,
famine, torture, the prison, the scaffold, can be calmly met by the
soul that is at peace with God, and has in prospect the blessedness of
heaven.</p>
               <p>Here it should be remembered, that the human mind, under
most favorable circumstances, is liable to imbibe a mixture of error
with the truth. And such is the weakness of human nature--in them that
are but partially sanctified, that error is maintained often with as
great tenacity and earnestness as truth. Men are partial to their own
opinions and often substitute these for the teachings of God's word,
so that while ostensibly defending the truth, they are really
defending their own creeds and dogmas. A false system of religion is
maintained with greater zeal than the true. Corrupt forms of
Christianity are adhered to and defended with more determination than
the pure religion. of Jesus. In this way we can account for the strife
and animosities, the bitter conflicts and contentions that have
prevailed among those advocating the same pure and peace-speaking
precepts. The history of the church is full of the conflicts of
opinion. 
<pb n="8" facs="vreed8.jpg"/>
Sometimes these conflicts take the form of theological
controversy. Where a spirit of charity prevails such controversies
result in the elucidation of truth and the establishment of the church
upon a sure foundation. Where, as is frequently the case, bitterness,
selfish ambition and party animosity prevail, the result is wide
separation, alienation of feeling, sometimes violent bickerings or
open warfare. The truth should be spoken in love and received in love;
and where Christians are compelled to differ it should be in the
exercise of a large hearted liberal charity.</p>
               <p>Error has had its martyrs as well as truth, but the martyrs
of error have broken loose from the safe moorings in which God has
placed the human soul, and been drifted by the winds of fancy,
prejudice, or selfish ambition, upon the dark sea of unbelief till
they have been given over to strong delusions to believe a lie.</p>
               <p>stoutly defending their opinions, they must put down and
overwhelm their opponents. Error knows its weakness, is cowardly and
treacherous and when unable to maintain its ground on the field of
fair discussion covers its discomfiture by an onslaught upon its
opponents and vents its spite in malicious attacks upon those with
whom it could not compete in honorable warfare. Hence the dire
assaults and bitter persecutions which have been waged upon the
advocates of truth. And the fearful conflicts, the long and bloody
wars, which from time to time have characterized the progress of truth
in the world.</p>
               <lg type="stanza">
                  <l>"Truth crushed to earth will rise again,</l>
                  <l>The eternal years of God are hers."</l>
               </lg>
               <p>This opposition to the truth was strikingly manifested
during the ministry of our Lord Jesus Christ on earth
<pb n="9" facs="vreed9.jpg"/>
He assailed the errors and sins of those occupying the highest
positions in society as well as in the lower walks of life, "Woe, unto
you Scribes and Pharisees, hypocrites! ye have made the word of God of
none effect by your traditions. Woe unto you lawyers, ye lade men with
heavy burdens and grievances to be borne."</p>
               <p>This fidelity in opposing error and wickedness which
characterized his entire ministry subjected him to unrelenting hate
and bitter persecution. While the multitude hung upon his lips, were
awed by his miracles or experienced the beneficent workings of his
power, the rulers, Pharisees and men of high social position were
violently opposed to him, maligned and evil entreated him, and finally
secured his barbarous crucifixion. He was charged with seditious
assumptions and political designs. "We found this fellow perverting
the nation and forbidding to give tribute to Caesar, saying that he
himself, is Christ a king." And when Pilate desired to release him
they demanded his crucifixion, for political reasons. "If thou let
this man go thou art not Caesar's friend; whosoever maketh himself a
king speaketh against Caesar."</p>
               <p>When the Apostles labored in fulfillment of their mission
to preach Christ to the world, their labors excited intense
opposition. The chief priests and rulers imprisoned and strictly
charged them not to teach or preach in the name of Jesus. Thus they
were brought into direct collision with the civil authorities. They
must either give up their heaven appointed work or they must be
prepared for opposition, conflict and death. They decided--how could
the votaries of truth decide otherwise--they decided, "we ought to
obey God rather than men." Hence their
<pb n="10" facs="vreed10.jpg"/>
persecution, the hunting of them by their enemies, subjecting them to
imprisonment and death. Herod, the governor of Judea, stretched forth
his hand to vex the church. He put James to death, and because he
perceived that it pleased the Jews he took Peter also. The Jews in
their opposition to the Apostles, were impelled, by hatred to the
truth, and Herod, in his bloody efforts to gratify them was actuated
by motives of personal aggrandizement or political ambition. So in
repeated instances, the apostles were charged with being disturbers of
society. "These that have turned the world up side down have come
hither also," "We have found this man a pestilent fellow, a mover of
sedition among all the Jews throughout the world, and a ringleader of
the sect of the Nazarines." Sometimes it is said, Jesus Christ and his
apostles did not meddle with civil or political affairs. They never
preached politics. Well, whether they did or not, it is certain they
were charged with doing it; and it is likewise certain that they
denounce error in every form and sin in whomsoever it is found. And
their preaching was mighty through God to pull down the strongholds of
error. The gospel did revolutionize society. The frame work of the
social organization being rotten, these wise master builders of the
temple of God swept away that structure, and wherever the gospel
prevailed, society in all its phases was utterly changed. We owe now
all that we enjoy of true liberty and social excellence, to the
gospel.</p>
               <p>In the early period of the church's history, Christianity
came in collision with the various forms of superstition, paganism and
irreligion; and as these constituted a very important part of the
social fabric, there must necessarily be great revolutions in
sentiment and an entire change in 
	<pb n="11" facs="vreed11.jpg"/>
the social organization. Christianity too came in collision with the
systems of philosophy that prevailed, and their were violent
controversies in consequence. An important part of the early history
of the church is made up of controversy with error. And these
controversies have been necessary to preserve the truth in its purity,
to save the church from corruption and ultimate destruction, from
causes within itself.</p>
               <p>The history of different nations is full of conflicts very
severe and bloody, in which the religious element, has sometimes been
strangely predominant. In many instances the church has been too
intimately blended with the state, and any conflict agitating the one
would necessarily convulse the other. And in many instances where
there was not this alliance, religious truth has been deeply
involved. You are all familiar with the conflicts of truth during the
Reformation of the Sixteenth Century. Europe was convulsed, and every
nation felt the consequence when a poor Monk from the monastery, at
Wittemberg, published to the world, the truths of the gospel;
proclaimed salvation free to all who would search for themselves, the
pure word of God; attacked the time-honored practices of
ecclesiastical tyranny, and with the simple weapons of gospel truth,
battered down the strongholds of superstition, and broke the chains of
ecclesiastical vassalage, which had held the nations in bondage. You
know the conflicts which ensued. Princes and warriors, kingdoms and
principalities were arrayed in deadly strife. The Pope, and the
Emperor in vain, combined their powers, to resist the onward progress
of the truth. Conflicts of opinion about religious truth, shook the
kingdoms, overthrew dynasties, divided families, arrayed relatives and
former
<pb n="12" facs="vreed12.jpg"/>
friends in most deadly hostility, and changed entirely, the moral and
social aspects of the nations. Read the history of England, especially
from the time of Henry VIII, to the reign of William and Mary.  See
the struggles between arbitrary power and ecclesiastical tyranny on
the one hand, and the advocates of an open Bible, a free church and a
free government, on the other. Those struggles were necessary, not
only for the preservation of pure religion to the nation but for the
establishment, of the government, upon a firm basis of constitutional
liberty; so that the historian Hume, who was no friend of the gospel,
has recorded his testimony that, to the Puritans more than any other
class of persons, England owes all of liberty and constitutional
rights she possesses. And a later historian speaking of the
revolutions that disturbed Europe, in 1848, from which England
escaped, said, "It is because we had a <hi rend="italic">preserving</hi>
revolution in the Seventeenth Century that we have not had a <hi rend="italic">destroying</hi> revolution in the Nineteenth. For the
authority of law, for the security of property, for the peace of our
streets, the happiness of our homes, our gratitude is due, under Him,
who raises and pulls down nations at his pleasure, to the long
parliament, the convention, and William of Orange."</p>
               <p>Look at the, history of France, the terrible persecutions
of the Huguenots, the wholesale murder, and punishment of the best
citizens, that the truth might be overthrown, and the aspirations of
her noblest sons for true liberty might be crushed. And when the
gospel was rejected and its adherents exiled, see what woes came upon
the nation, what conflicts from time to time raged; and though now
France is at peace, it is the peace of despotic rule, that at any time
may be changed into apolitical tempest, when the
<pb n="13" facs="vreed13.jpg"/>
grasp of the despot is broken. Read the history of the Waldenses. See
their martyr struggles to maintain the truth, and resist oppression,
when all around bowed to the Man of sin. Look at Switzerland in the
time of Zwingle and Calvin. Turn over the pages of Motley. Witness the
long and bloody struggles of the adherents of truth and freedom, in
the Netherlands. See the most powerful monarch then reigning using all
his resources, employing his ablest generals, and most artful
ministers, to overthrow the truth and fasten the chains of
ecclesiastical tyranny, upon the Netherlanders. See the noble, heroic
course of William the Silent; under circumstances the most
disheartening and appalling, in face of reverses, that crushed the
hopes of others, steadily going forward, impelled by this one purpose
to secure to his people, liberty and religious toleration; till as the
sun of prosperity was just rising upon his country, he was laid low by
the dagger of an assassin. Dwell upon the details of that bloody
struggle, the terrible enormities perpetrated, under the sacred garb
of religion, the horrors of the siege of Leyden, the sack of Antwerp,
the sack of Harlem, the terrible acts of the Blood Council, the cruel
atrocities of Alva, and Don John, and Alexander of Parma; the first of
whom boasted that during the six years of his administration he had
executed under his own hand 18,600 persons, besides the immense
numbers who perished by siege, battle and terrible slaughter. Every
conceivable mode of torture was practiced, and the cord, the axe, the
stake, the dungeon, knew no rest. See what men have endured for the
truth. What conflicts have been occasioned, by the efforts of bigots
and tyrants to overthrow the faithful adherents of the gospel.  See
how the most sacred ties have been sundered. The most
<pb n="14" facs="vreed14.jpg"/>
intimate relationships broken up, and the most fearful conflicts, have
been waged, by those who were naturally bound together by most
endearing bonds.</p>
               <p>Look at our own country; see violent conflicts of opinion,
culminating in a conflict of arms, and the land deluged in blood. See
families divided, brothers arrayed against brothers, fathers against
sons, those who had been associated in counsel, in office, in the
various pursuits of life, who had enjoyed the same privileges, were
united in the same church, and had been at the same communion table,
opposing each other in deadly strife. Why? Because a few unprincipled
men, who, could not rule the nation, upon principles which if allowed
to prevail, would have destroyed all true freedom, induced the South
to attempt the dangerous experiment, of destroying the nation that on
its ruin they might establish one, that in the face of Christian
civilization, dared to flaunt the absurd and wicked solecism, that
national freedom is to be based upon the bondage of a class. And good
men, have been so strangely deluded, that they could pray for the
success of this wickedness, and pretend that the Bible teaches that it
ought to succeed. God be praised,--let every friend of truth and
righteousness throughout the land, join in the hallelujah--God be
praised, that this wickedness has been rebuked; and He who can make
the wrath of man to praise him, will overrule this fearful crime, to
strike the chains from the limbs of the captive, and let the oppressed
go free.</p>
               <p>Some have mourned that we were living in such troublous
times. But it is no new thing. The conflict of truth with error has
been going forward, ever since the first lie was uttered in
Paradise. The powers of darkness have their day, and labor to
overthrow the kingdom of Christ. 
<pb n="15" facs="vreed15.jpg"/>
It is what the Saviour declared, should result from the prevalence of
his gospel. But the truth shall prevail. The powers of hell shall be
overthrown and every species of wickedness shall receive its merited
retribution. Our only anxiety should be, to be faithful to our duty in
this conflict.</p>
               <p>No nation that performs an important part in the history of
the world, escapes severe conflict. Such conflicts are like the storms
that purify the atmosphere, and save the land from pestilence. There
are some men whose patriotism only glows in the sunshine. So there are
some Christians that are terrified at the dust and smoke of
strife. They will relinquish the truth rather than their own peace and
comfort. They will go with the multitude and be borne along with the
current. Such Christians if they had lived in the martyr age, never
would have been burned. And if they had lived in the days of Christ,
they might have joined in the cry, "Away with him. Crucify him." In
all things we are to retain the truth of the gospel, "which if we
lose," in the words of Martin Luther, "then do we also lose God,
Christ, all the promises, faith, righteousness and everlasting
life."</p>
               <p>All truths are not essential to Christianity. Yet no truth
can be neglected with safety. All duties are not equally
important. Yet no duty can be neglected without sin. It is especially
important that we as a Christian people see clearly, and adhere
faithfully to the truth involved in the present national
conflict. True this is not strictly speaking, a religious war, a
conflict for the principles of vital Christianity. Yet it is very
nearly allied to such a conflict. It is a contest for some of the most
sacred principles of Christianity, which concern man
<pb n="16" facs="vreed16.jpg"/>
as an inhabitant of earth; for the application of Bible teachings in
reference to human governments, and the prevalence of gospel
principles in the treatment of all classes of men. It is a conflict in
which gospel truth is involved; if not the existence of the Church, in
this country, the successful prosecution of its heaven-appointed
work. See how the leaders of this rebellion have been anxious to
secure the sanctions of religion, have appealed to the religious
feelings and prejudices of the South; and Christian men, have not only
prayed, that the rebellion might succeed, but have taught that the
Bible sanctions some of the greatest wrongs that have ever been
perpetrated in civilized society. Not until Christian ministers took
this ground, and labored to maintain it on Bible principles, did the
political leaders, advocate a rupture with the national
government. And some who are not with the South, have, unconsciously
and undesignedly, or knowingly and intentionally countenanced this
wickedness, this perversion of gospel truth. Under these circumstances
have Christians and men who would be governed by Christian principle
nothing to do? Ought the pulpit to be silent? When already more than a
million of men have been sacrificed upon the altar of treason, when
the interests of millions more, for generations to come, are involved
in the right settlement of our national difficulties, when some of the
fundamental principles of Christian ethics, are openly impugned, and
the teachings of the gospel are in danger of being set at nought, can
Christian ministers remain silent without sin? Ought the ambassadors
of the God of truth to hold their peace, because some forsooth, will
cry, "You must not meddle with politics." Very well. But politicians
must not meddle with us; tell us when to
<pb n="17" facs="vreed17.jpg"/>
speak and when to be silent. We are here for the defence of the truth,
to denounce sin, in every form. And we say on the authority of God's
word, if you are a citizen of this country, loyalty to the government
of the United States is just as truly a duty, as loyalty to Jesus
Christ. As in reference to himself he declared, "He that is not with
me is against me," so if not the avowed friend you are an enemy to the
government. Christian principle requires you to come out boldly on the
side of law, and good government, and the rights of the
oppressed. Some think politics and religion, should be entirely
separate. But if you, cannot carry Christian principles into our
politics you should give up your politics.</p>
               <p>"Can ye not discern the signs of the times." That man must
be blind indeed, who cannot see the providence of God in this
conflict. The war might have been terminated long ere this. It would
have been terminated, if the counsels of men had prevailed. But there
were important ends to be attained and important principles of the
divine government to be vindicated. And again, and again, God has
disappointed our expectations, showing us that we must cease our
dependence on men, and faithfully do his will, in this conflict. Now,
when we were rejoicing in the prospect of a speedy termination of the
war, he who was more than ever confided in, and honored, as the
instrument of leading the nation out of the wilderness, is suddenly
removed. Why was this permitted? We honor our late lamented President,
for his noble generosity, his anxiety for peace, and the cessation of
all bloodshed; for his kind treatment of the enemies of the
nation. One of the last acts of his life, we are told, was an act of
clemency towards two leading rebels. We rejoice that history will
<pb n="18" facs="vreed18.jpg"/>
not record against him one act of unnecessary severity, or selfish
cruelty. But he knew not, perhaps, as none of us appreciated in its
full extent, the foul wickedness which has animated the Southern
rebellion. It was not safe, God saw it was not safe, to allow this
great crime to go unpunished. The serpent was strangled but not
crushed, and it must be permitted in its death-throes, to strike its
envenomed fang into the head of the nation, in order that the nation
who was assailed in the person of its head, might be aroused, to the
necessity of an utter crushing of the monster. We all desired peace in
the shortest time and easiest way. But God would not allow a
compromise with iniquity, or the relinquishment of fundamental
principles of good government.</p>
               <p>Providence is teaching us that three things must be clearly
understood, and maintained in the settlement of our national
conflict. Any settlement that is not based upon these, we think, will
not secure the divine approval or promote the permanent prosperity of
the nation.</p>
               <p>I. The first is the sacredness of law, and the divine
authority of government; our national government.--The divine
authority of government is a very different doctrine from the divine
right of kings, or of a republic, or any other form of government. The
form of government and the methods of its administration are to be
decided by men. But none are at liberty to reject all government, or
to resist the authority of a regularly constituted government,
administered without tyranny or oppression. Loose views upon this
subject have prevailed too extensively in this country. Because the
people have so much to do with government, the choice of rulers, and
<pb n="19" facs="vreed19.jpg"/>
determining the course of rulers, many fancy govermental authority
emanates from them. This is a pernicious error, and the step is short
from it, to the opinion that if government is not constituted, or
administered, according to their views or wishes, they have a right to
resist the government. If authority emanates from them and they do not
like its exercise they may renounce that authority. If the laws do not
suit them they may be disregarded.</p>
               <p>The will of God is the source of all authority in
government. This is true in the family, in the state, in the church,
and in the divine administration. Take the first form of government
that of the family. God has clothed parents with authority, and
disobedience of parents is disobedience to God. So in the state "the
powers that be are ordained of God," and resistance to a regularly
constituted government, administered without oppression, is resistance
to the authority of God. The violation of law is not only a crime
against the state, it is a sin against God. And although the civil
magistrate is not to execute the divine vengeance, he is to punish,
not merely as a matter of policy, or safety to the state, but because
the violation of law is sin and ought to be punished. Not only are
they guilty of sin who resist the laws, but they also who openly, or
secretly aid, countenance, or sympathize with, resistance of lawful
authority. It is said a man has a right to his opinion and should not
be molested for opinion sake. He has a right to <hi rend="italic">toleration</hi>, provided his opinions though erroneous,
are not pernicious or injurious to society. No man however, has a
right to an erroneous opinion, especially if that opinion is injurious
to his fellow men.. He sins against God and his own soul if he
indulges it. He sins against God and society if he promulgates it. 
	<pb n="20" facs="vreed20.jpg"/>
And it is the duty of all Christian men, and good citizens, to uphold
by their opinions as well as acts, the sacredness of law, and the
divine authority of government.</p>
               <p>Let us make a personal application of your doctrine. Your
neighbor thinks you are a bad man, dishonest, cruel, a thief, a
murderer. You say he has a right to his opinion. But he promulgates
it. He says publicly, you ought not to live in good society, and any
one that kills you will do society a favor. Do you allow him this
freedom of opinion and speech? Do you not arraign him for slander? And
if you are murdered by an assassin, is he not justly condemned as an
accomplice. The application is easy. Many have said, the government
was oppressive and ought to be resisted. The late head of the
government was a tyrant and ought not to live. Yet now, some of these
men are loud in their praise of the late President and put on the
signs of mourning for his loss. Either their present course is
shameful hypocrisy or their former sayings were a base slander. In
either case ought they not to repent and bring forth fruits meet for
repentance? Did not their opinions, freely expressed, nerve the
assassin's arm; and are they not, in a certain sense partakers of his
sin? Those who rebel against a righteous government, are guilty not
only of a political, but a moral wrong. And those who by word or act
countenance such rebellion, are partakers of their evil deeds. We
arraign all such, not before the bar of partisan judgment, but before
the tribunal of inspired truth, and charge them with sip, against the
Author of all government; with aiming to set at naught an ordinance of
heaven, appointed to subserve the best interests of men.</p>
               <p>If it is wrong to withold allegiance to God, it is likewise
wrong to resist the powers that are ordained of God. 
<pb n="21" facs="vreed21.jpg"/>
It is just as truly a sin to break the fifth commandment, as the
first. "By father and mother in the fifth commandment, are meant not
only natural parents, but all superiors in age and gifts, and <hi rend="italic">especially such as by God's ordinance are over us in
places of authority</hi>." We commend this subject to the careful and
prayerful consideration of those Christian men who have either in word
or thought approved of the Southern Rebellion, or who have either
openly or covertly, designedly or unintentionally; either from
mistaken views of duty, or partisan motives, attempted to embarrass
the government, in its efforts to overthrow this great
wickedness. Especially now that it has been decided at the ballot box
and by the military power, that the government shall be sustained, can
any further opposition be prompted by aught, but the spirit of faction
and diabolical strife.</p>
               <p>II. If what has been said is correct, it follows that
crimes against the government, should be punished. The sword is put
into the hands of the civil magistrate, for the punishment of
evil-doers. An evil-doer, here, is one who breaks the laws, or resists
governmental authority. He is to be punished, because he has done
wrong.--Not merely because good policy, the safety of the state, and
the good of society require it, but because it is an offence and
deserves punishment.</p>
               <p>Treason, "making war against the government or giving aid
and comfort to its enemies," is regarded as the highest crime that can
be committed against civil society. As such it deserves a very severe
penalty. If the ruffian, who murders an individual, thereby carrying
desolation and suffering to a single family, expiates as he ought, his
crime upon the scaffold, should any thing less be meted
<pb n="22" facs="vreed22.jpg"/>
out to those, who combine their malice and selfish ambition, to strike
a death blow at the heart of the nation, plunge the country into a
terrible war, cause the destruction of hundreds of thousands of lives,
and fill the whole land with mourning and woe? We would, by no means,
encourage the spirit which, since the assassination of the President,
there is danger, may gain the mastery over loyal hearts, that all
thought of mercy should be laid aside, and deadly vengeance with
relentless power, should fall upon the authors of our national
troubles.<ref target="#vreed.002.n01">*</ref> But we assert the teachings of God's word, in reference to
the punishment of crime. The enlightened Christian sentiment of the
community demands, that the leaders of the rebellion should be
punished. First, because they deserve punishment. Their crime is
immensurably greater, than that of an ordinary felon, as the
consequences of their acts are wide-spread and beyond
computation. Secondly, because there is no safety to the government if
such crimes are unpunished. A bounty is placed upon treason. And a few
years hence, or whenever unprincipled men may choose, we may be
afflicted with the same national calamities. The multitude of the
Southern people, were deluded, and have been sufficiently
punished. But let simple justice, as God himself has decreed, be meted
out to those who are the responsible authors of this wickedness.</p>
               <p>Punishment should be inflicted lawfully. There should</p>
               <note xml:id="vreed.002.n01" n="*" place="foot" anchored="true">
                  <p>On the Sabbath after the assassination of
the President the author endeavored to improve that sad event by
directing the minds of his people to God as the Governor of nations,
and to the fearful nature of those sins which filled the land with
mourning- But he purposely abstained from a full discussion of the
subject, till the intense feeling caused by the President's death, and
the passage of the corpse through our midst, had subsided, that sober
conviction might- take the place of momentary excitement, and we can
calmly contemplate the solemn lessons God is teaching us.</p>
               </note>
               <pb n="23" facs="vreed23.jpg"/>
               <p>be no mobs or vigilance committees, or taking the law into their
own hands, by individuals or bodies of men.</p>
               <p>III. The Providence of God is plainly teaching, that the
institution of slavery in this country must be abolished. As you are
aware, I hold no extreme views on the subject of slavery--have never
countenanced, but opposed, violent and unconstitutional efforts to rid
the country of the evil. While I, who have always lived in a free
state, would on no account hold slaves, there are circumstances where
it may not only be right, but a duty, for a christian to hold the
relation of master, until the slaves are qualified for, and can enjoy
the benefits of freedom. But slavery as it has existed in this
country, is an evil, an unmitigated evil, contrary to the spirit of
the gospel, the teachings of Jesus Christ, destructive of the best
interest of the slave and equally injurious, in a moral point of view
to the master. While five years ago, very few at the north would have
approved of any attempt to interfere with what was emphatically a
southern institution, for the circumstances of which, and all the
evils of which, the South alone was responsible, God is wiser than
men. He has made use of the wickedness of the slaveholders themselves,
to prepare the way for an entire removal of the evil. And now the
responsibility for the continuance of this evil is thrown upon us. The
people of the whole land are to decide, in the method pointed out by
the constitution whether slavery shall be permitted still to disgrace
our country, and in the face of our claim to give freedom to all, we
will still allow the perpetual enslavement of a particular class. With
this question brought home to us, no christian can remain silent or
inactive without guilt. It is a question which all must
<pb n="24" facs="vreed24.jpg"/>
indifference. If we adopt an erroneous opinion, and fail to appreciate
our responsibility in reference to the subject, if by our opposition
or supineness, or indifference, or silence, we retard the progress of
principles of true liberty, as a part of the nation, we not only fail
to understand our duty, but subject ourselves to the righteous
displeasure of the God of Nations. "Can ye not discern the signs of
the times?" Look at the developments of the past four years. See how
God has kept back our armies--held in check both rulers and people,
that there could be no cessation of hostilities, until both rulers and
people have been brought to the determination, that there shall be no
compromise with the abettors of human bondage. Has not the whole land
been made to mourn because of this war, inaugurated in the interest of
slavery; a war brought upon the country for the avowed purpose of
perpetuating the bondage of the African race? Have not hundreds of
thousands of our citizens perished, every community and almost every
family been made to mourn? And do we not hear the voice of God, as
plainly as in the solemn utterances to Egypt's haughty king in the
terrible plagues that scourged his land--"Let this people go." Have
not the votes of the American people by a majority of hundreds of
thousands, decided that there is to be no compromise with treason, and
no cessation of hostilities till slavery which caused the war is
overthrown? And has not the God of battles given success to our armies
upon this principle? Until even prominent Rebel leaders, have been
forced to acknowledge that the amendment to the Constitution
abolishing slavery, is a
<pb n="25" facs="vreed25.jpg"/>
political necessity, and the south must submit to it. And now if we
fail to do thoroughly, the work of God, if we fail to make an utter
end of this abomination, may we not expect, ought we not to expect,
the judgments reserved in God's magazine of wrath; that a worse than
Egypt's last plague may come upon us? And when the cry of wailing
comes up from all parts of the land, because the first-born in every
family is slain, and all hopes crushed, then we will obey the voice of
Jehovah.</p>
               <p>Here let me quote the words of President LINCOLN, uttered
in his inaugural address on the Fourth of March, last. "Fondly do we
hope, fervently do we pray, that this mighty scourge of war may soon
pass away. Yet if God wills that it continues till all the wealth
piled by the bondmen's two hundred and fifty years of unrequited toil
be sunk, and until every drop of blood, drawn with the lash, be paid
with another drawn with the sword, as was said three thousand years
ago, so now must be said. "The judgments of the Lord are true and
righteous altogether."</p>
               <p>It is said there is no danger. The question is already
settled. Slavery is already dead, past the possibility of
resurrection. We would gladly believe it. But what was the state of
feeling three weeks ago? Such was the universal desire for peace, that
some would have been ready to overlook all the sins of the South, and
welcome back to their privileges and rights and even to their places
in the councils of the nation, those who for years have sought its
destruction, to perpetuate slavery. God saw it necessary to check the
spirit of unholy fraternizing with the abettors of the worst forms of
social and political crimes. He laid the head of the nation low, that
we
<pb n="26" facs="vreed26.jpg"/>
might stop and see whither we were tending. God grant that other
victims may not be necessary.</p>
               <p>Is there no danger, when very many of our citizens are
liable to be swayed from principle, by regard for present or personal
interest? And when many more are in a state of indifference or
opposition to the prevalence of right principle?</p>
               <p>Is it said that this discussion is out of place. Here there
are no disloyalists or owners of slaves. I reply, there is no part of
the land from Maine to California, where, at the present time, such
utterances are out of place. And there is no part of the country,
where the truth should be spoken boldly, and persistent efforts made
to bring all to comprehend these great moral principles more, than in
<hi rend="italic">this good State of New Jersey</hi>; a state that has
had a glorious history; whose soil was drenched with the blood of
Revolutionary heroes; that has furnished a noble list of champions for
freedom, truth and righteousness, in the various civil pursuits; tens
of thousands of whose sons have testified their devotion to freedom
and good government, by shedding their blood in this war; but a state
that now holds the unenviable position of trying to stay the onward
march of freedom, and resist the sure indications of God's will. A
state, whose recent record upon this subject, confers little honor
upon her citizens. We may well blush and hang our heads to think that
we belong to a state, which though surrounded with the lights of
freedom, when every free state that has spoken, has given an
unequivocal testimony, and some that had been cursed with slavery have
risen and thrown off the deadly incubus, and when even southern
leaders, confess that the contest is fairly decided against them, has
<pb n="27" facs="vreed27.jpg"/>
said by the recent act of its legislature, "let the slave continue to
wear his chains! Let the proud master fatten and grow rich on the toil
and blood of the oppressed! Let the evil continue to curse the land,
and worse contests than those we have witnessed, be entailed upon our
children and our children's children! Let the fearful judgments of a
sin-avenging God be still further provoked!" Yet we are told that, we
as christian teachers, must be silent on this subject. Were we silent,
the very dust of the battle fields of Monmouth, Princeton and Trenton,
would cry out against us. Were we silent, the patriot dead would
hardly remain quiet in their graves; the bones of our gallant brothers
and sons, sleeping on soil cursed with slavery and laid there in the
fearful conflict of slavery with freedom, would rise up to rebuke
us. Nay, were we silent, we could hardly, with a clear conscience,
tread the streets of this city, almost every house in which has so
recently, been hung in the dark drapery of woe, because of a fearful
crime, perpetrated by the foul spirit of slavery. Were we silent we
could hardly lie down at night with the christian's confidence and the
christian's hope, lest the judgments of a holy God might come upon the
house of the faithless prophet, who saw the sword coming upon the
people but withheld the warning.<ref target="#vreed.002.n02">*</ref></p>
               <p>No, no, we must give our testimony against this wrong. We
call upon every right minded citizen of whatever creed, party or
interest, we call especially upon every christian man and woman, to
remove the foul stain upon our reputation, and rest not till New
Jersey takes her</p>
               <note xml:id="vreed.002.n02" n="*" place="foot" anchored="true">
                  <p>Ezekiel, 33: 6.</p>
               </note>
               <pb n="28" facs="vreed28.jpg"/>
               <p>place, the place which of right belongs to her, in the front rank
of the championship of freedom; till our legislators perform
faithfully the work, which justice, humanity, true political wisdom,
christian consistency, the teachings of the gospel, and the solemn
voice of God's providence imperatively demand.</p>
               <p>How can a christian people longer tolerate slavery. It
degrades the slave, but worse than this, it brutalizes the master. It
gives to unprincipled men, unlimited control over the person, the
labor, the conduct, the religious rights and privileges, the bodies
and souls of men.  It engenders a spirit of imperiousness and savage
barbarism, and therefore unfits slaveholders for the position of quiet
law-abiding citizens. Those educated under its influences can brook no
restraint; are reckless, law-defying, following no guide but their own
capricious will. While making loud pretensions to honor, they show an
utter disregard of honor, and even of the sanctity of solemn oaths.</p>
               <p>The spirit engendered by slavery, turned our once happy
country into an arena of terrible conflict. It has conducted the war
upon principles of atrocity and barbarity, at which every right minded
man must shudder. It has deliberately starved and butchered in cold
blood, prisoners of war; has subjected to indescribable tortures, men
whose only fault was, that they were true to their country, to liberty
and to God. It has perverted the judgments and debased the principles
of Christian men, and countenanced savage wickedness under the sacred
garb of religion. It has plotted in secret the most fearful crimes. By
the stealthy use of the torch, the dagger and the bullet, in wholesale
conflagration and butchery of unoffending citizens, it shows its
deadly hatred to all
<pb n="29" facs="vreed29.jpg"/>
free institutions. It has nourished traitors, assassins, fiends, in
the very heart of the government. It has turned away from the noble
advances of generosity, good will and christian charity, and in its
death struggle aimed to plunge the nation into anarchy by murdering at
once, all who held the reins of government. It has shown the
diabolical spirit of its great prototype and author-</p>
               <lg type="stanza">
                  <l>'Better to reign in hell than serve in heaven.</l>
               </lg>
               <p>Let then the foul spirit be effectually exorcised. Let it
be banished forever from the country, which God has so wonderfully
blessed, and so strangely chastised--banished forever, from the pale
of christian civilization. And if it finds a resting place, any where,
this side of the pit of endless darkness, let it be only with those
barbarous tribes that have never heard the words of Jesus,</p>
               <p>"All things whatsoever ye would that men should do to you,
do you even so to them."</p>
            </div2>
         </div1>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>